This is the Technical Difficulties
and we are playing
Two Of These People Are Lying
because two of these people will be.
Joining me are Chris Joel, Gary Brannan--
He said, "Why do you blow that bugle?"
And I said, "It don't
work if you suck it."
And Matt Gray.
The way the game works is,
the three of us have all picked
an article from Wikipedia
and written it down on
these pieces of card.
Tom is now going to pick
one of the pieces of card
and one of us will be telling the truth
about what the article is
and two of us will be lying.
And today we are talking
about... Evangelina Psarra?
"Psarra?" Psarra.
Egangelina Psarra.
Gary, we're going to
start with you this time.
Evangelina Psarra.
Is a musician in the field of sonic art.
Sonic art, is that...
Yeah.
It's just a hedgehog, doing
really bad Mona Lisas.
Does she perform the ring cycle?
[all] Wheey!
I'll get me coat(!)
Chris, Evangelina Psarra.
It is a skin disorder.
- Oh!
- Oh.
I think we were all surprised by that.
- Matt...
- You would be!
Evangelina Psarra?
Is a Greek...
...archer.
Let's start with that Greek archer.
Okay...
Confidence!
Could you tell me some more about them?
She competed in the summer Olympics.
Many years in a row,
from 2000 until 20...
was it '16, the last one?
Those are both summer Olympic years.
In 2016, she was ranked 8th
in the women's something else.
You know, when someone says
a very qualified statement
about where you're ranked.
Oh, yes.
Like some brands do, we are
"the something most thing
- "of the something or other thingy."
- Yes.
It was the women's something or other.
So, it's the name of the event,
but to me it sounded like
one of those things like,
"I'm the best... in this little category".
It was women's singles, or whatever.
I don't know how arching works.
- Arching?
- Yeah.
- Not archery, arching.
- Arching?
- Just very good at just arching.
- Just bend and a curve.
And then there was an entire paragraph
about her scores and how, I think,
that when she ranked 8th it was a 75 shot
to reach a score of 650.
Whatever that means.
I've never even watched any
professional archery but...
He's watched plenty of
unprofessional archery.
Just people getting
stabbed all over the place.
- It's just awful.
- Outside lane of the M1.
Out of the sunroof.
Oh!
Well, it's like archery
jousting but on the M1.
Motorway jousting!
Like going 70 on the motorway.
You've got two cars and
two massive boxing gloves.
Yes!
So, I picked an article
that was about that long,
thinking, oh there will
be some meat to this.
I wrote it down on the piece
of paper and then a lot of it
is about her victories
and a lot of scoring and
what people from what countries
beat her in the Olympics.
Let's talk about sonic art then, Gary.
What sort of art is being produced here?
Obviously sonic, other than, with sound.
Yes, yeah, well, some might call it music.
Others probably would not,
in that one of them was
burping into a length of drain pipe.
All right,
With a lot of reverb and
stuff around it and also a--
Do you feel you'd be able to give an
impression of what that might be like?
Bring me my drain pipe.
I haven't brought mine with me.
Can I just steal that?
- No.
- No?
Those are non-sonic art...
Maybe just resonant like that.
[loud burping]
I mean, now I have to give her royalties.
PRS on this!
Yeah, so that and stuff like
music that's pitched outside
the range of human hearing.
That kind of thing.
Ah, dog discomfort music.
- Basically yes so you--
- Ah, DDM!
You've got your EDM, you've got your DDM.
They're very different.
It's human discomfort,
and dog discomfort.
Apparently, she had very high,
she had a very wide
pitch of hearing and would go to other,
there was a thing in the article saying she
goes to other artists' performances,
likewise, at pitches outside the
range of human hearing
and she'd critique them
on their performance
because she could hear the edits.
Now, up until that very last bit,
I was with you Gary.
Right?
But, the audio engineer in here
and the person who edits video in here,
both kind of went: "you what?"
Well, don't take it up with me,
take it up with her.
- Chris.
- Yes.
A skin disorder.
A skin disorder and, for double points,
a notable example of selection bias.
Go on.
Evangelina Psarra, Evangelina,
to do with evangelism.
Originally, when described, thought to
afflict only the religious community.
- Well.
- Ooh.
Selection bias, because
they were the sort of people
that you could go in
and study and describe.
Where as, everybody else
who was wondering around
with this, well, not horrendous disease
but unpleasant disease,
was going, sort of... "uninspected"
isn't the word I'm looking for.
Isn't receiving the
appropriate attention from
the medical community of the time.
So, it gets described as
this thing that specifically
affects enclosed, religious communities.
Which is, of course, nonsense.
It is a boring, normal skin disorder
but once you've described something,
in science, it retains the name.
Oh, Chris, that is excellent.
That is either the best line of utter bollocks
we've ever done in this format...
Or, a very accurate description
of having utter bollocks
in the religious community.
Evangelina Psarra, if it turns out that this
is an archer, or a sonic artist,
that's just an awful thing to
do to their name.
God I hope, I hope it's a Sonic artist.
I really do.
- Yeah, so do I.
- So do I.
And that was either a
really good double bluff
or accidentally giving it up.
I don't know.
I don't, ah, all right.
Gary, I'm going to rule you out
because I don't think
dog discomfort music
is going to be a thing.
I think you accidentally
went into a bit of knowledge
that I have about finding
the edits and I don't think
high frequencies would change that.
So, Gary, I don't think it's you.
Obviously the correct thing
for me to do here is say,
Matt, it's a dull article about an archer
who's been in few Olympics, because,
obviously, that's a name.
Because, obviously, that's all true.
But.
Chris, no I...
Chris, I think it's you, am I right?
No, it's definitely an archer.
Aw!
What with all the real facts.
Is it the archer?
- Yeah.
- Oh!
I was hoping, I was really hoping.
Can I make a point this way?
You that bit about someone who can hear
the high pitch and the edits?
That person does exist.
I know them, they are a
person who does sonic art.
- Really?
- Yes.
How can... why does being
able to hear the high noises
change your ability to hear any edits?
Because, the piece has been
put together from separate
parts of high frequency noise and,
because it's high frequency noise,
there's clunky edits in it
all the way through.
This is in the days when you were doing it
with actual tape rather
that waveforms or anything,
Oh, so, you just hear the joins.
Came up at the end to say, "it's nice
but I can hear all the edits".
If everyone else can't hear it at all then
the person who can hear it
can hear the edits.
All right.
So you, sir, technically wrong twice.
Which kind of makes up
for the last episode.
Matt has gone and got himself
a new article.
If your wondering why Gary's eyes are
suddenly bloodshot and he's teared up,
that's because you missed a
five minute giggle loop
based around a toilet version
of British game show Bob's Full House.
- Which--
- Which is still not safe.
No, it's still not safe.
Bob's Full Bogs.
That's a better joke.
That's, yeah, oh, no,
it's just a series of doors!
"So, it's going to be, it's going to be
the third door from the left, it's..."
There's a ker-splash of water
from underneath it.
You've been wallied.
It was Russ Abbot.
All you can see of the
celebrities are just their shoes
and their rolled down trousers.
- He's not even a real Abbot.
- Let's, let's...
You okay, Gary?
(I can just see it...!)
When they've got the big board at the end,
it's just three racks of
toilet cubicles, like,
Celebrity Squares-style,
and they just hold up the, er...
trouble is, of course, because it's
Celebrity Squares-style
there isn't actually any plumbing
and it's just, kind of, open to...
Audience.
(You sound like a choking dog.)
In this episode, Gary
will be replaced by--
Sorry, sorry, sorry, sorry, sorry.
I'll be fine, I'll be fine.
I hoped you haven't pissed yourself.
These seats aren't wipe clean.
It's fine, it just goes down over
whoever's in the row below.
I can't...
You've gone the same
colour as Tom's t-shirt.
Come on.
Oh, come on.
It's when they've got the Krankies, both in
the same cubicle, it all falls apart.
Keith Harris and Orville...
"I can't go in public!"
"You can!"
Would you like a tissue?
Could I? Thank you.
F***.
We are...
no, he's gone again.
Come on, behave.
We are talking about the Green Monster.
The Green Monster.
Gary, I'll give you a minute
to compose yourself this time.
- Thank you.
- Chris, the Green Monster.
Is a land speed record car.
- Ooh.
- Yes.
Now, did it ever get the record?
Actually I'll come back
to you in a minute.
All right then.
Land speed record car.
Gary.
Yes?
And I ask this tentatively,
the Green Monster?
It was a 19th century rail engine
on the East Coast Main Line.
On the ECML.
All right, and Matt, the Green Monster?
- It's a brand of absinthe.
- Okay.
We'll start with the absinthe then.
We'll not get to the end if we do!
What is special about the Green Monster?
'Cause I've heard of the Green Fairy
but I've not heard of the Green Monster.
It's much bigger.
Is it just someone's poured some absinthe
into some Monster energy drink?
Ah, that would be one hell of a cocktail
and you would not sleep for weeks.
Spiritus sancti...
It's one of those articles, I've forgotten the
phrase they put on Wikipedia,
the bit on the top that says "this looks
more like a sales pitch than an article".
Oh, yes. Clearly, the
PR company has been involved.
It's a load of PR w***
saying "our wormwood is the--"
Wormiest.
Specially grown, wormiest, strongest--
Woodiest.
It occurs to me that I don't
know what wormwood is.
- I don't either.
- It's a herb. I think.
Is it a root or a bark or something?
Sort of sounds like it ought,
to be a root doesn't it?
It's MDA, it has
hallucinogenic properties.
It's biblic... it's mentioned
in the bible, as well, is wormwood.
- There's a bit...
- I've just realised,
Gary's not making this up,
because it's not his article.
No, no!
And lo, the Lord did take
three fingers of the green
and f*** me, the bush was on fire!
It's well known cause Reagan
quoted it after chapter--
What, in the bible?
I think even in the Tea Party's
most conservative dreams,
- Reagan is not in the bible.
- No, but he was in the film.
- What, of the bible?
- Yes, a film of the bible.
All right, so brand of
absinthe with a higher ABV
and a lot of PR guff about it.
Yeah.
All right, Gary, it's a
19th century railway engine
on the East Coast Main Line.
Now... you okay there?
What's... oh!
It's the toilet-based Bob's Full House.
It was called, in our little reverie just then,
"Bob's Full Bogs".
And not "Bog's Full House",
which it really should have been!
Yeah, but Bob would never allow it
to not have his name in it, would he?
That's true, that's true.
- Anyway, so it's--
- "Bog Outhouse."
Wooh, anyway, so the rail engine is
the Stirling Single, which is in
the National Railway Museum.
I believe. Or one of 'em.
It's the one that you look at,
it is green and--
Well, it would be.
But it's got a big wheel in the middle.
So, rather than have, its driving wheel--
That's not where you
normally put wheels on.
There normally on the--
- Well, it's on the outside.
- The outside.
Lengthwise, mate.
Yeah, yeah.
You mean, like, steering wheel?
Cause that's not how trains work.
No, I mean the big one
that goes round and round
- with the pumpy things on it.
- Oh, my.
So the driving wheel is a big central wheel.
About 11 foot.
I don't know how steam trains work.
F***in' Jesus!
Steam makes thing go like that.
It's connected to a wheel that goes like that.
Right, so, to try and get more traction,
'cause the whole thing is getting up
to a higher speed.
Which is what you're looking for.
The driving wheel was a big middle wheel,
about 11 foot high.
Right. Okay.
It was quite fast and it was pretty smooth
and it actually did quite well.
It was one of the first big successful
high-speed, long-distance engines.
Was it the penny-farthing of trains?
Pretty much.
Only it hasn't got a Victorian
gent wobbling atop it.
Well, it probably did, actually.
Not wobbling though.
Oh, yeah, no just stood resolutely.
All right, sorry mate.
- Not like, "whoa...!"
- "Oh! Bloody hell!"
It was known as the Green Monster,
it was big, it was fast,
it made a lot of noise
and, you know, you got flames
and smoke coming out of it.
All right.
Chris, the Green Monster,
the land speed record car.
Green Monster is a land speed
record car built somewhere in America
by a guy called Art Arfons.
It was one of the first jet cars...
Sorry, that's just the
Yorkshire version of Happy Days.
Our Fonz!
It's our Fonz, that!
Ey! Sit on it.
- Art Arfons.
What else have I told you?
It's the land speed record,
it was built in America,
by Art Arfons sometime in the early 60's.
Held the record three times
and was eventually beaten by somebody else.
- That's fine.
- And it wasn't green.
- It wasn't green?
- It was red and blue.
Do we know why or was
that just because America?
Because it was red and blue,
'cause the article said
it wasn't green, it was red and blue.
This is genuinely difficult.
You say this almost every time.
No, no, 'cause last time,
last time it was like, I mean...
I've been getting it right.
Earlier one it was like,
it should be Matt, it should be Matt.
I'm going to go with Chris on the guess.
But, in this case, I have,
genuinely, no idea.
Gary, I think that's
just a different train
that you've applied the
name Green Monster to.
I don't think it's Mallard,
but it's something like that
'cause you know your railway history.
I think you've just gone Green Monster,
so I don't think it's you.
Matt,
I'm tempted by that
but the thing that's convinced me, Chris,
is Art Arfons.
Which feels like a name you
wouldn't pull from somewhere.
You'd have to pull it from
a very specific place.
Yes, it would have to be someone else.
So, Chris, I think it's the speed record car.
Am I right?
- You are absolutely right.
- Yes!
Built 1960-61 after he broke up,
after the speed racing partnership
broke up with his brother, had a J79
out of an F104 taken from a junkyard.
Got hold of the manuals, despite the
government intervening and saying
"that is still classified,
you can't have it,"
balanced the engine not by getting
spare parts but by pulling parts out of it,
tested it by strapping
it to trees in his yard,
strapped it into a car and, eventually,
did 594 miles an hour.
- Good God!
- Two ways in 1964.
- S***.
- Good heavens!
And I only had to faintly check
the article on that one. Funnily enough!
Chris, congratulations,
that's a point to you.
That's two points to you, isn't it?
You got a point for the other one as well.
- Suck it!
- You win! Like it matters!
It doesn't matter that I win,
it matters that you lost.
Well, that where we're cutting that.