This is the Technical Difficulties
and we are playing
Two Of These People Are Lying
because two of these people will be.
Chris Joel.
Gary Brannan.
I'm fully toilet trained!
And Matt Gr...
okay. That got me.
That got me, well done.
And Matt Gray.
The way this works,
if you haven't noticed yet,
is the three of us will
pick a Widip-- Wikipedia article
--widi-widi-widi
wiki-wiki-Wikipedia article--
And put it down on one
of these pieces of card.
Tom is now going to select
one of these pieces of card.
Oh my goodness.
One of us will be telling
the truth about what this is
the other two have no idea,
and we'll be making it up.
We'll be lying.
And today we are talking about Henricus.
Henricus.
Chris, could you please
tell me about Henricus.
Noted, ancient Roman--
not ancient Roman.
It's not really ancient.
It is ancient Rome?
Yeah, ancient Rome,
actually that rings true.
I mean if he was modern
Rome that would be--
Yeah.
Noted Caeser-era Rome, there we go,
qualifier...
drunkard.
Okay, noted drunkard.
Gary. Henricus.
A horse!
- Henricus the Horsus?
- Yes.
You know what?
I'll ask the follow up details later.
That's how this works.
Matt.
Also known as Henricopolis.
It is a settlement.
Or was a settlement,
I should have said was.
Was a settlement.
All right.
- Gary.
- Yes.
A horse.
You wish for more information?
Well yes, is it an ancient horse?
Is it a modern racehorse?
Is it just some horse?
Just a piece of horse.
Can I say, strictly adhering to the
categories you have outlined there,
none of those.
- Ooh.
- Oh.
You said is it an ancient horse,
is it a modern racehorse
or is it just a horse?
It is none of those.
It's an old racehorse.
Okay.
It won The Grand National
in 1899.
Right.
And is notable for being the last horse
that was able to go round fences and win.
Go round fences?
Well, yeah, because the rules
of steeplechase
hadn't been
formalised by that point
and no-one would have thought about
what happens if the horse just--
- Just dodged the fences.
- Just get through and sort of...
With its rider still on it.
- Oh, that's amazing.
- If it's completely out of control, didn't...
Obviously, there are cases in... yeah!
You have a loose horse.
Yeah, you have a loose horse
but it's normally shed its rider
whereas in this point,
the rider actually stayed on
but couldn't control the damn horse.
And so it was dodging all the fences.
Therefore, comes first, 'cause it's not got
the slowing down effect
of having to jump over the fences.
And so it was the last one where they said,
well, it's not in the rules
that you actually have
to leap over the fences with
your rider on, that kind of thing.
I... I want that to be true.
Well, say it is then, you prick!
- Yeah, just do it. Be brave.
- Just do it.
You don't need to know about us.
Commit to Gary for once.
You don't need to wait for the others.
Come on.
All right, first horse,
ah, no, the last horse.
Correct.
To go around rather than over
and still be allowed to win.
Yeah, it was the point then
that they changed the rules.
All right.
Chris, a Caeser-era drunkard.
Yeah!
So. Just after birth of Christ
sort-of-time,
early ADs, guy is born in Gaul,
sees what's going down in the Holy Land
and thinks, "You know what, you know what,
there's some rubes for the taking here."
Has a relatively uneventful childhood.
Picks up the bottle a little bit,
in northern France.
But, obviously, this is
the era of occupation,
you can move slowly if you have to.
So he decides, right, I'm going
to find the centre of empire.
I'm going to start my
own personality cult.
I'm going to become 'the guy'.
'Henricus' will echo through the ages.
Jesus: just the warm up act.
I know what I'm about.
Manages to make his way,
over about the next 10 years,
to the centre of the empire in Rome.
By which time he is, as you can imagine,
well tanned, knows his way around,
knows what's going on.
Sets himself up with this little cadre
who've been following, as these stories
have been getting grander and grander.
"Don't you know I came from Gaul?"
And X happens there and, of course,
the next place you go
to nobody knows that.
And you continue this,
and you continue this
and you continue this.
Eventually washes up in Rome
with this cadre of 40, 50 people,
whatever else.
At which point the entire empire goes,
"'Excuse me? You what?"
Pontificating on the steps,
debating people, as they did,
completely takes the rug out
from underneath him.
Everybody gets thumbs down,
lions, the whole bit.
At which point he takes to
the bottle, famous drunk,
still shouting at the orators.
I can't tell if this is a
brilliant historical story
or your plan if you get sent back in time.
What do you mean sent back in time?
Did you know I'm from the north?
It's why he came down here.
It's taken him all of
six months to get here.
Found his way to the seat of empire
- which is obviously--
- Yeah, that's it.
Matt's kitchen.
And Boris is going to
feed me to the lions.
- Yeah.
- Topical.
Well, that'll be out of date
by the time that goes out.
Right, I have zero follow up questions.
It was an excellent story, well told.
I just am completely unable to tell
if that is something you made up
or if that is just a really
good telling of the article.
(Tom, you know that's the game.)
Yes! Matt.
Henricopolis.
It's going to seem really boring
compared to that now.
But, it has a slight bit of interest,
in that Henrico, or Henricopolis,
it has a few names,
was one of the first
settlements in the New World.
So it was in Virginia.
And it doesn't exist anymore.
No one's quite sure where it was.
But, there is now a Henrico County
in Virginia which is named after it.
And in its place now is-- ish, near it,
is a living history centre, it said.
I assume that's like Beamish.
Yes.
Load of re-enactors and--
sorry, are you okay there, Gary?
North American Beamish.
"It's a bit like Beamish",
is that how they market it?
Henrico Living Heritage
Centre, it's a bit like Beamish.
There's a fair portion of the
UK where that'd work.
What else did it say about it?
Oh, it's near to where Pocahontas grew up.
Man, that's difficult.
Wow.
Well done, everybody.
- Well done everybody.
- Well done, well done.
Well done, well done, good innings.
Seen him right off.
The thing is I don't have
any reasonable follow-up
questions on these either.
Because you have told the
entire history of a man
who may or may not have been Henricus.
You've...
I just don't think...
Okay, Gary, I'm really sorry.
There's no reasonable follow-up questions
except for you, you f***.
"I haven't struck you out yet!"
I just don't think that they'd've
awarded the Grand National
to someone who went around
the edges, even then.
I just don't think so.
It's not scrub out wrong,
but it's certainly not my first choice.
He's put parentheses around you
and torn the piece of
paper into another--
"No."
That's a great story.
That's a more plausible Wikipedia article.
Matt, I believe you.
Am I right?
Yes!
Oh.
Wow!
Hmm.
I think we're all surprised by that.
Well, Matt probably wasn't.
No, I was surprised as well.
By what?
I don't know.
You're doing quite well today, aren't you?
Apparently I am.
Yeah.
Shall I go get a new article?
Yes.
So we're genuinely all stumped by
the fact that that wasn't the--
I know, right!
Let's just surface that here.
That was f***ing amazing!
I want to follow that up in a minute.
But, let's just...
Tell me about Henricopolis.
"The city, i.e. of Henricus,
also known as Henricopolis,
"Henrica Town or Henrico was
a settlement in Virginia
"founded by someone in
1611, as an alternative
"to the swampy and dangerous area
"around the original English
settlement of Jamestown.
"It was named for Prince Henry,
"the oldest son of King James I."
- Bloody hell.
- The thing that sold me on it,
was changing the one to Henrico
and that also being an option.
That's exactly the sort of thing that,
the little detail.
When you said it was
Henricopolis or Henricus,
I was just like, oh, that's nothing.
I'm really stalling for time.
Henrico County sold that, somehow, to me.
"The sites of Henricus is located on
a neck of land called Farrar's Island
"which later became part
of the Shire of Henrico
"and was renamed Henrico County in 1637."
Gary, Gary, you're--
Ah, I've missed a great bit!
What?
The portion of Henrico County
that lays south of the
James River was detached
to form the present day
Chesterfield County.
- Yes!
- Chesterfield!
Spireites!
I was going to say, I'm from Mansfield,
I should immediately hate the place.
But, Gary, did you just make that up?
- Yes.
- Okay.
That was stellar.
- Yours was really good.
- It was excellent.
Genuinely, I was half-convinced,
for a while,
that they would have just let someone
go around the outside.
Well, if I was there, if
it's not even in the rules,
I could just imagine that--
Yeah, exactly.
Well, actually, it doesn't say
you got to jump over the fences.
Spirit of the law, you f***ed up.
Letter of the law,
we have to give you this.
Yeah, yeah.
No, that was really, really convincing.
Chris, did you make that up out
of whole cloth or was that--
Yeah!
- That's outstanding.
- That was good. I like it.
That was outstanding work, that really is.
You should publish it.
It was really good.
I was believing you and
it was my bloody article.
Yeah, I was believing you a bit,
but f***ing hell.
He got that.
- Yeah.
- Oh, thank you.
I thought it was a bit
too woolly in places but...
Oh, but you set the mood.
All right, Matt, again,
I'm somehow still surprised by this.
Could you go find a new article, please?
Yeah.
Matt's going to get a new article.
I'm going to pick this one from the three.
And for the second half
I'm going to try and
clean-sweep this again
'cause I've been doing well this series.
Dangers of the Engagement Period.
Gary.
[muffled noise]
Took a swig of tea,
thinking I was safe then.
Gary, Dangers of the Engagement Period.
Yes.
What is it, please?
- Qu'est-ce que c'est?
Well, I shall tell you.
What's behind the round window, Gary?
You will see by its syntactic expression
it's a very rough translation.
But, it is a manual produced
by the South Korean government
as a lovers' guide, or a couples' guide.
Oh, I'm definitely going
to ask you a lot of detail
about that in a moment.
Thank you.
I read hard.
I'm sure you have.
Chris.
Dangers of the Engagement Period.
Is a film.
Ooh.
That's all I'm getting
on this first round?
-Do you want some more?
- No, it's fine.
- Matt.
- F***er!
Sorry. Every time I say something,
well, here's my list of follow ups,
these two say anything, fine.
How is him saying "a film"
more plausible?
I mean, he didn't say
"South Korean lovers' guide"?
And yet he always credits detail.
Matt.
It is a series of documentary films.
Documentary films, all right.
So I will give you a rest here Gary.
I'm going to ask for more
details from Chris here.
Hi!
You just said "film".
I did.
Yes, can you please be more specific?
It is an film that came out in 1930.
Oh, that's a very early film.
It is a German film.
Right.
It was filmed in the
Netherlands. On a train.
It had Marlene Dietrich in it.
Hold on, is there any reason
you're talking like that?
I don't know.
I did something different last time,
can't I do something different this time?
Sure!
Yeah, so those are some more details.
Do you want me to string
them together or do--
Yeah, go on.
I feel like, oh, I can do this,
say, actually, in a string.
Yeah, so it's a 1930s German film.
Oh, a 1930 German film,
starring Marlene Dietrich.
It was one film before
"The Blue" something
which was her breakout role
that sent her to Hollywood.
It was filmed in the Netherlands.
It's set on a train.
It is about the "dangers of engagement"
because she,
they're on a train that gets derailed,
she falls in love with the baron
she's been sharing the coach with
or somebody of rank.
And then they spend the night
falling in love more after the train's derailed.
And then it all goes to pot
because she's engaged
to his American friend
or he's engaged to her American friend.
And then I assume they finish the film
with Marlene Dietrich marrying this guy.
Right.
Happy now?
- Yes!
- Good!
But I'm... after the startling show
of fabrication last time.
I don't know what to think.
This is excellent.
Good.
Carry on.
I love how you're spending
most of the time confused.
Yeah. I really am.
Matt, tell me about the documentary film.
What are the dangers
that it's documenting?
South Korean novels about being...!
Sorry, South Korean manuals about being.
We'll... we'll get to that.
Look at this! I'm saving this
measly aperitif for my main course.
I am, because of the phrase,
"South Korean lovers' manual".
We're saving that one, Gary.
It's better than the South Korean
lovers' automatic.
- Bolt action love.
- Ohh.
- Matt.
- Cold war.
- Oh.
- Yeah.
I don't think I've picked
anything particularly fun
this time but that's what they're--
I was using the random button
'til I got something of some meat.
So this is a US, kind of,
it seemed like hazily
military funded thing.
Oh, one of those ones that turns up
on the Prelinger Archives now. Yeah, okay.
I haven't had that phrase before
but it sounds like something
that pops up on archives.
I recognised a still from it,
it's got that seal logo on the front--
- It'll be one of the public domain ones, yeah.
- Yeah.
So what's the engagement period?
So that's when the engagement of war.
Ah.
So when they believed that
they are engaging in it.
It's one of those duck, cover,
hide in your bathroom kind of things.
But, a list of all the
dangers of what they could do.
Even if it's not necessarily nuclear
'cause they have enough
nuclear-specific ones.
But, all the other kind of ways
they could attack.
There could be commies in your area,
entire section called--
Red Dawn! This is Red Dawn!
"Red On Your Street", it said.
Oh, close enough.
All right, hush my smart mouth.
I know!
To think that they say it
in such phrases and that...
But, yeah.
All right, that's...
Oh, we've got some strong ones here.
And then we have a
South Korean lovers' manual.
No, I'm, teasing but--
If you use it right,
that's a strong one too.
Yeah, I'm teasing about
this Gary, but, honestly,
if your brain came up with
"South Korean lovers' manual" on its own...
I realise I say this sounds implausible
but also I don't know if that's something...
Like, if it was about trains, if it was about--
South Korean train lovers' manual?
If it was--
Train shagging?!
You okay there?
He's been spit-taking
for like 20 seconds now.
I had two problems there.
Number one, I was laughing
and I had tea in my mouth.
Number two, I need to descale my kettle
so I didn't really want
to swallow it either.
Urgh!
Lovely(!)
If you've come up with this...
This is not me saying,
"This is implausible".
This is me saying,
"This is going to be good".
Either because it's come from your head
or because you went through Wikipedia
until you found
"South Korean lovers' manual"
and then went, "Oh."
Do tell.
Produced by the South Korean government
in the wake of the Korean war.
Because you had a lot of, well, all right,
let's face it, it's blatantly sexist, isn't it?
Their target audience was young girls
who were getting engaged
to American soldiers.
- Ah.
- Oh.
The problem being then, is that,
the American soldier
inevitably moves home,
it all breaks down,
they get very disappointed,
it's causing all sorts of, what you would
call today, mental health issues.
So the point was to point out,
if you're getting engaged to someone
and you're very much in love and you
get engaged and it's all fine,
actually, he might go home,
it might all fall apart.
You will be very disappointed in love.
And these are the things that
you should be thinking about
when you're on your path
to getting married.
So it's kind of a
marriage-training sort of thing.
So "lovers' guide" is one way
of putting it.
Another way is marriage-training
but also warning text
that says, if you're going
to get engaged to a GI,
bear in mind, he might
already have a wife,
go home, leave you, dump you.
Or if you are going to stay with him,
here's all the things he needs
to know when he's in Korea,
here's all the things you need
to think about as a couple.
I want it to be that.
Yeah.
And you thought it was
going to be about f***ing!
- That's the point--
- That's chapter three!
This is, without doubt,
the most difficult one of this entire run.
Good Lord.
It's almost like we've had some practise.
And I should have had some practise.
And I've been picking
this quite well so far.
But I just don't know.
Which chapter's that?
Four.
- Marlene Dietrich.
- Yeah.
I think the dates are right.
I like the story around it.
I just...
I just, something in that
doesn't feel right.
You okay there?
Matt, "Red On Your Street" is--
Awesome.
Almost entirely convincing
but I don't think 'engagement period'
is the sort of thing the US military
would use for that.
I think this is the
first time I've done this
in this whole run we've
filmed in this block.
Gary, I think it's you.
Am I right?
No.
Ahh!
The one time I go for your option,
Brannan, the one time.
The one time you give me time
to f***ing think of something!
Oh, that was, oh, right, okay.
So we're down to the Marlene Dietrich film
or Red On Your Street.
Chris.
Filmed in Scheveningen in the Netherlands.
Well reviewed by Lotte Eisner.
Oh.
Points to Chris!
Can I tell you Matt, Red On Your Street--
- No, points to Gary.
- Points to me.
Yeah, point to Gary, point to Gary.
Red On Your Street, that was the detail
that nearly made me go for...
You okay there?
...kettle!
Kettle?
He needs to descale his kettle.
You need to descale your kettle.
It was fine earlier though, wasn't it?
It were all right then, yeah.
Thank you very much, gentlemen.
Congratulations to whoever won.
I haven't been keeping track of the scores
and you shouldn't have either.
Bye!
Bye.