This is The Technical Difficulties,
and we are playing
Two of These People are Lying because
two of these people will be,
-and they are Chris Joel.
-Hello.
-Gary Brannan.
-Good day… oh no, bollocks, no.
Start again,
I should do a proper line there, shouldn't I?
And Matt Gray.
You've missed your chance.
It's f***ing unfair, you know,
you'll never know what it was going to be
but it was absolutely peach.
And what we're doing today is: Tom is going
to try and see which one of us three are lying.
We have all gone through our phones,
looked at a Wikipedia article,
a different one each, written down the title on
a piece of paper down here and Tom picks one.
One of us tells the truth
about what that article is about,
yes, you can see the pen all over me
and the other two lie
because we've never seen the article before.
Alright, are we all ready?
Well, yeah,
I demonstrated my readiness at the start.
We are looking for Duryard or a Duryard.
-Durr-yard, D'yard. Duryard.
-Da yard!
Matt, why don't you kick us off?
Oh, w-- can I...
Have a drink of tea, have a think.
"Drinkin' my tea, ain't I?"
I should … I should point out that …
that apparently there may be swaps of
handwriting going on here so I cannot tell
who has written… written Duryard.
Matt, why don't you kick us off?
Anton Duryard, a cricketer, unfortunately,
I was reading the article,
I knew none of the words,
so I'm going to have to bluff this one.
Gary can make some up.
Well, the article was just "Duryard".
-Yeah.
-Like Prince.
He was just known as Duryard?
-Only the bat.
-Alright.
-Gary.
-A town in the south... west. Of Britain.
Chris.
Which is weird because it must be named…
the town that I found in Nebraska
must be named for it.
That's good, that's good, that's good.
Oh, now, either that's a brilliant strategy
or Gary pre-empted whatever is going on here.
We're going to,
we're going to start with Matt,
Matt. The cricketer, did you understand
any of the cricket terms that were in there?
Not really but the reason he is known
as Duryard is because when he…
I'm going to have to use a proper cricketing
phrase here: "did a good thing".
Did a good thing!
He was known for going "Duryard!"
and there's a photo of him on the article
with like both hands up,
like that kind of thing, yeah.
-Sorry both hands up and what?
-Into the camera, please.
Yeah, so he just called…
he is given the mononym from his…
from his cry let's say.
The word mononym has suddenly slightly
convinced me that this is not rubbish.
Alright.
Do you know what he did that was good?
No, it wasn't like once, it was whenever…
-Oh, right…
-How is it, he got points or…
Runs, I believe the term is.
Any time he got the runs...
He went "Duryard!"
Or, "Duryard..."
Grew up in Australia,
and it might have said New South Wales?
-Is that a place in Australia?
-Yeah.
That was either a really good bluff or…
You know what I'm like with places.
Unless they're Latin named, yes.
This tea idea has really worked out for him,
hasn't it?
I just really want a drink!
I poured it earlier,
when I'm coming up with the article,
setting up the cameras,
and I didn't have time to drink it.
Yeah, he was in New South Wales in Australia
and it said something about his cricketing
career in different places
and was it, like,
T20 something-or-other in it?
-It said different cricketing things.
-You perked up there, Gary.
-It's just the way I'm sat.
-"Oh, the T20!"
So the T20 is actually a cricket thing.
"The very fast cricket."
So either these are things that were in the
article that you've plucked words out of
-or they're things in the back of…
-"Too much! Slow it down."
Are you okay there?
We're talking about cricket,
you carry on doing the episode.
Or they're…
or they're things in the back of your head,
well, I'm not sure on that, alright,
-Gary.
-Yes.
Duryard, a town in the south-west of the UK?
-Yeah. What's… what's there?
Exeter.
Is this a small town spread very thin
around Exeter?
It's a county town,
it has an entire county in it!
Hands up, I misunderstood your question,
I thought you were asking what's in the
south-west to which my answer was Exeter.
I didn't realise you were asking
about the town of Duryard.
Is Duryard famous for anything?
For being…
for the people who live there,
it's the centre of their existence, thank you
very much, most of which are students.
-Students. Duryard, Duryard U.
-Duryard … Duryard University.
-Wait, because it's near Exeter.
-Yeah.
That students at the
University of Exeter live there.
There's probably a meaning behind it.
Well, the other two players here are…
both have their head in their hands.
And well they might, at the rightness
of the information I am imparting to you.
I'm just imagining the hoodies that say
Duryard U.
Well, it's not, it's Exeter,
it's the hall of a place they live.
What I like about these, Gary,
is that whether you're telling the truth or not,
you are extremely confident
in what you're saying.
Chris, the town in Nebraska.
The real town…
Unlike, I don't know,
some places in the south-west of England.
One of us speaks the truth,
the other only lies.
Duryard, Nebraska,
incorporated 1870 by Charles Duryard,
notable for nothing very much
being in the corn belt, except a stopping place
for the late westward expansion.
Westwood!
Yo, yo, yo, yo, yo!
Westward expansion, not Westwood,
Westwood is not expanding.
I don't know,
he's getting older, isn't he, he's probably…
Oh no, he's a thin one, he's a thin one.
-Is he still...?
-He's still svelte, yeah.
I mean, my respect to him,
I've not managed it and I'm at least
five years younger than him.
I mean I'm just going to cut
straight to the chase on this one,
I think it's Chris.
Matt, I…
I appreciate Anton Duryard.
And so does New South Wales.
I appreciate the word mononym
that came out of nowhere.
-I love the word mononym.
-And many things that...
but I believe you've pulled them
from your head, I don't think it's you.
-You're going to be sad.
-Gary, Gary,
I don't think there's a town called
Duryard near Exeter where there's a university.
Fine, I didn't say university though.
Chris, I believe you, am I right?
No, there isn't a university in
Duryard, Nebraska either.
-There is no Duryard, Nebraska?
-There is no Duryard, Nebraska.
So we already know I'm wrong.
So two of the people you've just been
really quite dismissive about…
At least 50% of them have every right
to be very upset,
I would say more like 75
the way you've treated some of them.
And, and one of us kept coming up with facts
when you were asking
and the other one kept talking
around in circles.
One of the two people opposite us
did the thing you like
which is give key details.
Matt, Matt, have I have I picked your article
for the third time in a row?
-Are you saying it's me?
-Yeah.
I was the one that was
talking around in circles.
-He kept giving you facts.
-I did!
There's a town called Duryard
with a university in it?
-Duryard.
-Yeah.
"...is an ancient area of Exeter in Devon,
once the hunting land of the Anglo-Saxon kings.
"The name comes from the Anglo-Saxon dear,
which means deer, and geard, which means fold.
"Today, much of the area is occupied by the
University of Exeter
"which has a hall of residence named Duryard."
Blimey! No...
-Unfortunately…
--F*** you up the wrong'un.
Unfortunately, Gary,
-that means you get no points.
-Why?!
Because you did not convince me
of the truth.
Well, that's a shame, but I had fun.
-"Will ye come back next week, Gary?"
-I will!
-"Ah, it'll be grand to see you."
-I had a great time!
Chris, you get a point for successfully
convincing me of…
of a town in Nebraska
with the western expansion.
Matt, I mean, good…
good cricket knowledge.
Thank you,
I know nothing about cricket.
Gary, I will point out that I asked the
question, "what's in Duryard",
and your answer wasn't "a university"
or "a hall of residence", it was, and I quote,
"Exeter".
No, you said… you said "Duryard,
a town in the south-west, what's there",
to which I said "Exeter".
Was I wrong?
I beg to the honourable member,
did I give a mistruth?
It is not my fault if you can't understand
your own bloody question.
He has a point.
Gary's going to go off
and get a replacement article,
we'll see you in a minute.
Good luck, chaps,
we are talking about...
Willoughby Run.
Gary, I'm going to come to you first,
what is Willoughby Run?
-It is a creek in Pennsylvania.
-Oh, that's a surprisingly solid answer.
You see, I'm batting you round like a cat,
one minute he's all shaky,
next he's all confident,
but last time I was shaky,
I was telling the truth.
That's not how the game's meant to work, Gary.
-It's got you on your toes though, to be fair.
-Yeah, well.
Oh, he not sure now!
Yes, Willoughby Run is a creek in Pennsylvania.
Chris, Willoughby Run?
It is a geological formation on the
Willoughby estate derived from the sort of thing
that is currently happening at the Willoughby Run in Pennsylvania due to erosion.
-An eroding...?
-River valley.
An eroding river valley.
Matt, Willoughby Run?
It is an album by jazz multi-instrumentalist,
Roland Kirk.
-It’s a good jazz name.
-It's a good jazz name.
-"That's a jazz name, motherf*****".
-That's...
-Sorry! Wrong meeting.
-That's okay.
-Gary, let's start with you.
-Yes.
Is there anything in the article other than
"it's a creek in Pennsylvania"?
-Adams County.
Pennsylvania, I think it's the Herr Creek
or the Herr River it flows into,
-Hurr!
-As in H-e-r-r, so Mr River.
-Alright.
-There's a picture of it.
What does it look like?
Can you describe it for us?
Well, trees in water.
Trees in water.
-Trees in water.
-Alright.
It's like you get in America, you know,
you get shallow water with all trees in it.
Alright.
This is… this is plausible because I can't…
in my head there isn't a big connection
between, like, "run" and the name of a river
so I feel like that's not something
that would come straight to your head,
so alright, I'll go with that. Chris.
-Hello.
-"You don't have the intelligence
-"to come up with a lie that complex."
-No, it's more than…
-"You idiot boy!"
-It's more that Chris has the exact same thing,
that I don't … like, "run" as a river thing,
as a geological feature,
you have some geological knowledge,
geographical knowledge?
I have a little bit
of geological knowledge, yes.
Tell me about Willoughby Run.
Willoughby Run is a v-shaped valley formed
in Cheshire on the former Willoughby estate
which dug through the native limestone
which is quite soft,
exposing chert nodules for which it is famous.
Exposing what?
Chert nodules.
Could you…
could you tell me about the chert nodules?
Chert… chert is a very hard rock that forms in
weird sort of reniform nodules.
-Reniform?
-Kidney shaped.
-Okay. That makes sense.
-Renal, yeah.
Latin.
He's got a Latin GCSE, do you remember?
This guy, this guy.
Which then get distributed in softer rock
when they rest sediment… er...
sedimentarily, because they don't get to erode
as fast as the rock that they came out of.
That's lovely and I absolutely believe
that's true and all from your head
and not from the article.
Not one bit.
A v-shaped… what did you call it,
something valley?
River erosion valley.
There's two shapes of valleys.
Well, you see that's also plausible.
Matt, an album by Roland Kirk,
do you know who Roland Kirk is?
No. But I looked on the list of
who was in the article, like the…
there is like a track list of the album
and the first track was co-written
by Burt Bacharach.
-Burt Bacharach?
-I know.
It was Burt Bacharach
and I think there's a producer,
the album's… what?
Sorry, I just remembered from years ago,
the phrase "Burt Bacharach
Back Sack and Crack".
It's just... and I can't tell if that's a joke
you're pulling back out of nowhere
or if genuinely Roland Kirk
worked with Burt Bacharach.
Who is Roland Kirk?
You could have just made that name up.
I know I could
and I have done every other time
but actually today I haven't made up the name
Roland Kirk.
It's an actual jazz multi-instrumentalist.
And it said…
this name I'm probably getting wrong,
it said that the album was produced
by Hal Moomin?
I must have got that wrong
because it's not Moomin,
but it's something similar to that.
And I vaguely recognised that name
but I didn't know why
and I didn't follow through
to the other article,
but he co-wrote some of the songs.
And I was scrolling through the track
which was about 10 tracks.
Later on in the album there was a track
that was co-written by two Beatles.
Which two?
Paul McCartney. John Lennon.
It could be an obscure Beatles number
they're covering.
Oh, possibly, yeah. Alright.
- It was from '65, that album.
-Because that'll be the right time,
but I can't remember when the first Beatles
records came out.
If you've picked the wrong year in the 60s,
that's a really obvious clue.
I'm pretty sure it said '65 on the article.
I realise this is the last one we're doing
but I…
in all of the six we've done so far,
this is by far the hardest decision.
All three of these are plausible.
We've finally learnt the game, chaps.
Says you. Me and Matt have both scored points.
-Chris.
-Hello.
-I'm going to rule you out because…
-You bellend.
I think pretty much everything there
has come from your head.
The only connection that I can't see there is
that "run" connected to a geological feature.
I think that … I think you might have
pulled this from your geology,
so I'm going to rule you out on this one.
Matt, I am really tempted to ask the Google
Assistant that I know you have in here
to just...
just play Willoughby Run by Roland Kirk.
But actually, Gary,
I think you gave few details this time,
you didn't come up with something
out of nowhere.
Gary, I believe you, am I right?
-You are correct.
-Yes!
-A point for the both of you.
-Oh!
And there is Willoughby Run.
-Oh, that's lovely.
-All trees in water!
Hey, it is.
It is absolutely all trees in water.
-There you go.
-Yeah, thank you very much, folks.
That's the end of the series.
We still don't have an outro.
-Bye!
But here's something for the end of the video,
I knew this was the last one we were doing.
I was telling you about the Roland Kirk album
'Slightly Latin'.
Oh, you're metagaming this.
I don't like this(!)