This is the Technical Difficulties
and we are
Two Of These People Are Lying,
because two of these people will be.
- Joining me are: Chris Joel.
- Hello.
- Gary Brannan.
- Hot and spicy casserole... by the yard.
And Matt Gray.
Is that a length or is it outside?
That's the noise your
mother made lasht night(!)
Anyway, the way this game works
is the three of us have all random-ish-ly
picked some Wikipedia articles
and written down the names or titles
of those articles on these pieces of card.
Tom is now going to pick
one of those articles
and all three of us will claim
that it's the one that we chose
and claim that we know anything about it.
What happens though is only one of us
is telling the truth and
two of us are telling a lie.
And today we are talking
about Ghost Festival.
Yes, it is annoying me that this is
slightly at a jaunty angle on here.
And I can't decide which way to hold it.
Ghost Festival, let's go
around the table on this one.
Matt, what is Ghost Festival?
It's actually "Hhost" Festival
and it's in Croatia.
Okay, uh, Gary, what's Ghost Festival?
A spiritual celebration in China.
Spiritual celebration in China.
Chris?
A series of minor vehicular events in
the American Midwest.
"Minor vehicular events"?
Okay, that was a horrible
way to phrase it.
It was a little festival that popped up in
the late 2010's when ghost riding
was big "on the YouTubes, yo".
Where you would gather
together in your mini-truck
or other vehicle and
ghost ride around a town,
well probably not around a town,
probably at some pre-determined car park
or some s***.
For young'uns out there, ghost riding?
Keeping your car moving while stepping
outside it doing funny poses,
generally styling it out,
probably not an accurate
phrase for the subculture,
so sue me!
And obviously as anything
gets big, somebody goes
"I'll do a festival!
"I can't afford or be bothered
to organise a festival..."
then somebody else takes it
over, then it dies in ignominy.
That's how most of these things work.
- Yeah.
- Where's Ignominy?
In the American Midwest!
Actually there is almost certainly a town
called, like, Ignominy, Nebraska isn't there?
Also, also, you'd watch that
Western wouldn't you?
- What?
- The Town Called Ignominy.
Oh yeah.
Mind you, that's probably
like, what's his name,
Bergman does a Western,
just a lot of people sat there going--
Is "Birdman" Batman's brother?
Bergman, not Birdman!
I thought you said Birdman as well, sorry.
Ingmar Birdman? [squawks]
Oh Ingmar Ber-- I know Ingmar Bergman!
I just thought you said "Birdman".
You're playing chess
with death but it is--
[squawks]
But it's a f***er wrecked as a crow.
"Actually I think you'll find that is
the accurate imagery, hm."
- "With respect to there of, hm."
- "Hmm, hmm, yes."
Ghost riding festival
in the-- the wilds of America?
Well not really the wilds, but the Midwest.
The flat bits, you don't want to do it
on a steep hill do you?
Not California, not New York.
- Bit in the middle.
- Downhill ghost riding.
Oh that's risky, that's risky, just
keep running to catch up with it.
- It's like cheese-rolling but vehicular.
- With a car!
Spiritual celebration in China?
Yes.
Do you know anything more about it?
It's a spiritual celebration in China
where they celebrate ghosts
is the short answer.
Gary, I'm just going to remind you--
I know the bloody rules,
I'm working my way round it all right?
You're going to have to
convince me that it's true.
Sometimes--
You don't get a point if
it is true on your side
and you convince me it's false.
Sometimes these articles, you have to be
blunt at the start, when you say
"what is a spiritual
celebration in China?"
the answer is it's a spiritual
celebration in China,
I think it's in the
seventh month of the year
you celebrate your--
celebrate ghosts,
they're unleashed from hell
and they come round
and this is what you're going to be like,
"you're making this up" but I'm not,
the ghosts have very thin necks
'cause they're not allowed to eat.
So you leave food out for them and stuff
but they're not allowed to eat
because they're ghosts
- they have lots of celebrations...
- He's just writing "t***"!
I know!
And it's pronounced 'thwaite'.
Thin necks, I'm writing thin necks!
Right, and you burn paper,
you have lanterns
and all that kind of stuff,
as you have in any of these
traditional Eastern celebrations.
It's probably a little bit like Day of the Dead
in Mexico, that kind of thing.
Not the film?
Not the film!
You can make a film of it I suppose.
What something really artsy and slow?
Really thin-necked ghosts.
Matt, it's a celebration in Croatia?
It's a festival rather than a celebration
but it's not like a music festival
it was 2011, it only ran for one year,
in an old, I can't think
of the word, mansion-y
like what's a cliff mansion called?
- Scary.
- Clifford.
Clifford the...?!
Clifford the cliff-top mansion?
That's a very different kids' book!
It's in an old house on a hill.
No, no, hold on, hold on we're still--
Clifford the big red mansion!
"All the children wanted
to play in Clifford
"but Clifford was too dangerous..."
Is that the one in Scarborough that
fell off the cliff that time?
Clifford the big red brick mansion.
Croatia, Matt?
It is a music, but
also creative arts festival
happening in a big house in Croatia
and it's got catacombs or tombs--
Ooh, say that again.
It's got catacombs or tombs--
Oh, that was less good that time.
Within the tombs there
are people, I don't know,
showing their wares, doing
like little arty things
and a few bands played in
the ballroom of it as well.
There weren't any I'd heard of.
- Well, it was Croatia in 2011?
- Yeah.
It's a small festival in--
It's before it got popular but, yeah.
See I was really hoping that I'd be able
to throw one of these out immediately.
Well just chuck Gary's, that's standard.
Yeah that's just standard, isn't it, yeah.
Have you been to the place he mentioned?
No, I'm not chucking Gary's,
'cause Gary's sounds,
Gary's the one I'm most
sure about at this point.
Well!
I like "minor vehicular events".
I really wish I'd not used that phrase!
Get a T-shirt with that on.
"I like minor vehicular events."
But I feel like it would have
been "Ghost Riding Festival",
something like that, it
don't think it would've
made it to Wikipedia so
I don't think it's that.
Have you see what's on Wikipedia?
I was going to say, having
trawled through some s***
on the train today, to
come up with articles...
Matt, I like everything about it
and it sounds like an
event I'd like to see
but the thing that killed it for me
was you going "it's
pronounced Hhost Festival"
Yeah, it has the IPA in the front of it,
it made no sense,
it didn't describe it but it
I'm obviously guessing the
IPA, 'cause I can't read IPA
but it didn't look like
what I would've expected.
If it was Ghost Festival
it wouldn't have had the IPA right?
Yeah, yeah. That's for
International Phonetic Alphabet
Not India Pale Ale, Gary.
I was kind of hoping
there, I mean--
Gary, I think it's you.
I think, and this might just be something
dredged off my mind that I'm confusing
with some other festival
that I've heard of
but Gary, I think it's you, am I right?
You think I'd be telling the truth
about the festival of thin-necked ghosts
that aren't allowed to eat?
Yes.
Correct!
Yes!
It is-- I shall reveal the legend--
"During the month the gates
of hell are opened up
"and ghosts are free to
roam the Earth where they
"seek food and entertainment."
Rather like opening up an
old people's home.
"These ghosts are believed to be ancestors
of those who forgot to pay tribute to them
"after they died, or those never given
proper ritual send off.
"They have long needle-thin
necks because they have not
"been fed by their family,
or as a punishment
"so that they are unable to swallow."
Right!
"Family members offer prayers
to their deceased relatives,
"offer food and drink,"
this is the best bit,
"and burn hell bank notes"!
- I've heard of that!
- What?
They're special paper fake bank notes,
made for the ceremony, I've heard of that.
Yeah, Gary, congratulations,
a point to you.
Yay!
- A point to me for guessing correctly
- Boo!
which I'm quite happy about.
And Gary, you need to go and find
a new article for the second half.
Gary has gone and got a new article.
I'm going to pick one
at random from this pile
Have you shuffled?
I have shuffled thoroughly!
- Thoroughly?
- Thorough-shuffle.
- How horrible.
- I know! And we have...
the 1878 North Lancashire by-election.
Now, there are a few things I can guess
from this title: it's a by-election,
in North Lancashire, in 1878, so
no, you know what?
Maybe it isn't, maybe it's something else.
I'm going to start with Chris this time.
The 1878 North Lancashire by-election
was a by-election in
North Lancashire, in 1878.
Do you want to tell me
something special about it?
Why on earth does that
have a Wikipedia article?
It happened on the 8th of April
because some guy, first
name or surname was Stanley,
I forget which, who was the incumbent
got made minister of, no, general--
- Crabs!
- No!
Had to go to hospital due
to unforeseen circumstances
with a lady that wasn't his
wife, don't write this down,
this is about me and
him talking about crabs.
Alright, okay.
Because he got made,
what's high up? Not Prime Minister--
Privy Councillor?
No, next--
Cabinet?
Yeah, something--
First Sea Lord?
Minister of war, something of war,
Chief something of war.
Alright.
Chief of War!
Boss of War, but not right
at the top of the tree.
Alright, incidentally, yes,
there is a First Sea Lord.
That's the head of the sea.
- Yes.
- The head of the Navy, isn't it?
He's King Navy.
I do like the fact that if we,
if Britain ever has a Space Force,
there will be the First Space Lord.
You'd have the job just for
the title, wouldn't you?
Marvel will sue.
Oh yeah, fair.
Lord of Space, just enough
to get round the trademark.
Slightly different theme-tune, just
two or three notes off-key at the end.
Gary, the 1878 North
Lancashire by-election?
That was a by-election held for the
North Lancashire constituency in 1878, which...
smart-arse...
is notable for the
winning candidate being dead.
Oh, now I know that's
definitely happened in the past.
Alright, winning candidate being dead.
Can't have happened in the future...?
Alright, Matt, the 1878
North Lancashire by-election?
- It didn't happen.
- Oh!
It was due to happen but it didn't.
Alright, let's... so we've got
one where the incumbent
became Minister of War--
Whatever it is, I feel like it was
a longer title than that.
Alright, one where the
winning candidate was dead
and one where it just didn't happen.
Matt, why didn't it happen?
Agricultural protests.
Oh!
All of the candidates were...
what's the word, seeming to be
championing a lot of the
newer technologies of the time
and all of the factory kind of stuff,
and that was driving work
away from the farmland.
So a farmer's union, were
tying to recognise the fact
that no one was representing them
and protested the by-election.
Like, tractors everywhere and stuff.
There's absolutely nothing
funny about that but--
I dunno, "tractors everywhere" is
sentence of the week as far as I'm concerned!
Opens under-stairs cupboard: tractor!
Just kind of rearing up and going for you.
Out of the fields!
"Thank you, mother, for the gruel -- aargh!"
They've got, like, bouncy suspension.
Ghosts riding their tractors!
I was just thinking Alfred Hitchcock's
'The Birds' but with tractors.
What, flying around a
room with Tippi Hedren?
Yes! Yes. Exactly that.
In a phone box!
Gary, the main candidate was dead?
What happened then?
Well he kind of got buried,
which is the normal thing that happens.
I though you were going
to say he got better!
Was there then another
by-election or did he actually--
Well, yes there was, because the winner,
I stress again,
was dead.
I mean, they haven't, you know--
Didn't he just serve out his term
very quietly in the corner?
Well it's 1878, maybe they didn't have
a procedural for that.
So you think they just transported a
flipping corpse to the House of Commons?
No! I just thought there'd be an empty chair!
It would've been more
useful than some of them.
Wheeey!
Unexpectedly ended up
briefly Prime Minister
around about the start
of the First World War
Like, the rod up the back to stay upright.
Someone had to crouch behind him to give
the maiden speech. What is this?
Weekend at Bernie's, only
parliamentary?
Weekend at Black Rod's!
No, he was dead, you prat!
I said that at the start,
stone actual dead.
He died during the course of the count.
Yes-- during the course of the count?
- Yes.
- "One, aha ha ha!"
Takes hours.
Not during the campaign, during the count?
Well, if he'd died during the campaign
it would be rather unfair to elect him.
- You'd think most people--
- This is what I was...
Right, exactly!
This is why I was confused.
He died in the course of the count,
so during the course of
the counting of the ballots
he had a heart attack and died,
or collapsed, you know
you assuming these things,
no one actually looked too closely
but, he were dead.
And then won?
Well he'd died but no one had realised,
they just thought he hadn't turned up
for the announcement of the result
so they read it all out,
The Member, I think it was Lord Stanley
or something, was duly elected
as a representative of the constituency
of North Lancashire and he's, you know--
Julie was elected?
Yeah, well he's dead isn't he?
Somebody's got to...
So obviously, it takes time for them to organise another by-election,
you can't just go
"oh shall we just have another go"?
So for a brief period of time,
their representative was,
and I stress this again,
a corpse.
All right.
And may I say he's one
of the best they had.
Corpses or politicians?
Yes.
Hoo. Gary...
- Good god!
- Gary, I'm going to rule you out.
I'm going to rule you out
because I think that's
just a story from
somewhere else that you've
tacked on to that and I
don't think it's yours.
The man is, of course, an expert in
late nineteenth century
North Lancashire politics.
I refuse to believe you know anything
about anything from Lancashire.
That's fair.
And I know it just for
the pure price of mockery.
I genuinely can't pick between you two.
I think if it didn't happen,
there wouldn't be an article about it.
I think it would be
under something bigger.
So Chris, I think your man
becoming Minister of War
is the most likely one
there, I think it's you,
- am I right?
- It is!
Yes, two for two!
And as was the spirit of the
time, he returned unopposed.
Oh right, okay.
Secretary of State for War,
I knew it was a bigger--
- Secretary of State for War.
- Wow, there we go.
Frederick Stanley, with a K.
- In Stanley?
Yeah!
"Oh, an obvious joke,
let's all go for that!"
Frederick Stanley.
Frederick Stanlick.
Stanlick!
"The K is silent, it's pronounced Stanley."
Congratulations then,
I can't believe I'm saying this
but there's one point to Gary,
there's one point to Chris...
Oh no. We've handed him the win.
I've got two points, I've won a thing!
Yay(!)
Wow, thank you for that sarcasm!
From Chris Joel,
Gary Brannan! Matt Gray!
Still don't have an outro.
No, we still don't.
Bye!