This is the Technical Difficulties,
and this is an experiment.
For the very first time,
I do not have a laptop in front of me.
I do not have any of the facts;
one of these three do.
Introducing Chris Joel.
I just like the idea that this
is literally the first time
since you turned about 14 that
you don't have a laptop in front of you.
That's pretty accurate.
Gary Brannan.
I adore distilled whippet s***.
And...
What's that a quote from?
Tom Baker.
Matt Gray.
The thing is, I can never say anything here
because I have to follow that up.
When you say 'that',
do you mean Gary or Gary's line?
-Gary.
-Okay.
Don't refer to me as "that"!
-The object over here.
-Fine, Gary's content!
****er put me in the nominative.
T-shirt.
Do him up the nominative!
Accusative!
Here's what's going to happen.
Actually, Matt,
why don't you tell them what's going to happen?
So he was sat around the corner with some
headphones on and each of the three of us
found a Wikipedia article
and we didn't show it to one another.
Tom is now going to pick up one of the titles
of the Wikipedia articles,
which we've put on the pieces of paper
down there
and we're all going to act
like we know what we're on about
and Tom has to guess which one of us
is talking s***
and which ones of us is telling the truth.
Alright, are we ready?
Going for this one.
Kebakko.
Now, can I say, called it:
because I said you would open it like that
and then do that.
A number of times to make sure
that he was perfectly encapsulating.
Chris.
Chris, I'm going to start with you,
what's kebakko?
Kebakko is a Polish sausage company,
kielbasa company, formed mid-70s
but died out in the early 80s
due to declining profits.
I mean that is entirely plausible,
Gary, what…
That's the idea of the game, Tom.
I know, but you know what's also important,
me commenting on what I think of your statement.
Conversation is how this show works.
Sorry, I'm not used to you
having an active role.
Neither am I.
I love the idea of a show where you just sit there
and go 'hmm, yeah' to every statement.
-And now the...
-Brannan, what is kebakko?
Kebakko is a type of Finnish convenience food,
it's a bit like a meatball,
-it's a bit like a kebab.
-Hmm.
A meatball on a stick.
-Correct.
-If that was true, that would be great.
It sounds awesome.
I really need, like, notebooks here
for me to write this down.
"Who said what to whom?"
You're not having a laptop!
Mr Gray, what is kebakko?
It's funny that you introduced me as Mr Gray
for that, it's actually a family name.
-Oh!
-Yeah, Marcel Kebakko was the, you know,
more famous of them
and they were touring circus artists.
You're all significantly better at bluffing
and improvising than I am,
I definitely need …
can we just … can I get a pen?
I actually need a pen and paper for this
so I can make notes.
Pause.
There.
Those are hands, Gary, not paws.
-Gary.
-Yes.
The Finnish snack food.
I have been to Finland,
I have been to convenience stores,
I do not believe that kebakko
is a thing I can buy there.
Well, you're a ****.
Sorry, what do you want me to say back to that?
It is!
What, so you've been to a multitude of snack…
of snack... dispensaries
and not seen this particular food?
He's checked every major brand
the length of the country.
Tom Scott only believes
what he has actually encountered.
Let's face it, if there was a product
that was balls on a stick,
Tom would know.
-Oh! Wow!
-You're right.
Wait. "Meatball dispensary."
We just glossed over a meatball dispensary.
Ball, ball, ball.
Is it like a gum ball machine,
you put your five cents and you get a meatball?
I see you have both been to Finland.
Full of marinara sauce,
it comes out pre-glazed.
You have your point,
it comes with a sauce,
it comes with…
it comes with a sauce.
I like how you said that
as you're reaching down.
It comes.
It comes with a sauce(!)
-Dipping sauces.
-Get your balls on a stick.
-Balls on a stick.
-They come with a sauce.
Balls on a stick covered in a spicy sauce,
do you have a problem with this?
I've got to be honest,
meatballs on a stick is an entirely plausible
Finnish food to have.
Yeah.
I just worry that what you've actually done
is taken meatballs from IKEA in Sweden
and desperately tried to backsolve
through kebab, so I think Gary,
-I'm going to rule yours out.
-F***!
It's down between...
Wow! "I am sorry, your arguing skills
are that bad, you're just... no."
Well, the case for the prosecution rests on the
fact that he never saw one
when he was
in Finland that time, there we go.
Matt, tell me more about
the travelling circus artist,
what sort of circus acts did they do?
They were actually notable
for the fact that they …
it was all, like, human pursuits,
I can't think of the phrase they used for that
in the article,
but, so it was all like trapezey
or swingy or, you know,
rather than animals doing things.
Which for the time
-which I think was 1850 something.
-Was it gymnastics, I guess?
Yeah, it didn’t use that word, it used
something…
There'll be a circus word.
Yeah, there was a circus word for it,
and they started off in,
I think it was near Lille,
and then made their way around Europe.
-And eventually got married to a Judith which…
-Judith!
-if you heard me giggling while you were
in the kitchen,
Marcel and... Judith Kebakko.
I was about to go no,
it's definitely Chris,
but that tiny little detail about Judith
is either the best bit of plausible rubbish
you've ever had or just a wonderful name.
-Is that a compliment?
Judith is a very plausible name.
-Yeah.
-I believe in people called Judith.
Judith the gymnast.
If I was to come up with a couple's name
off the top of my head...
It wouldn't be Marcel and Judith,
this is what gets me.
Marcel and Judith.
That's a genuinely difficult decision
between the two of you. Gary...
It's just discounted.
...you are half price.
-Doesn’t exist?
-No, I don't believe that.
Matt, I believe you. Am I right?
Yeah, you're right if you're saying
that I'm talking s***.
Oh!
I absolutely was sat here
for the last five minutes
trying to think of a wife's name
other than Judith.
You went with Judith!
And weirdly that was the most convincing
part of the entire bloody story.
That's what convinced me!
That was the last bit!
I was sat there thinking,
his wife wouldn't be called Judith!
No, I'm just going to have to sell it,
it's Judith.
Why did Judith get stuck there?
I was trying to think of a French sounding
or a German sounding female name.
Well, that's simple, Judith.
So just to be clear,
everything Matt said was a lie,
none of that is factual?
-Yeah, correct, yeah.
-Chris.
Also bulls***.
-Really?
-Mm-hmm.
F*** you.
F*** you. F*** you,
right in the ******* ***, there it is.
That was the least plausible!
Meatballs on a stick,
why would you put a meatball on a stick?
So you can hold it while you eat it,
it's a kebab.
Right, can I read it?
"It consists of meat, breadcrumbs, onions,
"eggs and spices,
the difference is mostly in shape
"instead of a ball,
kebakko can also be a piece of meat
"on a wooden stick and usually sold
in packs of 4 to 12.
"The name comes from the Turkish food,
kebab."
Wow!
I just… I envisioned this, like, long stick,
like you're roasting marshmallows or something
with a meatball on the end,
which does not seem like a good way
to eat a meatball.
"The usual way to eat them is to heat them
and serve them with various sauces for dipping,
-"the stick enables the kebakkos to be dipped
and eaten by hand."
So it's like a tiny little toothpick stick,
right, okay.
No, I think there's a little stick
and you just dip it in the sauce like a kebab.
Well, put it this way,
you know when you get a kebab, Tom?
-Yeah.
-The gesture you were doing before...
-Not a good way.
Do you eat a f***ing kebab like that
or do you have it sideways on?
-The man's a genius.
-I just thought it was like…
I was seeing like small meatballs on sticks,
like cocktail things.
Right.
Point to Gary.
A point, no, a point to Matt.
-A point to Matt.
-A point to Matt for convincing me,
congratulations, Judith.
Does that mean I win the show?
Depends, how long has the show been going
on for? We haven't worked this out yet.
We have taken a moment,
Gary has gone and got himself a new article
to replace kebakko.
There are three new ones in there,
so I do not know.
Please let mine come out again.
Yeah, it could be Gary's a second time,
let's pick it from down here and it is…
Folded.
Lentokenttä. Lentokenttä,
and we will start with Matt on this one,
Matt, what is Lentokenttä?
Amusingly, considering the previous one,
this is a region of Finland.
Region of Finland, yeah,
do you want to tell me any more about it?
Nah, you can ask later.
All right. Gary.
Amusingly, considering the previous entry,
this is a region of Russia,
now on the Finnish border,
in fact it's the music that comes
from that region,
traditionally played on the nose flute.
I'm almost tempted to just immediately strike
that because it was nearly there
until the words 'nose flute'.
And how well did these theories work last time?
-This is why I haven't struck it yet.
-I thought you were going to go the other way,
I thought you just weren't even going
to ask me and it's like, "it's the nose flute",
"F*** it, it's clearly the nose flute."
-Nose flute music.
-Yeah.
From a region of Russia
near the Finnish border?
-Correct.
-Chris.
Lentokenttä or "Lentokenttä!" is a fake Swedish
thrash metal band formed in 1983 in Detroit.
Wow!
Fake Swedish, what was that, something metal?
-Thrash.
-Thrash metal band.
So you've given me three entirely
plausible answers there.
Gary, let's start with you this time.
Just get the s*** out of the way first.
We're going to probe this s*** now are we?
-Yes, Gary.
-It's a spider.
-Is that in shot?
-Yes!
Spider!
-Gary.
-Yeah.
Lentokenttä,
could you tell me any more about it?
Well, the... the clue is actually in the title,
lento is a word that can be used in Finnish
to mean slow, so it's quite slow music
and it's quite mournful
and the nose flute,
though it may sound ridiculous,
when you think about it,
it actually makes perfect sense.
Mournful parp on the nose flute.
Don't mock cultural traditions, Matthew!
We're going to mispronounce it,
we're going to mock them.
Yeah, because if you're in the kind of climes
that you get on the Russia/Finnish border,
you're going to have your mouth covered up
with a scarf.
So you're more likely to play these things
through your nose
because it's the bit
you leave uncovered to breathe.
Actually that's interesting because that makes
sense for the band name as well
because then it's a pun on how fast the music
is rather than being slow and mournful.
So yeah, it's slow, it's mournful,
it's kind of used at funerals
but it's just because your mouth is covered,
you have what is called a nose flute,
I can't really pronounce it properly
in Finnish,
but you play it by blowing down there
and it makes a slow and mournful noise.
Do you have to pronounce it through the
nose flute, is that why you can't do it?
It helps, I imagine.
Get him a couple of straws out of the kitchen
and see how he does.
Although I have just read a Wikipedia article
on this, I have not played a nose flute,
so I cannot comment in detail
on the experience.
No, you see, the problem is,
Tom once went to near-Russia
and nobody was being buried with a nose flute.
To be fair,
Matt and I have been to that border,
we have both…
we both literally sat just a metre
or two from that border.
It's a very long border though.
-It's a very long border.
-Pipes stuffed up each nostril playing…
The thing is, I don't actually find that
entirely implausible.
Thank you, because it's f***ing true,
that's why.
Matt, all you have said so far
is "region of Finland"
and I refuse to believe that in the time you
spent looking at
presumably just the first few paragraphs
of the Wikipedia article,
all you got was region of Finland.
If only there was a way of giving
myself more time to come up with the answer.
Could you tell me more
about the region of Finland?
Yeah, it's in the south,
it's near Helsinki
and only 12 people live there...
ish.
-12ish.
-How big is this region?
I don't know, it didn't say,
but it's got an airport in it.
12 people and an airport.
Yet, it employs…
-I thought he was going to say Yeti.
-Yeti?
-Yeti!
-In an airport?
My brain went snowy. Yeti.
Welcome to Yeti Airport, Lentokenttä Yeti.
Yeah, but the Yeti's dressed as like a fifties
stewardess in my imagination.
Hair coming out of the…
between the…
well, basically like this shirt.
No, it's a uniform designed for a Yeti,
isn't it?
Oh, I want it squeezed in with all the fur.
No, I got that.
No, it's fully fitted to the Yeti, it's fine,
even the wee hat looks in proportion.
So that's quite a big hat then?
Well, yeah, but you know,
on a Yeti it looks small.
Alright, is that all I'm getting from you?
It's a region, south of Finland.
Yeah.
12 people live there,
but it employs a couple of thousand
because there's an airport there.
Helsinki Airport,
Vantaa Airport, I think it's called
because that's the closest place,
but Helsinki's the place people go to.
This is worth it just for the pained
Tom expressions.
-It's such a lovely change in dynamics.
-It is, it is because twice in a row
we're talking about…
we've talked about Finland
and I've spent some time in Finland,
and I've been wrong on this before.
And I immediately want to strike this off
because of course Helsinki Airport isn't…
it's near a town called Vantaa,
you've said it,
that it's Helsinki Vantaa Airport.
But I cannot conclusively say that the region
is not some area called Lentokenttä.
Well, I can add one bit if it helps.
Sure?
I'm not … I'm only going to get it slightly right
because I only read it a couple of minutes ago,
Airtropolis is kind of what they call the area.
Oh, that's cool.
-Airtropolis?
-That is awesome.
Wow!
No. No, I'm ruling you out, Matt,
it's one of these two, I'm ruling you out.
That sounds like something out of LazyTown,
sorry, Airtropolis.
It's about the right scale, isn't it,
total population 12,
name of the area, Airtropolis.
Full of talking planes.
And how can you think I'm lying?
Gary.
Oh, here we go again.
You haven't even gone to Chris yet.
Trustworthy face,
he can't see the lies through the beard.
Why am I getting a full body cavity search?
Because Chris came out…
Because to be fair,
yours mentions body cavities.
Yeah! Yeah it does.
Is the nose a cavity?
Yeah. Yes. Nasal cavity.
Look, it's a cavity,
I can put my fingers in it.
Well, I've never seen in a full body…
I mean a full body cavity search,
I've seen the odd…
up that, you know,
but I've never seen them go, and the nose.
You haven't watched enough episodes
of Border Force.
In fairness you're right on that front.
I'm getting pins and needles from laughing!
I can't hear what he's saying, can you?
-He's got pins and needles from laughing.
-I'm getting pins and needles through laughing...
I think it's this posture.
His shirt is cutting off his circulation
to his hands.
It feels like I've laughed myself into...
He's laughed himself into a circulatory
disorder, look at what you've done.
A lot of coal miners died that way.
This isn't funny.
-This is how all the comedians go.
-Yes.
The reason I'm not going for Chris
is the 1983 Detroit, it's just…
That's because that's where
they were formed and when!
Like I don't have much to ask you,
like do you know more about their music,
do you know about their…?
Six albums, broke up in 1990, one single
that bothered the charts for like metal,
if  whatever particular chart it is
came in at number 12.
The Billboard rock chart.
Billboard, whatever they're relevant to,
came in at number 12,
that was their brief spike
then sort of disbanded in ignomi...
ig-no-mi-ny.
That's easy for you to say.
It is if I put my teeth in now.
I think this is more likely
to be the fake metal…
the fake thrash metal band than it is…
No, they were a real thrash metal band,
they were fake Swedish.
-Fake Swedish.
-Because they're from Detroit.
I think that's more likely than funereal
border music based on the nose flute.
Here we go again.
So, Chris, I believe you, was I right?
No, it's bollocks. It's bu*******.
Wrong.
Matt?!
It's a region of Finland with 12 people
and an airport.
And I'm going to correct: Aviapolis.
-Aviapolis.
-Which is no less cool.
So both times, the person I have struck out
first has been the correct one.
The moral of this story,
don't be on jury service with Tom.
Don't be on trial when Tom's on jury service.
Shall I give you a quick summary
not from my memory?
Yeah.
"Lentokenttä, which in English means airfield,
"is a district..."
I've killed them.
It means airfield!
"There's no such place!
I have flown into Helsinki,
-"it can't possibly be!"
-How did I not know the Finnish word for airport?!
It is a district of Vantaa.
Yeah. Helsinki Vantaa Airport.
And the district is part of the
Aviapolis major region
and has been named after
the Helsinki Airport situated there.
Helsinki, it's literally the Finnish
for airport, how did I not know that?
It's the largest single job concentration
of all of Vantaa, 11,000 people work there
but only 12 people live there.
Ah, yes.
"Can't possibly be! Strike it from the record,
no chance!"
What we've learned here is that I'm useless
without a laptop in front of me.
And that's why this game is good.
It works, baby. I love this.
That's been the Technical Difficulties,
that's been Chris Joel.
I demand a third!
That's been Gary Brannan.
That's been Matt Gray.
We'll see you next time.