So let's just take a quick look - and
honestly this very daring of me. I've
actually put out the routine that does
this in C and will provide this for you
If you don't believe that this works
just compile the program I give you and
run it and say "Wow! it does work, it
doesn't crash!"  What I've done here is
I've just called it InsertThing. Those of you
who watched my previous [Pointer Power!] video
will say:  "Oh! but last time you had to
have special cases. You had to say: "Is it
inserting at the front, inserting in the
middle or inserting at the end? And are
we safe against inserting into a NULL list?"
This is so magic it takes care
of all of them! I only need one routine -
InsertThing. What it says, if you look
here, is the following:
Give me a pointer to a pointer to the
start of the list, this time. Not just a
pointer to the start. I want a pointer
to a pointer to the start. And also,
behind the scenes, and before you ever call
me up, prepare a THING here (a THING *
actually)  and this is going to be my
"burgers" object. I'm gonna feed that into
this routine saying: go on, insert it. So
that second argument is the THING to be
inserted, pre-prepared [tautology! apologies]
You can look in my coding and see the
preparation routine that makes a new
THING for you. Here we go, look:
THING **tracer = head;
That's exactly what we were doing on the LEGO.
We started off by making `tracer' point to
the head of the list at the beginning.
And again, things in C are declared by
their contents. `tracer's contents are **THING
So, Sean, what about `tracer'
itself? If I wanted to point at `tracer'
even. What's the type of the *box* `tracer'
if its *contents* are ** THING?
>> Sean: Well, it's gonna have three stars right?
>> DFB: Yeah! (in unison): " *** THING "
Yes, we start off at the head and
then this - it looks terrifying but it
actually is very straightforward.
It's basically he's saying
"While the thing that `tracer' points at
isn't a NULL" Now, if you look back on the
model, you start off by the `tracer'
pointing at the contents of the start
element `head'. Right, so you forcibly
dereference `tracer' once and you say: "That
blue box I'm pointing to at the moment. Let's
look at its contents - are they NULL, because if
so I'm at the head of the list?" No if you're not
NULL - remember this - this is the logical
double-& connector.  it says: "As long as
the THING *, that `tracer' is pointing into
isn't NULL and as long as - the string
compare is basically saying - and as long
as the new THING you want to put in is
still later in the alphabet than what
you are looking at, then carry on going
around this loop. But eventually what
should happen - if it's not a null list or
you don't get to the end the list - is
eventually you'll find your string
compare gives you the alphabetic
go-ahead. It's basically saying: "You've
got "burgers", you're looking at "chips" on
the existing list and that's it, stop!
"burgers" goes before "chips" so you come
out of the loop. If you don't come out
the loop you keep on going around the loop.
And here is the absolutely amazing thing:
it's that when at any stage you find
that the blue box you're pointing at
doesn't lead to what you're interested
in - you've not gone far enough down the
list and it's not NULL -  all you do is you move
that `tracer' pointer literally onto a
[next] blue box. You get the address of the blue
box within the structure. And that is
what this terrifying thing [in the program] does.
Here, I shall say this very carefully, it's
not exactly C's finest hour; it's a bit
terrifying when you first see it: (*tracer)
basically says "dereference `tracer'
once and go and look at the innards of a
blue box". That is done by saying
dereference tracer once and take the
next field of what you see. But, I don't
want the *contents* of the blue
box - the next part of the THING -  I want
its *address*. So, right at the front of all
this that single ampersand, means
"address of". So, as you're winding down
the list you're making `tracer' point to
the address of the next box that is
further along down the list. And you
keep on doing that until either you hit
NULL or you find an alphabetically correct
insertion point inside the THING. But
some people will say: "Surely it
matters which of those stopped the loop ?!"
No, it doesn't! The really magic
thing about this is that here's your
splicing routine at the end - just two
lines of code.  It's basically saying make
your new pointer - make its next field be
dereferenced `tracer'. And make *tracer be
the address of the new THING. It doesn't
matter if those THINGs are got to the
bottom of the list and you've hit NULL.
Believe me, look at it, work it out for
yourself. If I were to put in "zucchini" it
will put it in at the bottom of the list.
It will cope with the NULL. It needs no extra
special-case coding! That's the story
really that by going one level of
abstraction out, in terms of pointers and
given that you close your eyes to the C
syntax of how it does it - you've got a
really lovely thing which in one compact
routine takes care of all cases. So, why
isn't this better known about? Well, my
friends tell me that if I only had had more
exposure to assembler, in the 60s, I'd
have been taught this by somebody. It's
been known for years - it's old hat,
nothing new. My reaction when I saw this
was: "Well I wonder if other languages can
do it?"  Certainly our Algol 68 could, though.
it was hideously difficult, even
harder than in C, to do it in Algol 68?
But it could do. In C we took one
look at it said: "Yeah! it does it
differently, and it's got this `address of',
it can do it. And we did and proved it. So,
what about C++. Yeah! anything you can do
in C you can do in C++, because the one is
a superset of the other.
Java? No, when James Gosling invented Java he
didn't like the idea of user-level
pointers because they're dangerous and
you make mistakes. There's been a lot of
discussion about this already and
actually I totally agree with that view
They can be dangerous but sometimes
right down near the bare metal you love
and adore having techniques like this
because they enable you to do things
quickly and compactly. OK, so Java
can't do it and I don't think, having seen
the comments, that Apple's new Swift will
be able to do it. If you ban pointers at
the user level you can't do it. Some
old-timers may say:  "But what about Pascal?"
Yeah, Pascal has pointers but it won't
let you have pointers to pointers.
I strongly suspect that in the end,
frustratingly, it'll get so close in
Pascal but will not actually able to do it.
BCPL? That's where it came from [in C] anyway.
I am seeking confirmation of this from my
BCPL consultants and gurus but I think
BCPL can do this all right it's got @
as the address operator, not &.
So, there we are folks. Bottom line is a
little bit of extra abstraction - and you
think that's going to make it more
obscure and more non-obvious - but the
thing is in the end it actually makes it
more compact, neat and general-purpose.