>> Sean: It's interesting -- one thing that's kind of
struck me straightaway is [that] you
mentioned linked lists.  I've got it ringing
in my head that we did a video on linked lists
and people commented: "Nobody ever uses linked lists
in real life."  Would you say they're used here
because this is just for one or two elements here and there?
>> BWK: I think they're used here because it's
a data structure that expands gracefully.
In other words if we don't know when we
create that original table how many
items there are going to be in a
particular use of a particular slot in
the table, and so the linked list has the
advantage that it grows very gracefully
if something else, you know, if it keeps
going like this, the linked list adapts
very nicely.  This, changing the size of an
array like this, is kind of a biggish
operation, you don't want to do it very
often, but adding a single element to a
linked list is really easy.  If it's a
hash table you could add it either at
the end or you could add at the beginning;
doesn't matter what the order is in that
sense.  So linked list actually makes a
lot of sense for this context, and it's
only a singly linked list, which
is the easy one, because you don't
have to go backwards; you're always just
looking down to see whether something is
there or not.
So no, the linked list is an absolutely
useful data structure for this.  But, and
this is one of these things are kind of
intriguing and perhaps the reason why I
said that associative arrays are "if
you're only going to have one data
structure it's the one to have": you can
fake anything else with an associative
array.  So if that's your primitive
operator as it is in a language like Awk
for example, then with that associative
array you can make any other kind of
data structure that you want.  It may be a
little clunky, it may not run very fast,
but it's perfectly fine.
So for example suppose, and here I am
let's call it in Awk,
I want to build an array whose indexes
are the integers from 0 to whatever, just as
we're used to.  Well, gee, X of 0 --
that's a perfectly fine value.  I would
probably want to convert it to a string.
And then X of 1 is a perfectly fine
value.  It's like they're all there, no
cost, because this is really X of 0,
like that, right?  So, no problem at all in
simulating ordinary indexed arrays in
associative arrays or with an
associative array.
>> Sean>:  So this is like the Swiss Army knife
of arrays, right?
>> BWK:  It is the Swiss Army knife of data
structures: you can build any darn thing
you want with it.  And like Swiss Army
knives, it, you know, it doesn't work
perfectly for everything; if you want to
go and kill people on the battlefield,
Swiss Army knife's not quite right.  But
for this kind of thing, it's
absolutely wonderful data structure.
>> Sean: We talked a lot about hashes in the
security realm and also kind of checking
that things are what you think they are.
This is just the same, it's just a function, is it?
>> BWK: It's a function that takes some input:
arbitrary thing.  I've been talking as if
it were a string of characters; could be
a URL, could be people's names, or you
know postcodes, anything you want, and
converts it into an integer in a
particular range: zero to something.  And
then from that you can use that as a
surrogate for the original.  But you have
to watch out for duplication, so if you
have a lot of things, some of them are
necessarily going to hash to the same value.
>>  Sean: Yeah, because when things wrap
round and round and round you get these
collisions?
>> BWK: That's right. If I've got a
million things and I want to hash them
into a hundred distinct values,
something's going to give.  But one of the
things that happens in cryptographic
kinds of things where the hashing is
more complicated of course, is that you
can't go backwards.  Here's the hash, it's
a number between one and a hundred, you
have no idea which of the million things
produced that hash.  Although you could go
and try the million things and see which one
it was, but there's no guarantee that the
particular one that you picked was
also the one that somebody else had
picked.