[Sean, off camera]  If you're in the UK, and you know, you're using these services from abroad,
[Sean] how does that affect?
[Professor Anderson] Well,
um, I have been speaking to people
in the big service companies, and an example
of the thing that they suffer, and that really bothers them
is this:  Suppose you're Google.
The sort of thing that turns up
is that a family court in India
grants an order saying that you must hand over the Gmail
of somebody living in Canada
who's never been in India, and you must
keep quiet about it forever.
And this really puts you in a bind, because
how can you simultaneously employ
engineers in India, and
give believable assurances of privacy
to your users in Canada?
If you're an international company, you want to do both.
Now, what's been happening up to now, is that
the service companies have been directing all these requests
to lawyers in California.
And this is really driving law enforcement, um,
blue in the face with frustration.
Because it means that to get hold of stuff,
they've got to fill out forms, submit them to the U.S. embassy,
wait for months, blah blah blah blah blah blah blah.
Now, in order to deal with this problem,
what we really need is a new Cyber Evidence convention,
like the Cybercrime Convention
That is, we need an international agreement
which says that if courts in country A
want access to data in country B,
they should be able to get it quickly,
but subject to some rules.
And these rules are gonna have to include
firstly, transparency; so that
you get to know who got access to what, when;
you know, once the case starts,
or once somebody gets arrested, or whatever.
Second, there's got to be respect for jurisdiction,
so if a court in India wants to
compel production of a Canadian's data,
it's got to be run past a court in Canada as well.
And thirdly, there's got to be judicial warrants.
Because, in many countries,
you can't get access to stuff
unless an independent party -- a judge or a magistrate --
has been convinced that there's probable cause
and has signed a piece of paper to that effect.
Now, the UK government doesn't like that,
because they want such things to be done secretly.
They want warrants to be signed by ministers,
rather than by judges.
And they don't want to be hidebound by jurisdiction.
They want to be able to get at stuff in other people's countries as well.
And that's because
interception and surveilance in Britain
is driven by the intelligence agencies
rather than by the police.
And so long as *their* priorities are
what drive policy, then the police are
gonna continue to lose out,
and law enforcement is going to suffer.