Some of us would really like to move towards where we have a lot of these
moving in parallel and indeed IBM...
quite some time ago, 15 years ago
had something called the millipede
where they had lots of little sensors moving across the surface
and actually instead of doing the individual atoms, they were looking at a plastic film
and they would push the sensors in and create a little hole
and then they were really clever so that was the write process
the delete or the erase process was
they put the probe in the hole, heat it up and then pull the probe out slowly.
and what would happen was that the plastic would extrude and fill up the hole, so that they could delete it
so that was... Unfortunately, they discontinued that project
largely because flash memory came along
and sort of blew that out of the water
but it's a fascinating idea to think about,
could we actually push all those probes working together all the way down to the atomic level
>>It does feels a bit like the difference between writing something out by hand and using photocopy
yea
yea, I gue.. yea, exactly, yea
I'm not thinking about the actual mechanics of how the photocopier works
in terms of a very serial process where you're doing this
compared to just snapshot all in one go
that's a really good analogy
ok, go down the lab
Good!
The reason Philip's here is because of Brady's channels
'cause of Sixty Symbols, Philip left a job
in Brazil
So, Philip
Philip's gona be working not on silicon as we've been discussing.
But actually on the other thing I've mentioned, which was gallium arsenide (GaAs)
the systems we use to manipulate atoms are these ones
actually, Alex over here is imaging individual molecules
each blob you can see on the screen
is an individual molecule on a surface
and it's scanning actually in real time at the moment
and behaving itself
pretty well
So, that's an island, you can see the edge on one side, see the coastline
that's the edge of the molecular island
and then it's on a metal surface
So on the left hand side you see the metal and on here you see the individual molecules.
the greys are Carbon (C)
the reds are oxygen (O)
and the whites are hydrogen (H)
but that's sort of off the point of what we were discussing
It's just to show you in action that
we can, just as you're standing here, we're talking
you can see those individual molecules
It's all happening in here
this system is... Why we got all the stainless steel is
it's an ultra high vacuum system
the pressure in there is comparable to that you'd get on the moon
on the surface of the moon
or if you're on a good day, in space
a good day in space, or a good day here?
Either!
so the one question we're asked a lot
(I don't know if the Computerphile audience will be interested)
"why the heck have you got all the tinfoil everywhere?"
and it's not just because times are tough in terms of funding
it's because if we were just to pump this system and do nothing else
even with the best pumps in the world, it would sit there
and we would get reasonable pressures and vacuum
but we'd get nowhere close to 'in space'
pressures and type of vacuum we have in space
and the reason for that is every surface around is is covered in a thin film of water
and that water just sits there
and when we pump this down, we pollute the vacuum
so what we need to do is drive off that water
to drive of that water we bake, we literally bake the system
we put a big oven around it
just as we put tinfoil around a turkey
we put tinfoil around it, and we heat it up to 150°C
drive off all the water
cool it down
and then you get a good pressure
I guess the poster right here, to finally get back to silicon
so each of these individual blobs
is a silicon atom
and so we can not only see those silicon atoms
by bringing a probe in above the silicon surface
and this is actually the lattice we saw upstairs
what we can do is, we can use the probe to manipulate the individual silicon atoms
and that's what's happening here
and in fact we got all the way down to 2 atoms
and making an electromechanical switch
from flipping those 2 atoms, and we did a SixtySymbols video on that
Oh my dear 5 years ago, 2011
So, next step is going to be some kind of circuit than?
so that's very interesting
I must admit, we are driven not so much technology, and technological application
really not at all about technology and  application
what's driving us like, because we're physicists
is what are the fundamental forces between those atoms
how do we control the interactions
how do we control the bonding and change
what the electrons are doing at the surface
from a very "what are the fundamental limits of manipulating matter"
that's really what's driving us
rather than can we get a device out in 2 years
because a device is not coming out
well, we also operate at 5 degrees above absolute zero
there aren't so many devices that you want a helium cryostat beside it operating
and that's a fairly big operating cost
so, it's very fundamental science
>>That's gonna drain your iPhone battery, isn't it?
yea indeed