In front of me I've… mmf.
-In front of me I've got an...
-"Ooh".
"Ooh. In front of me... Ooh!
-"I say!"
-What's under there?
"In front of me I've got things
you're not allowed to see. Haha."
And now I will fiddle with my trousers.
Right, this is the thing, right every f***ing
show we've done ever,
be it kitchen, be it in here,
he has rearranged his crotchular area,
just as he's come on to do something...
oh, bloody hell.
Have you got that on camera?
Grant, are we rolling?
We are rolling.
Right, that needs to be an extra,
is the number of times across the years
that Matt has decided to reposition himself.
Please put your phones
back on aeroplane mode, like I haven't.
Wow, that's getting diminishing returns
every time.
I'm doing it because I find it funny.
That's fair.
That's why we're here, we find this funny.
We do this without you.
Are you okay there, Gary?
I don't know, I had a big Cumberland sausage
on the way down and it ain't half repeating.
One of 'em just starts going down.
"That was me!"
Curse this British food.
Then one of them pops,
"You hear the artillery!"
Is this the effect that the Glaswegian
paella is having on me?
What a filthy euphemism.
Glaswegian paella! It's sausage and chips.
And sauce!