I've dressed my cat in a Christmas jumper.
It's possible.
- "Hello, is that PETA?"
- Did it have panniers?
It would have, if they had been-
But my cat has tried on a Christmas jumper.
It's had two Christmas jumpers and she's had
a Christmas dress.
What are you putting in…?
AUDIENCE: Aww...
The dress was… shut up!
Don't encourage him!
The dress was medicinal.
Because she had a cut on her side and kept
scratching it and she didn't want to…
So you dressed her in frills?
Does it distract…?
Is she just constantly batting at her own
culottes instead of...?
So she tried and scratch the dress, couldn't,
the cut healed and she was a lot better.
Is this a cat-sized Christmas jumper and dress
or, like, human size?
No, it's human size you pillock(!)
Of course it was...
No, he just drops jumpers on it(!)
Actually, no, it wasn't cat sized, it was
small dog sized.
Okay.
Not so silly now.