This is the Technical Difficulties, we're
playing Citation Needed.
Joining me today, he reads books you know,
it's Chris Joel!
Hello.
Everybody's favourite Gary Brannan, Gary Brannan!
"And so the waitress asked, 'super sex'?
"And the vicar said, 'I didn't realise there
was a choice!'"
- I ****ed that one up.
- Yeah, you have.
The punchline is 'super sex'. Come back to
me! I'll try that again!
This week's closing gag will
be pr-- bep-- brpp--
I can talk.
Ooh! "I can talk!"
You can talk.
What? Ooh, it's all gone a bit meta.
- Shall we start again?
- Yes!
I've lost my line now! I'll make something
up, it'll be fine.
This is the Technical Difficulties, we're
playing Citation Needed.
Joining me today, he reads books you know,
it's Chris Joel!
Hello!
Everybody's favourite Gary Brannan, Gary Brannan!
Join me in my underground expedition to Noel
Edmonds' secret filing cabinet.
And the bounciest man on the internet,
Matt Gray!
Today's show is sponsored by the word 'contrived'.
Ooh! Ooh! Commentary! Ooh! Satire!
Wow! Zings off the room, that one!
Ow! I don't feel good about myself at all!
Has anyone got any burn cream?
I'm going to go around the horn again, if
that's OK!
"The horn"!
This is the Technical... did you just fart?
No!
"Well, could you?"
"Could you? Would you mind awfully...
"I think it would just break the atmosphere."
"Just turn round, and when it gets to you..."
Let's go for it. We're wasting mirth here.
I'm not sure we are!
This is the Technical Difficulties, we're
playing Citation Needed.
Joining me today, he reads books you know,
it's Chris Joel!
Third time's a charm!
Everybody's favourite Gary Brannan, Gary Brannan!
Join me in my secret exhibsts... oh for ****'s sake!