Well...
Marseille's better.
You've got the weather, haven't you, for the
duelling down in Marseille, yeah?
The weather for it(!)
"Turned out nice again!"
"Can we not duel today, it's that wet rain
that'll soak you through?"
"I've got it on my glasses,
I can't see where to stab!"
It's a point,
that's why I bought my flat cap.
Best thing I ever had,
my glasses are dry now.
What? For getting stabbed?
Well, I can duel…
"I went to Marseille hoping to get stabbed!
"Couldn't even start a duel, couldn't hit
the other fella."
"Glasses misted up, flat cap, see perfectly,
three confirmed kills."
Is this Yorkshire duelling?
Do you just, like, wear big trousers
and throw ferrets at each other or something
like that?
Okay, that's…
Well, if you want to find out, keep up with
the insults, pal(!)
To be fair, ferret wrestling is actually a
sport in ancient Yorkshire, was it not?
And by ancient I mean 1980.
Tom, Tom, Tom, Tom, Tom...
You know, ferret- it's a circus act isn't
it, putting ferrets down your trousers?
Well, I've pulled up the article...
You can get two down there.
They both seem fine though!
They're not worried.
They're not fighting.
They're peacefully co-existing.
I can't believe I'm going on to this article,
and to anyone who is hoping for this to be
an examination of the life of Julie d'Aubigny...
I've just pulled up the article on
ferret legging.
Which it turns out, is a thing.
It is, as practised by to-be-seventh Doctor
Who Sylvester McCoy, in his circus days.
Really?
Yes, along with hammering nails up his nose
and setting his head on fire.
Gosh.
Take that Capaldi, keep up, come on.
How much livestock have you had down your
breeches?
None.
Could you explain ferret legging?
'Cos there are some easy points
for the Yorkshiremen here,
well for one of the Yorkshiremen.
Well, we all do it, of course, for
the New Years' Eve...
As I understand it, don't you sort of tie
the bottom of your trousers with string
to stop an easy ferret escape as t'were?
Because they are clever little souls
and they'll work their way that
round the ankles is a good way out.
You drop 'em in.
I'm not sure what the middle bit is, right?
Once they're in, I'm not sure…
Great pain, I think!
Step 3, profit.
Yes, step 3, profit, yes.
So, actually, I'm giving you a point for the
general thing,
but you also get a point, Will, for the phrase,
"Great pain".
It's an endurance event.
Right.
It is an endurance event.
What is the current world record for having
a ferret down your trousers?
Single ferret?
Single ferret.
Is it awake or asleep?
If it's asleep you're cheating.
Yes, and I'm going to say, and angry.
I'm going to say, it's got to be less than
an hour,
because otherwise then the ferret is having
a nap.
Two hundred and seventy four days,
but the bloke that's achieved it
doesn't really want to report it to the record
books for Reasons…
I'm going to say 12 minutes.
I'm going to say three hours.
Yep, 5 hours 30 minutes
is the current world record.
We should point out:
ferrets are angry. In general.
I'd be angry if you stuffed me down somebody's
trousers!
"Competitors cannot be drunk or drugged, nor
can the ferrets be sedated."
There we go, fair rules.
What are you not allowed to wear?
Shorts.
Oh no, it's pants.
It's pants.
It's underwear, absolutely right.
Oh, the horror.
Oh my God.
I'm just thinking, there's a famous clip,
isn't there?
The late departed Richard Whiteley who fronted
a chat show for a very small amount of time
and the only thing that happened to him was
someone brought a ferret on
and he went to stroke the ferret
and the ferret bit his finger and wouldn't
let go.
And the shot is of Richard Whiteley lifting
the ferret up
as it dangles off his finger while he screams.
Imagine that with your gentlemen's bits!
Yes, so…
They don't let go!
"The ferret must have a full set of teeth
that have not been filed..."
And I'm giving you a point specifically for
that phrase, because it says,
"The sport is said to involve an ability to
have your tool bitten and not care."
I could probably take the first,
I think the second is where I start to struggle.
And if there is ever a sign that this is quite
a blokey show,
it's the fact that we have gone
from Julie D'Aubigny
to ferrets biting people's tools.
I don't think that counts as an ability.
Well, to be fair the ferret is doing all the
work isn't it?
Yes!
What can you attempt to do to dislodge the
ferret?
Shout at it, convince it nicely,
maybe give it some reading matter,
maybe give it a brochure for the lower end
of the trouser
and encourage it to go on a holiday down there.
It's a ferret tourist destination shop,
you know?
"No, I'm happy here!"
Yes.
You can attempt to dislodge the ferret,
but that can be difficult.
This is a thoroughly well-referenced article
by the way,
better referenced than the historical one…
Does it just say at the bottom, 'I watched
a bloke do this?'
Possibly.
This is the kind of thing they do in Pudsey
on a Wednesday night, isn't it?
Well, where may it have come from?
Er, the Vikings.
Not quite.
Why might you want to try and conceal a ferret
in your trousers?
Oh, poaching!
Oh, yeah!
Yes, absolutely right, to avoid detection
by gamekeepers.
I can say if a ferret is biting your cock
very hard
it's going to be very difficult not to be
given away when being a poacher.
I don't think you can stifle a cry that long
if we're talking hours' worth here.
Can you not just do that thing in
'Danny, the Champion of the World'
and tickle a fish until it falls asleep?
There's easier ways of making a living,
you know!
"Oh, another screaming person
leaving the park.
"Nothing untoward there(!)"
Well, there is a former world…
"How you doing, Jake?"
"Fi-i-i-ine...."
There is a former world champion whose name
is Reg Mellor and…
Of course, it's a Reg.
It couldn't be anything but a Reg, could it?
Who is credited with introducing what tradition?
And it's a clothing tradition.
Is it an ice bath?
No, it's a clothing tradition,
during the event?
Skinny-legged jeans.
It can't actually move once you've got it
wedged in there.
There's a thought, yeah.
Is there a requirement of the tightness of
lower-end clothing?
No, this is actually a lovely connection back
to duelling scars.
Swords.
Duelling scars, not duelling- they're not
duelling with ferrets.
Going back to my scars on people's arses as
a matter of bravery…
No, but in roughly the same way
that you would show off a duelling scar,
that you might want to make it worse,
you might want to make it clear what…
He drops his trousers
to show his ferret scars.
No, it's a clothing tradition.
Is it…?
Ragged trousers.
♪ Dirty shirt! ♪
Moleskin kind of corduroys, because they don't
rip as easy.
Some sort of crotchless trouser...?
I think that's chaps, isn't it?
That's the one!
Chaps.
No, white trousers.
Why?
- Blood.
- To show the blood?
Yes. You got there first.
Oh my God.
To show the blood from the wounds caused by
the ferrets.
Now, I would take up a job as
a painter and decorator
and then whenever I paint a room red I'd come
out and go,
"Look at that!
Ferret Champion of the World yet again!"
And no one would argue.