And the bounciest man on the internet,
Matt Gray!
Putting the butt into butter.
That's a big tub. No offence.
That's why he got sacked from the catering
industry!
It's true.
In front of me I've got an article from Wikipedia
and these folks can't see it...
"It's everywhere! I can't even see it to get
it off!"
Every fact they...
"I just keep wiping and it stays!"
"Water's just running off!
"I've made myself accidentally arse-waterproof!"
Which is great when I'm on a National Express
coach, let's face it.
Matt Gray's Gore-Tex Arse!
Salted or unsalted? I care not to taste.
In front of me, I've got an article from Wikipedia
and these folks can't...
Stork Arse Margarine!
"I don't know what happened! I gave his arse
a little pat and that's just..."
-- That was good. That was good.
I like that one.
-- Thank you!
Four men laughing in a kitchen.