...from Wikipedia and these folks can't see it.
Every fact they get p-- pfh-- pfft... damn it!
Ohhhh!
It just started to get away from me.
I've also just gozzed all over my screen.
- Gozzed?
- Gozzed!
I'm from Nottinghamshire!
And 1995.
In front of me I've got an article fromf--
Aaaa-hahaha!
- W****r.
- Take a breather.
Have a sip of water.
- And when you're ready...
- Then you'll be ready to start.
Okay?
- Right.
- You've got this one.
Sorry.
In front of me...
- We'll behave.
- I just thought...
WILL YOU STOP IT!
Do you know, we've done that so many times,
and it's much funnier when there's an audience.
Usually it's just us three laughing at him.
In a kitchen.
Now you can all join in too.
Okay, we'll behave.
Badly.
Consistently badly.
We've got to be out on time for this one.
In front of me I've got an article from Wikipedia,
and these folks can't see it...