2014, what did the local Highland League
football club do?
What, did they get a cow as a mascot?
Yes!
Did they get, like, a big comedy-costume cow?
Really?
Yes, you’re absolutely right, spot on.
Comedy mascot for the football team,
and that is now… that’s the local….
That can be a road to success and power.
I know someone who played the Hartlepool mascot,
who is a monkey.
Well, we know the Hartlepool
monkey story, right?
We’ve done that.
No, you should mention that, ‘cos that’s
not going to…
Hartlepool, town on the north east Coast,
Napoleonic Wars,
There is a shipwreck off the coast of Hartlepool.
No human survivors but washed up on the beach
is a monkey.
Okay?
Normal, normal, everyday kind of monkey.
The people of Hartlepool get the monkey,
try and talk to it.
Monkey just replies with, ook-ook-ook,
as monkeys would.
Wait, wait, hold on, sorry, the words
“try to talk to it” were in there.
Well, they saw this figure…
Hartlepool doesn’t have the greatest reputation…
It was a ship’s mascot, so it was in clothes.
It was dressed as a sailor.
Duh.
As they try to talk to the monkey, the monkey
– mehh! – didn’t reply.
So they thought the monkey was talking French,
and hung it as a spy.
They are therefore called the monkey-hangers,
Their mascot for the club is a monkey called
H’Angus the Monkey,
Who ran for mayor of Hartlepool… and won.
That is Stewart Drummond, according to this.
Yes!
Did you say you know him?
My brother knows him, yeah.
He got sent off a lot of times for being a
naughty monkey at the football.
In very inappropriate fashions, by the way.
There have been several H’Anguses since,
they’ve been all successively sacked.
There’s something about the costume,
I believe it’s bewitched.
I think that’s the way I’d call it.
I’m sorry, is this like the
Defence Against the Dark Arts teacher?
Someone’s placed a curse on them,
and no one will survive in the monkey costume
for more than one season?
I think so!
It’s not like Yorkie the Lion at York, he’s
well-behaved.
Yes, you’re… wh… you know what, I’m
not even telling that story, yes, that was…
Yes, very naughty monkey.
Yes!
Let’s move on…