If you've never watched this before, you're in for a treat(!)
Every season we get new people.
You... oh my god, the s*** you're about to
endure, let's face it!
Go back to the start, make your decision from
there!
No, go back to like season 3. We hit our stride
about then, I think.
Oh, thanks for dissing our early work, you
****!
I sat in a small room just outside... where
was it, not Carlisle...
Wrexham!
- Wrexham!
- Not Carlisle?!
There's 100 miles in it!
Is this because it's all top left?
F***ing hell, in cosmic terms
that's spot on!
Don't get all Carl Sagan on my arse!
'Carl Sagan's Carlisle'!
If you're getting a cheap day return it's
not exactly...
"Oh, in a cosmic sense it's the same..."
You try telling that to the person manning
the exit barriers at Carlisle Station!
I think you'll find that's why I lost my job
as a f***ing Uber driver.
Carl Sagan's Carlisle: "you find me here in
the lovely town on the borders of Scotland".
"I should be 100 miles further south..."
Where Carl Sagan from?!
- Carlisle!
- Canada!
Gentlemen, we have peaked too soon.
- Tell me about it.
- Speak for yourselves.
"Speak for yourself, ducky."
Do you want to explain the rules?
Nah, f*** it.
It's like all the others!
Today's...