For those just tuning in?! This is YouTube.
You're not just going to open up YouTube and
find yourself half way through a video!
I did wonder.
I occasionally get emails from internet startups
who want to try and get our videos on something.
I got one from someone who's trying to "bring
the TV experience to YouTube".
So it removes all the ability to skip back
and forth, or over things,
and just shows you one video...
Ah, so you go to a place, can't find anything
interesting,
and then turn it off again(!)
That... that's not quite how I phrased it
to them, but yes. That's essentially...
No. The answer's no.
However, if you want to give us a massive
studio like BBC TV Centre's TC1...
We wouldn't know what to do with it!
That's true.
Oh, oh, I'd have a go. Don't you worry about
that.
You still want to run down the stairs like
"Game for a Laugh" onto a shiny floor, don't you?
Yes. And what will happen is, like that bloke
on Catchphrase...
You'll skid on your heels and land in the
camera!