And keep that going please,
for the start of the show!
No, keep going!
This is the Technical Difficulties,
we're playing Citation Needed.
Joining me...
F***ing hell.
What the f***?!
We're starting the show.
"Well, no.
"No, I'm not here for this, no, no."
Let's do that again.
And why might they have been called
the Black Legion?
Did they go at night?
No. No.
Did they go in the day?
I mean they went whenever was best for the…
Was it camouflage tactics?
Did they cover themselves in mud or something
to hide in bushes and stuff?
Ooh,  I'll give you a point
for camouflage tactics, but it wasn't mud.
S***.
That would be the Brown Legion,
and that's very different.
It's now time to play "Beano character
or shipping forecast area?"
Gnasher, Dennis, Softy Walter,
rising slightly.
Westerly three or four, becoming good later.
Fatty, Smithy, failing.
But we did it for Sark, let's do it for
the French as well.
We might get an invite there
at some point as well.
Threaten to play football
and never follow through?
I followed through when they took up the offer.
Thank you very much.
-Alright, this was a French…
-Poo.
Sorry?
He made a poo joke.
It's funny because it's about poo.
It was just you went,
'poo' as well.
This…th...