The crazy eights as in the number.
Eights, so it's not the crazy After Eights?
Oh my God, do you know,
I really don't like those.
I've discovered that after we got,
bought a load of them.
-After Eights.
-After Eights, they're s***.
It's taken you how many years to work out
you don't like After Eights?
I'm growing up, I am maturing and I believe
I can have my own opinions now.
And one of my firmly held ones
are that After Eights are w***.
But you're reaching the stage in life where you
should be getting excited by After Eights.
-What are they for?
-The kids have gone to bed,
you've invited some people around
for a light brandy.
And I want to eat some toothpaste
and chocolate, why?
Exactly. And possibly
a brandy snap with squirty cream in it.
Oh!
"Combined! Standard! Extreme."
Are you selling razors over there?
Yeah.
The new Matt Gray CSX!
"With 32 blades.
8, then 8, then 8, then 8."
"For the extreme shave."
i.e., a shaver that would be that big,
you just put it against your face,
you go, 'Uh,' and you're done.
You've got no skin left.
Or is it a ham slicer?
That's going on the cutting room floor.
Are you going for the Imothep from
The Mummy look and just…
"In a world with some bad things inside it."
"And a city with all bends in it."
I can have a new career in narrating.
I'd do that, I'd listen to that, go on.
Go on, do Harry Potter for me.
There's audio description
and then there's the audio lack of description.
Just loads of silence and
you just lean in and go,
"I don't know what he's doing,
he's on a stick or something. Magic?"
No, so the bloke with the hair
and he's driving the movingy thing,
but the movingy thing can't be driven because
it's running at... that... kind of...?
No, fine.
It's close, I'll give it.
Schting! Cutting room floor.
Phenolic acid.
Is it an acid?
-I'm not, I'm not…
-Can we just get a runaway train of Gaviscon
to hit it 'cos that'd...
That's what you want for your hangover.
Yeah, it really is,
the runaway train that is Gaviscon.
With a proper hopper with like a hose,
"Aargh!"
Hand actions I shouldn't be doing on camera.
Gaviscon.
Yeah, that's not the internationally approved
symbol for Gaviscon, there.
Wrong white liquid.
It's pink, isn't it?
Moving on.
See a doctor.
So anyway, doctor...
Yeah, the movie had Devil's Cu…
both of you okay there?
Yeah. Stops your heartburn though.
Gets right to the insides.
Sorry.
It's going to take them a good 20 seconds
to recover from this.
Just so... I should point out, you see 15 minutes,
we're going for about 45 here, so...
It makes you wonder
what Pepto-Bismol is really, doesn't it?
Thought: runaway train film with all Alien on it.
And just as the train goes honk, the
little mouth comes in and out.
No, they've just got a seven and a quarter inch
train in the front.
Coming out of a landscape
that looks just like Ian Holm.
Tha's a joke that landed
for one person here.
Welcome to the Holm Hills.
Let's let them kiss,
and they made a baby.
Sorry, I'm all over the place today.