Fillies in Philly?
Thereby undoing all the good work said establishment
ever did!
Yes!
Yes, he proposed a…
You t***.
I mean, don't get me wrong, that's genius.
The first chartered women's institution of
higher education in Philadelphia.
(Fillies in Philly...!)
"I say, dear boy, I thought of that one on
the train here!"
"Rah, rah, rah!"
This is what private education gets you(!)
Okay.
So what did he think… w…?
You're just going to need a wait a second.
It's over, mate. It's over.
I'm going to direct this at Chris, actually.
Hello!
What did he think...?
It's gone.
He's gone.
I should leave it until there's no chance
of a spit-take.
I'm dead!
Like that one.
That's actually straight through to the green
room back there.
So he's just taking a minute, to just...
You okay there, Matt?
You've just given someone an OBE haven't you?