Traverse-le-alley, good grief.
Will, you have slotted into Matt's seat
just perfectly.
When I ate him I stole his powers.
That's how it works.
You actually had a buzz cut, didn't you, before
you went in…
Yes.
The man was clean shaven and five foot one.
It's the kind of 'American Werewolf in London'
transformation.
"Augh!"
"I'm making puns!"
But a horrible werewolf, because you have
to eat the werewolf.
Oh yes, that's…
Oh yes.
That's a horrible reverse werewolf.
Note to self: fairy story for later.
That's a wolf that under the full moon turns
into a really confused human.
"Huh?"
Scooby Doo!
Scientific basis for Scooby Doo.
"Raggy?"
In the day, he is a mild-mannered
banker called David.
And then when the full moon shines he…
I'm getting Heart of a Dog now, Bulgakov.
Have you not seen that?
Or read that?
Mikhail Bulgakov short story about a doctor
who transplants
the heart and testicles of a man onto a dog
and the dog slowly humanises.
Oh, that's cool.
It's dark.
It's grim.
Scientists, please check, would that work?
Do we have any scientists in the audience?
We're not specialists…
No, it wouldn't work.
No.
We've been told that wouldn't work.