...in front of me I have an article from Wikipedia, and these folks can't see it.
Every fact they get right is a point
and a... [thump] ding?
A point and a massive thud on the table!
You've forgotten the button again!
Oh. Button's in my bag. Balls.
Button's in your ballbag...? Ha!
I need to get my button. I'm sorry.
Blimey.
As you can see, viewers, it's started well.
I hope this stays in(!)
Tom's gone to get his button out of his... his sack.
So I'd like to welcome you to after the credits.
Shut the door and lock it. We win!
-- By default!
-- It's our show now.
Such cheating!
By the way, to everyone --
this is never going to get in it --
No, I can't ****ing see his screen!
'Cos that would defeat the whole object!
I can't see it 'cos it's over the back. He can see it, but he's blind in the left eye.
Have you ever tried to look at the side of an LCD screen?
You can't see anything!
Besides, all he has on there is high-class Dutch pornography
until he looks at it to tell us what the article is anyway(!)
*High* class?
Have you ever seen both his hands above the table in any of these episodes?
I think not.
Are we just starting again, then?
No, no, we'll cut something together from that, I think.