Why might it have been called Sergeant Reckless?
Did it s*** like a mister?
...no.
That would be rather reckless.
...no, it didn't. No.
What, like a hippo spray? That kind of thing?
Oh, don't — I've seen that.
If you've never seen a hippo s***,
make your way to your nearest zoo and see a hippo s***.
I'm sorry, it is well worth —
Basically, a hippo -- going back to our word of the day, which is 'helical' --
has effectively got a propellor on its arse.
Yes.
And will just kind of go
[flatulent noise]
...like that.
I've only been to a zoo once in my life...
Did it end with you kind of taking your glasses off,
and there being a perfectly glasses-shaped piece not covered in s***?
No, fortunately I was out of the splash zone.
Other people were *not* out of the splash zone.
But you were solidly in the guff zone.
It basically backed itself up against a window...
Beep... beep... beep...
No, no, no: thpppt... thppt... thppt...
Yep.
'Hippo reversing.'
Can you imagine being the bloke — we were talking about jobs like the army and whatever else —
can you imagine being the fellow at the zoo
whose job is to go in with the squeegee and the bucket to clean the s*** off the hippo window?
Whatever your job is at home, you're sat there going, 'God, I hate doing this.'
Just imagine being the fellow in the gumboots and smock
that has to walk into the hippo enclosure three times a day and go,
[Squeegee noises]
There you go. There's two elements:
One, you're dealing with a load of hippo s***.
Two, whatever you do, your work is only gonna bring joy to people
for a maximum of about an hour and a half
before that ungrateful bastard in the pen does it all over again.
What is it, two minutes and we've already got to s***?
Yeah. Yeah.
You're the one that brought in misted s***!
You are — I don't know where that came from.
I don't know why that suddenly appeared, but that was all on you.
Well, I say, 'all on you'...
Atomized feculence, that's what you brought to the table.
That's a prog rock band if ever there was one.
First album: #1. Second album: #2.