To be fair, Lorz went on to win the Boston Marathon —
[Sharp, trumpet-like fart]
[Laughter]
You thought you were going to
get away with that, didn't you?
[Gasping]  Yeah, I did.
I can see the waveform!
Don't anybody tell him about
anything else anybody's won!
Gary Brannan: farting at marathon winners.
Farts at victory!
[Sings 'Chariots of Fire' melody']
[Blows raspberry]
Yeah, what happens if Gary actually wins anything?
He follows through.
That's why I never have.
What, followed through, or won anything?
Not the latter.
Um, Frederick Lorz went on...
Frederick Lorz went on to win
the Boston Marathon the year after.
But Thomas Hicks was...
You okay?
No, he's lost it.
He's lost it.
Everybody take five.
We'll reconvene when he can breathe.
[Hums 'Take Five']
[Guitar riff]
Will it help if I poke you?
Might happen again.
TOM: Okay. Um...
CHRIS: Mi mi mi mi mi...
Frederick Lorz went on to actually win the
Boston Marathon the next year — don't you dare!
Why are you laughing?!
Let me get this line out. We'll edit it together.
TOM: Frederick —
MATT: Get it out.
Frederick Lorz actually went on
to win the Boston Mara...  [Laughs]
[Laughter]
GARY: [Blows raspberry]
Are you on satellite delay?
Frederick Lorz actually went on
to win the Boston Marathon the next —
GARY: [Laughs]
TOM: I can't look at Gary!
I can't look at him! He looks like
he's having the worst s*** of his life!
Well, that's the post-credits quote and no mistake!