Did their faces go all like that as they went
over the top?
No, that’s sustained.
You’ll get that if you get sustained Gs.
This is…
It’s more a sort of “ga-dumf” feeling.
‘Cos when you jump and hit the floor, briefly,
your feet are getting a few Gs.
But it’s so brief that it doesn’t matter.
I’ve got a friend
who’s a massive rollercoaster fan
and I went with her to a…
Thorpe Park, if we’re allowed to name check,
and before each ride she’d be like, right,
this has maximum G of this,
and this many flips, and the other,
but then the whole ride is just me sitting
there counting them going
“yes, that works out,
ooh yep, that’s there”.
And so it turns into somewhere between
rollercoaster riding and accounting,
which is kind of fun.
Tell you what, that’d be a job to get into,
accounting on a rollercoaster.
Well, no, you just design the rollercoaster
so it’s basically the pound after Brexit.
And it’s just… no, there’s the drop!
Satire!
That exists, it’s the first drop on the
Pepsi Max Big One.
I was going for Oblivion at Alton Towers.
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
You could have a whole theme park!
“You want to go on the tulip ride again?”
“Yeah, let’s do it.”