A friend of mine's brother was Mr Wimpy.
Wait, what?
In the Huddersfield branch of Wimpy, he was
Mr Wimpy.
Is that like a mascot costume?
Yes, it's like a beefeater, but his eyes are
obscured by the hat.
But you look through the mouth,
just mark you.
But what happened was,
he wasn't allowed to talk at all,
that was one of the strict rules.
Mr Wimpy must never talk to anyone,
because obviously you don't want this weedy
15-year-old accent coming through.
"Hi, 'appy birthday!"
That kind of thing.
But what happened was he tripped up on the
way down the stairs to a kids' party,
rolled down and the kid just hoofed him in
the head for five solid minutes.
You try not screaming
while dressed as Mr Wimpy.
Apparently quite difficult.
I was going to go off on one about, like,
costume characters and how that-
I can't beat a kid
hoofing Mr Wimpy in the face.
I really can't.
While the guy screams silently within.
Now there's a metaphor in there,
I'm pretty sure.
Doesn't a friend of ours still have a £20
Wimpy voucher that he won?
Whoa, really?
He started…
Sorry - 2,000 pence.
Yes, I think he did some "banter" with them
on Twitter
and they decided to send him a voucher
and he hasn't got around to spending it,
because there aren't that many Wimpys…
There aren't.
Particularly not near him.
And he did once go up to the place,
look at it and just go,
"I can't."