I was going to say, is it like of those onesies
that's for two people, so is it a twosie,
but without the bottom bit so it's…
Oh, what, like a two, like a…
A two person jumper with two head holes?
A tumper.
-But only two arm holes.
-Yeah, two head holes.
No, one head hole, two arm holes.
No, two head holes, two arm holes.
Yeah, one head hole, two arm holes
is a sweater, Gary.
That's just a regular…
that's just a regular sweater.
Is it some high school American pledge ring
Valentine's Day nonsense,
that is also, I don't know, connected
with a spree of murders,
so it ends up with the word curse appended?
No, but you've just invented
a great horror film there.
-It's like the...
-Or a Goosebumps book!
It's like the Sisterhood
of the Travelling Plant…
Travelling plants!
-Triffids!
I knew the minute that was out of my mouth,
I wasn't going to get to correct myself there.
No.
I've never understood this desire
to make the fabric,
when there's perfectly good whole cloth
and sewing machines.
You sound like some kind of business owner
of the 19th century.
"Why must we weave these things?"
I'm a fine 19th century seamstress,
I'll have you know.
I can just imagine you coming up with someone
knitting, 'What's that s***? Here!'
It's two bits of material, brrum, brrum,
chop, poncho, done.
"For this we have machines. Next."
Do you like my poncho description there?
Brrum, brrum, chop.
It's two seams and a hole.
It's true though.
You don't need to cut the material
other than the hole.
Yeah, you only need to cut the material once.
I'm still talking about ponchos!
Nobody help him.
For the fickle lover, the poncho curse.
Is that the one night stand equivalent?
"I made you a ponch..."
Oh, you f***ed off.
I thought you said pickle.
Pickle! What?
I know, that's why I'm sat here going…
-I mean...
-"For the pickle lover."
An onion sized poncho.
-Like a little gherkin with a poncho on it...
-A gherkin can't wear a poncho,
it's got no shoulders.
It'd just shoot straight through the middle.
"You ungrateful f***!"
You'd have to make it an umbrella.
Alright, or a full height but stiff poncho.
So the bottom corners sit on the ground
and then the head's just pokingup...
A tent?
Yes!
-No, no.
-Pickle tents.
"Darling, I made you a pickle tent,
finally we can be briny lovers!"
Bloody cornichons,
they always leave you.
That's like my first law of everything,
which is don't be a knob.
That's basically 'do unto others'.
Yeah, yeah, it's don't be a knob,
you're going to claim expenses?
Don't be a knob, you'll be fine.
Going to travel...
Going to travel first class? don't be a knob in
there. It just works. Don't be a knob.
-Don't.
-And if you are a knob, stop it.
Yeah, you.
-No, not you, you.
-You. You.
-You, Nigel.
-We see you.
I don't actually know anyone called Nigel.
Three people who are called Nigel just...
One of which is Farage
and he has a massive change after this.
Oh, yeah, you think Farage watches this?
He f***ing might as well.
The wheel spins and lands on France.
Charming image of aliens from Dr Who,
knitting.
Cybermen have their own
kind of attachment.
-Yes.
-No, that's just a loom.
That's just, yeah, both arms are there.
What else do you do on long space journeys,
knit each other jumpers?
And then in the end when they land
and try and take over,
they've all fallen out with each other already.
"This does not suit me.
"How can this not fit, we are all the same
size and shape."
"We have four arms,
why have you knitted only two?"
"Why are they both on this side?"
"Who else are you seeing, Janet?"
You could use a Dalek as the spindle thing,
the...
"I cannot feel I am
subjective in this relationship."