[Applause]
Now —
No one saw that movie.
Not only did I not know this was happening,
they changed their shirts in the time between
me opening that door and me on stage,
so I don't know how the hell that happened...
...but well done.
[Applause]
And I must say that you're a very lucky audience
that you didn't see my gutty midriff then.
[Laughter and a whoop from the audience]
And you may yet.
Gutty Midriff sounds like the name of a burlesque star.
[Laughter]
From Rotherham.
Funny you should say that...
GARY: That's my mother!
Ooh, now you're...
CHRIS and GARY: Ooooh!
Can I also give a quick shout out to the people
who brought their own TechDif merchandise?
MATT and GARY: What?!
TOM: There's five people in a row there with —
TOM: Seven... There's a lot of people
with different slogans on the T-shirts there.
GARY: That's fine. I'm cool with that.
TOM: Which is just... that's...!
We should get a photo afterwards.
We ought.
Yes. Yes.
Right.
Are we ready for the second show, gentlemen?
GARY: [Laughs]
MATT: Never.
Have to be.
AUDIENCE MEMBER: Matt, the door's open.
[Laughter]
GARY: [Hums theme from 'Chariots of Fire']
What I love about that shout is not just:
thank you, the door was open...
but also the fact that you called on Matt,
who is furthest away from the door...
[Laughter]
...to get the door.
Um... all right.
He's the only one with the professional
door-closing certificate, though.
Oh, that's true, actually. I'm not licensed for that.
We'd best open it again.
GARY: Union rules. We're all dead.
All right. Is everybody ready?
[Non-committal muttering]
Then, as we go into recording the second show,
can we have a big round of
applause as the show begins?
[Applause]