Is this what I had on my stag do?
I remember that!
Well, you do more than I do, let's be honest(!)
I just remember the injuries, Tom,
and the pain involved.
Oh, no, I thought you were talking about the
meal afterwards!
Not the paintball.
Oh my god. Yes, and that.
-- His stag do, we went on paintball.
-- We did.
And then they said, right, stags and the birthday
boys, line up for the shooting gallery.
One shot at you.
Which I was fine with.
I thought, I can take that.
I've had more than that in the course of the
day
I'd been wearing a pink tabard with a target
on it for all of it
which is "what you do when you're on these
things"(!)
So I've taken a fair few shots to all over
my body.
And then they say, "one shot" -- no, it's
not one shot.
Everyone just unloads their guns towards you.
Yeah, I think the point I realised afterwards...
you're supposed to run away.
Everyone apart from you did.
And I just stood and took a hail of pellets!
Like, we took a few shots...
I was in that position!
Then most of our group went "no, no, that's
enough"
"This is wrong!"
Everyone else is like "he's not running"!
The point was, I'm just stood up, I'm supposed
to just stand there and go
"have at it again", basically, but I think
they'd have brought out, I imagine,
a paint cannon or something
that would have just loaded up with a tin
of Dulux, just firing it!
In the tin!
The thing I remember more from that paintball,
Tom,
is you trying to use your grenade.
Oh, I'd forgotten that!
There was a castle at the top of the slope,
Tom's idea was to try and somehow, I don't
know,
spook them out that a ghost was coming or
something
by throwing a very small can of smoke...
I had a smoke grenade! I wanted to use the
smoke grenade!
Yeah. I don't think the appropriate place
to use it
is a) a heavily armed fort
which gives away where we are, lest we forget,
because they'll see where it came from,
and b) one of those that's on a hill
where you didn't quite get it to the apex
of the hill
and it rolled back down towards us...
It was a smokescreen!
...disguising us within a smokescreen
which is novel(!). Let's put it this way.
In military terms.
Unless we'd sprang out from the other side
of the smoke,
we had very little hope.
That's fair.
You... you fumigated your own side.
Although, if you're getting me with this,
then I'm going to get you with the aerial
ropes course.
Where you had the zip line...
And it wasn't a zip line down. Zip line across.
So you put enough energy in, you'll go off.
Unless...
I'd like to stress at this point, it was a
very shallow angle on the rope. Right?
...unless you fail to stick the landing,
in which case you bounce off the far tree,
and you just...
Did you do a Boris Johnson?!
-- No! -- Yes! In the middle, dangling...
Oh, actually, yes.
And someone has to come along with a large
thing for him to grab on to
and drag him over
And then I nearly did it again!
Yeah, you nearly did.
All right? It was like one-all, on that one.
On the other hand, you got married, so you
won in the end.