Now, the question I have to try and think of the
answer of is did they have too much or too little?
Ah!
"Aargh! So much butter!"
-I'm going for too much butter.
-Butterlanche!
-Butterlanche.
Right, is that an arse avalanche
or a butter avalanche?
Beneath the butter, loads of butts.
Well, considering I heard 'the Norwegian
buttock crisis' the first time out...
-Oh!
-Then again, too many or too few?
-"Altogether too..."
-And do you get an extra hole
or do they bifurcate around a central orifice,
or...?
"Oh, there are too many arses."
What accent was that?
Because that wasn't Norwegian, Gary.
You can't use WD40 on it.
No, you can't, that's a penetrating fluid.
-Oh, it is.
-Oh, Jesus.
Sorry, it's a real bugbear,
WD40, not a lubricant.
(Penetrating fluid...)
-It’s a water displacement.
-Yeah.
Are you okay there, Gary?
Have you just heard the words
'penetrating fluid'?
Yeah, okay, good.
-Give him a minute.
-I can't go to Halfords again.
Every cloud has a silver lining.
A buttery lining.
A salty, buttery middle.
Oh, imagine the rain.
"It's raining ghee."
Hallelujah.
It's raining...
So is it all stuff that people either
can't be arsed to make any more,
or they've decided it's not good for you
and it's gone out of fashion kind of stuff,
and then everyone's forgotten about it?
Yeah, pretty much, it may not be forgotten
about but it could be.
Or rules have presented it being done like
unpasteurised milk, that kind of thing.
Ooh, yes, so just in terms of categories.
Can we just clear this one?
'I said, you want it pasteurised, she said'...?
'I'll be happy if it comes up to my chest.'
Thank you.
I thought I'd leave you with that one.
It's not funny, if you don't set up
the whole bath of milk thing beforehand.
Oh, milk, oh, right.
Yeah.
You see, you've done this once before, Gary.
I know, I know.
If you're going tell a joke…
-You have to tell people the joke.
-Yes.
I'll write that down.
Hey!
Wait, I've got one of those.
Oh!