There's a 'See also' here for 'Digby Tatham-Warter'.
Is that a surname or a place?
That is a name.
He was known for bringing
something into battle as well.
Oh God...!
His family.
Little Timmy with the scarf around the neck!
A melon baller.
Refused to kill anyone unless he gouged their
eyes out.
Was he the complete opposite, did he bring
something really soft?
It is exactly the sort of thing that if you
are an Englishman going into battle,
stereotypically you would hit someone with
or poke someone with.
An umbrella?
An umbrella, yes.
Just imagine!
One guy with a claymore, the other just twirling
the umbrella.
He had trouble remembering passwords.
What did he think that carrying an umbrella
into battle would do instead?
Identify him, so people knew who he was without
the damn passwords?
Identify him as what?
A man who doesn't like getting his head wet?
"Damnably English!"
Yes, absolutely right.
I quote, 'Only a bloody fool of an Englishman
"would carry an umbrella into battle.'
"Hello.
"I'm a bloody fool of an Englishman!
"Nice weather."
Self-defining as 'a bloody fool of an Englishman?'
- Yes.
- Wow.
What did he actually manage to do with that
umbrella?
- Stab himself.
- Did he poke someone with it?
A little bit more than that.
Capture 42 men.
Because he'd walk up behind someone,
poke the point of the umbrella in the small
of their back
and say he's got a whole regiment behind him
or something like that.
It's exactly the kind of stunt a guy like
that would try and pull.
No, he disabled a German armoured car
by incapacitating the driver
by poking the umbrella through a slit.
"An umbrella!"
Whatever the German word for umbrella is,
I'm very sorry,
"An umbrella, was?"