I always thought that, as the curtain closes
and the coffin sort of slides away:
Thunderbirds music.
Actually, no, Stingray would be better,
with the whole city descending.
No, I was thinking the bit where they...
you know, Thunderbird 3, they sort of go back.
GARY: Ohhh, yes!
Have the thing tilt over backwards like...
That was Thunderbird 1, wasn't it.
Not 3... 3 was the sofa.
Thunderbird 2 would be a better coffin delivery system...
if we're actually going here...
MATT: [Laughs]
TOM: Yeah, that's true.
Because you've got the combination of slides that could
take you all the way down to the crematorium.
Gentlemen! Gentlemen:
Themed crematorium.
MATT: Oooo.
GARY: [Gasps]
Also... How does Thunderbird 3 launch?
[Roar of flame]
Are you saying Jeff Tracy should have combined
his millionaire's tropical island with a crematorium?
Yeah. And then when you're picking up the urn...
you've basically got Thunderbird 2 comes along
and all the pods go by...
CHRIS: 'Oh, there's Granddad!'
TOM: [Mechanical whirring]
Are we making a series of crematorium gags here?
Yes. To be...
To go where no man has been before.
Crematorium Thunderbirds jokes, let's be clear.
Let's be fair. We're not completely stupid and irresponsible.
We're talking about, you know, aligning kids' favourites
with death. It's what they all need.
So you could have like a Virgil Vigil?
Ohhhh.
I like... that's not worth biscuits, it's just a...
Yeah. That's a golf clap. A golf-clap pun there.
It's a lovely knock-down...
Four... only just made it over the ropes.
GARY: Yeah. Yeah.
MATT: 'Golf-clap pun...'
Tell you what you could do...
You could replace all the paintings of the sons with whoever it is that's dead, couldn't you?
Yeah, but the thing is, when the eyes light up...
...that's when you know they've hit the flames!
If you *haven't* watched Thunderbirds, the last
couple of minutes have been very confusing for you.
GARY: Pause it. Just get a 'Best Of'.
TOM: Yeah.
Erm... we were on the coffin ray.
Do they spread the Black Death?
[Coughs]
TOM: Ahh!
GARY: Ahh...
TOM: Golf-clap pun.
GARY: Yeah, golf clap...
We'll just signal that one for...
Why are we reaming Matt today? What's he done?
TOM: It's normally me, so I'm not complaining.
CHRIS: Ah, fair.