Was he a spy?
Ooh, no.
More towards the dark end of those arts.
Was he a spy at night?
-- No...
-- With Patrick Moore!
Impersonator!
Ooh, very...
I'm looking for a particular word...
Like, impersonator implies he... what are
you cackling at?
Sean Connery on with Patrick Moore!
It's "The Spy at Night" with Patrick Moore!
"Today, I'm sat here behind someone's head
"watching if he's a philandering husband.
"Now here's Brian May with a large telescope
into his wife's bedroom."
Brian May looks like Russ Abbot peering out
of a cloud.
He's not wrong. He's not wrong.
Google Russ Abbot and Brian May, he's right.
It's just the thought of, like, a...
Where did that come from?!
The Sky at Night!
Patrick Moore's in the suit and everything
but just, like, camouflage paint on his face.
"I'm using my large telescope to spy on the
lady next door."
[Translating these subtitles? Add your name here!]
Sorry, I'm slobbering.
Lovely!
No, it--