I took a canal boat holiday with some friends once.
(Were they Martians?)
No, they weren't Martians. Has anyone ever
been on a canal boat holiday?
- Yes.
- I haven't.
- You know when you open and close a lock gate?
- Correct.
You've got the lock gate.
To open the… the little…
The… what are they?
Paddles.
Paddles! The paddles that let the water
in and out of the lock.
- You use what is called a windlass.
- You do.
Which is basically a big crowbar-like-thing
that you put in
Wind it like that
And then, while the paddles are open,
You hold onto the windlass.
So it doesn't chin you.
- Yes.
- Oh, the force of the water makes it go…
She makes it spin round very quick!
Yes. I was given the instruction
"hold onto the windlass"
roughly at the exact point that I let go of
the windlass
at which point it performed one complete revolution
and hit me squarely in the balls.
Poseidon's kick right there!