He's got the beard, I've got the bulk...
Wow! That's... that's a slogan there.
Let's make lots of money!
That's a poster with you two and:
'He's got the beard. He's got the bulk.
Together, they are...'
Bulkbeard!
There we go.
[Laughter]
That sounds like the next Marvel one.
Bulkbeard!
I just think it's a really fat pirate.
[Laughter]
Discount men's grooming warehouse.
[Pirate voice]
'No, you go board it. I... I can't move.'
He's just flopped in a big chaise longue on the poop deck.
'Arr. Bring back any snacks they may have.'
Sorry, it's getting close to a Wogan pirate.
Little bit. Little bit.
[Wogan impression] 'Bring back any snacks they may have.'
Must Wogan all impressions!
No, no, no, it's not like anyone will mistake that. I've been doing a lot of Woganing.
'Bring back any biscuits!.'
'Or sausages. Or any cream horns.'
— This is just Wogan.
— It's not!