If you prefer this show in audio form, then
head over to techdif.co.uk
where the old episodes are available as downloads
for your MP3 player
I'm sorry, I'm talking like I'm from the 90s,
aren't I?
Is it available in a datablast at the end?
Oh my god, yes!
Oh no, no, wait, I'm confusing my enthusiasm
for that
with my enthusiasm for Violet Berlin.
If you want to see the first season of how
we did this
but without our ugly mugs then you wouldn't
be seeing it
you'd be watching the newly recorded podcasts
or some s***
I'll try that again, you can see what I'm
driving at.
-- I'll have a go.
-- Actually, that probably covers it!
If you like to listen to these instead of
staring at us all the time,
these are available as podcasts
and they're available for your various MP3
devices
record players or wax gramophones at techdif.co.uk.
Do you want to watch this?
But without watching it?
On a bus in a tunnel?
Download it.
techdif.co.uk.
-- That's it!
-- Audio-y!
Right?
Cut!
Print!