China is threatening to invade Taiwan
Will the US defend the only Chinese Democracy?
Or should Taiwan have Nuclear weapons?
This is China Uncensored,
I’m Chris Chappell.
The United States has promised to come to
Taiwan’s aid
if China ever invaded.
In the 1950’s,
the Chinese Communist Party put that to the
test,
in the First and Second Taiwan Strait crises.
But the United States does not have a formal
mutual defense treaty with Taiwan—
unlike with Japan, South Korea, and the Philippines.
Some people are worried that Taiwan
needs either greater US support,
or a little something more in their corner—
nuclear weapons.
I sat down with Ian Easton of the Project
2049 Research Institute
to find out more.
Ian, it's great to have you back on the show.
Chris, it is a great pleasure to be here.
Thank you for having me back.
Absolutely.
So right now the president of the United States
is able to meet with the leader of North Korea,
but he can't meet with the president of Taiwan.
What does that say about the US-Taiwan policy?
I think it says that this policy is deeply
troubled.
That in many ways it's hypocritical that we
treat a vibrant,
thriving democracy like a pariah state that
our diplomats
are not allowed to recognize the Taiwanese
flag
or call the Taiwanese government or people
by their proper names,
but we can recognize the flag of an enemy
like North Korea
or a strategic competitor like The People's
Republic of China.
And what makes this particularly absurd is
in this case
the US government policy is actually serving
to legitimize
a very very oppressive and troubling authoritarian
state
run by the Chinese Communist Party and the
PRC
and delegitimize a thriving pro-American democracy
and actually weakening Taiwan's national security
situation
and then by extension weakening our own national
security.
So I know the United States has mutual defense
treaties
with a couple of countries in Asia
like The Philippines and Japan.
I know the US has certain military obligations
to Taiwan,
but how close is that to the mutual defense
treaties
of these other countries?
Well there's a huge gap that's there.
And what is troubling about that is the fact
that
the Taiwan Strait flashpoint is actually
a far more dangerous and unstable flashpoint.
It's far more dangerous for long-term
US national security interests.
If you compare the defensive Taiwan, for example,
to the defensive South Korea
or the defensive Japan or The Philippines
or Australia or even Thailand or other treaty
allies in Asia,
it's clear that Taiwan is far more difficult
for us to defend.
It's a far tougher war plan for us.
And it's far more dangerous because it could
very quickly escalate,
and the Chinese have many,
many advantages that they would not have
in any other potential scenarios that we would
worry about.
And so by not having iron clad security guarantees,
and actually putting Taiwan inside of our
security umbrella
the way we do with other democracies in East
Asia
and some countries that are actually not even
democracies,
not allowing Taiwan also to have a nuclear
deterrent.
So for example, Israel is another small nation
that faces an existential threat from its
neighbors
in the way that Taiwan faces an existential
threat
from The People's Republic of China.
Israel, though, will never be taken over
not only because they have a great military
and they have very strong US support
but also because they have nuclear weapons,
and only a nation that has completely lost
its mind
and is suicidal is ever going to invade another
nation
that is armed with nuclear weapons.
And so what this in effect does is
it creates at the strategic level,
which is where all of the most important
historic decisions get made,
the decisions that either make or break world
order right?
That's becoming increasingly destabilized
because we have a thriving democracy of 23
million people
facing off against a deeply authoritarian
country
of 1.3 billion people.
That authoritarian nation has nuclear weapons.
They have a very impressive and growing military
force,
and they also have ambitions,
and they actually covet their neighbor's territory.
In this case, they want to annex Taiwan,
and you have Chairman Xi Jinping
going on TV just a couple months ago
making it crystal clear for
everybody in the Chinese Communist Party
who works for him and the armed wing of the
party,
the people's liberation army,
will also of course work for him.
Then his intentions are to retake Taiwan and
The United States
is not well-equipped to deal with this
because we don't have troops in Taiwan,
we don't provide Taiwan with iron clad security
commitments.
We have the Taiwan relations act which is
domestic law.
It was passed in 1979 and signed by President
Carter.
That is a very rough substitute for an alliance,
but there's a huge gap there.
And that gap is growing in time as Chinese
power grows.
And so what that does is it creates a destabilizing
situation,
and ultimately as we get into the 2020s,
what they could mean for us is that the probability
for a really horrific war is actually increasing
over time,
and I think that is something we should all
worry about.
Well as you say, China has nukes.
Taiwan has some F16s.
What possible deterrence can Taiwan have?
Exactly.
And so right now their deterrence
is based on a loose idea that the United States
is going to come to the rescue.
And of course the US military ...
The Taiwan Relations Act says that the US
military
has to prepare for this contingency,
for defending Taiwan,
and that by law the US military,
and specifically the Indo-Pacific command
in Hawaii,
which controls all of our forces in the Pacific,
that they have to maintain the capacity to
respond
not only to a Chinese invasion of Taiwan,
but also to Chinese intimidation or coercion
of Taiwan.
So these would be less-stressful scenarios
like blockades or air and missile operations,
things of that nature,
that we have to maintain the capacity to respond,
but it doesn't guarantee that we will respond.
So that's the difference between these
other mutual defense treaties we have.
Exactly.
And the other big difference is the other
defense treaties
are linked to our strategic nuclear forces
where this is not.
And for our other allies,
we actually have US troops stationed there
as a trip line.
So for example,
right now if you look at NATO and you look
at the Baltic states,
Lithuania, Latvia, and Estonia,
they're very vulnerable to a potential Russian
invasion.
And Putin has made clear that this is something
that
might happen to them if they're not careful.
But of course it's not gonna happen.
Because we have a thousand NATO troops deployed
to each of those three countries as a trip
line.
Now could those troops actually defeat an
invading army?
The answer of course is no.
Could the Berlin Brigade,
during the Cold War,
have actually defended Berlin from a Soviet
invasion?
Of course the answer is no,
but they serve as a deterrent because a potential
enemy
has to know that if they do invade,
they're going to end up killing American troops
that we have skin in the game.
And that means that we then become willing
to escalate
horizontally and potentially vertically
to a very dangerous level if the enemy attacks,
and because of that they don't.
And so we know from history of great power
competition
that this is a very healthy thing to do,
but we're not doing that with Taiwan,
and Taiwan because of its size
no matter how hard they train,
no matter how much military equipment and
training
they can get from The United States,
in my view it's not going to be sufficient
for them
to maintain a credible self defense force.
That there has to be something more.
I'm not advocating for Taiwan to get nuclear
weapons.
I'm not necessarily advocating for The United
States
to rush to provide nuclear guarantees to Taiwan,
but I do think we need to think
much more carefully about deterrents,
and there may be conventional means of deterrents.
There may be economic or political or trade
or other measures that we could use,
but at the end of the day we have to come
up with
some substitute for nuclear weapons.
Otherwise, the Chinese can just escalate their
way
out of this problem
and end up taking over Taiwan,
which would really undermine our national
security interests.
So China says it wants a peaceful resolution
to the One China policy.
Is that the same as peace?
Well they absolutely do want a peaceful resolution.
The problem is they have a different definition
for peace.
Their definition for peace is they subvert
the enemy.
They undermine the enemy.
They intimidate the enemy.
They use psychological warfare and political
warfare,
legal warfare.
They get in the hearts and minds of the enemy,
and they get the enemy to surrender
without actually putting up a physical fight.
So they use a form of violence.
Now is it really peaceful?
No.
Because intimidation and coercion
is still a type of violence.
It's just a form of violence
that's much more mental and psychological
and much less kinetic,
much less physical.
And so that's what their ideal end-state is.
Is for the Taiwanese and the Americans
to surrender without actually fighting.
That's certainly what they're trying to do.
Thank you again for joining us.
This was absolutely terrifying as it is
every time I have you on.
Chris, it's a great pleasure.
I also feel your terror.
And I look forward to hopefully being able
to
continue the conversation in the future.
Thanks again.
Absolutely.
We could also just, you know,
get together and like huddle in a ball together.
That would make me feel a little uncomfortable,
to be honest.
Okay.
I'd feel reassured myself.
But I will give you a hug after we turn the
cameras off.
Wonderful.
You know, four hugs a day is just the minimum.
Good policy.