On this episode of China Uncensored:
Venezuela is a socialist paradise!
Not for its citizens,
but for the Chinese Communist Party.
Hi, welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
Venezuela.
A country in Latin America currently ruled
by hungry,
hungry dictator, Nicolás Maduro.
It’s funny because he’s eating an empanada
on national television...
while his people are suffering from malnutrition
caused by his economic mismanagement.
“Fernando Contrera says he's lost 40 pounds
since the troubles started.”
And this is common throughout Venezuela.
“We're hungry.
There's hunger.
I stand in line all day long,
but I don't get anything.”
“I haven't bought milk for months.
Meat and chicken are extremely expensive,
if you can even find them.”
“These are the cuts of fish that people
are eating, they're fish heads, look.
Pieces that were only eaten by dogs before.
No offense to dogs.”
I mean, c’mon.
Dogs aren’t offended when you eat their
food.
They’re offended when you’re so hungry,
you eat them.
And if that’s not bad enough, the Venezuelan
currency,
the bolívar, has been a bit unstable lately.
The International Monetary Fund projected
one million percent inflation this year alone.
Wow, that’s wildly unstable.
It’s like the Lindsay Lohan of currencies.
You know, everything seemed fine in like 2004,
but eventually everything just fell apart.
“The currency is so devalued,
some shopkeepers weigh the money,
rather than waste time counting.”
Although it’s inspired at least one entrepreneur
put the cash to good use—
by making stuff like this handbag that can
be sold
for more than the cash itself is worth.
And Venezuela’s instability has also garnered
interest
from a much bigger entrepreneur: China.
In fact, empanada aficionado and brutal dictator
Nicolás Maduro
just got back from China.
...where he asked Xi Jinping
if he could please borrow a cup of sugar...
and like 5 billion dollars.
China has already loaned Venezuela about
70 billion dollars in the past ten years,
and apparently tens of billions haven’t
been paid off yet.
And even though Maduro is obviously a sub-sub-sub
prime borrower,
with the most worthless currency since Zimbabwe
had to issue those one-hundred-trillion dollar
notes,
...China isn’t worried.
Because Venezuela has the world’s biggest
oil reserves.
And that makes for some pretty sweet collateral.
Venezuela will sell 9.9 percent of shares
in an oil joint venture called Sinovensa
to the Chinese state-owned oil company
China National Petroleum Corporation, or CNPC,
for an undisclosed amount of cash.
China will own 49 percent of Sinovensa after
the sale.
And China will also be put in charge of
some of the drilling and oil extraction.
Maduro said the Sinovensa sale formed part
of
the plan to invest $5 billion over the next
year
in Chinese projects to double oil production
and send a million barrels per day to China.
“I calculate approximately five billion
dollars.
We will invest, together with China,
some five billion dollars in the course of
the year.”
And this is important, because even though
Venezuela
has the world’s biggest oil reserves,
it’s extremely bad at actually getting the
oil out.
That wasn’t always the case.
Venezuela used to be a wealthy nation,
thanks largely to its oil exports.
But in 1998,
Venezuelans elected socialist visionary Hugo
Chavez.
A few years later,
after anti-Chavez protests
at the big state-owned oil company PDVSA,
Chavez decided that the workers there
were not politically reliable.
So he fired 40% of the workforce,
including some of the best executives,
and put his own supporters in charge.
And now...
“With three times the quantity of people,
we produce one third the oil.”
Hey, at least he created jobs, right?
Even if they don’t accomplish much.
Anyway, China is incentivized to help by injecting
its own know-how and skilled labor into the
industry.
Because China wants the oil,
and definitely doesn’t want to be repaid
in Venezuelan currency.
So the China deal gives Maduro some breathing
room
to continue the Venezuelan socialist experiment
without having to actually reform
its corrupt and stupid economic policies.
Meanwhile, China gets its hands on
Venezuela’s natural resources,
and also grows its ability
to project influence in Latin America.
To quote Chinese state-run media,
it’s “mutual trust and win-win cooperation.”
Yes, Chinese state-run media Xinhua included
plenty of win-win rhetoric in its report
on the meeting between Xi and Maduro,
saying Sino-Venezuelan ties were taken “to
a higher level.”
Though I wonder how much it has to do with
helping Venezuela,
as opposed to helping the Chinese Communist
Party
become a dominant world power.
State-run Xinhua News quoted Xi Jinping as
saying
that Venezuela and China “should strengthen
multilateral coordination and cooperation,
and continue to intensify communication
within the United Nations.”
This could mean that in exchange for helping
Maduro stay in power,
the Chinese regime hopes that Venezuela will
vote in line with
China’s interests in bodies like the United
Nations,
as well as the China-CELAC Forum,
CELAC being the Community of Latin American
and Caribbean States.
And China is helping Maduro stay in power.
Not just through extending billions of dollars
in credit,
but also through actions like selling him
weapons
that Venezuelan riot police can use
to deal with those pesky protesters.
As for Venezuela’s part,
Xinhua News reported that Maduro
“highly agrees with Xi's concept of advocating
to build a community with a shared future
for humanity.”
I wonder what kind of shared future they have
in mind?
"According to official figures from the public
ministry,
between 2005 and June 2017,
there were 8,292 extrajudicial executions
in Venezuela.
This is a very high figure.
We are talking about approximately
22 percent of the homicides in the country
are carried out by the state.”
Or maybe this?
“Everyone in the world needs to know this—
we Venezuelans are dying of hunger.
We are living in a dictatorship in disguise.
Everyone is a witness to this.
There are many people that are afraid
and can’t speak out because they have us
gagged.
If you speak out they send the militias to
harm you or kill you.”
Or maybe it’s the future in which the socialist
leader of Venezuela
feasts on steak, while the rest of his country
eats fish heads.
No seriously, this video is from Maduro’s
trip back from China,
where stopped in Turkey and ate some delicious
steak
at a restaurant run by celebrity chef “Salt
Bae”.
Which was then followed by this unintentionally
hilarious Tweet
from US Senator Marco Rubio, saying:
“I don’t know who this weirdo Saltbae
is,
but the guy he is so proud to host
is not the President of Venezuela,
He is actually the overweight dictator of
a nation
where 30% of the people eat only once a day
and infants are suffering from malnutrition.”
I guess it’s a good thing that Senator Rubio
does not know who Salt Bae is.
And before we go,
it’s time when I answer a question
from one of our supporters
on the crowdfunding website Patreon.
Maxxxxxxx asks:
“dinner with either president xi or trump?
And why?”
Why not both?
I hear Mar-a-Lago has the best chocolate cake.
Thanks for your question, Maxxxxxxx.
So what do you think about China’s deal
with Venezuela?
Leave your comments below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
As I mentioned,
China Uncensored is supported mainly through
direct viewer contributions.
Go to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored or click
this orange button.
Check out all the cool rewards you get for
being a Patreon supporter—
including, of course, having me answer your
questions on the show.