on this episode of china uncensored
duck, duck
there's a lot of dead ducks here
i wouldn't johnson's it on your house
chris chapel china continues to inspire
people towards vegetarianism with the
caramel of dead animals
it keeps washing up in people's water
supplies
by recently reported that six thousand
decades washed up in a major shanghai
river
authorities think they were dumped by
pig farms upstream after the pigs died
of disease which is of course ridiculous
how could a couple of pig farms dumped
six thousand dead pigs
obviously that number should be much
higher
seven thousand
yon
eight thousand kamon china has next to
no regulations at least on businesses
ten thousand are you can fight so there
are a lot of dead pigs
fourteen thousand would be too little
how about sixteen thousand disease dead
pigs in their drinking water
do you know how many mika read you could
make with them
technically none the grades aren't
actually made out of pork but you get
the idea
and it's not just shanghai where people
had turned the rivers into graveyards in
hunan studio city they found another one
hundred dead pigs then right around the
corner and trying to stop italy found
fifty more
and it wasn't just pains
one local authorities said they were
dead chickens and ducks to
and it wasn't just in hunan province
sichuan province had half thousand dead
docs
thousand dead docs
don't worry though officials are saying
even though they don't know where all
the dead animals are coming from or why
they're dying like it's going out of
business
the water safe to drink and there's no
risk to humans
you know this is looking more and more
like a biblical plague tumi so let's see
we've got blood frogs hale this is
passed on ps
locust darkness
was the last one
old boy
thanks for watching this episode of
china uncensored
be sure to follow me on twitter and like
china and centered on face book and as
always subscribe in comment below
once again i'm chris chapel see you next
time