An out of control Chinese rocket
Crashes to Earth
And China blames the US
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
Good news! We’re all still\h
alive! Because this week,\h\h
debris from an out-of-control Chinese\h
rocket crashed into the Indian Ocean.
The Long March 5B rocket blasted off April\h
29, carrying components of China's planned\h\h
space station Harmony of the Heavens. But the\h
Chinese space agency lost control of the rocket\h\h
as it continued its 17,000 mile\h
an hour orbit around the earth\h\h
edging closer and closer with each\h
pass. Sky watchers caught glimpses\h\h
of it as it tracked as far north as New\h
York and as far south as New Zealand.
This was a big embarrassment\h
for the Chinese Communist Party.\h\h
Back in April, Chinese state-run media had proudly\h
touted the successful launch of the rocket.
China started out late to the space race. China\h
launched “its first satellite only in 1970,\h\h
13 years after the Soviet Union and\h
12 years after the United States.”
But dominating space has become a\h
priority for the Chinese Communist Party.\h\h
In 2019, China became the first country to land an\h
unmanned spacecraft on the dark side of the moon.
But the timing of this latest\h
rocket crash is particularly bad.\h\h
Later this month, China’s first unmanned\h
Mars rover is expected to land. But people\h\h
aren’t talking about how great that is.\h
Instead, people are now talking about this.
Criticism is now crashing down on China\h
after rocket fragments rained down near\h\h
the tropical islands of the Maldives. "It's an\h
alarming thing for them to be doing.'' Harvard\h\h
Smithsonian astrophysicist Jonathan McDowell\h
says China's rocket has a design problem.
Well, you don’t need to be an astrophysicist\h
to know that! But please continue.
(We normally make sure they\h
don't go into orbit at all,\h\h
or if they do, they have a restartable engine\h
which can bring them down in a controlled way.\h\h
Let's be clear here, it's not that China can't,\h
right? It's that they don't. That's exactly right.\h\h
Was it price? Was it laziness? I\h
would think it was a lack of concern.
It’s not surprising there’s\h
a lack of concern. You see,\h\h
China’s space program is actually run\h
by the Communist Party’s military.
In fact, because of the military link of China’s\h
space program, “Since 1999, the US has imposed\h\h
export controls on satellite technology to China.\h
And in 2011, Congress passed a law that imposed\h\h
restrictions on NASA engagement with China.”
Even though NASA hasn’t been great about that.
But China is actually banned from\h
the International Space Station.\h\h
So China is building its own. If only the rockets\h
carrying parts for it could make it to space.\h
After China lost control of the rocket, they\h
were pretty quiet about the whole thing.
NASA has been critical.
In a statement Nasa says “it\h
is clear that China is failing\h\h
to meet responsible standards\h
regarding their space debris.”
But now that the Chinese rocket has safely\h
crash landed in the middle of the Ocean,\h\h
China is taking responsibility.\h
By blaming the US for hyping fear!
It was 20 tons of flaming space debris\h\h
hurtling down on our heads! That’s\h
a reasonable thing to be afraid of!
But my favorite state-run media, the Global\h
Times, says US fussiness is a low ploy.
“These people are jealous of China’s\h
rapid progress in space technology.”
“Some of these people even try to use the\h
noises they made to obstruct and interfere\h\h
with China’s future intensive launches for\h
the construction of its space station.”
The Global Times says, “There is\h
also no evidence proving that the\h\h
landing points of US rocket debris are more\h
controllable compared with those of China’s.”
You know, evidence. With Chinese characteristics.
Now it’s true that uncontrolled space\h
debris is not a problem unique to China.\h\h
Back in 1979, the US Skylab space station broke up\h\h
over the Indian Ocean and scattered\h
debris across Western Australia.
Last month, SpaceX debris\h
landed on a farm in Washington.\h
But the criticisms of the Chinese military’s\h
space program aren’t about accidental debris.\h\h
They’re about careless rocket design and whether\h
China is cutting corners to win the space race.
And the Chinese Communist Party\h
is deflecting those criticisms\h\h
by blaming the US for...criticizing them.
Failure will happen as humanity\h
tries to reach for the stars.\h\h
But failure is not something the Chinese\h
Communist Party has ever been willing to face.\h\h
Which is why it’s so much easier to blame America.
And now it’s time to answer a question from a\h
member of the China Uncensored 50 Cent Army,\h\h
fans who support us and our efforts to expose\h
the truth about the Chinese Communist Party\h\h
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
Kenneth Crips asks, “Japan has always made it\h
clear they will not tolerate the Chinese mainland\h\h
invading Taiwan. I don’t know what China is\h
thinking. They are surrounded by enemies.”\h
That’s a very good question. It’s true, China\h
is surrounded by countries that are not happy\h\h
with its aggressive expansion or\h
desire for global hegemony. But,\h\h
as top-ranking Communist Party official Yang\h
Jiechi once said, “China is a big country and\h\h
you are small countries, and that is a fact.”\h
He was talking to Southeast Asian countries.
There is a limit to what any of the countries\h
surrounding China can do because of how much\h\h
power the Chinese Communist Party has. Sure,\h
all of China’s neighboring countries could unite\h\h
and form alliances against the Communist\h
Party—and to an extent they’re trying,\h\h
but it’s harder for a bunch of\h
countries to all work together,\h\h
than it is for the CCP to put enough pressure\h
on the weakest country to break that alliance.
Now, if an equally big country stood\h
behind them, like the United States,\h\h
that could present a real problem for the\h
CCP. But as Jim Fanell , the Former Director\h\h
of Intelligence and Information Operations for\h
the U.S. Pacific Fleet has told us on the show,\h\h
we’ve entered what he calls the decade of concern.
The idea is that in 2049, the CCP will celebrate\h
the 100 year anniversary of the founding of the\h\h
People’s Republic of China. The CCP has to take\h
Taiwan before then. It also knows if an invasion\h\h
of Taiwan happens too close to 2049, China will\h
be an international pariah. No one would be\h\h
celebrating the anniversary with China. Not good\h
for a country that wants to be a global hegemon.
But the CCP also knows that\h
it takes about 20 years\h\h
for the rest of the world to\h
forget something. For example,\h\h
in 1989, the Tiananmen Square Massacre\h
made China an international pariah.
20 years later, leaders from around the world\h
celebrated in Beijing the 2008 Olympics.
That’s why now is the decade of concern. The\h
CCP believes that if it takes Taiwan now,\h\h
the rest of the world will have\h
forgotten by the 2049 anniversary.\h\h
So what the Chinese Communist Party is thinking\h
is that it can’t afford not to take Taiwan now.
Thanks for your question Kenneth and your support.
And a big thank you to everyone who supports China\h
Uncensored on Patreon. We could not do this show\h\h
without you. So thank you for joining us in the\h
fight to expose the Chinese Communist Party to\h\h
the world. If you’re interested in joining, head\h
over to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored. You’ll get\h\h
a bunch of cool perks, including the chance\h
to have me answer your question on the show!
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next time.