On this episode of China Uncensored,
KFC has a new menu item in China.
Only this one,
you can’t eat.
Unlike its other menu items
which you just shouldn’t eat.
China has a new umbrella-sharing program,
and it’s all wet.
Plus China has a knockoff version of Disneyland...
and it’s even worse than you’d expect.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Have you ever thought,
I’d love to buy a new smartphone,
but I also love fried chicken!
If only there were some way to combine the
two!
Well, now your burning desire can be quenched!
KFC China has released...this.
Yes, this is real.
KFC is partnering with Chinese telecom giant
Huawei
to create a limited edition smartphone
to celebrate 30 years of KFC in China.
It's finger lickin’ good!
And it absolutely will not spy on you.
It comes in original KFC red,
and of course,
has the classic 11 secret herbs and spices.
I wonder if they’ll make a version
that’s two smartphones,
with a third smartphone in between.
We’ve all been there.
You’re out and about,
then suddenly, it starts raining!
And you don’t have an umbrella.
Well, one Chinese company,
called “Sharing E Umbrella,”
tried to start an umbrella revolution,
with an umbrella-share program.
Simply pick up any one of the conveniently
located umbrellas
across 11 different Chinese cities.
Probably should have put that
under an awning or something.
But in trying to help stop people
from being washed away,
they got washed out.
As the founder of Sharing E Umbrella
told the South China Morning Post,
“Umbrellas are different from bicycles.”
An astute observation.
Basically, you downloaded their umbrella-sharing
app,
and get a code to unlock a nearby umbrella
for a small rental fee.
Unfortunately, the app didn’t really explain,
well,
where you can return your umbrella.
And so a lot of people just kept them.
Almost all 300,000 of them.
And I don’t think the founder
will be singing in the rain now.
And hey,
remember that time you and your family
went on that magical vacation
to Nanchang Wanda theme park?
No?
Well apparently no one else does, either.
It opened last year but it’s losing money
fast.
It was created by the Chinese mega conglomerate
Dalian Wanda Group.
After it opened,
its founder told state-media
that he planned to set up
20 new theme parks across China,
so he could, quote,
“ensure Disney is not profitable
for 10 to 20 years in this business segment
in China.”
Well, speaking of being not profitable,
Dalian Wanda’s own theme parks.
This week, they announced they’re selling
their theme park business.
Dalian Wanda has too much debt,
and kinda needed the $9.3 billion dollars.
If only I had some theme parks
I could sell for a billion dollars.
“Uncensor Land.”
What?
It would be about exposing lies in the media.
Speaking of the happiest place on Earth—
Tibet.
Well, at least according to Chinese state-run
media.
And yet, despite how happy the Chinese Communist
Party
tells them they are,
Tibetans for some reason are outraged!
About many things, I suppose.
But the latest issue is that China
is making a region that was once part of Tibet
into a UNESCO World Heritage Site.
Well that actually sounds quite
decent of the Chinese Communist Party.
Maybe they’ve turned over a new leaf!
Or...not.
The Chinese regime went through a huge long
process
applying for the UNESCO status
through the United Nations.
And not just so they could tie with Italy
for the world’s most UNESCO heritage sites.
Yes, everything is a competition.
But China just lost,
because right after it added Hoh Xil
to its UNESCO stash,
Italy added two more.
But anyway,
what’s wrong with making this beautiful
region a World Heritage Site?
Well, in getting the UNESCO designation,
China got an exception
to have two-and-a-half-mile-wide corridor
with a highway and railroad
running through the middle,
as well as to develop some of the area around
them.
Because nothing protects pristine natural
habitat
like industrial development.
But the main reason Tibetan groups opposed
it
because the UNESCO designation allows Chinese
authorities
to kick out the nomads who’ve lived in the
area
for generations.
Of course, they’ll supposedly be resettled
into villages.
But then they wouldn’t be nomads anymore,
would they?
And finally in this week’s news,
the host of the world’s most popular New
York-based
English language comedy news show
about China-related current events,
became a viral Internet sensation,
...when he found out that instead of reading
Harry Potter on his Kindle,
he had accidentally read fan fiction.
Slightly inappropriate fan fiction.
Hey, it could happen
to anyone!
We’ll be right back.
I know, this video was fantastic. You're welcome.
But it doesn't stop here.
You can watch this, and two more segments, one ChinaUncensored.tv right now.
Yes, we're posting entire half-hour episodes to our website
with segments that aren't on YouTube yet.
So click here and check it out.