On this episode of China Uncensored,
will China become the next Syria?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
Oh say can you see,
by the dawn's early light,
the deep shadow of the Stars and Stripes?
The Chinese Communist Party sure can.
And it wants the Chinese people to as well.
That footage is of the five-year nightmare
that is the Syrian Civil War,
and not China.
But it could be China!
If the evil Western Powers have their way.
This video was posted by China’s Supreme
People’s...Procuratorate?
It’s kind of like China’s Attorney General.
This is the office that officially enforces
China’s arbitrary laws.
You see, “Currently China is peaceful and
stable,”
but if the US has its way,
China could become the next Syria!
Are you Syria-ous?!
Hey, it doesn’t have to be Syria.
It can be any place of political strife:
Iraq, Ukraine, Turkey,
or whatever’s going on in this unexplained
scene
from Batman versus Superman.
Seriously, can someone please tell me what
that was all about?
So how is the US planning to turn China into
the next Syria?
Is it by sending US presidential aides to
meet with top Chinese leaders?
Oh no!
It’s far more insidious.
You see, some people claim to have legitimate
concerns
about how the Communist Party governs.
Like, Chinese human rights lawyers.
Or ethnic minorities, like Tibetans.
Or the people of Hong Kong and Taiwan,
who are at a very real risk of having their
freedoms
encroached upon by Mainland China.
But it’s not like these groups have real
concerns that should be addressed!
They’re phony concerns, part of the hostile
US agenda.
Wow, that was some scary choral music.
I also like how they paint Joshua Wong,
the 19-year-old Hong Kong student activist,
as if he were a Mad Max villain.
The video goes on to accuse Western powers
of using
"democracy, freedom," and, even worse, "rule
by law"
to overthrow countries like
the Soviet Union.
Yes, that's exactly how it happened.
The ultimate aim of the video?
Warning people to stay alert and protect China
from color revolutions, by...
studying hard in school and working hard at
their jobs,
especially if they are scientists.
It's like the video was made by two hardline
Chinese military generals
and Tiger Mom, Amy Chua.
Who probably shamed the generals
because they couldn't play piano,
and then made them call their mothers.
What's that, Shelley?
The person who actually made the video
is a Chinese PhD student studying International
Relations in Australia?
Listen up, Lei Xiying, I've got a bone to
pick with you.
Why didn't I make it into that propaganda
video?!
Because I’m actually backed by a subversive
foreign force:
You, my 50-Cent Army!
So what do you think of the United States’
plan to turn China into Syria
by backing separatist forces like evil human
rights lawyers?
And what color would your revolution be?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Hey, did you like my episode about China’s
Pokemon Go Knockoff—City Elves Go?
Well I want to give a special shout out to
my friend Wookong,
as in Monkey King Sun Wu Kong,
for providing the footage of that game.
I was too busy playing the real game to get
it.
You should check out his channel.
It’s a great way to learn about Chinese
culture.
I mean, don’t you want to know about China’s
most famous assassin?!
Click here or in the link below.