A Pro-Democracy Legislator
In a city on the brink of totalitarianism
Is there hope left for Hong Kong’s liberty?
Welcome back to China Uncensored,
I'm Chris Chappell.
Joining me today is Hong Kong attorney
and activist Tanya Chen.
She is a member of Hong Kong's legislative
council.
Thanks for joining me today.
Thank you Chris.
These protests have gone on for over a hundred
days.
Police have said they might have to shoot
a protester
and then on October 1st,
they shot a protester point blank in the chest.
How has that changed the situation?
First of all, I do believe that a lot of Hong
Kong people
found that the brutality and use of force
has escalated
since the 1st of October.
And especially we have seen a lot of different
occasions
that our police seems to have lost control
and acted
in a very aggressive way.
And not only to the protesters,
but also to the first aiders, the reporters
or journalist
as well as the bystanders.
So I think this is a very dangerous situation
that our
supposed to be a professional team of laws
enforcement team
now acted in such a way and I of course,
I have no idea why there seems to be such
a escalation,
a very obvious escalation of force,
but at the same time I really worry that there
may be
some instructions or commands
from the high level of the police force
which encourage the frontline police officers
to use force with I would say with lesser
control.
Do you think the more aggressive tactics
of some of the frontline protesters
are also responsible for escalating the situation?
Well of course you can see that there
is a kind of escalation on both sides,
but still you can see our police officers
got a lot of different weapons.
Though sometimes we will call it less lethal
weapons,
but still they are quite dangerous.
For example, tear gas, batons,
especially the use of batons in the past,
we can see that the police officers use batons.
I don't think they used batons
according to international standards
or even their instructions.
So all these are in fact a very powerful and
dangerous weapons
that the police force are using.
And there's been some accusation that they're
even
using their rubber bullet guns and their tear
gas
in improper way aiming for the head.
Yes, exactly.
I think all these incidents and different
scenes
make people really worried about the escalation
of force,
and it seems that they are now kind of
a taking a revenge on this protesters.
So this is absolutely another level,
and it's very difficult to turn away from
the hatred
or these kinds of revenge or these kinds of
emotions.
So it's very important for the government,
for Mrs. Carrie Lam to understand the situation,
the danger,
and the situation is so critical,
that I would say she is just three centimeter
away
from a point of no return.
And that's why I really hope that she will
positively answer
or at least responds to our five demands.
Do you think there's any way the Hong Kong
government
or Carrie Lam can deescalate the situation
now
if they're that close to the edge?
Absolutely.
She has the power,
she is our chief executive and if she really
understand
or at least she has some reflections or inspiration
after having dialogue with the citizens
in the last dialogue sections last week,
I really think that she would now really appreciate
that the five,
the importance of these five demands to the
future of Hong Kong;
for example, like an independent commission
of inquiry.
I think at least more
than half of the citizens
that have a chance to speak, raised this point.
So this is a very clear demands
and of course with the support of polls,
all these very important information that
she can refer to and she can of course
give a positive answer to our society.
And of course the five demands,
it's a universal suffrage.
I think that's clear.
Without universal suffrage,
we can't even hold her accountable to Hong
Kong people.
So I think this is the only way forward if
she
positively responds to our five demands.
Speaking of the investigation into police
brutality,
I know recently you spoke at the UN asking
for their help to investigate that.
What role do you think the international community
has in the Hong Kong protest?
After these more than 110 days of protest,
it seems that we have a great difficulty
in getting this independent commission of
inquiry.
And you can see very clearly that the biggest
obstructions
or objections is from the pro establishment
camp.
But still, we really hope that the UN, the
United Nation,
the human rights committee will appreciate
our situation
and will set up this independent inquiry.
I think this is the fairest way to look into
the matters
of not only police brutality,
but if they want to investigate the course
of this whole protest,
please do.
I think that's the way to go forward.
And this is the only way that we can understand
the situation
and to improve in the future.
Now there's been talk of passing an anti mask
law
or invoking emergency ordinances to stop the
protests.
Do you think that would work?
Frankly speaking, I don't think that will
work,
they will only make people even angrier.
And after using all these very brutal force
unnecessarily
and disproportionately,
you can see that people still took to the
street,
even without the notification from the police.
And it seems that the people, well actually,
people are quite determined to fight this
battle.
And so with all these anti mask law or even
a curfew,
I'm afraid that they won't turn people away.
They would just make people again take to
the street,
and join any assembly or walk or march they
can.
Don't the people who are pushing the anti
mask law
and the emergency powers ordinances,
don't they know that people will just ignore
those?
Those who are pushing these laws,
are those who encourage.
I believe they are those who encouraged
Mrs. Kerry Lam to put forward,
or at least to push the extra edition bill
four to five months ago.
So I don't think these people
understand the present situation in Hong Kong.
Or they understand it,
but they just turn a blind eye to the critical
situation.
Or maybe it's something that the Chinese government
wants to do
because after pausing, or actually after the
1st of October,
the National Day, they can do anything they
want, they think.
And probably they will use even more high
handed method
to suppress or to press Hong Kong people.
So this is a part of their strategy.
What do you think legislators like yourself
can do to challenge Beijing's will in Hong
Kong?
Unfortunately we are the minority
under the present political situation.
It might be very difficult for us
to get all these motions or even these motions
to be passed.
But if the government,
or if Mrs. Carrie Lam,
once you pass this very powerful law, for
example,
like the anti mask law, based on emergency
regulations ordinance,
I think this will have a very longterm
and negative effect on Hong Kong.
And it will definitely affect Hong Kong's
economy
and international reputation.
So I really want to remind her
that though it may have some short term effect,
it will definitely adversely affect Hong Kong
in long run.
What would these emergency regulation ordinances,
what would they do?
What kind of powers
would they give Carrie Lam?
First of all, these emergency regulation ordinance
is a very powerful ordinance because the name,
you can tell from name,
and Mrs. Carrie Lam can avoid to take the
bill
to the legislature for legislature's scrutiny.
So she together with the executive council
can pass a law,
which is even inconsistent with the present
ordinances in Hong Kong.
For example, like the Bill of Rights.
So it's very easy for her to take away our
freedoms,
our civil rights without any scrutiny of legislature.
So it's a very, very dangerous,
but at the same time a very powerful law.
So it seems like there's some kind of shady
things
being done with basic law.
Yes, yes.
And at the same time,
it's very difficult for legislators to voice
or even to interrupt the only value left probably,
it's our courts.
But is it again for court to resolve political
problems?
I don't think that's the appropriate venue
for courts to do so.
So more than 2,000 people have been arrested
since the start of these protests.
You yourself were arrested
for participating in the 2014 umbrella movement
and given a suspended prison sentence.
What are these protesters facing after arrest?
First of all, of course is the pressure.
If they got arrested, and they've got bail,
of course they need to follow the bail terms,
no matter it is a court bail, or a police
bail.
Secondly, they may be charged.
The prosecution may lay charges against them
anytime,
and whether this situation will affect their
decision in the future,
I don't know.
But obviously for example, like for me,
I've been arrested for three times and they
charged me
at the very last occasion, with two very,
very unusual charges.
One is incite people to commit a public nuisance.
And the second one is incite others to incite
public nuisance.
Exactly.
That's the reason why I need to name my two
counts of charges
because it's not usual.
And in fact, at that moment you can see that
in Hong Kong
we have other charges that is more normal
and usual
that can be used by the prosecution.
But by charging us with, we call it a [inaudible]
offenses.
That means aiding and abetting or inciting.
This kind we call it [inaudible] offenses.
The maximum penalty of these offenses is seven
years,
so they can immediately escalate the maximum
penalty of our charges.
So they make sure that we are going to face
the most serious charges that they can handle,
or at least they can try to prove.
So that's our situation.
And of course from 2014 until now,
we have only gone through the first level
of the court.
So we have our case,
it has been handled by the district court
and now we are waiting for a court of appeal,
and probably will go to the court of final
appeal.
So the whole process may take three to four
years to finish.
And so, I can only tell those who are being
arrested,
please do seek your legal advice.
But at the same time, as a legislator with
a legal background,
I would tell them that think twice before
they act.
Because I think most of them are prepared
or at least prepared in a sense that they
understand
the possibility of being charged.
But still you may need to face them
and you may need to face them for a very long
time.
So I still believe that people should think
twice before they act.
So when you say that, should they not be protesting?
Or how can they balance this fight
that the protestors believe was staying safe?
As far as I understand, some or most of the
protesters
do understand that they are participating
in different kinds of activities.
And all these activities, some of them may
lead to
various potential legal charges or criminal
charges
that may affect their future.
The only thing that I really want to tell
them is to think twice
because that is something that not only will
be faced by yourself,
your own self, but maybe faced by your whole
family.
But I respect that decision.
But still this is a decision
needed to be made with sufficient information.
For example, like legal information,
as well as an understanding of the potential
consequences,
legal consequences and the consequences on
their future.
So is the Hong Kong judiciary system,
is it still impartial or are these politically
motivated arrests?
Well 40 arrests, of course,
because it's all handled by the police,
I still believe that the police can do a better
job.
For example,
You can see the difference between
the umbrella movement versus now.
For example, normally during the Umbrella
Movement
for those who are arrested,
the police normally would only detain them
for 10 to 16 hours.
And then they finished their investigation,
and they would release them on bail
or just detain them until conditional release.
But now, normally they would just detain them
for 40 hours
with a house search.
And with two, three, four statements, and
those irregularities
that I've heard from the lawyers,
and even worse, it's really worse.
It's really horrible.
During this protest.
For example, the lawyers wait outside
to meet their clients for hours.
Even more than 10 hours without seeing them.
And though the are clients requested to see
their lawyers.
But without seeing their lawyers, the caution
statement
were taken without legal advice.
Without meeting their lawyers beforehand,
despite request has been pleased or made to
the police officers.
So these are absolutely taking away their
civil rights
and it's against the practices and against
law,
but the police just ignore it.
And I think lot of malpractices
happened during these four months.
And because I'm lawyer,
I went to North Point police station,
I think on Monday.
And the first thing we do is to file a complaint
with the duty officer at that police station,
because the lawyers have been waiting
for more than 10 hours to meet their first
client.
And they have a whole list provided to the
police
more than 10 hours.
So that's the situation.
And those malpractice, I can't say limited,
but at least it's kind of under control
during the umbrella movement.
So I think this is something that is unfair,
impartial and definitely is affected by
their political affiliation or political views.
So I think this is absolutely unacceptable.
It doesn't seem like the protestors are going
to give up,
but it also seems like the Chinese communist
party
is not going to give ground.
How does this end?
I'm afraid that the Chinese government
is going to use a even more harsher or stronger,
harder attitude.
They were just having harder and tougher attitude
to us.
Hong Kong, so now Carrie Lam is just a puppet.
I'm afraid that the Chinese government will
just
interfere in all kinds of matters,
which supposed to be under our local jurisdictions.
For example, like the extradition bill.
I understand there is rumors saying that,
or there is news saying that our chief executive,
Mrs. Carrie Lam, Lee needs to get the approval
in order to withdraw the bill.
So I'm afraid that Chinese intervention in
our local matters
will become more and more often.
All right.
Thank you so much for joining me today.
Thanks.
Thank you very much.
Thank you Chris.
Thank you.