On this episode of China Uncensored,
it’s been 20 years since the British
gave Hong Kong back to China.
And everything is awesome.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
20 years ago tomorrow,
on July 1, 1997,
the British handed Hong Kong over to China.
1997 was a simpler time.
It was the year we told you what we want,
what we really, really want.
The year we ran through Platform Nine
and Three Quarters for the very first time.
And the year we promised Leo
that our hearts would go on,
by watching him die in a movie theater
like 14 times.
Wait.
1997 was 20 years ago?
Shelley, I think I'm glimpsing
my own mortality.
Make it stop.
Oh good.
In an MmmBop it's gone.
But in China in 1997,
the theme was reunification.
Look how happy it made everyone!
At the time,
Hong Kong, the Pearl of the Orient,
had been under British rule for 156 years.
Their lease for Hong Kong was signed
not with the Chinese Communist Party,
but two governments prior,
when the Chinese emperor wore golden robes
and the British queen wore a fancy crown.
Wait, she still does.
The reasons why the British
had to return Hong Kong to China
are so complicated that they should be
a whole other episode—
and let me know in the comments below
if you want me to do that episode—
but suffice it to say:
Chinese leaders made it clear:
what we want,
what we really, really want
is for Hong Kong to be part of China again.
So starting in the 1980s,
the Chinese Communist Party began
negotiating the handover with Great Britain.
They agreed on the principles of
“One Country, Two Systems”
and “50 Years, No Change”,
where yes,
Hong Kong would technically become part of
China,
but would get to keep its basic freedoms,
rule of law,
and capitalist economy—
complete with dangerously unregulated street
signs.
And the CCP would definitely,
in no way change Hong Kong
for at least 50 years.
Plus 2047 was so far away!
I’m sure by then we’ll all be living on
that moon colony
New Gingrich keeps talking about.
Anyway, at the time of the handover,
in 1997, there were some concerns about
what the future of Hong Kong would become
under the Chinese Communist Party’s rule.
After all,
it had been only eight years since Tank Man.
But most predictions for the future
of Hong Kong were optimistic.
At the time,
The Economist suggested that Hong Kong
“could serve as a laboratory
for political change on the mainland.”
A former Washington Post correspondent said
Hong Kong will “infect China with democracy.”
And The New York Times called Hong Kong
a Trojan Horse that could “destroy those
in power,”
and suggested that perhaps
“it is the Chinese Communist Party leaders
who should tremble about whether
their style of life and leadership
can long survive” when faced with
the shining beacon of Hong Kong’s freedoms.
Granted, there were also a few
negative nellies out there,
like an article in Fortune Magazine called
The Death of Hong Kong.
It predicted Hong Kong would
lose its global standing,
that English would lose its place to Mandarin,
that legislators and the Chief Executive
would be selected by the CCP,
and that power struggles in Beijing
would ultimately determine
who really rules Hong Kong.
But a lot of Hong Kongers
were also cautiously optimistic.
After all, most Hong Kongers
were ethnically Chinese,
and like I said,
the big theme at the time
was reunification with the motherland.
So they held a giant ceremony,
did their awkward handover thing,
and everyone celebrated together
in weird harmony.
Including a huge gala
where the biggest Hong Kong stars
sang a medley of popular songs,
some of which had their lyrics changed
to be about Hong Kong reuniting with China.
So how did it all turn out?
Are the 7 million residents of Hong Kong
better off?
Well, of course!
The Chinese Communist Party
kept all its promises.
For six years.
And then they tried to sneakily implement
Article 23,
a draconian anti-subversion law,
under the guise of national security.
It was designed to allow police
to burst into people’s homes,
search their stuff,
and arrest them without a warrant,
just because they’re suspected of
“subversion” of the Chinese Communist
Party.
It also criminalized speech
that instigates subversion,
whatever that means.
Oh, and it made things
that were illegal in mainland China,
also illegal in Hong Kong.
But Hong Kongers discovered
what Article 23 was all about.
And some of them marched
through the streets in protest.
And by some,
I mean half a million people.
The CCP wasn't expecting so many people
to oppose Article 23,
which was then withdrawn.
And the CCP was forced to back down.
For a while, at least.
Until they realized
what Hong Kongers really need
is more effective brainwashing.
So in 2012,
they tried to force Hong Kong schools
to teach what they called
“Patriotic Education.”
It would give children
“lessons on appreciating mainland China,”
and “[gloss] over major events
like the Cultural Revolution
and the Tiananmen Square crackdown.”
And there’s nothing wrong with patriotic
education,
according to Chinese state media.
But once again,
those rebellious Hong Kongers didn’t agree.
And once again,
thousands took to the streets to protest,
including many high school students.
And once again,
they forced the CCP to back down.
If those high school students
had just been patriotically educated,
none of this would have happened.
But anyway, the Communist Party
just wouldn’t give up.
It just kept going and going.
Like the Energizer Bunny,
but evil.
You see, an important milestone was coming
up.
The CCP had promised that in 2017,
Hong Kongers would be able to directly elect
their chief executive for the first time,
instead of having someone chosen by
a select pro-Beijing election committee.
So in 2014,
the CCP announced that, yes,
they would indeed keep their promise
and allow Hong Kongers to elect
their chief executive,
as long as the pro-Beijing election committee
could “assist” Hong Kong’s democratic
process
by pre-selecting all the candidates
that people could vote for.
You know, to make sure the candidates
“love the country and love Hong Kong.”
It's like one of those diets
where you can eat whatever you want,
as long as it's broccoli.
You probably know what's coming next.
100,000 Hong Kongers
came out to protest.
Police beat them and fired tear gas.
Or as they call it in China,
Patriotism Vape.
Side effects may include
shedding tears of love for your country.
Those protests became the Umbrella Movement.
It was called that because Hong Kong protesters
used umbrellas as shields
against the Patriotism Vape.
Umbrellas are not always
the most effective shields.
But probably more effective than...
whatever I was trying to do here.
A lot of people were afraid the Umbrella Movement
would turn in Tiananmen Square 2:
Electric Boogaloo.
But it didn’t.
Which is good,
because the sequel is always
worse than the original.
Anyway, Chinese state-run media
largely tried to ignore the Umbrella Movement,
and when they couldn’t they framed it
as a secret American plot to undermine China.
See?
Hong Kong was a Trojan horse after all!
Ultimately the protests faded away
and the next Chief Executive
was a pro-Beijing candidate
chosen by the election committee.
So did Fortune Magazine
accurately predict Hong Kong’s fortune?
Well, it did accurately predict that legislators
would eventually be selected by the CCP.
And Hong Kong did lose
some of its global standing,
as China’s entry into the WTO
helped the CCP build up cities
like Beijing and Shanghai.
In 1997, Hong Kong “accounted for some
16 percent of China’s GDP;
that figure has now shrunk to 3 percent.”
And Mandarin has replaced English
as the second most common language,
as close to a million mainland Chinese
have moved to Hong Kong.
And the future of Hong Kong
is definitely connected to the power struggle
between current Chinese leader Xi Jinping
and former commander toad,
Jiang Zemin.
But Chris, you say -
This all sounds so depressing.
Is Hong Kong's future just one of doom and
gloom
under the CCP?
Well, that just depends on your perspective.
Like from the perspective
of my favorite state-run media,
The Global Times,
everything is great since
“decolonization is finally coming to Hong
Kong."
And state-run Xinhua News informs us that
“Democracy, but a mirage during Britain's
150 years of rule,
has been greatly expanded.”
And if you're still not convinced,
Xinhua even released a rap video
ahead of the celebrations,
about how cool things are in Hong Kong now,
and how it's forever part of the motherland.
Here's how they describe the handover:
“All Chinese people had tears on their faces.
Lowering humiliation, raising sovereignty.
Raising up our dignified sovereignty."
See?
Everything is great.
But to be serious for a moment,
one of the things I really admired
about people in Hong Kong
when I was there last year
and especially in 2014
during the Umbrella Movement,
was their genuine love of Hong Kong
that drove them to resist the CCP's
encroachment on their way of life.
And it has made a difference.
If Hong Kongers hadn't stood up against the
CCP
in the last 20 years,
the CCP would have imposed
an anti-subversion law
that would ruin Hong Kong's freedoms,
patriotically re-educated their kids,
and given them the formality of
"universal suffrage" without a real vote.
So yes,
the future of Hong Kong
does depend on what happens in
the Party's internal power struggle.
But it also depends on the people of Hong
Kong,
and whether they continue to resist the Party.
Because one thing's clear:
the Chinese Communist Party
won't stop trying to control Hong Kong.
And for those of us outside Hong Kong,
the last 20 years is a warning.
A warning to Taiwan about what reunification
with a China controlled by the CCP
would look like.
And a warning to the rest of the world
about how well the Communist Party
keeps its promises.
But hey,
as the Xinhua rap video points out,
at least Hong Kong is getting
the world's longest bridge.
Which is what they want. What they really, really want.
So what do you think of the handover
of Hong Kong to China?
Leave your comments below.
Once again,
I’m your host, Chris Chappell,
see you next time.