China Uncensored host, Chris Chappell
came to Taiwan on November 19,
and held a fan meet-up.
Nice to meet you.
Chris Chappell!
So two years ago,
I was in Hong Kong for the Umbrella Revolution.
Did I ever say I narrowly escaped death?
Let the record show that we narrowly escaped death.
Every country that I'm traveling to,
I will have narrowly escaped death.
One thing I want to make very clear is, on the show,
I never want to have anyone think,
"China is bad. We should get rid of China."
The problem is the Chinese Communist Party,
which has trashed China,
which has brought a lot of damage to the Chinese people,
the Communist Party is the problem.
Alright, any more questions? Yes?
With the new Trump presidency...
- I knew this would happen!
Thank you for coming, I'll see you all later!
I just want to give a big thank you to Arthere Café
for hosting the China Uncensored Taiwan fan meet-up.
If you're ever in Taiwan, be sure to check it out.
They've got great food and great drinks.