On this episode of China Uncensored
Five Chinese Military Fails
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I'm your
host Chris Chappell.
China's military.
The largest standing army in the world!
Now sure, they know how put on a good show
when the rest of the world is watching.
Wow, that's just creepy.
But the People's Liberation Army has its problems,
too.
Like that it's riddled with corruption.
And many of the top generals
are just high-ranking Communist Party officials
without real combat experience.
And the fact that soldiers have to spend
20 to 30 percent of their time studying Party
propaganda,
singing patriotic songs, and discussing Marxist-Leninist
thought.
Though that doesn't mean they aren't a force
to be reckoned with.
In fact, their last large scale deployment
was a complete success!
In Beijing.
In 1989.
But when the opponent isn't a group of unarmed
protesters,
things might be a little more difficult.
So here are five Chinese military fails
Number 5
You want your artillery to be powerful.
Strong. Intimidating.
So it might not be so great for your image
if people see this when you're transporting
your artillery down the street.
Number 4
Here's a unique training method.
Surely it's a good idea to play a game hot
potato
with a live grenade.
I feel like there's potential for this to
go really, really badly.
Number 3
In Chinese movies like this one,
soldiers demonstrate great skill with grenades.
But life does not always imitate art.
Number 2
But when grenade fails prove too embarrassing,
leave it up to state-run media to turn a fail
into a propaganda piece.
"In the few seconds between life and death,
we see the glorious tradition of our army,
which has already become a part of the blood
of our military officials and soldiers."
I don't think the viewers bought it.
And Number 1
When you're not accidentally blowing things
up,
at least you should be able to blow up your
targets on purpose.
Here, the reporter is ready to witness the
military's technique for demolishing a tower.
That was a really long silence.
So those are 5 Chinese military fails.
What do you think? Leave your comments below,
and be sure to subscribe for more episodes
of China Uncensored.
And I just want to take this moment
to thank all of you who make this show possible
by supporting China Uncensored on Patreon.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell, see you next
time.