Hi, Chris Chappell here, live in Korea
—when I recorded this.
I've chosen this as the perfect location
to announce the winners of the
3rd Annual China Uncensored
Viewer Contest Gala Extravaganza Spectacular
Event Thing!
I received so many Year of the Monkey submissions
that it was hard to choose just one.
So that's why I chose two!
These are the two winners.
You'll receive in the mail a special
collector's edition China Uncensored poster
autographed by…
me! Chris Chappell.
So thank you to everyone who entered.
Check out the Facebook page to see all the
entries
and if you're the winners
you should email me your addresses so I can
send you those posters.
Thanks again to everyone who participated.