On this episode of China Uncensored,
Emails, sche-mails.
Wait, that doesn’t sound right.
Why be a Christian, when you can be a Communist!
And finally, maybe caving to China over Taiwan
was not such a good idea.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
You know, when I heard about the Hillary Clinton
email scandal,
I was saddened—
because it had nothing to do with China.
Oh, if only it had been China that hacked
her emails,
not Russia!
Well good news, America!
It’s possible China may have also
hacked Hillary Clinton’s emails.
According to two sources who spoke to
the conservative news website The Daily Caller,
a Chinese company inserted code on her server
that forwarded copies of Clinton’s emails
to China in real time.
And the Intelligence Community Inspector General
apparently warned of the problem,
but the FBI failed to act.
But on the plus side,
it gave Trump the chance to talk about CHINA,
Crooked Hillary, and the Tainted FBI all in
a single tweet.
It’s like Trump getting a McFlurry,
with Oreos, and a cherry on top.
The FBI has denied Trump’s tweet,
but hasn’t made any statements regarding
the Daily Caller report.
Of course, a spokesman for Clinton has denied
the server was hacked from China.
All we know for certain is from this DOJ report.
It says that former FBI Director James Comey
originally said it was “reasonably likely”
that hostitle actors gained access
to Clinton’s private email server,
but later changed it to “possible.”
The FBI also claimed that although it was
possible,
they did not find conclusive evidence of it.
So...no proof from the FBI,
just two anonymous sources
talking to a conservative media outlet.
Not exactly a solid indictment.
But it sure makes a clickable headline for
China Uncensored.
In other news, following trends can be dangerous.
Don’t give in to peer pressure—
just because all your friends are doing something
like, taking Holy Communion
—kids these days are doing that—
don’t just blindly join in.
Christianity is not for everyone.
But communism is!
It will be required.
At least that’s the message the Chinese
Communist Party
is giving to Christians in China.
They’ve been forcing house Christians to
sign statements
saying they renounce their beliefs.
This is a standard one, republished by VOA.
The statement says, among other things,
“I had limited understanding of Christianity.
Taking on Christianity as my belief
is also blindly following the trend.
Now I have a more comprehensive understanding
of religion and religious beliefs.
After further studying Christianity,
I have a clearer understanding of my spiritual
needs.
I announce that I will not participate
in Christian religious activities
from now on and I will no longer believe in
Christianity.”
Christians have never been treated well in
China.
First you have to belong to a church
approved of by the Communist Party—
or your belief in Christianity is illegal.
There are tens of millions of “house Christians”
who belong to underground churches
or illegal Bible study groups.
But the Communist Party’s persecution of
Christians
has gotten pretty extreme in recent years.
Like tearing down crosses…
which sometimes randomly catch fire,
whoops, how did that happen?
Or telling people to replace
pictures of Jesus with pictures of Xi Jinping.
Look, if Nero couldn’t stop the Christians,
the Communist Party sure isn’t going to
be able.
Then again, maybe in its own way, the Communist
Party
will embrace some parts of Christianity.
If only to keep its soldiers upright.
President Trump has finished trade talks with
Mexico
and apparently, no more NAFTA.
But obviously the bigger question on everyone’s
mind
is what does this mean for the ongoing trade
war with China.
And experts say Trump’s success means China
will be in a more defensive position moving
forward.
According to some experts in the financial
services company ING Group,
“It strengthens the US position to play
hard-ball with China.”
Here’s what Trump’s National Economic
Council Director
Larry Kudlow had to say.
Our deal with Mexico shows that free trade,
fair trade can be done.
That a pro-growth trade deal can be made.”
“I think in this global game of world trade
politics
I think China is now on the defensive because
they see the US is getting some momentum and
I think that's great.”
And here’s what President Trump had to say.
“They want to talk,
and it's just not the right time to talk right
now,
to be honest, with China.
It's been—it's too one-sided for too many
years,
for too many decades, and so it's not the
right time to talk.”
Of course, that’s not the feeling in Beijing.
Two former top Chinese officials told the
South China Morning Post
that China will win the trade war.
And you can always trust top Chinese officials.
Speaking of good ideas by top Chinese officials:
The One Child Policy.
For decades, the law was that most couples
could only have one child—
or face stiff penalties or forced abortions.
The idea was to keep China’s population
from growing too quickly.
But eventually, Chinese officials realized,
oops,
the current population is getting old,
and we didn’t make enough young people.
So a few years ago,
they changed it to a Two Child Policy.
But even that wasn’t enough
to fix China’s demographics problem.
So now, for the first time in decades,
Chinese people may be allowed to have multiple
children,
and hopefully less forced abortions.
There’s a draft reform law to China’s
Civil Code
would end the two child limit.
But don’t think that obsessive top-down
family planning controls are over!
One Chinese think tank has even proposed a
plan
to force couples who don’t make enough children
to pay extra taxes.
China’s first homemade aircraft carrier
has hit the water.
And despite being made in China, it didn’t
sink.
It’s part of the Chinese regimes attempts
to project military power around the world.
But it’s not just limited to the world.
The Chinese Communist Party also has its sights
set on space.
China has launched a record number of satellites
this year.
The two most recent launches were part of
“the Beidou system,
China’s answer to the US GPS precision timing
and navigation system.”
China wants to rival the United States in
GPS technology.
But it's also part of a much larger campaign
of space warfare,
that seeks to place the Chinese regime as
the dominant space power.
And finally, you know how all those airlines
have been
caving to Chinese demands to stop labeling
Taiwan
as a separate country in their drop-down menus?
I mean, I get it.
Taiwan is small,
and Mainland China might have
the world’s biggest market for airlines
just a few years from now.
Well, guess what?
Caving to the Chinese regime’s demands
is not working out.
Surprise, surprise, the Chinese government
is giving big subsides to Chinese airlines.
And US airlines are finding it quote,
difficult to make a profit.
Truly, I am shocked.
Although one airline found has a clever workaround
to deal with the Communist Party’s demands
to include
Taiwan as part of China.
On the United Airlines website,
there’s a page that allows you set your
location
“for currency-slash-payment purposes”.
And they list a bunch of countries.
China, Taiwan, and Hong Kong are listed separately,
but based on their currency,
not their country-slash-region status.
Taiwan’s foreign ministry thanked United
for its flexibility.
I mean, even though Taiwan is definitely
part of the People’s Republic of China,
the Communist Party
can’t deny that Taiwan has its own currency,
right?
What’s that, Shelley?
Nope, they’re still upset.
Apparently, my favorite state-run media The
Global Times
wrote this article called “United Airlines,
Don’t Think About Outsmarting China.”
It accuses United of “attempting to fool
Chinese”
and “playing word games.”
Right.
Because it’s not like the entire “One
China” policy
is some kind of giant word game that the Chinese
Communist Party
wants the rest of the world to play.
And now it’s that time when we answer questions
from fans
who support China Uncensored on the crowd
funding website patreon.
Weesh asks,
How did you guys come up with
the “wacky Chris plus straight man Shelley”
personas?
Did that happen organically or by design?
What are you talking about?
Shelley is almost impossible to deal with—
she’s a total diva who says the wildest
things.
Whereas I am the rock of this show.
What’s that Shelley?
No.
I don’t know what you’re talking about.
Everything I just said was completely true.
Stop rolling your eyes at me!
I can hear it!
Thanks for you question, Weesh.
And remember, YouTube is constantly demonetizing
us—
taking away ads temporarily or permanently
across tons of our videos.
That’s because we talk about “controversial
topics”
that don’t fit into their well manicured
“community guidelines.”
So we rely in support from you, the viewers.
If you can, support us by contributing to
the show on Patreon.
I know I pitch this every episode, but seriously,
you are what keeps the lights on.
If you want to learn more, I’ve put the
link below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Want to learn more about China?
Then check out our new podcast, China Unscripted!
Matt, Shelley and I sit down with China experts
to talk about some of the most critical China
news out there.
Trust me, it’s way more entertaining than
it sounds.
Look for the China Unscripted Podcast on iTunes,
Stitcher, and Spotify,
as well as on YouTube.