On this episode of China Uncensored,
who wins Brexit?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m host
Chris Chappell.
You know, I’m a busy man.
That’s why I like portmanteaus.
Things are so much easier to understand when
they’re one word.
Like brunch.
Or sharknado.
And most recently, Brexit.
Yes, the UK narrowly voted in a nationwide
surveymonkey poll
to leave the European Union, which,
to use the traditional English vernacular,
“didn't quite go as planned.”
So yes, Brexit may have cost us all,
“a bit of pocket change.”
But really, who’s the br’inner in all
this?
And who’s the br’oser?
Bresides Britain of course?
China.
China just hit the propaganda jackpot.
As Quartz puts it,
“Brexit gives China’s Communist Party
concrete evidence
that democracy can be catastrophic.”
Chinese state-run media is eating it up.
The UK leaving the EU is like a bomb;
The ground is moving and the mountains are
shaking.”
One professor at Renmin University of China
said democracy is “a game,”
that was “kidnapped by populism,”
and resulted in “tragedy.”
And can you imagine what “tragedies” would
befall China
if people there got to vote?
And it’s a good thing for the Chinese regime
that Brexit
has become such a propaganda boom
because in every other respect,
Brexit is a disaster for China.
Well, maybe not the Chinese stock market.
That’s actually gone up since Brexit.
But that’s only because China’s central
bank
poured billions of yuan into the market since
the vote.
And that kind of top-down benevolence just
doesn’t happen in a democracy.
But unfortunately for the Chinese regime,
Brexit has foiled their long term plans for
infiltrating Europe.
China has invested heavily in the United Kingdom.
Britain is currently China’s top destination
when it comes
to investing in Europe.
20% of all Chinese direct foreign investment
in Europe goes to the UK.
And the British government knew which side
its biscuits were buttered on.
The United Kingdom has made no secret of the fact
that it wants to strengthen ties with China.”
And that’s thanks largely to soon-to-be-former-Prime
Minister David Cameron.
He was the first head of state in the European
Union
to publicly push for a free trade deal between
the EU and China.
Yeah, the Chinese regime got in good with
Cameron.
They even made plans to build a bunch of nuclear
reactors in England.
It was part of the so-called Golden Era China-UK
relations.
“I think this is going to be a very important
moment for British-Chinese relations which
are in a very good state,
something of a golden era in our relationship.”
I mean, it can really only go up since the
Opium Wars.
But anyway, under Prime Minister Cameron,
the UK was the first EU member that wanted
to give China
Full Market Economy status.
That would have made it it harder for the
EU to impose tariffs
on cheap Chinese goods that flood the European
market.
But that’s all likely to change thanks to
Brexit.
That’s partly because other powerful members
of the EU
don’t have such a cozy relationship with
China.
Germany’s Economy Minister recently said
Germany needs to
take “an aggressive position against China.”
China is already in an economic slump,
with growth at a record low of
“no one really believes their GDP data anymore.”
So anything that could slow China’s trade
with Europe
can now do real damage to China’s economy.
Even China’s relationship with the UK itself
may get a bit icy.
This recent report to Westminster by activists
and conservative MPs,
called the Darkest Moment,
says the UK should distance itself from China.
One of the report’s authors, Dr. Christopher
Hancock,
said in a statement that
“British citizens can, and must,
attempt to change their government’s hitherto
misguided response to [China].”
So as David Cameron steps aside,
it might be the “hitherto” Golden Era
that takes a Brexit.
Or is it a Chexit?
So what do you think about the impact of Brexit
on China?
Leave your comments below.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.