the problem with the national security law is is\h
that it's firstly it's so vaguely written that\h\h
uh you know any one of us um i'm sure would be in\h
breach of many categories of it and and the fact\h\h
is also it has this extra territorial application\h
so actually i mean i've been in breach of the\h\h
national security law many times a day every\h
day since it was introduced just by sitting in\h\h
in this chair in London and uh and talking\h
about hong kong you're British? you didn't guess\h\h
um well so because it is extra territorial it\h
just seems to me that you know that this has\h\h
become a red line for the chinese communist\h
party they i don't think they're gonna\h\h
back down from this but obviously the\h
international community can't let this\h\h
stand so kind of like an immovable object meaning\h
an unstoppable force what's where is this going\h\h
well i think it it definitely uh marks obviously\h
it marks the total end of hong kong's autonomy and\h\h
basic freedoms and and the rule of law um it's\h
surely a turning point for the international\h\h
community um i mean the international community's\h
response rhetorically has been quite strong\h\h
in terms of actions the actions that the united\h
states and the uk have taken uh are certainly\h\h
very welcome but i think there's a real need for\h
others in the international community to step up\h\h
and really for the whole free world to unite um\h
in our outcry at what's happened to hong kong\h\h
not just because it's devastating for hong kong\h
but actually if the ccp is allowed to get away\h\h
with what they've done they won't stop there you\h
know we talked about taiwan a few minutes ago\h\h
taiwan will be next and our own freedoms will\h
be after that i mean wouldn't you say that they\h\h
have essentially gotten away with it though so\h
far uh yes i think that that is true um and that's\h\h
why we need a much more robust international\h
response so that um yes they may get away with\h\h
it but we need to ensure that they pay the highest\h
possible price so that means targeted sanctions\h\h
uh and and other forms of pressure so that um\h
they may get away with it but but not without cost\h\h
well so you mentioned the sanctions the u.s\h
government has put on um many officials in hong\h\h
kong uh which which might actually have an impact\h
on the chinese communist party because it uh we\h\h
actually did an episode about it uh how it cuts\h
off potentially chinese banks from the u.s dollar\h\h
do you think there's anything more that can be\h
done and in particular what more can the uk do\h\h
well so we have the u.s sanctions which are very\h
welcome but i think it would be even stronger if\h\h
uh if if many other parts of the free world\h
uh also introduce sanctions so i think the uk\h\h
which now has um magnitsky\h
style sanctions legislation\h\h
should be looking very seriously at uh at imposing\h
either magnitsky sanctions on um carrie lam\h\h
and uh some of the senior police officers\h
responsible for police brutality and officials\h\h
in beijing who are responsible for uh destroying\h
the sinai british joint declaration and\h\h
and uh breaking their promises to hong kong\h
um or if um there's a possibility that uh\h\h
the current magnitsky legislation um the criteria\h
may or may not uh be able to be applied to\h\h
to hong kong and that's debatable but if that's\h
the case and the british government should either\h\h
amend the legislation or or introduce a\h
separate sanctions regime but but either\h\h
way uh i think the uk should introduce targeted\h
sanctions and then i think other countries uh\h\h
european countries canada australia and and if\h
the free world really unites and coordinates these\h\h
kind of measures then then i think that could have\h
uh uh an impact what do you think's stopping that
you