China rams a Filipino fishing boat
and you won't believe how Duterte responded.
Or maybe you will
Huawei employees have been secretly
working with China's military.
What a surprise.
And Trump and Xi will meet at the G20.
What will they talk about?
Probably chocolate cake.
Hi, welcome to China uncensored I'm Chris Chappell.
I'm Shelley Zhang.
So we're here in Hong Kong
covering the protests however we figured
is probably pretty important to cover
some of the other China news going on
out there
So we're gonna do sort of off-the-cuff
run down to some of the biggest China
news stories that have been happening.
Shelley why don't you lead us off with
the top one?
Okay so two weeks ago a
Chinese boat rammed a Filipino fishing
boat in the South China Sea.
So it was in this area called Reed Bank which falls
in the Philippines exclusive economic
zone.
So that's pretty close to actual
Filipino territory; this is not disputed
waters.
Exclusive economic zones are
about 200 nautical miles outside of the
actual land of the Philippines so yeah
it's still I think within some area
where the Chinese obviously have these
vessels in the area that are fishing
boats...
in quotation marks were very low.
She made quotation marks.
There are fishing boats and they are part of
what's called the you know China's
maritime militia and if you'd like us to
do a video on that in the future please
let us know in the comments below it's
pretty interesting.
But anyway so 22 fishermen were thrown into the water and
then the Chinese boat kind of fled the
scene but luckily the fishermen were
rescued by a boat from Vietnam.
Now the interesting thing about this is how much
Duterte has kind of downplayed it.
He called it he just called it a maritime incident.
These are not ironic quotation marks.
No these are actually said a
maritime incidence.
A maritime incidence and there was no confrontation.
People have gotten so upset about this like
there's talk about actually trying to
impeach Duterte sort of based on the
idea that
part of his duty is to protect the like
territorial integrity of the Philippines
and now people are kind of saying well
you're not doing that
Duterte had a very interesting response
event though, Shelly.
I think the headline
here says impeach me I'll put you all in
jail.
Duterte also said that you know
China could fish in the Philippines
exclusive economic zone because China
the Philippines are friends.
That got a little taken out of context in some of
the media where it seemed like oh he was
giving China permission because we're
all friends here but actually what he
meant was he didn't think China would
fish in the exclusive economic zone
because their friends.
The full quote is I don't think that China would do that, why? Because we're friends.
So yeah you know China would never do
anything bad to their friends.
That is the issue that a lot of smaller
countries feel with dealing with China
is that you know we're a small country
what can we do to China if we tell them
not to do this I was just laughs and do
it anyway.
Well one last thing though is
that you know after he said this and
became very controversial then his
spokesman came out and said that no no
the president will not relinquish the
Filipino Philippines sovereign rights
over our country's exclusive economic zone.
So just to clarify that's not what
he said.
It's nice when the president
needs a spokesman.
The other big story is
in the u.s. the Democratic debates are
happening and one thing that has come up
a lot is the threat China is to the US.
So there was a question there two nights
of democratic debates...
Oh god it's like nobody gets
voted off the island after these they
keep going but anyway the the first
night there were the candidates, almost
said contestants, were asked what
America's greatest geopolitical threat
was and four out of ten said China in
some capacity.
These are contestants and
not candidates is that does that mean
there's gonna be swimsuit competition?
I sincerely hope not.
I don't know, Andrew Yang...
And then on the
second night there was again a couple of
questions about China.
Okay, so mayor Pete Buttigieg... got that right... said that we have to recognize the China challenge as
a serious one and that China's using
technology for the perfection of
dictatorship.
Senator Michael Bennet said
the president's been right to push back
on China but he's done it the wrong way.
Similar with Andrew Yang who said
acknowledges of China's an economic
threat but says the tariffs are not the
right way to go.
So you know ultimately
it's a democratic debate they're gonna
talk a lot about US domestic issues but
China is shaping up to be one of the
things that's gonna be big in this
election.
And what's interesting it's
like it's clear at this point to
everyone that China is a bipartisan
issue so they have a challenge of saying
yes we agree with Trump that China is an
issue but he is totally wrong on
everything how he's doing with it that's
why we have to be voted in.
Well the interesting thing is that when you got
10 candidates on a stage none of them
actually said what they would do about China.
Like a couple of them said that
they wanted to reset the us-china
relationship but what does that mean? Unclear.
And then there's a whole issue
of Biden and his family's questionable
ties.
That's a story for another time so
In other news pro-beijing
forces in Taiwan have actually been
acting up.
That was a big deal in recent
elections in Taiwan that the Chinese
Communist Party was doing a lot of
things to sort of promote candidates
that were more in line with the
Beijing's agenda.
Yeah now there's been a
Foreign Policy to piece that's kind of
gone into that which is pretty
interesting.
Maybe we'll do an episode
about that later.
Meanwhile tens of
thousands of people in Taipei stood in
the rain for four hours that was Tuesday
I believe calling for a ban on Pro CCP
media outlets in Taiwan and that's a big
way
the Chinese Congress party is sort of
United Front works and countries around
the world as they buy Chinese language
media or invest in certain ways and then
that's the sort of subverts the message
Yeah it's interesting because there's
been such a big pushback against these
what they call in Chinese red media so I
don't think this this parade this
protest was scheduled before the Hong
Kong protests started happening but
there was definitely kind of increased
turnout because of what's happening in
Hong Kong and probably a greater fear
among Taiwanese people.
Yeah because I'm
gonna change the dynamic of it and one
of those pro-beijing groups I think
there was a quote from one who said our
God is China.
That's totally
normal and not you know worrying at all
That God demands human sacrifice: organs
It's the same thing! The Chinese Communsit Party's like the Aztec religion it's all
about ripping out people's hearts.
Moving on you know how do Chinese people feel
about pork products?
Um, honestly I think
that if you were to lose all pork
products in China that might cause the
downfall of this Chinese Communist Party
So it's a bad news that the African
swine fever is devastating
pigs in China.
It's really putting them
on the spit...
Uh or the opposite since you
don't want to eat those.
Yes yeah so so
there are official figures that's
something like 25 percent of the of the
pig population is being culled inside
mainland China.
It's very bad it's like bird flu but...
Well I you know we've also read that the
actual figures are much higher than that.
Because when do they ever report
accurate figures into Chinese media?
Yeah
very very bad situation.
Nevertheless, despite how bad the pig situation is Chinese actually banned meat imports
from Canada as part of their you know
general not liking the Canadians very much.
Well there was a banned meat additive
that was found in one shipment of
Canadian meat and so of course that is
very dangerous and they need
ban all meat shipments from Canada.
The Chinese Communist Party is very big on food safety,
as you all know.
So then the interesting twist of this story is that
now Canada is looking into suspected
foul play regarding the origins of that
bad meat.
Fowl play?
I thought we were talking about pigs.
If it wasn't clear what I was
going for.
No I think it was I think it
was pretty clear.
But anyway so
they're they're saying that it looks
like some of the you know customs
documents are forged in that shipment
and maybe it didn't actually come from
Canada so more to come on this breaking story.
A real pig-headed conspiracy.
Alright moving on moving to more interesting
developments with Huawei.
According to Bloomberg, Huawei employees have been
working with the Chinese military on
research projects.
Here's my shocked face.
I am shocked. I thought it was a private in the
private company was owned by employees.
Now to be fair to Huawei
the way Bloomberg discovered this is
they did some research into publicly
available so they did some research into publicly disclosed studies and in these studies
they said there was evidence of Huawei
employees not the company itself but
just individual employees doing research
with the Chinese military kind of things
like artificial intelligence or radio
communication.
Or maybe Huawei had no
idea that they're doing this.
Like no, we know we had no idea this was going on
I mean sort of Bloomberg's thing is
saying like you know we we we know this
is happening from just the very few
publicly disclosed studies that are
actually available most of these
military studies are you know never make
it to the public never make it online so
this could be a much bigger thing than
Huawei says is absolutely not a thing
Well I mean the whole thing about China
talking about civil-military fusion
right that we've done a few episodes
about so a lot of these are kind of
technologies that could be used in
non-military applications but also are
used in military applications.
And this is entrapping a lot of Western tech
companies
like Microsoft and Google they've all
been doing research with Chinese
military universities who then are
probably using this same kind of
technology like AI facial-recognition
in like Xinjiang to help wipe out an ethnicity.
I mean there was also
Australian universities that had that
same issue.
Yeah as well all over the
world yeah so research projects with
China maybe if someone asks you the
Chinese military asks you to work on its
research project you don't want to do that.
Yeah this is the sad thing because
you keep hearing more about how China's
building like this
techno authoritarian dystopian society
and it's not like they're coming up with
this themselves they're getting this
technology from Western tech companies
so these Western tech companies are sort
of involved in creating a system that is
trying to replace freedom and democracy.
It's a terrible thing
Cicsco!
Okay okay moving on.
Well still more with Huawei.
So the Trump
administration has put a ban on US tech
companies selling a lot of technology to
Huawei however some US companies have
found loopholes to still supply Huawei
despite the export ban.
And this this first came out you know in The Wall
Street Journal.
So basically there's like
this loophole to the export ban that if
foreign-made products include no more
than 25 percent us content then they're
able to kind of get it in.
Now the nice thing is according to Kevin Wolfe a
former us Assistant Secretary of
Commerce for the export administration
The Commerce Department could fix this
pretty easily.
Yeah yeah basically
without and doesn't even need to go
through Congress for approval so this is
a loophole that's pretty easy to close
but it just shocks me that like as like
it's so transparent like the reality of
Huawei of how it's very very tied to the
Chinese Communist Party and yet US tech
company are still like oh gosh is there
any way we can do business with them?
Other Huawei news, Huawei actually has
sued a US company CNEX,
Or C-N-E-X. I'm gonna go with CNEX.
Sounds cooler.
Say they stole Huawei intellectual property but a US
jury ruled that the semiconductor
company CNEX did not do that.
CNEX also filed a countersuit
against Huawei saying that they, it was
them trying to steal their technology
and the jury did find that Huawei did
misappropriate their secrets but didn't
award them any damages.
And in our final
story for the day, the G20 is about to
start.
I know you're all excited you've
been waiting for that I mean who doesn't
love geopolitical summits.
Oh well these
are technically an economic summit.
Geo economic political whatever.
Alright so the big news is like everyone
wondering what's gonna happen with the trade war.
The US-China trade war.
So far President Trump has
held off on doing new tariffs however he
has said that is on the table if a trade
agreement can't be reached.
According Trump's schedule he's meeting
with Xi Jinping on Saturday the second day
of the G20 for 90 minutes so everybody's
kind of wondering what's gonna happen
when with that meeting.
Meanwhile Treasury secretary Steve Mnuchin has said that got the markets a little
excited by saying that the US and China
were about 90 percent of the way to a
trade deal before it became a no deal
and then he says that he thinks that
there's a path to complete the trade
deal.
He is a China optimist.
He is a you
know what is the path, we're not sure.
Yeah I think you read a funny
tweet about that.
Oh that like there was somebody who
tweeted about you know I am you know 90%
of the way to going to the gym I've
bought all my clothes I've bought all the
weights I've all I have to do is
exercise and then I will lose weight so...
Yeah yeah
So that's kind of what the 90 percent
means is they got almost all the way
there until they actually deleted all
the enforcement mechanisms which meant
that it meant nothing anymore..
That was the last time
so yeah we'll keep you updated with
things on the G20 and obviously stay
tuned for all to our Hong Kong coverage
since we're here we're expecting July
1st to be a pretty big day.
July 1st is obviously the anniversary of when the UK
gave Hong Kong to China.
So it's like an un-independence day.
Exactly un-independence day.
And you know in our
last video if you haven't seen it we
talked about how Hong Kong protesters
were protesting to all these countries
ahead of the G20.
They're buying ads in
newspapers, ads came out in 10 different newspapers.
Try to get these countries to actuall bring up Hong Kong.
So that's a G20, save Hong Kong.
You know so they're really looking for some quality foreign
interference and that's pretty
embarrassing especially after the
Chinese authorities said that nobody was
allowed to talk about Hong Kong at the G20.
So sure they're gonna listen to yeah
Speaking of, hey Chris,
Yeah, what's that, Shelley?
Do you know who
brought up the Hong Kong at the G20
already?
Who?
Everybody's favorite
Japanese prime minister.
Shinzo Abe?
Yes, so Shinzo Abe has already talked
about Hong Kong with Xi Jinping.
He has stressed the importance of a free and
open Hong Kong under one country two
systems in light of the extradition bill
and he also mentioned the importance of
the human rights situation in Xinjiang with the Uyghurs.
Well if the Chinese
Communist Party didn't already hate
Japan I'm sure they do now.
All right so I think we're gonna sign off for now.
Stay tuned for more and let us know what
you think of this kind of a format for
our headlines.
Thanks for watching, once
again I'm Chris Chappell.
I'm Shelley Zhang.
And don't forget to
support the show on patreon visit
patreon.com/ChinaUncensored to
find out how you can support the show
and get some cool perks as well.
Talk to you next time.
Bye.