Like sands through the hourglass,
so is this episode of China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
As a professional China watcher person,
I like to use the three C's
when describing the People's Republic.
Yes, it's complicated, confusing, and contradictory.
For example,
if you've been paying attention to Western
media reports on China,
you've seen headlines like this.
The Communist Party is locked in an
unprecedented internal power struggle.
Ok, that seems pretty clear.
But wait.
You've also seen headlines like this,
about how Xi Jinping is a tyrannical dictator.
So...Xi is an absolute dictator with total
control...
in a system fracturing because of non-stop
power struggles?
Complicated, confusing, and contradictory.
Check!
Western media has consistently focused on
Xi Jinping
being the source of everything bad happening
in China.
Yes, when Xi came to power in 2012,
some people had high hopes he’d be a reformer.
But under his rule,
China seems to have become worse...
And worse...
And worse.
Even though Xi has repeatedly said
“China is a country ruled by law.”
And Party members must
“abide by the country’s constitution and
laws.”
Riiiight.
I mean is this guy a huge hypocrite?
Or is he just having crazy mood swings?
Well, there could be another explanation.
You see, getting to the top of the Communist
Party,
or rather, surviving long enough to get to
the top
of the Communist Party,
requires careful planning and maneuvering.
It's full of scheming, deceptions, backstabbing,
revenge,
mysterious disappearances, mysterious reappearances,
and lots and lots of murder.
What's that, Shelley?
Yeah, I guess it is kind of like a soap opera.
What would it be called?
The Old and the Restless?
All My Comrades?
General Hostility?
General Hostility.
I actually kind of like that one.
Let's go with that.
Previously on General Hostility,
Scheming!
Deceptions!
Backstabbing!
Revenge!
Mysterious disappearances!
Mysterious reappearances!
And lots and lots of murder!
I think that pretty much brings us up to speed
on General Hostility.
And on today’s episode,
I think Xi Jinping has amnesia!
Xi seems to be acting...erratically.
He abolishes the labor camp system,
only to have black jails spring up in their
place.
He emphasizes judicial transparency and independence,
and then arrests human rights lawyers.
He talks about getting rid of nuclear weapons,
and then Chinese media reports that China
parked nuclear missiles near Russia's border.
What is going on?
Gasp!
It wasn’t amnesia after all!
It's was Xi Jinping's evil twin separated
at birth,
Xi Pinjing!
So that's who's been undermining Xi at every
turn!
Or, is it?
It turns out that wasn’t Xi’s evil twin!
That’s a mask hiding the real evil criminal
mastermind,
Stefano DiMera!
Uh, wait, wrong show.
I mean, evil criminal mastermind
and former Communist Party leader,
Jiang Zemin!
If you’ve been watching General Hostility
since the beginning,
you know former leader Jiang Zemin
established a massive Orwellian security system
that gave him and his cronies total control
over China.
Then Xi Jinping comes along
and tries to take control himself.
And he uses what he calls an anti-corruption
campaign
to purge Jiang’s allies.
But they’re fighting back.
Even as head of the Communist Party,
Xi Jinping doesn’t have absolute power
to do whatever he wants.
Xi Jinping still must answer
to the Politburo Standing Committee,
which includes these three guys,
who are big in the Jiang Zemin faction.
And they’re trying to stop Xi from becoming
too powerful.
So are all the bad things you hear about in
the media
really Xi’s fault?
Well, he has said some things that make him
seem like a dictator.
Like speaking out against Western Values.
Saying universities should be Communist Party
strongholds.
And religious groups must obey the leadership
of the Party.
But he’s also said things that make him
look like a reformer.
Like China must learn from western economics
and political science.
And pushing for judicial independence and
transparency,
And said that for rule of law to be established
in China,
“power must be exercised in accordance with
the constitution.”
Granted the constitution’s preamble makes
it clear things will
always be “under the leadership of the Communist
Party of China.”
Plus that whole abolishing labor camps thing.
Labor camps where a huge part of the system
of control
established by Jiang Zemin.
And demolishing those was a big win for Xi.
So are all the bad things really the doings
of Xi’s rivals
to make him look bad?
Well, that also is probably not entirely the
case.
But this is why reading Western media reports
about China
can be so confusing.
You could say that the media are also getting
played in this power struggle.
Come of them can see that there's a struggle
going on,
but usually their reports make it seem like
everything going on in China is because Xi
Jinping
wants it that way—
when it's often actually the opposite.
And then the negative media reporting on Xi
Jinping
becomes part of the power struggle itself.
Because when Xi Jinping looks bad,
it's a win for his enemies.
So what would Xi do if he was in complete
control?
It's hard to know.
Meaningful reform is pretty much impossible
from within the Chinese Communist Party right
now.
Since if Xi tries to change things,
Jiang's faction will try to undermine him.
They don't really want things to change,
since that would expose what they've done
in the past.
So to move forward,
Xi Jinping will need to purge these three
guys
on the Politburo Standing Committee tied to
Jiang.
And he’ll try to do it as soon a possible
so he can fill the slots with his own people.
And of course one day,
Xi Jinping will go after the big baddie himself,
Jiang Zemin.
So is Xi a reformer, or a dictator?
Find out, on the next several...
hundred episodes of General Hostility.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
See you next time.