US companies have been hit
by a massive cyber-heist.
Sensitive information from nearly 80 million
people
has been stolen.
The Department of Justice thinks it knows
whodunit.
Sophisticated hackers operating in China
But maybe the worst is yet to come
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
The United States has just indicted two Chinese
hackers
and charged them with cyber crimes.
Very serious cyber crimes.
The first alleged cyber-criminal:
Fujie Wang, aka Dennis Wang.
Here’s his wanted poster.
The second accused hacker:
Zhou Zhihong, aka Deniel Jack.
That’s right.
Deniel Jack.
Here’s his wanted poster.
Bringing him in is going to be hard.
There are a lot of lookalikes out there.
In an announcement last week,
the Department of Justice said Dennis Wang
and Deniel Jack
are members of an “extremely sophisticated
hacking group
operating in China and targeting
large businesses in the United States”.
The DOJ indicted the duo for a range of cyber
crimes
that include intentional damage to a protected
computer
and conspiracy to commit wire fraud.
Their biggest of their several cyber-intrusions
dates back to 2015.
The target was a company called Anthem.
It’s one of the biggest health insurance
companies in the US.
Now you might think:
That’s just karmic justice for those big
insurance companies
ripping off Americans.
But the thing is,
the hackers weren’t after lower insurance
premiums.
They were after the sensitive personal data
of nearly 80 million customers—
including, maybe yours.
The indictment says the hackers
broke into Anthem's computer networks
using a bag of sophisticated tricks.
First, "spearfishing"—
where they targeted Anthem employees
with emails containing malicious hyperlinks.
Click the link and it automatically downloads...
"Malware"—
where they installed malicious software
that runs automatically and installs
a "backdoor"—
which is a tool that lets hackers control
a computer remotely.
It’s like when you get an email in weird
English,
promising you an “all expanses paid cruise
in Bahama”—
if you could please just click on this link.
And then they steal everything.
According to the indictment, Wang and Jack,
“collected files and other information
from the compromised computers and then stole
(i.e. exfiltrated) this data of interest using
encrypted archives
and computers under their control.”
And where did all that stolen data get exfiltrated
to?
China.
And what did all that stolen data contain?
Personally identifiable information
of some 78.8 million people,
including names, addresses,
income data and social security numbers.
So don’t be surprised if you start getting
personalized spam
from a guy selling knockoff whiskey.
But more seriously,
if the hackers decide to sell the data,
this could potentially be a huge opportunity
for identity theft.
According to the Social Security Administration,
identity thieves can use your social security
number
to get credit in your name
and "then they use the credit cards
and don't pay the bills."
Using credit cards and not paying the bills?
They’re even ripping off a traditional American
pastime!
So it's not just virtual spam pinging your
mailbox.
It could mean very real,
very physical debt collectors beating down
your door.
Although an Anthem spokeswoman
was quick to tell the Wall Street Journal
that
“There is no evidence that information obtained
has resulted in fraud.”
Does that mean the hackers stole data
on nearly 80 million people for no reason?
Or just not for fraud?
Because there’s also blackmail.
Anyway, just how bad is a data breach
involving nearly 80 million people?
Well, according to Assistant Attorney General
Brian Benczkowski,
“The brazen China-based computer hacking
group
committed one of the worst data breaches in
history."
One of the worst data breaches in history?!
Oh man, you hackers are in big trouble!
Just kidding.
They’re in China.
Don’t worry, the Chinese authorities
will soon find their secret hideout.
So they can send them bottles of champagne—
and a little note card thanking them
for their contribution to win-win mutual cooperation
with the United States.
Now, if this story sounds familiar, it is.
I’d call it, “Hackin’ 2: Electric Boogaloo.”
Back in December,
US prosecutors announced cyber-crimes charges
against two other Chinese hackers.
“Today the criminal justice department
is announcing criminal indictment of two hackers
associated with the Chinese government.
The charges include conspiracy
to commit computer intrusions
against dozens of companies in the United
States
and around the world.”
And FBI Director Christopher Wray said at
the time
that cyber threats from hackers
with links to the Chinese regime
are as bad as it gets.
“As evidenced by this investigation,
the threats we face have never been more severe
or more pervasive
or more potentially damaging to our national
security,
and no country poses a broader, more severe,
long term threat to our nation’s economy
and cyber infrastructure than China.”
What’s that, Shelley?
The US government also indicted
Chinese hackers in November 2018?
Ok, so this is more like Hackers Part 3:
Rise of the Machines.
What?
They also indicted Chinese hackers and spies
in October of 2018?
Ok, so this is more like the Kingdom of the
Crystal Hack,
the fourth sequel that no one asked for.
What’s that, Shelley?
The US government also indicted Chinese hackers
in 2017...
And all the way back in 2014,
when they indicted hackers who were actually
members of the People’s Liberation Army?
Forget it.
I’m done with this joke.
Only the Star Wars movies
have enough sequels to deal with this.
And believe me,
I’m ready for *that* series to be done.
I guess this is why the US government has
said
there’s a new “hacking spree” coming
from China.
But while these indictments might show that
the US government means business,
they also show that they’re not actually
good
at stopping the hacking.
So my advice is:
If you get an email in broken English,
with an attachment claiming to offer you
an all-expanses paid cruise—
don’t click on it.
So what do you think about
the cyber-crimes indictment
against Wang and Deniel Jack?
Leave your comments below.
And while you’re here,
it’s time for me to answer another question
from a fan who supports China Uncensored
with a dollar or more per episode—
through the crowdfunding website Patreon.
Colin Lee Bradford asks
“You seem desperate for questions sometimes.
What is your favorite type of question?”
My favorite questions are ones
where viewers ask about my favorite type of
thing.
Good question Colin.
And if you want your question
answered on the show,
go to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored
and support us with a dollar or more per episode.
Then you can ask me about my favorite brand
of toothpaste,
or favorite style of elevator button.
The important questions get answered right
here.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.