The Coronavirus Outbreak
reveals China’s darkest secret
And why is a Mr. Bean impersonator
becoming a mouthpiece of the Chinese Communist
Party?
That and more on this week’s China News
Headlines
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell
The coronavirus has exposed plenty of authoritarian
tendencies
in the Chinese Communist Party.
They covered it up for more than a month.
Then, the police started forcibly quarantining
people—
whether they were sick or not.
Local officials welded people into their homes.
And if people complained...into the box you
go.
Or if you tried to show the world what was
happening,
you disappeared...indefinitely.
But the coronavirus is also raising awareness
about one of the Chinese Communist Party’s
darkest secrets:
forced organ harvesting from political prisoners.
Earlier this month,
Chinese state-run media trumpeted a huge achievement:
the first double lung transplant on a coronavirus
patient.
It was a story that got picked up by Western
media.
But Bitter Winter,
a website that researches religious persecution
in China,
points out that there are some...
concerns about the transplant.
“The patient, who on February 24th,
was given days to live following
rapid deterioration of his lung function,
had only to wait a matter of five days before
a perfectly matching,
‘consenting,’\h brain-dead donor could
be found,
conveniently a mere seven hours by high speed
train.”
If you know anything about organ transplants,
you know that’s suspicious.
It normally takes months or years to get an
organ.
This of course came out shortly after an international
tribunal
ruled that “Beyond reasonable doubt...
in China forced organ harvesting from prisoners
of conscience
has been practiced for a substantial period
of time
involving a very substantial number of victims.”
For more on the tribunal,
check out our recent episode,
How to Make Money in China: Selling People’s
Organs.
Chinese leader Xi Jinping has gone to Wuhan,
China—
the epicenter of the coronavirus outbreak—
to visit patients.
Well, he didn’t visit them in person, obviously.
He’s visited them through this TV screen.
Wow, he’s standing kind of far away.
Maybe he thinks you can still get infected
through the screen.
But Xi Jinping’s visit to Wuhan
is a sign that the Chinese Communist Party
believes that the worst of the coronavirus
outbreak in China is over.
And his visit is just one of many reasons
the residents of Wuhan
should feel grateful to the Chinese Communist
Party
for their response to the coronavirus.
And if they don’t feel grateful enough,
then they need gratitude education.
That’s according to Wuhan’s Party Secretary.
He’s the new top official in Wuhan,
after the last guy got fired
for covering up the spread of the virus.
That announcement came after
the Vice Premiere of China visited Wuhan.
She was given a tour by local officials
who were showing off how cleaned up the city
had become
and how much food grocery stores had.
Local residents had this to say.
And as you might guess from that clip,
the Wuhan Party Secretary’s call for gratitude
education
didn’t go over well.
In fact, the backlash was so big that the
original article
was pulled from the internet.
And “Media have been ordered not to share
the original article,
publish commentaries,
or otherwise address the issue at all.”
Yeah, they really need some gratitude education.
China already had a vast network of surveillance,
with things like AI facial recognition cameras.
But that system has gone into overdrive
during the coronavirus outbreak.
And to help ensure that all Chinese people
show the appropriate levels of gratitude to
Communist officials,
that system will probably be here to stay.
And don’t worry,
authorities will be able to see how grateful
you are,
even if you’re wearing a mask.
But some people just don’t know how to be
grateful.
Like this guy, Xu Zhiyong.
He’s a well known Chinese activist
who called Chinese leader Xi Jinping’s
response to the coronavirus
“clueless.”
He now faces up to 15 years in jail for subversion.
And he should be grateful it wasn’t more.
Then again,
maybe he’ll gratefully volunteer his lungs
for transplant.
And you know who’s really not grateful?
Tibetans living overseas.
In New York on Tuesday,
a thousand Tibetan protesters came out
to commemorate the anniversary of the Chinese
Communist Party
“liberating” Tibet in 1959.
“Liberating” Tibetans from their lives,
that is.
At least they’re grateful to be in America,
where they can protest the Communist Party
without getting their organs harvested.
Speaking of crimes against humanity,
there’s a Mr. Bean impersonator in China:
Mr. Pea.
That’s pea, like the vegetable, not...nevermind.
Here’s Chinese state-run CGTN for more.
“Nigel arrived in Wuhan tourism purposes
and chose to stay there after the outbreak.”
Yes, he chose to stay there.
And ever since, he’s become a propaganda
tool
for the Chinese Communist Party.
“Widely circulated clips of Mr. Pea
show him enjoying the lockdown life in Wuhan,
and applauding the government’s ‘brave’
decision
to quarantine the city.”
Yes, nothing says “brave government decisions”
like locking up citizens.
“The safety measures taken here on a daily
basis
by the population of Wuhan,
are nothing short of being incredible.
The government has done an amazing job.”
I hope Mr. Pea enjoys his 15-minutes of fame
as a Mr. Bean impersonator
who shills for the Chinese Communist Party.
And I thought nothing could be more humiliating
than doing community theater.
But the point is, everything is fine in Wuhan.
Which is why the government is telling people
there
to get back to work, ya lazy bums!
I’m sure the Communist Party is doing that
because the coronavirus is really under control,
and not because the economy has cratered
because workers have been staying at home.
A lot of builders have gone out of business
as well,
because the real estate market is collapsing.
But business everywhere is hurting.
In fact, in the US, the Council on Foreign
Relations
was going to hold a roundtable discussion
called “Doing Business Under Coronavirus.”
But then the Coronavirus conference was canceled
because of the coronavirus.
Very reassuring.
But the coronavirus hasn’t slowed down
China’s military ambitions.
The Chinese navy is outbuilding everybody.
I mean, priorities, right?
Johns Hopkins University has created an interactive
map
showing the coronavirus outbreak.
It’s been used for months by governments
and news organizations around the world.
And now the Taiwanese government is lodging
a protest over it.
Why?
Because Taiwan is no longer called Taiwan.
It’s called “Taipei and environs.”
That’s just what the World Health Organization
calls Taiwan.
You know, I don’t think it’s the coronavirus
that’s making me feel sick.
But the good news is that
after lots of negative publicity about the
decision,
Johns Hopkins has decided
to change its map back to saying “Taiwan.”
They’re now using the US State Department’s
naming conventions
instead of the WHO.
And coming up next,
I’ll answer a question from a fan
who supports China Uncensored on Patreon.
But first, did you know YouTube has been secretly
unsubscribing people from the show?
Take a moment to make sure you’re still
subscribed.
And if you haven’t subscribed,
what are you waiting for!
And now for the question
from China Uncensored 50-Cent Army Member,
William Adderholdt,
“The WHO's name for the coronavirus "COVID-19"
hasn't caught on.
Any idea why?
And what would be a good replacement name?”
Good question.
Coronavirus is actually the name of a family
of diseases.
For example, SARS is a coronavirus.
So in mid-February,
the World Health Organization dubbed this
coronavirus COVID-19.
This was their reasoning behind the name.
“We had to find a name that
did not refer to a geographical location,
an animal, an individual or group of people
and which is also pronounceable and related
to the disease.
Having a name matters to prevent the use of
other names
that can be inaccurate or stigmatising.”
And obviously the W.H.O. wouldn’t want to
do anything
that would hurt the feelings of the Chinese
Communist Party.
But they only issued the new name months
after the virus first began to spread in China.
That was a long time for the public
to only have “coronavirus” as a name.
People got used to it.
And it sounds better than COVID-19.
What would be a better name for a deadly disease
spreading around the world and killing people?
Well, sounds like Communism to me.
But I think that might just be confusing.
Thanks for your question.
And thank you for watching.
Remember, YouTube has been demonetizing
almost all of our videos.
They’d have run us out of business
if it weren’t for support from fans like
you
who contribute on the crowdfunding website
Patreon.
I call them the China Uncensored 50 cent army.
If you’d like to hear your question answered
on the show,
join the China Uncensored 50-cent army
by going to patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.