Taiwan’s Election Results Are In
And the real loser is the Chinese Communist
Party
Find out how Hong Kong protests
Played a big role in the elections
Welcome back to China Uncensored,
I’m Chris Chappell, coming to you from Taipei,
Taiwan.
Taiwan’s historic 2020 presidential and
legislative elections
happened over the weekend.
And like pretty much everything in Taiwan...
The elections were adorable.
See?
Adorable.
Adora--no wait, that’s horrifying.
Ok, not everything was adorable.
The election was targeted with a disinformation
campaign
from the Chinese Communist Party.
And people were feeling it.
The biggest catchphrase of the election, “dried
mango strips”
refers to a feeling of impending national
doom.
But even with the impending doom, the Tsai
campaign
still found time to release an anime adventure
game called
“What?!
I, a Taiwanese third-year high schooler from
Class 2,
suddenly fell into a different world and met
the president?!”
Why don’t *American* presidential candidates
release
anime adventure games?
But back to the non-anime Taiwan election.
In which current president Tsai Ing-wen won
in a landslide
against her opponent Han Kuo-yu.
In fact, Tsai got more votes than any presidential
candidate
in the history of Taiwan’s democracy.
And Tsai’s party, the Democratic Progessive
Party,
also won a majority of seats in the Legislative
Yuan.
The election was a major defeat for Han’s
party, the KMT.
One of the biggest differences between the
two parties
is how they treat China.
The DPP has been a strong supporter of Taiwan
sovereignty,
and resisting pressure from Beijing.
The KMT has pushed for stronger ties with
China,
with the goal of boosting Taiwan’s economy.
As the votes were counted,
it became clear pretty early on that this
election
was going to the DPP and Tsai Ing-wen.
That created a wave of euphoria at the DPP
rally.
And...not so much as the KMT rally.
We watched the ballot counting in Taipei’s
district four,
traditionally a KMT area.
In the last election,
the DPP didn’t even bother to run a legislative
candidate.
This time, the majority here voted DPP.
A year ago, few people would have predicted
this.
The KMT had had a surge in popularity,
especially as economic issues became a focus
in Taiwanese politics.
In the 2018 regional elections, the DPP lost
big to the KMT,
and Tsai Ing-wen was forced to step down as
the DPP chair.
At one point, it looked like she might not
even be
the DDP candidate for the 2020 elections.
So how did this happen?
Well, there were a lot of factors.
Including the fact that
people either really loved or really hated
Han Kuo-yu.
And then this happened.
For months, Hong Kong has been embroiled
in protests against the Chinese Communist
Party.
The Communist Party, and how Taiwan should
deal with China,
is always a big focus in Taiwanese elections.
But the Hong Kong protests gave Taiwanese
voters a clear picture
of what they did not want to happen here.
“Have the Kong Kong protests affected how
you might vote today?”
“Yes, it made me think, ‘I have to vote
today.’”
“Why?”
“Because we don’t want to be (the) next
Hong Kong.”
“We don’t want to be the next Hong Kong.”
The Chinese Communist Party considers Taiwan
a Chinese province
and has vowed to get Taiwan back under its
control.
If they can’t do it economically,
then they’ll do it with the military.
And while Han Kuo-Yu called for closer economic
ties with China,
promising that it would help average Taiwanese
people get rich...
Tsai Ing-wen made Taiwanese sovereignty and
comparisons
with Hong Kong a central piece to her campaign
strategy.
And Hong Kong protesters even went to DPP
rallies
to witness Taiwan’s election.
“We are from Hong Kong and we are coming
to Taiwan
to support the freedom and democracy in Taiwan.”
And while KMT supporters showed plenty of
enthusiasm at their rally,
there were no Hong Kong protesters in sight.
It’s not hard to guess which presidential
candidate
was Beijing’s favorite.
So people were very worried that the Chinese
Communist Party
would try to interfere with the election.
Tsai Ing-wen actively made it an issue during
the campaign.
Han Kuo-Yu...not so much.
Mayor Han, do you still think CCP
didn't interfere with Taiwan Election?
You made my right ear deaf,
let me switch to my left ear now.
Which media are you from?
You tell me that first.
I'm from NTD.
I see!
Any other questions?
But the landslide victory for Tsai and the
DPP
shows just how concerned the Taiwanese people
are about China.
The Chinese Communist Party, obviously,
was not too pleased about the election results.
In fact, the official Xinhua state-run news
agency
blamed foreign forces,
including the US, for Tsai’s win in the...
Taiwan regional leadership election.
So glad we could be here for the Taiwan regional
leadership election.
But what happens next is the real question.
The Chinese Communist Party tried
to use money and intimidation in Hong Kong,
and that failed in the recent Hong Kong local
elections.
The Communist Party tried to use money and
intimidation in Taiwan
and that failed, too.
Will China resort to more brutal tactics in
Hong Kong and Taiwan?
How will the United States respond?
One thing is clear—
supporting the CCP is no longer
a good choice for your political career.
The chairman of the KMT was forced to resign
after the humiliating defeat.
And while Han Kuo-Yu will now carry on as
the mayor of the southern city of Kaohsiung,
he’s likely to face a recall election.
And I just have to say personally,
I was moved seeing these elections
and how passionate the Taiwanese people are
about democracy.
I hope that’s a spirit we can all bring
to the 2020 US presidential elections.
Well, that and an anime adventure game called
“What?!
I, an American third-year high schooler from
Class 2,
suddenly fell into a different world and met
the president?!”
Thanks for watching.
And once again a big thank you to the fans
who support China Uncensored on the crowd
funding website Patreon.
We wouldn’t be able to come to Taiwan to
cover these elections
if it weren’t for their support,
please leave a thank you to them in the comments
below.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.