Zombie companies in China.
They’re bad for economic growth.
and they’re eating up money like tasty brains.
But there’s just no easy fix.
for China’s coming zombie apocalypse.
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Zombies.
They’re running amok in China.
And no, I’m not talking about World War
Z,
the book version,
where the zombie apocalypse is triggered
by organ trafficking in China.
I’m talking about Chinese zombie companies.
And they’re not as easy to kill
as the Chinese Communist Party would like.
That’s according to a study called
“The mystery of zombie enterprises:
stiff but deathless.”
China’s zombie enterprises
are state-owned companies
that are consistently unprofitable—
companies that, in a free market,
would go bust.
But in China’s state-managed economy,
they’re artificially kept alive,
thanks to what the study’s authors call
repeated “blood transfusions.”
Which makes them seem
more like vampires than zombies.
Zampires?
Vombies?
These “blood transfusions”
are state-sponsored loans and subsidies.
They’re what make these failing zombie companies
“stiff but deathless.”
These zombie companies are a problem
for China’s economy as a whole—
because they’re unproductive,
they don’t innovate,
and they don’t contribute to economic growth.
Just like real zombies.
“The persistence of zombie enterprises
not only occupies precious resources,”
the study says,
“but also causes financing problems
for other enterprises
and lowers the production efficiency
of the whole industry.”
As this legion of the undead stumbles along
thanks to Chinese government subsidies,
it hurts productive companies...
by eating their brains.
Or at least by eating up resources
that productive companies would otherwise
get.
According to the European investment bank,
UBS,
China’s economy is becoming less and less
efficient—
partly as a result.
Compared to a decade ago,
it now takes twice as much capital
to create the same amount of GDP growth.
It’s hard to pin down
the true number zombie firms in China,
because, well, the Chinese Communist Party
is not real good at transparency.
In the same way that a brick wall
is not real good at being a window.
Official data from the State-owned
Assets Supervision and Administration Commission,
or SASAC,
says there are about 2,000 zombie companies
run by the central authorities.
But that’s just a fraction.
Add in all the zombie companies
overseen by local governments,
and you get at least 10,000.
But even that number is not easy to pinpoint.
Because officials aren’t really motivated
to do accurate reporting.
“This is a case where these local governments,
it seems, a number of them,
have drawn up list
of zombie companies in their jurisdictions,
but are holding back on revealing those to
the banks...
And it’s also the case, we’ve heard,
that banking regulators in some of these provinces
are also being kept in the dark.”
And that was back in 2016.
At the time,
there was a broad push to fix
broken parts of the Chinese economy.
And Premier Li Keqiang
launched an initiative for
the “active and safe disposal of zombie
enterprises”.
But fast forward three years,
and that still hasn’t happened.
Earlier this month,
the head of China’s biggest aluminum producer
warned that zombie enterprises are hampering
China's economic transformation.
The zombie apocalypse is so nigh,
that Xi Jinping himself recently vowed
to slay the zombie hordes once and for all.
He warned that China must be on guard
against ‘grey rhinos’—
which are highly obvious yet ignored threats.
Which is weird,
because in other countries,
people think of rhinos as endangered species
that should be protected.
Anyway, back in December,
11 top Chinese regulatory and policymaking
bodies
got together and pledged to
get rid of zombie companies by 2020.
Just like Premier Li Keqiang pledged to do
back in 2016.
But this time, it’s gonna be for real.
And these regulators promised
to publish a list of zombie companies within
three months.
So that was December.
Let’s see, January, February, March,
hey that’s three months and...no list.
Instead, we got only a statement on March
from Xiao Yaqing,
head of the state assets regulator.
And he was like,
“Everything’s fine.
State-owned enterprises
are totally independent market players.”
Although I’m not sure I trust a guy who—
judging by this photo—
is probably an actual zombie himself.
I know what you’re thinking,
“That’s just a joke,
that photo probably just had bad lighting”.
No, I’m serious.
I’ve looked through a lot of photos of Xiao
Yaqing
and I’m pretty sure he’s an actual zombie.
Either that or he’s personally giving
blood transfusions to the zombies.
Zampires.
Vombies.
Xiao said that anybody who claims
there’s a systematic arrangement
for state-owned companies to get subsidies
from the Chinese state is spreading fake news.
Because these companies “are self-operated,
self-financed, self-sustained,
self-disciplined and self-developed.”
Except...he’s lying.
And he probably want to eat your brains.
Remember that report,
“the mystery of zombie enterprises –
“stiff but deathless”’?
Turns out it’s not that big of a mystery
why
zombie companies—especially the biggest
ones—
continue their long march of the undead.
Brains.
Sorry, I meant jobs.
Zombie firms might pile
mountains of bad debt on the banking system
and hurt the economy in the long term
by being unproductive—
but in the short term,
they provide jobs.
And for the Chinese Communist Party,
jobs and economic prosperity
are the only reasons they’re still in power.
Just ask driver Wong Wei.
He blames his lost job in the coal industry
when the Chinese regime moved to lay off
1.8 million workers in several zombie industries.
“I borrowed more than I can afford
just to buy this truck”
says driver Wong Wei,
“now no work,
I’m angry with the government.”
So Wong Wei thinks that
the Chinese government is going the incorrect
direction.
I guess he should know.
Zombie companies operate on a simple formula.
They “exist as a direct result of the resources
and credit endorsements they receive
from the government.”
And “the companies that offer a greater
number of jobs
receive more government subsidies.”
And there are more poorly thought-out incentives.
Local officials get job promotions
if they meet employment targets in their regions.
So as long as a company provides jobs,
local officials try to protect it from getting
shut down.
And as a result,
local officials hide bad companies
from central regulators who might want to
put them
on lists of zombie companies to be eliminated.
Sometimes, local officials even help them
get more loans through hidden
off-balance sheet transactions.
“S&P credit analysts were using
some colorful language to describe
the risks around this,
saying that the debt they’re talking about
is,
the potential debt,
is like an iceberg with titanic credit risks.”
“Put that on top, by the way,
of what we know the official numbers
in terms of debt \hin China,
260% at the very least to GDP,
and it starts to add up to
some pretty frightening numbers.”
And for people who’ve been around the block
a few times,
like this retired businessman,
China’s plan to kill off or restructure
its horde of zombie companies is doomed to
fail.
“Even if they start to reform, it won’t
be deep because it’s related to the stability
of the Communist regime and it’s related
to the nature of the government.
The Communist government is established on
the state-owned economy.
If they carry out deep SOE reform, they have
to change themselves.”
And nobody wants to change themselves.
So what do you think about China’s zombie
company apocalypse?
Leave your comments below.
And now it’s time for me to answer a question
from a member of our 50-Cent Army
who supports China Uncensored
through the crowdfunding website Patreon.
Sean Connelly asks:
“Does the fifty cent army pledge level
in any way refer to the Chinese company tencent?
And if yes, what is the deeper meaning behind
it?”
Good question, Sean.
The term 50-Cent Army doesn’t have
anything to do with Tencent.
Or the rapper 50 Cent.
The original term refers to
how the Chinese Communist Party
pays online commenters to manipulate public
opinion
by posting things online that support the
Party line.
In Chinese, they’re called the Wu Mao Dang,
which means 50-Cent Party.
They’re sometimes also called the 50-Cent
Army.
Originally the name came about
because they were supposedly paid
the equivalent of half a Chinese dollar—
50 cents—per post.
When I first launched our Patreon site back
in 2015,
I decided it would be clever to create
our own group of supporters,
and call it the “China Uncensored 50-Cent
Army.”
I asked fans to contribute
50 cents or more per episode
to support the show.
A year later,
credit card companies made a new rule
that the minimum pledge had to be $1 dollar...
but I kept the name “50-Cent Army.”
Thanks for your question, Sean.
And thank you for joining the 50-Cent Army!
Possibly by accident.
And thanks to all my 50-Cent Army soldiers
who support China Uncensored.
It’s only because of your support
that we’ve been able to keep this show going
for so many years.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.