On this episode of China Uncensored,
looting and polluting is not the way!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I'm your host Chris Chappell.
The Amazon!
Home to some of the richest biodiversity on
the planet.
One in ten species in the world make their
home here.
Pristine waters, lush forests, and...
Oh right. That.
Yeah that's a Chinese oil exploration
rig.
You see, China has just bought a chunk of
the Amazon rainforest
in Ecuador the size of nearly two New York
Cities.
The deal was announced at the end of January.
For just 80 million dollars,
a consortium of two Chinese state owned oil
companies
will get to poke around for oil in the pristine,
untouched Amazon.
"Our world is in peril!
Gaia, the spirit of the Earth,
can no longer stand the terrible destruction
plaguing our planet."
But when your best option for preserving the
environment
is a superhero whose only weakness is getting
dirty...
"How do you like my pollution pod, Captain Planet?"
"Weak. Feel weak..."
Well, I guess we don't really need the rainforest,
do we?
What's that, Shelley?
Oh, it's critical to sustaining life on earth.
Anyhow, there are apparently more concerns
than just environmental.
Indigenous tribes living in the region
are also going to be affected by the intrusion
of Chinese oil production.
But not to worry,
because according to Ecuador's constitution,
the government must consult with local groups
before approving any environmental projects
like this.
And they did!
In fact they met with 360 community representatives,
according to this local news report.
"They threatened the people, saying
'If all of you don't accept,
the government will come with police and military
and they will remove you from this territory.'"
See?
Successful consultation.
I guess Ecuadorian officials have been
learning negotiation tactics from China.
Anyhow, this oil deal was just part of $7.5 billion worth
of new financing agreements between the two
countries.
And Ecuador already owes China billions.
Since 2009, China has invested $11 billion
in Ecuador.
See this beautiful waterfall along the Coca River?
Won't be there for long,
thanks to the $2.2 billion hydroelectric
dam China is building.
It will provide enough power to light more
than a third of Ecuador.
It's also, however, built in an area prone
to earthquakes,
and sits next to the base of a volcano that
erupted as recently as...
last year.
And this is the problem:
It's tempting for a developing country like
Ecuador
to take money from the Chinese Communist Party
and its state-owned companies,
but it carries a prices.
Often times, deals with China also bring along
China's,
shall we say,
longstanding respect for worker safety.
They also bring steep interest rates,
and you can basically kiss the rights to your
natural resources goodbye for years.
China will get up to 90% of Ecuador's oil
shipments.
And a lot of that will go towards paying off
those loans.
Ecuador is like the young, bright-eyed college
student.
And China, the student loan lender.
It seemed like a good deal at the time!
Now, wait, aren't US companies also doing
the same thing?
Well, yes, actually.
For example, in 2011,
an Ecuadorian court ordered Chevron to pay
damages for
polluting the rainforest.
And now big oil has to pay for its crimes.
Oh, nevermind.
Of course, a key difference is that Chevron
is a private company,
not state-owned like the Chinese ones.
And the US government allowed Chevron to be
sued in a US court.
In China, no court would allow its state-owned
companies to be sued.
But regardless, there should be a lesson here for Ecuador.
Don't let foreign oil giants destroy your
rainforest,
because that's kind of what happens when you
let them in.
So why would Ecuador go for this deal?
Money.
It needs the money.
And why would they work with China over, say,
the United States?
Because the Chinese regime lends money to
governments
that can't or won't do business with the West.
Despite problems with some private companies,
in general loans from Western countries come
with demands
for government transparency, freedom of the
press,
and at least some degree of environmental
protection.
The Communist Party of China, on the other
hand, makes no such demands.
"'Cause greedy human beings
will always lend a hand
with the destruction of
this worthless jungle land."
Part of the reason Ecuador's economy has turned
to toxic sludge
is thanks to its socialist president, Rafael
Correa.
President Correa's father was a cocaine smuggler
imprisoned by the US.
Some experts believe he blamed the US for
his father's eventual suicide.
That could be why one of the first things
he did as president
was expel a critical US military base of operations
for the War on Drugs.
Then, in 2008, he decided that the billions
of dollars in debt
Ecuador owed to Western countries was "immoral
and illegitimate,"
and decided to stop paying.
Ecuador went into default.
And since this was 2008 during the global
financial crisis,
oil prices collapsed,
and the developed world wouldn't do business
with him.
So Ecuador turned to the Chinese regime for
money.
But this kind of deal may backfire for China
too.
In the CCP's relentless push for greater international
power,
they're pegging the Chinese economy on corrupt,
unstable regimes.
Not just Ecuador.
They've also loaned money to such clear winners
as
Yemen, Zimbabwe, and Syria.
China might not ever get this money back,
and that's money taken out of the pockets
of your average Chinese citizen.
As for the fate of the Amazon, well...
"The power is yours!"
Or maybe China's.
“威力屬於你們！”
So what do you think?
Is Ecuador making the right decision?
Leave your comments below.
And check out our Facebook page for more content.
Once again, I'm Chris Chappell.
See you next time.