The World Freaks Out
Over a Deadly Chinese Virus
How far will it spread?
This is China Uncensored,
I’m Chris Chappell.
An outbreak of a deadly coronavirus
from the Chinese city of Wuhan is spreading.
It’s now surpassed the number of people
affected by SARS in 2003.
SARS was another deadly disease
the Chinese Communist Party tried to cover
up,
which only made it worse.
It was a bad idea that time.
It’s a bad idea now.
The initial coverup of this new coronavirus
has made the spread worse,
and the coronavirus has now spread to every
region of China.
The rest of the world is freaking out.
Despite the fact that there are still
fewer than one hundred cases outside China.
World Health Organization officials have now
declared it
a “global health emergency.”
The rest of the world is responding to the
coronavirus in different ways.
Foreign companies operating in China are shutting
down.
For example, Starbucks has closed 2,000 stores
in China.
So hey, there you go.
There’s your silver lining.
At least people don’t have to suffer from
a terrible disease
and terrible coffee.
Other companies are doing even more to help
the people trapped in China.
For instance, there’s been a huge shortage
of medical masks.
So Boeing is donating a quarter million.
Meanwhile, a Danish newspaper printed this
political cartoon.
Which the Chinese Communist Party was really
not cool with.
The Chinese embassy in Denmark demanded an
apology
for hurting the feelings of the Chinese people.
You know, I think the Chinese people would
prefer an apology
from the Chinese government for covering up
the virus.
But, the Chinese people won’t be getting
an apology.
The Danish newspaper refused.
And to no one’s surprise,
the Chinese Communist Party is also not apologizing.
Fortunately for Americans living in China,
the US State Department chartered a plane
to evacuate US Citizens in Wuhan back to the
United States.
Don’t worry,
“The individuals on board the flight were
screened before take off,
monitored during the flight by medical personnel
and screened again when the plane landed.”
They’re also being voluntarily quarantined
at a military base in Southern California
for three days.
The US is planning more evacuation flights
from Wuhan.
And other countries have also been looking
at
evacuating their citizens from Wuhan.
Some, like Japan, have also been given the
go ahead by China.
Not Taiwan, though.
Meanwhile, Russia is just closing its entire
border with China.
And when Putin says, “Close the southern
border,”
no one in his country is allowed to protest.
And if you’re watching this show illegally
from China,
now might be a good time to leave.
Because commercial airlines around the world
are suspending a lot of flights to and from
China.
It’s either an attempt to halt the spread
of the virus,
or there’s a curious lack of demand for
flights to China right now.
Good news, though.
Australian scientists have been the first
to recreate the virus outside of China.
Wait, why is that good news?!
Well, supposedly this is a major breakthrough
that will hopefully help find a cure.
That, or some intern is playing a real life
version of Plague Inc.
But with the virus spreading rapidly around
the world,
international health organizations are like,
can we...please help, China?
Please?
And the Chinese regime was like, naww.
They denied help from the CDC.
That’s the US Centers for Disease Control.
I mean, you wouldn’t want them snooping
around
and exposing a massive coverup, right?
But after more begging, the Chinese regime
announced
it would finally accept some limited help
from the World Health Organization.
The organization in turn “praised China’s
response to the outbreak,
including its rapid identification of the
virus
and its ‘openness to sharing information
with W.H.O. and other countries.’”
The World Health Organization praised China’s
response?
I wonder if that has anything to do with why
they got access to China.
Or maybe it’s because the head of the organization
is such good buddies with Xi Jinping.
And that’s it for this update on the coronavirus.
What do you think of how the world is freaking
out?
And how are you freaking out?
Tell me in the comments below.
And, want to stand up to the Chinese Communist
Party yourself?
Join the China Uncensored 50 Cent Army.
That’s what I call the fans who support
China Uncensored
through the crowd funding website Patreon.
YouTube demonetizes a lot of our episodes,
so we rely on your support to keep the show
going.
Today’s question comes from William Adderholdt.
“I have a question for the show.
What exactly are these "live markets"
where the epidemic supposedly started?
How unsanitary are they?”
Good question.
These markets are often called “wet markets”
in Chinese.
They’re usually open air markets
where you can buy food from different vendors.
And they sell everything from fruits and vegetables
to raw meat, seafood, and live animals.
They’re a huge part of China’s food supply
chain.
And some of them are...not super sanitary.
Chopping fish on the floor.
Butchering pork without gloves.
And freshly slaughtered chickens just hanging
around.
This is the Huanan Seafood Market in Wuhan—
regarded as the epicenter of the outbreak.
It’s been closed down now.
They sold all sorts of weird stuff.
This was a menu at one of the more...exotic
animal stalls.
To be fair, according to some reports,
the *first* person reportedly infected with
the coronavirus—
on December 1—never came into contact with
that wet market.
There’s a lot of conflicting information
right now
and it will be months before we know what
happened.
But the virus did somehow spread *to* that
market.
And wet markets are the perfect place to spread
disease.
Because they’re pretty much unregulated
and having live animal feces,
blood from slaughtered animals,
and fresh produce all next to each other is
extremely unsanitary.
But what doesn’t kill you makes you stronger,
right?
Thanks for your question.
And thank you for watching.
Hope you all stay safe and healthy.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
This is China Uncensored.