On this episode of China Uncensored,
the US thinks it might not be the best idea
to let a Chinese company control your financial
data.
Huh, wonder why.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Shelley Zhang.
Chris is on vacation until Friday,
snoozing in his own desert paradise.
But the news never sleeps,
so I’m here to talk about how the US blocked
China’s 1.2 billion dollar takeover
of the US-based company MoneyGram.
MoneyGram is like Western Union,
but less well known.
Like Mandy Moore is to Britney Spears.
Except MoneyGram is probably not going to
have
a career comeback playing the mother
of three mixed-race triplets,
making Americans ugly cry
every Tuesday at 9.
Ok, seriously, though,
you can use MoneyGram to send money.
It’s helpful when you can’t deliver cash.
Or mail a check.
Or use a credit card.
Or PayPal.
Or bank transfer.
Or Venmo.
Ok, so I have never used MoneyGram,
but apparently a lot of people do.
Because MoneyGram operates
in pretty much every country.
It has 347,000 agent offices worldwide.
That’s 10 times the number of McDonalds.
I know.
I also thought there were way more McDonalds
than that.
Although—to be fair—
some of MoneyGram’s “offices”
are just electronic kiosks.
Which is nice,
because then you can give them money
without having to talk to other people.
Something McDonald’s is also working on.
MoneyGram is based in Dallas.
And it’s worth 1.2 billion dollars.
At least, that’s what the Chinese company
Ant Financial was willing to pay for it.
Ant Financial is owned
by Chinese billionaire Jack Ma,
seen here.
He has...flair.
Yeah.
He’s bad, he’s bad.
You know it.
Jack Ma also owns the world’s largest retail
company,
the Alibaba Group.
Alibaba runs several websites
that are like the Chinese versions
of Amazon and eBay.
But much bigger.
You can buy everything on there—
from, you know, phone chargers,
to beauty products,
to a wide selection of interrogation chairs.
You know, there’s just something about
a company advertising its convenient and durable
interrogation chairs on Taobao.
It just says so much about
what’s happening in the country.
Perfect for prisons and police stations.
Ten year guarantee!
Ok, back to Alibaba before I scream.
Alibaba made so much money for Jack Ma
that he created his own financial services
company
just to process the payments.
He called it Alipay.
Later, he spun it off into Ant Financial.
The weird name is because—
and this is not a joke—
Jack Ma thinks the small merchants
who sell goods on Alibaba
are like ants.
And if they say why, why?
He’ll tell them it’s just Human Nature.
Anyway, after a year-long review process,
the Committee on Foreign Investment in the
United States,
or CFIUS,
rejected Ant Financial’s takeover
of MoneyGram last week.
They said it posed a national security risk.
There were “concerns over the safety of
data
that can be used to identify U.S. citizens.”
CFIUS is a committee formed of members
from 16 government agencies,
including the Commerce Department,
State Department,
and Homeland Security.
Its main purpose is to review cases
where a company from a foreign country
wants to acquire a US business
that has sensitive technology,
data, intellectual property,
et cetera.
Then it approves or rejects each transaction.
Imagine it like having your mom approve
everything you buy before you buy it.
Do you really need another life-sized BB-8?
Honey, I’m just looking out for
your national security.
But unlike your mother,
CFIUS actually approves
the great majority of these transactions.
In recent years, though,
CFIUS has blocked a bunch of large deals
involving Chinese companies.
Like in 2011,
when CFIUS prevented telecom company Huawei
from buying a US company.
US Presidents can also directly step in
to block a deal,
like in 2016
when President Obama blocked the sale
of US assets of a tech company
to China.
Or in 2017 when President Trump blocked the
sale
of Lattice Semiconductor to China.
Still, even with this increased scrutiny of
Chinese firms,
a lot of people were surprised
that CFIUS told Jack Ma to Beat It.
Remember the time Trump
met with Jack Ma last January?
This is what he said.
“We had a great meeting, and—
a great, great entrepreneur,
one of the best in the world—
and he loves this country.”
At the meeting,
Jack Ma told Trump he wanted to
create a million jobs in the US,
by having US merchants sell stuff
on Alibaba.
Jack Ma hasn’t done that so far.
Not even close.
He’s actually been focused on
having his other company, Ant Financial,
take over MoneyGram.
It would have taken as many as
2,700 American workers,
and put them under the control
of his Chinese company.
Now, that’s not Black or White,
but it’s also not the same as creating jobs.
Jack probably figured he had
a good relationship with The Donald—
what we call in Chinese “guanxi.”
A sort of relationship currency
that’s more valuable than gold in China.
But Jack Ma is learning that guanxi
has a pretty weak exchange rate
with the US government.
They might still reject your takeover plan—
even though you guys are totally besties
after that one meeting you had.
So how did Chinese state-run media
respond to the rejection?
“We hope the U.S. can create
a fair and predictable environment
for Chinese enterprises to invest
and start businesses.”
Which is like a lionness saying to
a group of gazelles,
“Hey c’mon, guys.
You gotta give me a fair chance.
What’s with the running away?”
You see, the Chinese regime
has never created a level playing field
for foreign businesses.
In fact, if you’re a foreign company,
you’re not even allowed
to set up shop in China
without having a Chinese joint venture partner,
giving your partner a majority stake in the
company,
and handing over some of your intellectual
property.
So when it comes to MoneyGram,
if the roles were reversed—
and it had been a China-based company
that an American company wanted to buy—
the Chinese regime would have
flat out rejected it.
And they wouldn’t have even bothered
reviewing it for a year.
Chinese officials understand that
this is frustrating for American companies,
and they’ve tried to use it as leverage
in the past.
“Past meetings between the two countries
have seen China ask the US
for easier passage of its deals
in return for access to the Chinese market—
something the Obama administration
repeatedly declined.”
But now,
not only has the US been screening
more and more of these Chinese investments,
the EU will be too.
Because the fundamental problem
is that every major Chinese company
that is big enough to invest outside China
will have direct or indirect ties
to the Chinese Communist Party.
That’s just how it works.
But it means that as
more Chinese companies go abroad,
they’ll get heavier scrutiny because
other countries have concerns
that their technology and intellectual property
will be used by the CCP.
And what will happen with Ant Financial?
Well, Jack Ma will probably have to
take a good look at the Man in the Mirror
and realize that he’s not as smooth a criminal
as he thought.
But his company will be fine.
As for other Chinese companies
looking to buy foreign assets,
well, they won’t stop til they get enough.
So let me know what you think
of the US government’s rejection
of the MoneyGram takeover.
Bonus points for using Michael Jackson lyrics
in your reply.
I’m Shelley Zhang.
See you again soon.
Thanks for watching this episode.
Chris will be back at the end of the week.
In the meantime,
check out some of our other videos
here on the left.
And if you have suggestions
for other topics we should cover,
send an email to ChinaUncensored@gmail.com.