On this episode of China Uncensored,
Terracotta Warriors are vandalized.
I’m giving that a thumbs down.
I know what I don’t want at my funeral.
And finally, Chinese prisons love fashion...
manufacturing jobs.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
You’ve probably seen photos of these guys:
The Terracotta Warriors.
They survived in an underground tomb
for 2,000 years.
Ten of them were on loan
to a museum in Philadelphia.
And this week,
some idiot American snapped off
one of their fingers for a souvenir.
Ten of them were on loan
to a museum in Philadelphia.
And this week,
some idiot American snapped off
one of their fingers for a souvenir.
He was attending an “ugly sweater party”
at the museum,
when he snuck into the Terracotta Warriors
exhibit.
That’s not a joke,
that’s what he was actually doing.
It was almost the perfect crime.
If only he hadn’t left
his fingerprints on the statue.
And if only there weren’t surveillance footage.
And if only hadn’t sent photos
of the thumb he stole
to friends on SnapChat.
The man was arrested by the FBI
and is now out on bail.
He faces a 10 year prison sentence
for defacing the 4.5 million dollar statue.
On the bright side,
for the few days he had that thumb,
boy...he was a master hitchhiker.
The Terracotta Warriors exhibit will be open
until early March.
Critics give it one thumb up,
and one thumb off.
Now, even more outrage!
This time from me.
They’re cracking down on funeral strippers.
Apparently, in some rural communities,
it’s believe that the more people
that attend a funeral,
the more honor for the deceased.
How do you get more people?
Well, traditionally people hired
Chinese opera singers to draw a crowd.
But this is modern China.
So now the answer is obviously, strippers.
According to the Global Times,
China’s Ministry of Culture has set up,
“a special ‘hotline’ for the public
to report any ‘funeral misdeeds’”.
And you know what, in this instance,
I have complete faith that local CCP authorities
will quickly, and personally,
get to the bottom of this issue.
Moving on to international news.
Philippines President Rodrigo Duterte:
The man who once vowed
to personally ride a jet ski
to plant a Filipino flag on Chinese-occupied
islands
in the South China Sea.
But that was two years ago,
and boy have things changed!
Earlier this week,
President Duterte made waves
when he joked that the Philippines
should become a province of China.
It was part of his speech
at the Chinese Filipino Business Club.
“If you want, you (China) should just
make us your province.
Like Fujian.
Call it the Philippine province of China.”
He went on to add,
and once again, I'm not joking:
“If China were a woman,
I’d woo her.”
And really, what woman wouldn’t want
to be wooed by Duterte?
Am I right, ladies?
Duterte then brought up the controversial
military installations that China
is building in the South China Sea.
He told people to relax;
those have nothing to do with the Philippines.
“It’s really intended against those
who the Chinese think would destroy them—
and that is America.
We are not a part of that.”
Haha, yes, clap for that.
And the Financial Times
has interviewed Peter Humphrey,
who spent 23 months in a Chinese prison.
Humphrey used to be a British Private Investigator.
But he was jailed in 2014
and kept in a small cage.
And that’s where he learned all about fashion!
I mean just look at this little ensemble he
wore
to his mandatory state-run TV confession.
According to Humphrey,
“The prison was a business,
doing manufacturing jobs for companies.
Mornings, afternoons and often
during the after-lunch nap,
prisoners ‘laboured’ in the common room.”
Humphrey said that what they made
included packaging for fashion retailers
H&M and C&A.
Nothing’s more fashionable than slave labor!
Of course, both H&M and C&A
say in their supplier code and conduct agreements
that prison labor is not okay.
And of course the companies
are investigating the matter now.
But maybe they should have been wondering
why it’s so cheap to get things made in
China.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Well the Chinese Communist Party
is certainly rotten.
But you know what never goes bad?
Food from Thrive Life.
Thrive Life sells freeze dried meals
that stay fresh.
And if you order through the link
in the description below,
China Uncensored gets a cut.
I wouldn’t ask you to eat their food
if I didn’t also personally love it.
So support your belly and China Uncensored
by buying some delicious food from Thrive
Life.
The link is below.