A top figure in Huawei was arrested in Canada.
Now the Chinese government is threatening:
“Release her, or else.”
And Canada says, “Or else, what...eh?”
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
This is Meng Wanzhou.
She’s the Chief Financial Officer
of China’s biggest private company, Huawei.
But she made a big mistake:
Going to Canada.
See, Meng was at the Vancouver airport on
December 1st,
changing flights, when Canadian authorities
arrested her.
She’s suspected of orchestrating a scheme
by Huawei
to use the global banking system
to evade U.S. sanctions on Iran.
And now she’s stuck in a Vancouver-area
prison
called the Alouette Correctional Facility
Center for Women.
The Alouette is a dangerous place.
First they pluck the feathers off your head,
then your beak, then your neck...
And that was a very obscure joke
for all 3 of you who speak French.
Anyway, Meng’s arrest in Canada ought to
be a lesson:
She should have spent her winter visiting
a tropical island nation like Vanuatu.
Not so much for the warm weather—
but because they don’t have an extradition
treaty with the US.
Meng was arrested in Canada at the request
of US authorities.
The US accuses her of misleading multinational
banks
about Huawei’s control of a company operating
in Iran,
putting the banks at risk of violating US
sanctions
and potentially incurring severe penalties.
If extradited to the US and convicted here,
she could face up to 30 years in prison.
But even in her temporary Canadian jail,
she’s been badly abused.
Don't take it from me.
Take it from my favorite Chinese state-run
media The Global Times.
They say her human rights are being violated.
They write that,
“She has been subjected to rude and degrading
treatment.”
For example,
being put in handcuffs and even ankle braces.
I agree.
How dare Canada treat her like a common Chinese
dissident!
She’s a VIP with connections!
Actually, that’s not true.
A common Chinese dissident would have been
beaten up
at least once or twice by now.
But the point is,
Meng is not only the CFO of Huawei.
She’s also the daughter of Huawei’s founder,
Ren Zhengfei.
He’s worth 3.2 billion dollars.
And he’s a former officer of the People’s
Liberation Army.
That makes her not just an heiress to the
Huawei empire,
but potentially a key figure in the Chinese
Communist Party’s
shady relationship with Huawei.
Huawei has faced accusations of conducting
espionage
on behalf of the Chinese Communist Party,
and of undermining American security
by illegally using advanced US technology
to give the Chinese military an edge.
Richard Fisher, Senior Fellow
at the International Assessment and Strategy
Center,
told The Epoch Times that Huawei
and another Chinese company ZTE are quote
unquote
“cat’s paws for Chinese Communist Party
domination.”
Now that should really give you pause.
The Chinese company ZTE is a competitor of
Huawei.
And the US recently banned ZTE
from buying components from U.S. manufacturers.
It was punishment for illegally selling telecom
equipment
containing American technology to Iran and
North Korea.
And Huawei could soon face similar sanctions.
Because it’s also under investigation
by the US Department of Justice
for violating Iran sanctions.
So it’s little wonder that the Chinese Communist
Party
has rushed to threaten Canada over Meng Wanzhou’s
arrest.
Here’s my favorite Chinese Foreign Ministry
Spokesperson
and second-favorite Mortal Kombat character,
Lu Kang:
“For Canada,
if they do not correctly handle this matter,
there will be serious consequences.”
Then things got weird.
“You asked,
what kind of serious consequences would these
be?
I can tell you in one sentence—
it is totally up to Canada."
“Totally up to Canada?”
Isn’t that a bit like putting a convict
in charge of their own sentencing?
“Your honor,
for all the grievous crimes I’ve committed,
I hereby sentence myself to...
total freedom and a six pack of beer!”
And can you really count on Canada for self-discipline?
I mean, it is the country that just legalized
marijuana.
And its Prime Minister, Justin Trudeau,
is nicknamed the “Shiny Pony”.
Seriously.
He got that name in 2012
when he fought a Canadian senator
at a charity boxing match.
“Justin Truuuuuuudeau!”
“He’s wearing liberal red, of course.
I call him the Shiny Pony.
He looks like he’s in some sort of zen yoga
trance.”
Which, let’s face it,
was really a chance to show off his tattoo.
So can you really count on Canada’s Prime
Minister
to read between the lines of China’s
“it’s totally up to you” threat?
Clearly, you can’t.
Shiny Pony did not get the hint.
He told the press that he wasn’t going to
do
any political favors to get Ms. Meng out of
jail.
“I can assure everyone that
we are a country of an independent judiciary
and the appropriate authorities took the decisions
in this case
without any political involvement or interference,
as must be the case.”
This is something maybe Chinese authorities
don’t understand.
But Canada—yes, Canada—
does have rule of law.
“The Prime Minister or Minister cannot phone
the judge
and tell them to release the person,
so what’s China demanding under our rule
of law,
under our system,
is not a doable thing.
That being said,
China certainly has the means
to inflict pain on its relationship with Canada.”
So after all of the Chinese regime’s confusing
threats
that didn’t sound like threats,
it finally took Party mouthpiece People’s
Daily to lay it on straight.
They directly warned Canada that
“The only way to avoid paying a much heavier
price
is for the Canadian side to correct this error.”
So what they’re saying is...
Unless Canadian politicians break the law,
violate their extradition treaty with the
US,
and release Meng,
there’ll be hell to pay.
So how did Shiny Pony react to that?
“As I said the appropriate authorities
took the decisions in this case.
We were advised by them with a few days notice
that this was in the works.
But of course there was no engagement
or involvement in the political level in this
decision
because we respect the independence
of our judicial processes.”
Yeah, Canada is not letting her go.
And you know,
as much as I like to make fun of Canada and
Justin Trudeau—
and oh man, I do!—
in this case, I have to say...
TKO Justin Trudeau!
“Justin Trudeau, you did it!
You’re not the shiny pony, you’re the
stallion!”
Let’s just hope he sticks to his...surprisingly
big guns.
So what’s happening with Meng Wanzhou’s
case now?
Well, in accordance with Canadian law,
she went through a hearing to determine
whether she should be released on bail
due to health concerns while her case is being
decided.
The judge ended up granting her bail,
which means she won’t have to stay in prison
as her case proceeds.
Meng’s extradition case could last months
or even years,
since under Canadian law,
she can appeal an extradition decision
all the way to the Canadian Supreme Court.
Meanwhile, I’m sure that there’s no way
that
the Chinese Communist Party could try to put
more political pressure on Canada to release
Meng.
Like for example,
detaining a former Canadian diplomat in China.
Well, whaddya know.
So what do you think about China’s threats
to punish Canada for not releasing Meng?
Leave your comments below.
And before you go,
it’s time for me to answer a question
from one of you who supports China Uncensored
through the crowdfunding website Patreon.
WinniePooh asks,
“Do you think conflict will still exist
between the US and China
if god turns China into a democratic and wealthier
country?
Or is it possible for a democratic country
to become the 2nd most powerful country
which can challenge the US?
Good question.
Firstly,
turning China into a democratic and wealthy
country....
This is something Chinese people
have to take action on themselves.
And to do that,
they’ll have to bring the Communist Party
and its worst henchmen to justice.
Because China can never have meaningful democracy
under a Party that sits above the rule of
law.
If China does eventually become a country
with democracy,
and rule of law, and wealth,
would we have a conflict?
Well, there might be disagreements.
It’s normal to not see eye-to-eye
on every issue with every country—
even our allies.
This is why each leader needs to continuously
forge bonds,
and sometimes re-negotiate treaties.
But it’s pretty rare for democracies
to go to war against other democracies.
So I think that once China ditches the Communist
Party
and establishes rule of law,
it will be on its way to real prosperity,
and will potentially be a long-term ally of
the US.
It’s pretty clear that we’re capable of
being allies
with big countries like India,
wealthy countries like Japan,
and Chinese democracies like Taiwan.
Thanks for your question, WinniePooh.
Wait, you’re not...
Couldn’t be.
And for everyone else,
do you want help us
make more episodes of China Uncensored?
Please support our growth
by pledging a dollar or more per episode.
Go to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
The link is below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
You know, sometimes I feel like I could make an entire
show
of just directly reading Chinese state-run
media out loud.
For example, the recent People’s Daily article.
“To arrest someone without offering a clear
reason
is an undisguised infringement upon
the human rights of that person.
The Canadian side,
even though there had not been a trial
and determination of guilt,
went entirely against the spirit of the law,
choosing to infer guilt
and placing the person in handcuffs and fetters.
To treat a Chinese citizen like a serious
criminal,
to roughly trample their basic human rights,
and to dishonour their dignity,
how is this the method of a civilised country?
How can this not make people furious?”
Yes, how can a government that tramples
on the basic human rights of Chinese citizens
not make people furious.
Good question, People’s Daily.