Is there a bright side to the deadly Coronavirus
outbreak?
The Chinese Communist Party has found one
In the most horrifying way you can imagine
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
You know, say what you will
about the Chinese Communist Party,
you have to admire their relentless optimism.
Take the coronavirus outbreak for instance.
Now *you* might be completely overwhelmed
by this immense human tragedy.
But the Communist Party can see the silver
lining.
For example, greenhouse gas emissions are
down!
How’s that for some good news?
Or how about this,
China spares no effort to improve
governance capability amid epidemic.
That sounds impressive right?
Until you realize that “governance capability”
is a nice way of saying Mao-style social control.
Now to be fair to the Communist Party,
it’s not clear if it is using the coronavirus
as an *excuse*
to ratchet up the authoritarianism.
Or if ratcheting up the authoritarianism
is the only way they know how to deal with
the coronavirus.
It’s a “which came first,
the chicken or the egg” situation.
Either way, I think we can all agree that
the people in China had too much freedom.
Which is why, as authorities “crack down”
on the coronavirus,
they’re abducting and beating up citizens
across the country.
And holding them to the ground and...
spraying them with disinfectant?
I don’t think that’s how this works.
Or simply welded into their homes,
where I really hope they have enough food.
These people were playing Mahjong,
when authorities busted in
and really showed that table who’s boss.
That’s because mahjong and card games have
been banned.
There’s a reason why an epidemic disease
is being treated the same way the Party
treats political dissidents.
Chinese leader Xi Jinping has fired
both the party secretary of Hubei province
and the party secretary of the city of Wuhan,
where the coronavirus outbreak began.
In case you don’t know,
the Party secretary outranks
the governor or mayor of the same region.
In Communist China,
it’s the Party members who are really in
charge.
So who did Xi Jinping replace
the Party secretary of Hubei province with?
Why, Xi Jinping’s close ally Ying Yong.
He’s a good friend of Xi Jinping’s.
He,
“rose through the political ranks in Zhejiang
Province,
where Mr. Xi himself began his climb to power.”
And Ying Yong got loads of experience dealing
with sick people
when he worked in the “Public Security Bureau,
including [positions] overseeing antidrug
and antiterrorism agencies.”
Because anyone who is against the Party,
must be sick.
Like the young woman in Hubei province
who became an internet celebrity
for complaining about the lack of treatment
she got at a hospital.
“She was coerced into making a ‘confession’
video
in which she told her followers not to ‘spread
false rumors’
and to respect the country and its communist
leaders.”
Fortunately, these kinds of complaints will
happen less and less.
Because censors are using WeChat and Twitter
to find and silence people who are sharing
non-state approved messages about the coronavirus.
Giving the state apparatus more power to control
people
is also very effective at helping them distribute
aid.
Sure, warehouses full of donated food in the
city of Ezhou go to rot.
But the family members of police get plenty.
This video is from the wife of a police officer
in Ezhou.
She talks about getting so much food that
she’s going to give extras to her relatives.
Sharing is caring.
Of course most grocery stores still manage
to get supplies.
Unless police come in to confiscate the goods.
Don’t worry,
they put it back after they got caught on
camera.
Now obviously, in the pursuit of doing what’s
best for the people,
Party officials might make a few mistakes.
Like how their severe lockdown meant that
a child
got locked in his home with his dead grandfather.
But as of two weeks ago,
Party officials in Wuhan
had the crematoriums working 24/7.
And effective quarantine procedures are strictly
enforced,
like by putting people in boxes on the back
of trucks.
Wow, she sure is screaming.
I mean, the box is tiny,
but how scary could it be?
Unless you believe this account from a former
patient in Wuhan,
who told a taxi driver about seeing other
patients
being put in body bags
and being sent to crematoriums while still
alive.
Now, this video hasn’t been independently
verified.
And we haven’t heard other reports like
it.
But, considering the Chinese Communist Party
is killing political and religious prisoners
for their organs...
...the idea they’ve uh, “disposed of”
sick patients who are still alive,
becomes unfortunately less far fetched.
But don’t worry,
because the Chinese Communist Party
has definitely ensured basic human rights
in its virus fight.
What do you think about the growing authoritarianism
in China?
Let me know in the comments below.
Take a moment to subscribe to this channel
before you go,
even if you already subscribed,
because YouTube has apparently been unsubscribing
fans
with no notification.
And remember,
YouTube is targeting all our coverage of the
coronavirus.
They try to pressure us to stop covering it
by demonetizing our episodes.
But they can’t stop us as long as we have
the China Uncensored 50-Cent Army.
Those are the fans of the show who support
us
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
As a thank you to them,
I answer their questions at the end of some
of my episodes.
Today’s question comes from Logan.
“Did YouTube tell you exactly what Chris
said
that got you guys in trouble?
Do you have any strikes against your channel?”
Ah, I think Logan is talking about our recent
episode,
China’s Coronavirus “Cure.”
If you need a reminder what that cure was,
it was this.
A lot happened after we published that episode.
First YouTube instantly demonetized it.
No reason was given.
We appealed.
It was reviewed by a human,
and then permanently demonetized.
No reason was given.
Then three days after it was published,
YouTube completely removed the video from
the internet.
No reason given.
We appealed it and made
a lot of noise about it on social media,
and then YouTube relanted and put it back
up.
But then YouTube age restricted the video.
Again, no reason given.
This all means you still can’t see it
if you’re not signed into a YouTube account.
That kills the views.
We appealed that,
but so far, no response.
Now obviously none of that makes any sense.
And since YouTube is being entirely silent
on it,
we have no idea what happened.
So far there are no actual strikes against
our channel.
We’ve published more than a thousand episodes,
and there have been zero strikes
for anything like copyright violations,
illegal things, etc.
Strikes would actually risk
the entire channel getting shut down.
Of course I really can’t say I know
what would constitute a strike
and who we would talk to if someday YouTube
really did decide to take down China Uncensored.
But that’s why your support on Patreon is
so important.
It gives us the flexibility
we need to be able to keep making the show
no matter what curveballs YouTube and Google
try to throw at us.
Thanks for your question Logan.
And if you’d like to join the China Uncensored
50-cent army,
go to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored to learn
more.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.