On this episode of China Uncensored,
the future of the Internet is peace and security -
run by the world’s biggest violator of human rights.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Nothing makes me feel hopeful about the future of mankind
like a new world order run by the benevolent
Chinese Communist Party.
But that’s a long way off.
We may just have to accept a China’s new
world order
in cyberspace for now.
Last week, this policy paper called
"International Strategy of Cooperation on Cyberspace"
was issued by China’s Ministry of Foreign Affairs
and the Cyberspace Administration of China.
Among other things,
the paper calls for “upholding sovereignty
in cyberspace.”
Basically, it means the Chinese regime wants cyberspace
to be viewed in the same way it treats China’s land,
air, and seas.
Can you build artifical islands in cyberspace?
Don’t worry.
They only want to do benevolent new world
order stuff—
like “prevent cyberspace from becoming a
new battlefield.”
Nice try, China!
Cyberspace is already a battlefield.
That's what I learned from my favorite 90s
live-action kids show
adapted using stock footage from Japanese television!
What?
Like you didn't watch Superhuman Samurai Syber-Squad.
Yes, cyberspace is crawling with monster viruses
that are...
knocking down lots of things.
The Chinese Communist Party wants to pretend
it’s Servo,
our cyber hero.
But don't be fooled.
It was Kilokahn all along.
Mwuhahahaha!
Anyway, like Kilokahn,
what the Communist Party wants is not just control
of its own domain,
but the entire world.
Last week’s latest policy paper
essentially lays out that plan...
but in warm, fuzzy language.
It mentions “peace” 18 times in 12 pages.
I mean, did you know that
“China has been a force for world peace,”
“advocates the principles of peace,”
and is “committed to upholding peace and
security
in cyberspace?”
If they say it often enough,
it must be true.
And last Thursday,
an official from the Cyberspace Administration
of China
told reporters that
“The Chinese Internet is fully open”
and that “all Internet companies are welcome
in China.”
Did you hear that, Google?
Oh wait, “as long as they comply with
Chinese laws and regulations,
refrain from undermining China's national
interests
and interests of Chinese consumers.”
Never mind, Google.
The fact is,
China’s Internet Freedom ranking is just below
Iran and Syria.
So not super free.
The Chinese Communist Party maintains
a tight grip on the Internet
with what’s known as the Great Firewall—
a massive,
nationwide censorship and monitoring system.
The regime claims it’s necessary for national
security.
Or in other words,
cracking down on dissent.
Fortunately, last week’s policy paper
doesn’t have any power to let the Chinese
regime
control the world’s Internet.
It’s just something they’re going to present
at the BRICS economic summit later this year.
Unfortunately, this policy paper won’t be
the end of it.
And it’s not the beginning, either.
For many years,
the Chinese regime has been working towards
grabbing
more control of the world’s Internet.
In an episode last October,
I told you about how China is trying to influence
ICANN,
the world’s Internet address book.
So why does the Chinese Communist Party care
so much
about controlling the Internet in the rest
of the world?
No, the end game is not about censoring Americans
from searching for topics banned on the Chinese
Internet,
like the Tiananmen Square Massacre.
A key part of it actually has to do with economics.
The Chinese regime can only do so much
with its draconian Internet security laws
and tons of secret police.
To maintain power,
it has to keep the Chinese middle class happy
with economic incentives.
So to keep the economy running,
the Chinese regime has invented
a vast system of economic espionage
to steal other countries',
and particularly America's,
innovation and intellectual property.
“U.S. companies and the U.S. economy
lose approximately $5 trillion each year,
or over 30 percent of the U.S. GDP
when you factor the full value
of the stolen innovation.”
And so in 2015,
then President Barack Obama sat down
with Chinese leader Xi Jinping,
and they agreed, no more to economic cybertheft!
Other forms of hacking were still okay.
That’s not a joke.
But a big chunk of the Chinese economy,
and by extension the rule of the Chinese regime,
depends on stolen innovation.
So whaddya gonna do?
Simply find legal ways to do the same thing.
This is when you start to see China
rolling out all kinds of cyber security laws,
for national security.
Laws very similar
to what China now wants to roll out globally.
In July 2015,
China passed the National Security Law,
“to make all key network infrastructure
and information systems
“secure and controllable.”
Later that year,
the Counter Terrorism Law was passed that
“Requires internet service providers
to help authorities decrypt data and provide
‘technical means of support’ in terrorism
cases.”
And at the end of 2016,
the Cybersecurity Law was passed.
It requires that network operators
must accept government supervision.
According to Forbes,
it could “theoretically cover every organization
or business
with a linked computer system.”
And companies around the world freaked.
Because basically what that all meant
is the Chinese regime can look at anything
that happens
on a computer inside China,
including the computers of Western companies
operating in China—
or even Western companies that don’t operate
in China,
but use servers inside China.
And it’s done under the guise of national
security
and counterterrorism.
Essentially, if the Chinese regime requires
companies
to give it access to any and all data passing
through China,
this is a “legal” way to get a hold
of foreign intellectual property.
Of course many companies tried to rebel.
And the Chinese regime hit back hard.
Companies like Microsoft, Qualcomm, and Apple
were hit with surprise early morning raids
of their China offices,
fines, heavy criticism in the media,
the whole shebang.
And then they mostly backed down.
And gave in to the idea of following Chinese
law.
Because who doesn’t want a piece
of the magically delicious China market?
And that’s just one example of how the Communist Party
is trying to influence Internet policy.
This latest proposal,
is really just a small step in a much larger
plan
that’s been going on for years.
And the end game, as always,
is maintaining the Party’s control over
China.
Argh!
That blasted Kilokahn,
trying to rule the internet!
Speaking of which,
where's my gritty reboot of Superhuman Samurai
Syber-Squad?
Get on it, Hollywood.
I mean, it’s not like Matthew Lawrence
is doing anything right now.
So what do you think of the Chinese regime’s
plans
for the Internet?
Leave your comments below.
While you still can!
Thanks for watching this episode of China Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Now go out there and kick some giga-butt.