On this episode of China Uncensored,
is it really a lie if you're just not telling
the truth?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I'm your host Chris Chappell.
You know it's a bad sign when the guy in charge
of your country's statistics gets arrested
for corruption.
Especially when one of the last things he
says in public is this.
"We should say that we are full of confidence
for the growth and operation of China's stock market."
Hmmm, that's funny.
Because on Tuesday, Chinese stocks fell to
their lowest level in 13 months.
Anyway, that was Wang Baoan,
the I guess now former head of China's National
Bureau of Statistics.
He was arrested just hours after giving that
speech.
Talk about a tough crowd!
Oops, did I say "arrested"?
Because that's not what happens in the Communist
Party!
You get "put under investigation."
In Wang's case, for "severe disciplinary violations."
If you're not familiar with this type of Communist
Party Newspeak,
"under investigation" is what they usually
say about officials being taken down in Xi
Jinping's so-called "anti-corruption campaign."
That's another Newspeak phrase that means
you may have done something corrupt,
but you're actually being taken down for,
most likely, political reasons.
So far, tens of thousands of Communist Party
members have been put under investigation.
This kind of political takedown happens a
lot in China.
And it's not very transparent because the
Communist Party is not actually a legal entity
in China.
It's an extralegal entity!
Not extra in a good way,
like getting that server at Chipotle who gives
you extra guacamole.
Extralegal like "it exists outside the law."
So if a member of the Communist Party does
something wrong,
it's up to his communist comrades
--not the court system--
to find the best way to "reform" him.
This usually involves getting sacked,
put in detention with no lawyer or judicial
oversight,
followed by...
show trial!
And of course, the worst punishment,
denying the technically un-accused of their
black hair dye.
Now so far, there haven't been any specific
charges leveled against Wang.
In fact, it's not even clear whether the investigation
is related to his role as head of the National
Bureau of Statistics
because before that, he was China's vice minister
of finance.
But the fact that Wang's most recent role
is the guy in charge of reporting China's
GDP figures...
well, if you're thinking what I'm thinking,
that's what everyone else in the world is
thinking.
It's a bit sensitive.
And that's a problem because people already
think China makes up its economic data.
Officially, China's GDP is growing at 6.9%,
the slowest pace in 25 years.
But a lot of experts think it's actually much
lower,
despite what Wang claimed last week
you know, before he got put under investigation.
But you got to feel sorry for Wang.
He had a tough job: give the Communist Party
frank, steely assessments of China's actual
economic strengthens and weakness.
And then tell the public that everything's
fine.
Of course I suppose he didn't have to take
that job.
Anyway, what do you think that the arrest
--er, investigation of Wang says about China's
economy?
Make up your wildest guess, since we really
have no way to know.
Leave your comments below and subscribe fore
more episodes of China Uncensored.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell. See you next
time.