On this episode of China Uncensored,
China is now the most threatening country.
Sorry Kim.
Chinese troops are messing around in Djibouti
And finally,
the Chinese regime has a new plan to make
every Uighur Muslim in Xinjiang really happy.
This is China Uncensored.
The United States considers Taiwan
to be its unsinkable aircraft carrier--
its friend in the Pacific that will never
let America down.
So if the Chinese Communist Party follows
through
with its promise to attack Taiwan,
that could mean the United States and China
coming to blows.
But at least according to some in the United
States,
military, the US and China coming to blows
might be inevitable.
At least, that's what I'm getting from General
Joseph Dunford.
(Corner Box)
He told Congress,
"I think China probably poses the greatest
threat
to our nation by about 2025."
Yes, according to this general,
China, then Russia,
then North Korea are the greatest threats
to the United States.
In that order.
General Dunford wasn't talking just about
China versus Taiwan,
but about the threat of China's military in
general.
And considering that North Korea made a video
about blowing up the White House and the Capitol
Building,
you've got to wonder what a bigger nation
is capable of.
Probably better video quality, for one.
And Chinese troops are training for war--
at least, in Djibouti.
Yes, things are blowing up in Djibouti
as the Chinese military carries out
its first live fire drills in Africa.
That's after the CCP built its first overseas
military base there.
Hopefully, the Chinese military will stay
contained in Djibouti.
But maybe Chinese construction in the area
will take off.
And if it does,
I have the perfect man for the job:
The guy who designed this:
the Career and Entrepreneurship Comprehensive
Service Base
of University Graduates in Zhengzhou.
That building has become the current laughingstock
of the Chinese internet.
But don't expect people to be sharing it on
WhatsApp.
Because WhatsApp has been blocked in some
areas of China.
Again.
It comes just a few weeks ahead of the 19th
Party Congress in mid-October.
You see, the CCP would hate it if people were
to share
sensitive information through WhatsApp--
information like ...
what people think about stuff.
Yeah, guys, having opinions doesn't make the
country better.
But you know what does?
Creating jobs.
The CCP is working hard to make sure life
is great
for all the happy ethnic Uighur Muslims in
Xinjiang.
And the best way to do that of course is through
job creation.
And the fastest growing job segment in Xinjiang
is--security!
Over the past 12 months,
authorities have posted ads for hiring
100,000 new security personnel.
That's a ridiculous number of people to hire.
By comparison,
that's more than the total number of US Border
Patrol Agents,
TSA Officers, and FBI Agents combined
in the ENTIRE United States.
The population of Xinjiang is less than a
10th of the US.
Just imagine 100,000 security guards in Xinjiang
riding around on segways
and eating lamb kebabs.
In fact, Xinjiang has already spent around
$6 billion
on security in the first half of 2017.
That's more than 50% of the region's income.
And it's all thanks to Chen "Entire Country"
Quanguo.
That's not his nickname,
that's just the translation of his name, Quanguo.
Fresh off his tenure as
one of the most brutal Party Secretaries of
Tibet,
now he's turning Xinjiang around.
Why, just look at these 10,000 happily employed
citizens.
And all those happily employed folks
are helping keep Xinjiang under full lockdown.
Which the people love.
Why, this is what one shoe vendor told to
NPR reporters.
"It makes me feel safer.
They've built police stations every few blocks
or so.
The police check us every day,
no matter if you're a doctor, teacher, anyone.
It's all for our safety."
China, leading the way in treatment of ethnic
minorities
since the liberation of Tibet.
What do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I'm your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Oh?
Hi there.
I'm just sending pictures of Djibouti
to a friend on WhatsApp.
But if you want to see something really good
on the Internet,
you should go to China Uncensored.tv.
We upload full half hour episodes there every
Friday.
So you could have seen this and other segments
earlier.
Now if you'll excuse me,
it's back to Djibouti.