china is threatening war over taiwan but a
recent donation of u.s coveted vaccines makes
that seem a little less likely
welcome to china uncensored i'm chris chappell
well it's something that doesn't happen every
day a bipartisan group of u.s senators took
a military aircraft to visit taiwan the three
senators arrived on a u.s air force c-17 not
plane available of transporting troops and
cargo cargo like artillery battle tanks and
helicopters taiwanese media reported that
it was the first c-17 visit since at least
1995.
meanwhile my favorite chinese state-run media
global times said it was the most serious
provocation since u.s president joe biden
took office which of course is just a fancy
way of saying that it angered china the arrival
of three u.s senators in taiwan bearing covet
vaccines is part of the u.s playing catch-up
at vaccine diplomacy the chinese communist
party has been selling its coveted vaccines
around the world selling not donating and
those vaccines come with many strings attached
those strings include being politically obedient
to the chinese regime which is why even though
taiwan is struggling with a covet 19 surge
it's still refusing chinese vaccines and with
good reason china is trying to use coveted
vaccines for political leverage in taiwan
china cut off taiwan's access to germany's
bioentech shots and when japan donated 1.2
million vaccines to taiwan china said japan
was using the vaccines as a tool of political
self-interest the party loves to accuse others
of doing what it does i'd say it's a guilty
conscience but i don't think the communist
party feels guilt but the binding administration
is now making a push to donate covet vaccines
to the world donate not sell unlike china
and one u.s official said u.s vaccines don't
come with strings attached senator tammy duckworth
one of the senators who visited taiwan said
taiwan is getting first dibs it was critical
to the united states that taiwan be included
in the first group to receive vaccines because
we recognize your urgent need and we value
this partnership the chinese communist party
hates when the u.s recognizes taiwan like
this but china's response to this visit has
been surprising and it has many chinese citizens
infuriated i'll tell you more after the break
welcome back so as you can imagine the chinese
communist party is not happy about u.s senators
visiting taiwan in a military aircraft chinese
jets have been making daily incursions in
taiwan airspace for months china considers
taiwan part of its territory and my favorite
chinese state-run media the global times calls
this latest move by the u.s and taiwan salami
slicing tactics they're accusing the u.s and
taiwan of using small actions to get closer
diplomatically slice by slice and the communist
party knows about salami slicing since they're
using it to take over more territory in the
south china sea and on the indian border the
communist party also doesn't get irony so
as this global times editorial asks how should
the mainland respond turns out by doing nothing
nada zip state media including the official
xinhua news agency didn't report on the trip
while the chinese foreign ministry sidestepped
a question about the plane but later foreign
ministry spokesman wang wan bin broke out
his inner wolf warrior with this incendiary
rhetoric the u.s should avoid sending any
wrong signal to taiwan independence separatists
and causing further damage to china-u.s relations
and peace and stability across the taiwan
strait these are the same people who have
been threatening to invade taiwan for years
right in 2005 china passed a law saying it
had the right to use non-peaceful and other
necessary means to prevent taiwan from formally
declaring independence chinese state remedia
have threatened war if u.s military aircraft
go to taiwan they said that would be crossing
china's red line it threatened to destroy
the taiwanese airport the u.s aircraft and
start a war well i don't see a war starting
could it be the chinese communist party was
just bluffing that it's all bluster a bully
who backs down at the first sign of pressure
i'm shocked as were many of china's nationalistic
youth was all that talk of a red line in war
just that talk one popular huevo comment china's
version of twitter said our red line is no
red line if this is the case how can foreigners
treat taiwan as part of china another online
commentary said this is a salami-slicing move
that is continuously pressing your red line
maybe china's wolf warrior is just a sheep
in wolf's clothing and now it's time for me
to answer a question from a member of the
china uncensored 50 cent army fans who support
us and our efforts to expose the truth about
the chinese communist party by contributing
through the crowdfunding website patreon bananapancakes
asks so is she going to go handmaid's tale
to solve china's population problem this was
in response to my recent episode about china's
new three child policy after decades of the
one child policy and then the brief to child
policy the communist party is now allowing
chinese people to have three children that's
after it became clear all those forced abortions
and sterilizations have caused a population
crisis except as i mentioned in that episode
chinese people don't really want more kids
in fact many want no kids intense workplace
competition inadequate child care and widespread
job discrimination against pregnant women
have made childbearing an unappealing prospect
for many so will the chinese communist party
resort to handmaid's tale tactics in the sense
of how a small group of elite men suppress
the population forcing the lower class to
work in dirty dangerous conditions it's already
doing that but will it start forcing women
to have children well considering under china's
family planning policy women had their menstrual
cycles recorded on blackboards for all to
see i don't think the communist party has
an ethical problem with getting right up in
people's personal business in fact they don't
see it as your personal business they see
it as the state's business so i really wouldn't
be surprised if one day the three child policy
goes from a recommendation to a requirement
in fact i talked about hoChina is threatening
war over Taiwan
But a recent donation of US Covid Vaccines
makes that seem a little less likely
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
Well, it’s something that doesn’t happen
every day.
A bipartisan group of US senators took a military
aircraft to visit Taiwan.
The three Senators arrived on a US Air Force
C-17 freight plane.
They came to Taiwan to announce a donation
of 750,000 US-made Covid vaccines.
But the real message was delivered to China,
in the form of a US military transport plane
capable of transporting troops and cargo.
Cargo like artillery, battle tanks and helicopters.
“Taiwanese media reported that it was the
first C-17 visit since at least 1995.”
Meanwhile, my favorite Chinese state-run media,
the Global Times said it was “the most serious
provocation...since US President Joe Biden
took office.”
Which of course is just a fancy way of saying
that it angered China.
The arrival of three US Senators in Taiwan
bearing Covid vaccines is part of the US playing
catch-up at Vaccine Diplomacy.
The Chinese Communist Party has been selling
its Covid vaccines around the world.
Selling, not donating.
And those vaccines come with many strings
attached.
Those strings include being politically obedient
to the Chinese regime.
Which is why, even though Taiwan is struggling
with a COVID-19 surge, it's still refusing
Chinese vaccines.
And with good reason.
China is trying to use Covid vaccines for
political leverage in Taiwan.
China cut off Taiwan’s access to Germany’s
BioNTech shots.
And when Japan donated 1.2 million vaccines
to Taiwan,
China said Japan was using the vaccines as
“a tool of political self-interest”.
The Party loves to accuse others of doing
what it does.
I’d say it’s a guilty conscience, but
I don’t think the Chinese Communist Party
feels guilt.
But the Biden Administration is now making
a push to donate Covid vaccines to the world.
Donate.
Not sell.
Unlike China.
And one US official said US vaccines “don’t
come with strings attached.”
Senator Tammy Duckworth , one of the Senators
who visited Taiwan, said Taiwan is getting
first dibs.
“It was critical to the United States that
Taiwan be included in the first group to receive
vaccines because we recognize your urgent
need and we value this partnership.”
The Chinese Communist Party hates when the
US recognizes Taiwan like this.
But China’s response to this visit has been
surprising.
And it has many Chinese citizens infuriated.
I’ll tell you more after the break.
Welcome back.
So as you can imagine, the Chinese Communist
Party is not happy about US Senators visiting
Taiwan in a military aircraft.
Chinese jets have been making daily incursions
in Taiwan airspace for months.
China considers Taiwan part of its territory.
And my favorite Chinese state-run media, the
Global Times, calls this latest move by the
US and Taiwan “salami-slicing tactics.”
They’re accusing the US and Taiwan of using
small actions to get closer diplomatically,
slice by slice.
And the Communist Party knows about salami
slicing—since they’re using it to take
over more territory in the South China Sea.
And on the Indian border.
The Communist Party also doesn’t get irony.
So as this Global Times editorial asks, how
should the Mainland respond?
Turns out, by doing nothing.
Nada.
Zip.
“State media including the official Xinhua
News Agency didn’t report on the trip while
the Chinese Foreign Ministry sidestepped a
question about the plane.”
But later, Foreign Ministry spokesman Wang
Wenbin broke out his inner wolf warrior with
this incendiary rhetoric.
“[The US] should avoid sending any wrong
signal to ‘Taiwan independence’ separatists
and causing further damage to China-US relations
and peace and stability across the Taiwan
Strait.”
These are the same people who have been threatening
to invade Taiwan for years, right?
In 2005, China passed a law saying it had
the right to “use non-peaceful and other
necessary means” to prevent Taiwan from
formally declaring independence.
Chinese state-run media have threatened war
if US military aircraft go to Taiwan.
They said that would be crossing China’s
“redline.”
It threatened to destroy the Taiwanese airport,
the US aircraft, and start a war.
Well, I don’t see a war starting.
Could it be—the Chinese Communist Party
was just bluffing?
That it’s all bluster?
A bully who backs down at the first sign of
pressure?
I’m shocked!
As were many of China’s nationalistic youth.
Was all that talk of a redline and war just
that?
Talk?
One popular comment on Weibo, China’s version
of Twitter said, “Our red line is no red
line.
If this is the case, how can foreigners treat
Taiwan as part of China?”
Another online commenter said, “This is
a salami-slicing move that is continuously
pressing your red line.”
Maybe China’s Wolf Warrior is just a sheep
in wolf’s clothing.
And now it’s time to answer a question from
a member of the China Uncensored 50 Cent Army,
fans who support us and our efforts to expose
the truth about the Chinese Communist Party,
by contributing through crowd funding website
Patreon.
Banana Pancakes asks, “So is Xi going to
go Handmaid’s Tale to solve China's population
problem?”
That was in response to my recent episode
about China’s new three child policy.
After decades of the one-child policy, and
then the brief two-child policy, the Communist
Party is now allowing Chinese people to have
three children.
That’s after it became clear all those forced
abortions and sterilizations have caused a
population crisis.
Except as I mentioned in that episode, Chinese
people don’t really want more kids.
In fact, many want no kids.
“Intense workplace competition, inadequate
child care and widespread job discrimination
against pregnant women have made childbearing
an unappealing prospect for many.”
So, will the Chinese Communist Party resort
to Handmaid’s Tale tactics?
In the sense of how a small group of elite
men suppress the population, forcing the lower
class to work in dirty, dangerous conditions...it’s
already doing that.
But will it start forcing women to have children?
Well, considering under China’s family planning
policy, “Women had their menstrual cycles
recorded on blackboards, for all to see.”
...I don’t think the Communist Party has
an ethical problem with getting right up in
people’s personal business.
In fact, they don’t see it as your personal
business.
They see it as the state’s business.
So I really wouldn’t be surprised if one
day, the three child policy goes from a recommendation
to a requirement.
In fact, I talked about how the Party could
start forcing people to have babies in this
recent episode.
Thanks for your question and your support,
Banana Pancakes.
And a big thank you to everyone who supports
China Uncensored on Patreon.
We could not do this show without you.
So thank you for joining us in the fight to
expose the Chinese Communist Party to the
world.
If you’re interested in joining, head over
to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
You’ll get a bunch of cool perks, including
the chance to have me answer your question
on the show!
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next
time.
w the party could start forcing people to
have babies in this recent episode thanks
for your question and your support banana
pancakes and a big thank you to everyone who
supports china uncensored on patreon we could
not do this show without you so thank you
for joining us in the fight to expose the
chinese communist party to the world if you're
interested in joining head over to patreon.com
china uncensored you'll get a bunch of cool
perks including the chance to have me answer
your questions on the show once again i'm
chris chappell see you next time you