On this episode of China Uncensored,
China just landed a military plane
on one of those islands it created in the
South China Sea.
You know, the islands that are for peaceful
purposes only.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored. I’m your
host, Chris Chappell.
Ah, the South China Sea:
what my favorite Chinese state-run media Global
Times calls
“a sea of peace, friendship and cooperation.”
Which is exactly why China landed a military
aircraft on Fiery Cross Reef on Monday
as shown here on Chinese state-run television.
Fiery Cross Reef is one of those disputed
islands China has been building up in the
South China Sea.
It’s also claimed by Vietnam and the Philippines.
But China is the one who’s built a 1.8-mile
long runway there
long enough to land military planes.
But don’t worry, Monday’s landing was
for a rescue mission
to airlift three sick civilians to a hospital.
That’s according to Chinese Foreign Ministry
Spokesman Lu Kang.
Sorry, this Lu Kang.
He told reporters on Monday that:
“On Chinese territory, something like this
is not out of the ordinary.”
Right. It is totally normal to land a military
plane on Chinese territory.
But I think the rest of the world’s concern
is that this island is maybe not Chinese territory.
It’s just being occupied by Chinese facilities,
including a runway long enough to land military
planes.
But if you think that China landing a military
plane on a disputed island,
then broadcasting it prominently on state-run
television,
is a signal that China intends to aggressively
fight for its territorial claims there,
you’d be wrong.
The real threat to peace and stability is
America—and the Philippines.
They just completed two weeks of annual joint
military exercises.
“These activities from the Philippines and
America
are poisoning regional and inter-country relations,
and are exacerbating regional conflicts
and are increasing tensions in the region,
damaging the peace and stability of the South
China Sea.”
Yes, the ones damaging peace and stability
are the countries that are not building permanent
military facilities there.
Alright Lu Kang, Finish Him!
“This also exactly proves who was the real
promoter of the militarization of the South China Sea."
Because while the Philippines calls for international
court arbitration over the disputed territory,
China just stations its military there.
With tensions so high in the region,
it’s unclear what’s going to happen.
But one thing’s for sure:
China’s not going to win a Flawless Victory.
So what do you think? Leave your comments
below.
And if you like this show, please support
us on Patreon.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell. See you
next time.