On this episode of China Uncensored,
how China is trying to dominate India.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
India and China have a lot in common.
They're the world’s two biggest countries;
with the world’s most ambitious economies;
And they both...
like Lady Gaga?
Uh, and of course,
they both love movies,
as we know from the world-famous Bollywood
and...Chollywood?
Ok, Chollywood is a terrible name.
But, everyone loves Bollywood,
even Chinese leader Xi Jinping.
In a recent meeting
with Indian Prime Minister Modi, Xi Jinping
told him he’s seen Dangal,
the recent Bollywood smash hit.
Dangal has become the 20th
highest grossing film
in Chinese box office history.
Another thing Xi Jinping loves—
yoga.
And not just because Premier Li Keqiang
looks great in yoga pants.
He’s been working on his downward slumdog.
No, it's because at the meeting with Modi,
Xi also made sure to remind him
of China’s recent Yoga day.
Because if there’s one thing
the Chinese Communist Party loves,
it’s people meditating.
Moving on.
But despite having so much in common,
India and China can at best be described
as frenemies.
And since both want to be top
slumdog in Asia,
that means trouble.
What’s that Shelley?
I should stop making Slumdog Millionaire puns
because it’s a British film?!
Next you’re going to tell me the James Bond
movies
are American.
What?
Co-productions?
Holding companies?
Wow, that's really complicated.
Anyway, back to the topic.
Here are 5 way China
is trying to dominate India.
Number 5:
The Friend of My Enemy
India and Pakistan don’t exactly get along.
They’ve had four wars since 1947.
But fortunately for Pakistan,
it has a friend in the Chinese Communist Party.
Pakistan was one of the CCP’s
earliest allies,
back when no one wanted
to be the CCP’s friend.
You know,
because of all the mass murder.
Starting in the 1970s,
the CCP helped Pakistan
build nuclear weapons—
by providing blueprints, t
echnical know-how,
and enriched uranium.
And today,
the CCP is working with Pakistan
to build the China-Pakistan Economic Corridor.
It’s a 62-billion-dollar plan
to flood Pakistan with Chinese investment—
everything from railways
to energy projects.
And for its part,
the CCP has used its influence in the UN
to shield a Pakistani
who India considers a terrorist.
Basically, Pakistan is India’s
biggest military threat.
And the CCP is taking full advantage.
Number 4:
Border Buddies
Aside from China and Pakistan,
India shares a land border
with four other countries:
Myanmar, Nepal, Bangladesh, and Bhutan.
And the Chinese regime is spending
billions of dollars to become friends
with those neighbors,
you know,
making them indebted to China,
often literally.
It’s part of China’s One Belt,
One Road Initiative.
That’s where the Chinese regime
drains developing nations of their resources
through large-scale infrastructure projects
and massive loans,
in exchange for making China
the economic center of the world.
It’s win-win.
The Chinese regime
gets money and power,
and the other countries get to become
tribute states.
At least they get high-speed trains.
This is Myanmar,
the country formerly and sometimes
still known as Burma,
which was confusing for everyone.
Until they complained about being
a slave to their record label
and said they would now be known
only by this symbol.
China has built the country
formerly known as Burma
a handy oil pipeline
that’s part of a 10-billion-dollar
Special Economic Zone.
China is using this to,
let’s say,
improve relations.
In Nepal,
China is the main financial backer
of “two special economic zones,
a pair of hydropower plants,
and an international airport.”
And that’s just part of the 8.3 billion
dollars
China has pledged to invest there.
India is also investing in Nepal,
but only less than one-twentieth as much.
Come on, India!
Don’t you know you catch more flies
with billions of dollars of investment?
Bangladesh is also getting wrapped up
in Xi Jinping’s One Belt.
And China’s belt is pretty high.
And as for Bhutan,
the tiny, traditional nation
that cares more about Gross National Happiness
than Gross National Product...
...well, they’re not super into
big infrastructure investments.
So China has sent “circus artists,
acrobats and footballers” to Bhutan.
Nice try, China,
but you’re not going to win Bhutan
with circus artists.
But the overall plan here
is for China to have more influence
on India’s neighbors
than India itself does.
Number 3:
Economic Corridors
India has boycotted China’s
One Belt One Road Initiative,
mainly because India thinks China
would use expensive infrastructure projects
to subjugate India and indebt it to China
forever.
But just because India is boycotting that
one initiative
doesn’t mean it doesn’t have
economic ties with China.
India is already part of the Bangladesh-China-
India-Myanmar—or BCIM—
Economic Corridor.
And earlier this month,
China’s National Development and Reform
Commission
and the State Oceanic Administration
announced the launch of the snappily named
China-Indian Ocean-Africa-Mediterranean
Sea Blue Economic Passage,
or…CIOAMSBEP.
It will connect the “Bangladesh-China-
India-Myanmar economic corridors,”...
...with the China-Pakistan Economic corridor.
Now you might be wondering:
Why would India go in for hooking up
with Pakistan like this?
Well, it seems when China announced the plan,
they didn’t bother asking New Delhi.
But with the promise of such economic fortune
dangling over the heads of so many
of India’s neighbors—
neighbors China has already been courting—
how long can India hold out
before it has to go with the flow?
Number 2:
Playing Both Sides
Of course many of India and China’s neighbors
see what’s happening
and try to play both sides.
Take Sri Lanka, for example,
an island nation just off the southern
coast of India.
For years, the Sri Lankan government
fought a bloody war against
the Tamil Tigers.
It sounds like a high school football team,
but no,
it was a dangerous group
of rebels/freedom fighters,
depending on who you ask.
A lot of the civilians
were raped and killed on both sides
during the 25-year war,
and the Sri Lankan government
has been accused of war crimes.
Suffice it to say,
Sri Lanka isn’t too popular
on the international scene—
especially right after the war ended
in 2009.
But the Chinese regime
swept in with 8 billion dollars in loans
to build infrastructure,
and a promise not to get all judgy
about those human rights atrocities.
But now, India also wants access
to Sri Lanka.
And it’s actively competing with China for
it.
India’s prime minister visited Sri Lanka
in May
and talked about their “strong relationship.”
But then a few days later,
Sri Lanka’s prime minister went to
the One Belt One Road Forum in Beijing,
where China offered up 24 billion dollars
to the country.
It's like Sri Lanka is pitting
its divorced parents against each other
in order to get better Christmas presents.
And finally…
Number 1:
Boots on the Ground
Earlier this week,
Chinese troops crossed
part of the border with India,
and destroyed two Indian army bunkers.
The bunkers were part of a plan by India
to establish 17 Mountain Strike Corps
along the Arunachal Pradesh,
a disputed territory that,
according to China and nobody else,
is called South Tibet.
The new corps would have
“two new high-altitude infantry divisions
as well as armoured, artillery,
air defence, engineer brigades...
fully formed with 90,274 soldiers.”
That will be useful considering that
basically every year,
Chinese troops try to
march across the border there,
as seen in this shaky video.
Wow, so their border
is basically just a low pile of rocks.
What they really need is a wall.
Or at least a large fence.
So what do you think of
China’s plan to surround India?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode
of China Uncensored.
Remember, this show is made possible
because of support from viewers like you.
Please, visit our Patreon website
and contribute, for example,
even a dollar per episode.
Don’t force us to become a part
of the One Belt One Road Initiative.
Once again, I’m your host, Chris Chappell,
see you next time.