On this episode of China Uncensored,
Hey Google.
I’ve got a search for you right here.
America is spending big to counter the Chinese
Communist Party
And finally, Chinese people are dying to...
choose what happens to them after they die.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Our top story—
an anonymous Google employee has leaked a
secret plan—
Google is creating a censored search engine
just for the Chinese market.
It will appeal to the sensibilities of a Chinese
audience.
And by that,
I mean it censors all the stuff the Chinese
Communist Party
doesn’t want them to know about,
like the Tiananmen Square Massacre.
I guess it’s a good thing Google already
removed
the “don’t be evil” bit from its code
of conduct.
We’ll have more on Google in a future episode.
In other news—and this is big, folks—
Democrats and Republicans have agreed on something:
spending money.
Congress just passed the National Defense
Authorization Act.
It’s the defense policy bill that determines
the annual budget for the Defense Department.
Let’s just say it’s a pretty big budget.
And it specifically targets the Chinese Communist
Party
on a range of issues, like:
military activity in the south China Sea,
theft of US technology,
and propaganda warfare.
It’s part of a larger trend.
US lawmakers have finally watched enough China
Uncensored
to figure out that the Chinese Communist Party
has been waging
unrestricted warfare against the United States.
And they’re actually willing to take action.
Of course speaking of US-China war,
I can’t help but think about the current
trade war.
President Trump had threatened a 10% tariff
on 200 billion dollars worth of Chinese goods.
The Chinese Communist Party was not happy.
So, Trump decided to double down and make
it a 25% tariff
on $200 billion dollars worth of Chinese goods.
The Chinese Communist Party...
is even not happier.
And they’ve vowed to retaliate.
While those tariffs are not in effect right
now,
and won’t be until after “a period of
public comment,”
the Chinese regime is already crying blackmail.
And they have a point.
I mean, Trump is basically threatening them
with high tariffs
unless they actually start following international
trade
and intellectual property rules.
Which is exactly the same as blackmail.
And you know, it’s not just that.
Trump is being unfair when it comes to Taiwan,
too.
The US has the audacity to allow the Tsai
Ing Wen,
President of the Republic of China,
also known as Taiwan,
also known as the country/region-Who-Shall-Not-Be-Named,
to stop over in the US on her way to Belize
and Paraguay next month.
I mean, can you believe it?
The Chinese Communist Party is, unsurprisingly,
demanding that the US stop the stopover.
Maybe they’re just concerned that she’ll
have
a bad impression of the US.
Especially if she has a four-hour layover
at LAX.
And finally, why is this Chinese parking lot
full of coffins?
Well, I mean, I get it.
I know what it’s like to be dying to get
a space.
Get it, because it’s a parking lot,
and...ok moving on.
But in this case, it’s part of a campaign
in southeast China
to ban coffin burials.
So Chinese authorities are rounding them up...
And destroying them...
Sometimes even during a funeral
I really don’t think that’s showing proper
respect to the dead.
Police are even digging up graves.
So Chinese police literally are grave robbers.
Wonderful.
And guys, I’ve seen a lot of movies.
I know how this ends.
Zombies.
But seriously, this is causing outrage in
China.
On September 1,
Jiangxi Province officials will implement
a zero burial policy.
That means people will have to be cremated.
A lot of Chinese people are not comfortable
with that.
But when has the Chinese Communist Party cared
about
the feelings of the Chinese people?
Mao Zedong called China’s burial traditions
a “feudal superstition.”
The same Mao Zedong who has this lovely glass
coffin
in the middle of Beijing.
Though technically,
it was never a burial.
To give you an idea
of how passionate Chinese people are about
this,
a few years ago, another Chinese province
tried to do this.
So, before the deadline for no more burials,
6 elderly people killed themselves
so they could be buried in the ground.
I mean, at least that’s commitment to tradition?
What do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And now, it’s that time when we answer questions
from fans
who support the show on the crowd funding
website Patreon.
Guus Schut ask, “Have the people in Xinjiang,
actualy posed a threat when it comes to terrorism?
Is there another side to the stories
or has the CCP made up this story?
Interesting question.
As many of the folks watching know,
Xinjiang is home to the Uighur ethnic minority,
which is mostly Muslim—
or at least come from a Turkic culture.
And despite all the love the Chinese Communist
Party gives,
just like those no good Tibetans,
there are those in Xinjiang
who want freedom and independence.
These people call Xinjiang, East Turkestan.
Which is why for years,
they were referred to as separatists or splitists.
That’s the same language used against Tibetans.
But following the terrorist attacks of September
11,
the Chinese regime had a brilliant idea.
Let’s start calling them terrorists!
And while that term had been leveled against
Uighurs before,
the party doubled down after 9/11.
As this Jamestown Foundation piece put it,
“There is no doubt that China has taken
advantage of
the world campaign against terror
in order to serve its domestic politics and
foreign pursuits.
For the first time,
China felt unconstrained in using force.”
And language is powerful.
When you call a bunch of Muslims terrorists,
it makes it a lot harder for them to get international
sympathy,
even if they’re being severely abused by
the Chinese regime.
Is there what we in the US would call
terrorism going on now in Xinjiang?
Well, the Party has not provided
much convincing evidence of terrorism.
Even so, it wouldn’t be too surprising.
They’ve been oppressed for decades.
They have no outlet to speak.
They’re being forced to abandon their religious
traditions.
It’s possible—just possible—
that the Communist Party’s actions
are actually creating the urge to be terrorists.
But also—and this is probably the majority
of cases—
people who are not criminals
are being charged with the terrorist label.
But really, with the lid the Chinese regime
keeps on things,
we may not ever know what’s really going
on in Xinjiang.
Thanks for you question, Guus.
And before you go,
I’d like to ask all of you:
If you can,
please support China Uncensored
by contributing a dollar or more per episode
on Patreon.
We rely on viewer support,
so every bit helps keep the show going.
And as a way of saying thanks,
you can send me your questions
that I’ll answer on the show.
Plus, there’s some other neat things you
get
when you sign up to support the show.
You’ll learn more about that
on the China Uncensored Patreon site.
Link is below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Hey, if you haven’t heard,
we have a new podcast,
China Unscripted.
Along with Shelley, and Matt the producer,
I go into way more detail than we ever could
on the show,
which means more jokes too.
So subscribe to us on iTunes.
Once again that’s China Unscripted.