China’s military is on the rise
Deadly new weapons could destroy Taiwan
And the US is helping China build them
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
You can help us continue to uncensor China by\h
joining what I call the China Uncensored 50\h\h
Cent Army. All it takes is as little as a dollar\h
per episode on the crowd funding website Patreon.\h\h
Check out all the cool perks you\h
get on Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
China has a secret weapon. One so devastating,\h
it could even make an invasion of Taiwan\h\h
possible. What is this secret weapon? American\h
greed. And stupidity. Don’t forget stupidity.
Ok, technically that’s two secret weapons.\h
China is building advanced weapons\h
systems using American technology.\h\h
And the Americans who are profiting\h
are looking the other way.
China is using American microchips\h
to build hypersonic weapons.\h\h
Hypersonic missiles can travel\h
more than five times the speed of\h\h
sound. Current missile defense systems\h
are next to useless against them.
With these weapons, China could target US Navy\h
ships or US bases in the Pacific. Or even Taiwan.\h\h
Which China has promised to invade.\h
Chinese hypersonic missiles launched\h\h
from the Chinese mainland could\h
reach Taiwan in just minutes.
It looks like China’s military tested\h
one of these hypersonic missiles\h\h
during a recent military drill.
These are not easy weapons to develop, though.\h
They require complex testing using supercomputers.\h\h
Supercomputers require semiconductors, basically\h
the brains of these computers. And semiconductors,\h\h
“are now China’s top import, valued\h
at more than $300 billion a year,\h\h
and a major priority in China’s latest\h
Five-Year Plan for national development.”
The US has long restricted companies from selling\h
sensitive technology to the Chinese military.
But what about selling US technology\h
*private* Chinese companies? That’s legal.
And that’s where Phytium Technology comes in.
It’s a private Chinese company,\h
founded in 2014 as a joint venture\h\h
of the state-owned conglomerate\h
China Electronic Corporation,\h\h
the National Supercomputing Center in\h
Tianjin, and the Tianjin municipal government.
That...doesn’t sound private to me.
But who owns Phytium now? Well, according to\h
public records, “Phytium’s ownership has changed\h\h
hands over the years, but its shareholders\h
often have links to the [Chinese military].”
That doesn’t sound private to me!
Currently, Phytium has partnered with the China\h
Aerodynamics Research and Development Center.\h\h
Together they’re doing research on hypersonic\h
missiles. Oh, by the way the China Aerodynamics\h\h
Research and Development Center,\h
“is run by a PLA major general”.
That doesn’t sound private to me!!!
In fact, the China Aerodynamics\h
Research and Development Center,\h\h
“has been on the U.S. trade\h
blacklist — called the “entity list”—\h\h
since 1999 for contributing to\h
‘the proliferation of missiles.’”\h
And in 2016, the US Commerce Department\h
put even more restrictions on it.
These connections are all in publicly available\h
documents. And yet, several American companies\h\h
work with Phytium, because it’s technically a\h
private Chinese company. And if you’re technically\h\h
*allowed* to sell them sensitive technology\h
and make money from it, what’s wrong with that?
According to Eric Lee of\h
the Project 2049 Institute,\h\h
“Phytium acts like an independent commercial\h
company. Its executives wear civilian clothes,\h\h
but they are mostly former military\h
officers from [a military university].”
That military university is the National\h
University of Defense Technology,\h\h
or NUDT. We’ve talked about it several times\h
on the show. Think of it like the MIT of the\h\h
People’s Liberation Army. We did a whole\h
episode about how Australian tax dollars\h\h
are funding these Chinese military\h
universities, even on nuclear weapons testing.
Thanks, Australia. No, seriously. It’s nice\h
to know it’s not just the US being stupid.\h\h
And greedy.\h
And if it makes you feel better,\h
even Taiwan is being stupid.
A lot of Taiwanese companies rely on the China\h
market. 35% of Taiwan’s trade is with China—a\h\h
country that has promised to invade them!\h
Talk about sleeping with the enemy.\h
Taiwan now makes some of the most advanced\h
semiconductors in the world. Especially the Taiwan\h\h
Semiconductor Manufacturing Company. They make\h
microprocessors for Phytium. Which is using that\h\h
technology to run tests on hypersonic missiles\h
that could be used against Taiwanese troops.
There are other Taiwanese\h
companies involved as well.\h\h
But whether it’s Taiwanese or American\h
companies, they all say the same thing—their\h\h
technology is not going to the Chinese\h
military because Phytium is a private company.\h
This is crazy! The Chinese Communist Party is even\h
open about what they call Military-Civil Fusion.\h\h
The State Department has\h
said it’s a way for the CCP\h\h
“to ensure that new innovations simultaneously\h
advance economic and military development.”
And the Military-Civil Fusion\h
program is personally overseen\h\h
by Chinese leader Xi Jinping. Who\h
is also the head of the military.
THAT DOESN’T SOUND LIKE IT’S PRIVATE TO ME!
In the final days of the Trump Administration,\h
Phytium and a few other Chinese companies were\h\h
going to be placed on an export black\h
list. But they ran out of time to do it.\h
But there’s good news! This past week, the\h
Biden administration officially added Phytium,\h\h
along with six other Chinese\h
companies, to that blacklist.
It’s nice to know that the Trump and\h
Biden administrations can agree on\h\h
not selling US technology to companies literally\h
making missiles to be used against the US.\h
Maybe there’s hope after all.\h
And now it’s time for me to respond to a\h
member of the China Uncensored 50 cent army,\h\h
fans who support the show on Patreon.
davidKansasCity says, “It's past time\h
for the Philippians to take ownership of\h\h
all the cool stuff China built for them on\h
the islands in the Philippians territory…”
Ahh, it would be something if the\h
Philippines managed to take all those\h\h
nice man-made islands the Chinese Communist\h
Party built. But that won’t be so easy to do.\h
For one, several of those islands have missile\h
launchers on them. And are heavily militarized,\h\h
despite the Chinese Communist Party’s\h
promise to...not militarize them.\h
Chinese leader Xi Jinping made that pledge during\h
a press conference with President Obama in 2015.
But hey, it depends on what your definition\h
of “militarized” is. Am I right?\h
At this point, the Philippines, along with\h
other countries like Vietnam, are having a\h\h
hard time just preventing China from taking\h
over more territory in the South China Sea.\h
You see, China sends out a fleet of *private*\h
fishing boats into disputed territorial waters.\h\h
Those *private* fishing\h
can number in the hundreds.
But these *private* fishing boats are actually\h
part of what the CCP calls the maritime militia.\h\h
Except when the Chinese embassy denies they exist.
And wherever China’s maritime militia\h
goes, the Chinese coast guard is close by.
During a recent surge, the Philippines counted,\h\h
“254 [Chinese] ships as well as four\h
Chinese warships that day in the Spratlys”.
So if another country were to fire on\h
the quote unquote civilian fishermen,\h\h
the Chinese Coast guard can rush\h
to their defense and be the hero.
In fact, China recently passed the Coast\h
Guard Law that allows for just that.
The law allows the Chinese Coast Guard to\h
“‘use all necessary measures including weapons’\h\h
when China’s ‘national sovereignty,\h
sovereign rights, and jurisdiction\h\h
are being illegally infringed by foreign\h
organizations and individuals at sea.’”
Think of it like Military Fishing Fusion.
There are other issues holding back the\h
Philippines and all the other countries\h\h
in territorial disputes with the Chinese\h
Communist Party. China plays a big role in\h\h
their economies. And the coronavirus has given\h
the CCP yet another weapon in their arsenal.\h
“Access to vaccines has become\h
a key concern for Duterte:\h\h
Metro Manila was locked down again last week\h
amid the nation’s worst coronavirus surge\h\h
and the Philippines currently sources\h
most of its supply from China’s Sinovac.”
But unless something is done to actually\h
stop the Chinese Communist Party,\h\h
they will keep steadily expanding their\h
reach until they control everything.\h
Thanks for your support, davidKansasCity.
You can also ask a question I might\h
answer on the show. If you’d like that,\h\h
go to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored and\h
contribute a dollar or more per episode.\h\h
Your support is a big part of how\h
we can afford to make this show.
Thank you for watching. Once again\h
I’m Chris Chappell. See you next time.