On this episode of China Uncensored,
what are the US presidential candidates saying
about...
"China"
"China, China, China"
"CHINA!!!"
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I'm your
host, Chris Chappell.
You know, as a patriotic American,
there's nothing I love more than watching
democratic process in action.
And by democratic process, I mean this.
But there's one thing it seems the presidential
candidates can all agree on:
The biggest problem America has,
the true threat that must be addressed, is
China.
"China is waging cyber warfare against America."
"They're also trying to hack into everything
that doesn't move in America."
"China is also a growing danger to our national
security."
"The trade agreement with China was an unmitigated
disaster for American workers."
"China thinks we are  truly the dumbest people on Earth."
Now far be it for me to criticize anyone for
criticizing China.
In fact, I think all of you know why I criticize
the Chinese regime.
But for the leading five candidates,
one of them will most likely be the US president
less than a year from now.
So just how would each of them deal with China?
For more, I'm joined by former political correspondent,
Matt Gnaizda.
Thanks, Chris.
Now Matt, you used to cover politics as a
news reporter.
I don't like to talk about that time in my
life, Chris.
I've seen things...that cannot be unseen.
I know what's under Donald Trump's hair.
Do I want to know?
Do you want to have nightmares for the next
10 years?
Ok, never mind then.
So these top five candidates
they've all been talking a lot about China,
but which of them have actual experience dealing
with China?
Two of them do.
Hillary Clinton has by far the most political
experience with China.
When she was first lady, she met a lot of
Chinese officials.
Then, as Secretary of State, Hillary Clinton
co-chaired the US-China Strategic and Economic
dialogue.
She also traveled to China twice during that
time.
Her second trip coincided with blind Chinese
activist Cheng Guangcheng's escape from house
arrest to the US embassy in 2012.
Those were exciting times.
And the other?
Donald Trump.
He has no real political experience,
but he's done lots of business with Chinese
clients.
He's had his products made there,
and he's sold properties to big-time Chinese
investors.
Does that...count as China experience?
He thinks it does.
"I love China. I sold an apartment for 55 million dollars to a Chinese gentleman.
Ok, let's get to the main issue.
All the candidates have talked about China
taking American jobs.
Would any of them actually do something about
it?
Look, Chris: convincing voters that you'll
fix the US economy is the best way to get elected.
That's kind of cynical.
That's kind of politics.
It's true that millions of US jobs
have disappeared over the last 15 years since
China joined the World Trade Organization,
with America's help.
Those particular jobs aren't coming back.
So I think that if elected,
all the candidates except one would support
continued free trade with China.
No matter what they say now as candidates.
You said all the candidates except one?
That's Bernie Sanders.
As a US Congressman, and later Senator,
he had actually opposed pretty much every
trade deal with China,
starting with Bill Clinton's original push
to get China into the WTO.
So maybe Sanders, as president,
would actually try to pull back.
The problem is, even if he wanted to,
it's unclear that he'd really have that power
since the president needs the support of Congress.
What about human rights?
Well, Chris, as you of all people know,
it's easy to criticize the Chinese government
for its for human rights abuses.
It's hard to actually do something about it.
Are we still talking about the candidates?
Oh, sure.
So Ted Cruz.
He's been outspoken against forced abortions
in China
mainly because he opposes abortion.
Hillary Clinton has been outspoken against
forced abortions in China
mainly because she supports a woman's right
to choose.
Marco Rubio has called for the release of
political prisoners,
and to block US visas for Chinese officials
who've violated human rights.
And Bernie Sanders has probably been the boldest.
While in the House of Representatives,
Sanders actually co-sponsored resolutions
about Chinese human rights
including HCR68, a resolution that specifically
condemned the persecution of Falun Gong.
What about Donald Trump?
Oh, Trump hasn't said anything about China's
human rights.
In a way, he kind of agrees with China.
What?
Well, China's position on human rights is...
to actually change the definition to include
allowing people to make money as a human right.
And Donald Trump supports making money.
So the Chinese leaders must like Donald Trump.
You'd think so, but actually no.
My favorite state-run media, Global Times,
recently published an editorial that was very
anti-Trump.
Chinese leaders think Trump lacks the nuance
and diplomacy to have a good relationship.
Like that Tweet where he said
"the concept of global warming was created
by and for the Chinese in order to make U.S.
manufacturing non-competitive."
Yeah, that's just...not a widely accepted
view.
So which candidate would serve America best
when it comes to China?
None of them.
None of them?
Let me put this in context, Chris.
Back in 1992, a young, passionate Bill Clinton
took a tough stance against China.
In his first presidential campaign,
he criticized George Bush Sr. for "coddling
dictators."
Or as Clinton called them,
the "butchers of Beijing" because of the Tiananmen
massacre.
"We need to be a force for freedom and democracy
and we need to use our unique position to
support freedom
whether it's in Haiti, or in China, or in
any other place."
But then, by the end of his second term,
Clinton just wanted to do business with China.
"I don't believe it's right to crack down
on people for their religious views,
or their political expression,
or because they want to be in an association
like the Falun Gong.
I don't think that's right.
But I don't believe that we will have more
influence by giving them the back of our hand."
I guess that explains why Clinton offered
the palm of his hand to Jiang Zemin,
the man who just authorized the mass murder
of the "Falun Gong."
Exactly. So Bill Clinton ended up coddling
his own dictators.
But you know, that's because Bill Clinton
was a Democrat.
And Democrats are known to be hypocrites.
So then presidential candidate George W. Bush
comes along.
And he has a tough stance against China.
In a 1999 interview on CNN,
he said that Clinton, quote "made a mistake
[in] calling China a strategic partner."
Bush argued that we need to view China as
a competitor, not a partner.
And then he went on to treat China as a "responsible
stakeholder" instead.
Well, at least when it came to Jiang Zemin,
the dictator who killed huge numbers of his
own citizens,
Bush maintained a dignified distance, right?
Yeah. But you know, that's because George
Bush was a Republican.
And Republicans are known to be hypocrites.
So you're saying...?
I'm saying don't rely on the next US president,
whoever he or she may be.
Because once you become president,
campaign rhetoric goes out the window.
Thanks, Matt. I guess.
The pleasure was all mine.
So what do you think the next US president
should do about China?
Leave your comments below.
And if you like China Uncensored,
please support us on Patreon.
Because after this episode,
I don't think we're going to get much funding
from the CIA.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell. See you next
time.