bjbj,(,( Chinese Admiral Discovers Weak Point
of US Military Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I m your host, Chris Chappell. The US military
pivot to the Asia Pacific region is undone.
Stability in the region will deteriorate and
North Korea will rain nuclear fire up on all.
And it s all because of the plucky wit of
one intrepid Chinese Admiral. The US is about
to deploy the new Zumwalt-class destroyer
in the Pacific, a three and a half billion
dollar, 15,000 ton vessel of death equipped
with the latest stealth technology and high
powered electromagnetic rail guns. But much
like Superman has his kryptonite, the Zumwalt
has a weakness its designers never could have
imagined. Chinese fisherman. That s right,
according to Admiral Zhang Zhaozhong, the
chief weapons specialist and strategist for
the Chinese navy, all he has to do is send
out fishing boats, wobbly in the water, inching
toward the Zumwalt, place the explosives onto
its hulls [and] blow many holes in the hull.
It will be finished then. The Zumwalt is no
good! But, but what about submarines?! I mean,
those are underwater! Looks like the US is
one step ahead of you Admiral Zhang. Not to
fast. Zhang has a plan for that too. You see,
seaweed is the one challenge the US never
imagined a submarine in the ocean would ever
encounter. The Yellow Sea is too shallow.
So as Zhang, again the chief weapons specialist
in China, says, they can lay out ropes of
seaweed that will get caught in the propellers.
Then they won t be able to move. I wonder
what he ll suggest to stop fighter jets. Admiral
Zhang has become known for his admirable,
but often wrong optimistic predictions. In
2003 he said the US would never attack Saddam
Hussein. The next day they did. He said Libyan
rebels would never find Moammar Gadhafi s
hiding place, just a few hours before they
found and killed him. When North Korea was
preparing to launch a rocket last year, he
said they had an 80% chance of success. It
exploded moments after launch. Man, I m glad
I don t live in a country that makes ridiculous
military predictions that are instantly disproven.
gd@b [Content_Types].xml #!MB ;c=1 _rels/.rels
theme/theme/themeManager.xml sQ\}# theme/theme/theme1.xml
G$$DA : BR \{i5@R V*[_X ,l\Y Ssd+r] 5\|E Vky-
V4Ej 6NGU s?^V * 7;wP EBU` 5<V8
LStf+] C9P^ wB>VD GGHPXNT, /M,W m2iU [[v _Xtl
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.rels 6?$Q
K(M&$R(.1 [Content_Types].xmlPK _rels/.relsPK
theme/theme/themeManager.xmlPK theme/theme/theme1.xmlPK
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.relsPK
<a:clrMap xmlns:a="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/main"
bg1="lt1" tx1="dk1" bg2="lt2" tx2="dk2" accent1="accent1"
accent2="accent2" accent3="accent3" accent4="accent4"
accent5="accent5" accent6="accent6" hlink="hlink"
folHlink="folHlink"/> Chris Normal.dotm Chris
Microsoft Macintosh Word PICT kZg9c o\{JRc
@g9Ns\{ o\{g9^ g9g9kZo\{c kZg9Z g9kZg9c g9o\{s
g9kZg9c kZg9o\{kZo\{s g9o\{s kZo\{s kZo\{kZg9kZs
o\{g9g9o\{w o\{o\{s o\{o\{c o\{o\{g9kZs g9kZs g9kZo\{kZw
g9o\{o\{s g9kZw kZg9o\{g9g9o\{s o\{!c g9kZo\{o\{w
g9g9s kZo\{g9g9o\{o\{s kZo\{g9kZg9o\{g9kZs o\{o\{c
g9o\{^ o\{kZkZZ g9g9 g9kZkZZ g9o\{g9g9o\{^ kZg9kZg9g9^
o\{o\{^ g9kZs kZg9o\{g9kZc g9o\{Z g9g9Z kZkZZ
kZg9 o\{!w o\{kZo\{s kZo\{o\
g9g9o\{ o\{kZ g9$s o\{g9c g9o\{^ g9g9c o\{g9Z g9kZg9s
AkZV g9g9Z o\{kZV g9o\{V g9g9Z kZkZ\{ kZo\
kZg9kZR g9o\{Z g9g9Z g9g9Z g9kZ^ kZg9o\{c g9g9c
kZkZs g9kZkZ\{ kZo\{o\{kZo\{g9kZ kZg9s g9g9c o\{kZo\{w
g9g9o\{kZo\{kZo\{o\{g9c o\{kZo\{ g9o\{kZg9o\{o\{c kZg9s
o\{o\{w g9kZo\{w kZg9\{ g9o\{^ g9kZo\{g9s g9o\{g9s
g9g9kZkZs kZo\{o\{g9kZV kZkZs g9kZV o\{kZg9s
g9g9kZg9kZs kZkZg9w kZkZ kZg9c g9g9V g9o\{g9
g9kZo\{s g9o\{g9w o\{o\{g9o\{s g9o\{c o\{kZg9o\{c
g9kZg9\{ kZg9kZc o\{kZc g9g9o\{o\{c kZkZZ g9kZ^
g9o\{ >kZc kZg9Z kZNsZ kZg9V g9kZR g9o\{s o\{g9s
kZkZs o\{o\{kZ kZo\{w kZo\{w o\{kZs o\{kZkZ kZkZg9c
g9o\{c Nsg9kZs kZg9Z o\{g9 @g9V kZg9V kZkZo\{s
o\{o\{s o\{o\{w g9kZ Bo\{Z kZg9^ g9o\{Z kZg9^ g9kZc
kZkZ^ g9Nso\{V NskZV g9g9^ g9o\{V g9g9kZg9c
kZg9c o\{o\{s o\{g9o\{s o\{o\{s g9o\{o\{ o\{kZc kZg9g9c
g9kZc o\{g9c g9kZc o\{g9o\{ kZg9 o\{g9c o\{o\{g9V
g9kZ kZ1c g9kZkZZ kZg9o\{g9w g9kZkZg9c g9kZ^
kZg9o\{g9g9^ g9g9Z g9kZg9kZc kZg9g9s kZkZg9o\
o\{o\{s o\{o\{kZkZo\{s o\{o\{s o\{o\{s o\{o\{w o\{kZs
o\{kZg9\{ g9o\{g9s kZg9c g9g9kZg9c Title Microsoft
Word 97-2004 Document NB6W Word.Document.8