Chris Chappell has a Masters
from New York University,
and then moved into journalism focusing on
China,
and in the last six years
has produced China Uncensored--
a television program that appears on cable
TV
and online in the United States.
And so the topic for tonight's talk
is "China's Growing Influence on the West
and Its Politics."
Chris Chappell, you're very welcome.
Thank you.
Hi, welcome to the Sydney Institute,
I'm your speaker Chris Chappell.
Thank you.
For the last six years,
I've hosted an American TV show
called China Uncensored.
We use humor to talk about
what's happening in China,
and how that affects the world.
In that time we've talked about
enough China topics
to fill 1,000 episodes.
But since I only have half an hour tonight,
I've decided to cut it down
to just the terrifying highlights.
China's influence in the West is growing.
And the Chinese Communist Party,
which rules China with an iron fist,
is using Australia and New Zealand
to test out tactics they plan to use
around the world to influence politics,
and undermine democratic societies.
The New York Times says, quote,
"China has long treated Australia
as a laboratory for soft power experiments."
That's right:
China chose *you* to experiment on.
Congratulations.
And that's why I've made
the trip here from New York.
But what does all this mean?
Well, tonight I'm going to give you a little
insight
into the Chinese Communist Party,
and I'll talk about how they wage what they
call
"unrestricted warfare" against Western countries,
including Australia.
All countries want influence.
But the Chinese Communist Party is different.
Both in methods and goals.
If we hope to understand this,
we need to understand
the nature of the Chinese Communist Party.
Because it operates in a fundamentally different
way
than any other government in the world.
Historically, China was an incredibly powerful,
influential country.
Not just in Asia.
E
ven as far away as Ancient Rome.
Roman statesman Pliny the Elder,
in his book Natural History,
complained about the trade deficit
Rome had with China
because the Romans had an insatiable appetite
for Chinese silk.
So for 2000 years,
the West has been complaining about
the trade deficit with China--
from Pliny the Elder
to President Donald Trump.
It wasn't just trade.
People have always been inspired
by Chinese culture.
All you have to do is take a look at
European attempts to imitate Chinese art
in the 17th and 18th centuries.
Yeah, back in the day it was the West
making cheap knockoffs of Chinese products.
People would look at a vase and say,
"Made in France, ugh".
Of course in the modern era,
China's prestigious position in the world
changed--
after centuries of warfare,
economic turmoil,
and colonialism.
And then in 1949 the Communist Party
"liberated" China.
It liberated people from their land,
their wealth,
and in many cases their lives.
Mao Zedong launched a systematic campaign
to annihilate traditional Chinese culture
and replace it with the culture
of the Communist Party--
a culture of struggle.
Under Mao Zedong,
violent struggle became the cornerstone
of Chinese society.
Children against parents,
wives against husbands,
students against teachers,
and of course,
Communism against the free world.
It's been a long time since Mao.
And on the surface,
it seems like China has changed.
There are no more Red Guards.
In Shanghai,
you can pay for your Big Mac on your iPhone
on the way to the next Avengers movie.
But behind it all,
the Communist Party is still there.
And it controls the government,
the courts,
and even businesses.
And unlike other bad parties,
this one--you can't leave.
And if you try,
things can get pretty unpleasant, pretty fast.
The Chinese Communist Party
has not fundamentally changed.
It's still an authoritarian state
that attempts to control
every aspect of society--
including the economy.
It maintains its philosophy of struggle.
And its war against the free world
has never ended.
That's not me saying that.
That is top Chinese military leaders
openly saying that.
In 1999,
two colonels from the People's Liberation
Army,
or PLA, coined the term "unrestricted warfare."
In fact, they wrote a book
called Unrestricted Warfare.
It describes how a country like China
could rival the West.
They said "The first rule of unrestricted
warfare
is that there are no rules,
with nothing forbidden."
Like after hours at a bar in Kings Cross.
Unrestricted warfare is a war
without a single shot fired.
The PLA book says that
"the struggle for victory
will take place on a battlefield
beyond the battlefield."
But the goal is the same as any war.
'
The Chinese Communist Party wants to become
the world's primary superpower
and primary influence on other nations.
I hope you like Chinese food.
But seriously,
for a regime that's secretive about everything--
from pollution levels,
to state executions,
to even basic economic data--
they've been surprisingly transparent
about their goal to become a superpower.
Chinese leader Xi Jinping
has openly spoken about it.
Again, all countries want influence,
but remember, the Chinese Communist Party
is not a normal government.
The Australian Security Intelligence Organisation--
ASIO--recently revealed they consider
the Chinese Communist Party an extreme threat,
and the level of espionage
and foreign interference in Australia
is worse now than at the height of the Cold
War.
Which, if you have forgotten,
was not a pleasant time.
The Chinese Communist Party's unrestricted
warfare
has several components.
Today I'm going to focus on how
unrestricted warfare uses propaganda
and censorship, economic interests,
and political and academic infiltration.
Let's start with propaganda.
As you may know,
the Chinese Communist Party is engaged
in a global propaganda campaign.
One goal is to promote
a positive view of China
and it's happy-go-lucky authoritarian regime.
If that doesn't work,
then their goal is censorship--
to marginalize and suppress critical voices.
Like mine.
And maybe yours.
The Chinese regime spends
10 billion dollars a year
on overseas propaganda.
That includes things like:
all-expenses paid,
red carpet trips to China
for Australian politicians and journalists.
I'm going to guess those tours
don't include labor camps.
Their propaganda budget also goes to
paying Western media companies,
like the New York Times and Fairfax,
to put articles from Chinese state-run media
in their own newspapers and on their websites.
Which apparently is legal.
The Party also buys up Chinese-language media
in Australia and around the world.
They want to make sure they report correctly
on the Party's benevolent rule.
But propaganda doesn't end with the media.
A key part of the Communist Party's influence
operations
is the United Front Work Department.
Remember that name,
because we'll be coming back to it.
The United Front is a top level branch
of the Communist Party.
Chinese leader Xi Jinping has called it
the Communist Party's magic weapon.
He's a big Lord of the Rings fan.
How magical is this weapon?
Here's one example.
There's a group linked to the United Front
called the China-United States Exchange Foundation.
They spent hundreds of thousands of dollars
last year
lobbying Congress about US-China relations.
According to Foreign Policy magazine,
the group also cooperates on projects
with influential US think tanks,
like the Brookings Institution
and the Carnegie Endowment for International
Peace.
These think tanks can have a big impact
on US policy making.
And a group linked to the Chinese Communist
Party
is working with them to shape how the West
views the Chinese Communist Party.
But if the all-expenses paid trips,
state-run articles,
and pro-Communist Party policy papers don't
work,
then there's the other side
of the propaganda coin--
censorship.
And in the West,
the Chinese Communist Party relies on
applying just enough pressure
to encourage self-censorship.
The Chinese Communist Party
has a list of topics they don't want discussed.
Among the most sensitive are Tibet,
Taiwan independence,
and the Falun Gong spiritual group.
So what happens if you touch China
in these sensitive zones?
Overseas Chinese journalists have had
their families back in China threatened.
Scholars have been denied research visas.
Western journalists have been kicked out of
China.
It doesn't always happen.
But it happens just enough to make people
hesitate to cover these topics.
I'm sure many of you have heard of
the book Silent Invasion,
by Professor Clive Hamilton.
It discusses in detail
the ways the Chinese Communist Party
has been infiltrating Australia.
But Hamilton's original publisher,
Allen & Unwin,
scrapped the book.
Censoring a book about Chinese censorship
was not the best idea.
Hamilton's book was eventually released
earlier this month by another publisher,
Hardie Grant --
showing that self-censorship
has its limits.
Besides propaganda,
the Communist Party's unrestricted warfare
is also carried out through exploiting
Western economic interests.
The United Front also plays a role here.
In January,
Clive Hamilton and researcher Alex Joske
wrote about the United Front Work Department's
influence in Australia.
They said "Many leading figures
in the Australian business community
now serve as megaphones
for Beijing's messaging
to the Australian government
and the wider public."
And that the business community
also fears "the risks of retaliation
when statements are made
that Beijing does not like."
Statements like "Taiwan is a country."
Or, "Pandas are fat."
One of the biggest problems
for companies entering China
is corporate espionage.
For years, Western companies
have been eager to get into the Chinese market.
What they don't realize is that
the Communist Party has a strategy:
Why innovate, when you can just steal
other people's ideas?
This is not something the Party
tries to hide.
Intellectual property theft
is literally written into
their national economic plan.
In 2007, they released a document
called the National Technology Transfer Promotion
Plan.
They might as well call it,
"How to Steal and Not Get Caught."
Here's how it works.
Chinese military hackers
steal a company's intellectual property--
and give it to a Technology Transfer Center.
They reverse engineer the technology,
and give it Chinese businesses.
Then those businesses make cheaper knockoffs
of those Western products.
That's what happened to the Australian company
Codan.
One of their major products is metal detectors.
ASIO discovered that a Codan employee's laptop
was hacked during a business trip in China.
Blueprints for the company's metal detectors
were stolen,
and cheap Chinese knockoffs
flooded the market--
still carrying the Codan logo.
But the Codan CEO
said the Australian government
was unwilling to help since,
at the time,
a free trade agreement with China
was on the line.
The company had to cut its prices in half.
In one year,
their net profits fell from 45 million dollars
to 9 million.
Apparently the free trade agreement is:
China takes your stuff, for free.
But don't worry.
Last year,
Australia and China reached a deal:
no more cyber intellectual property theft.
And while they were shaking hands on it,
China stole Australia's watch.
How much do companies lose?
Trillions.
According to information security
company BLACKOPS Partners,
"U.S. companies and the U.S. economy
lose approximately $5 trillion each year,
or over 30 percent of the U.S. GDP ,"
to Chinese intellectual property theft.
In addition to corporate espionage,
the Party uses infrastructure investments.
Like the One Belt, One Road Initiative.
On the surface,
it's about building massive infrastructure
projects
around the world
with the goal of facilitating global trade.
Last year,
Chinese leader Xi Jinping
pledged to spend 124 billion dollars
on the plan.
In the West,
the Communist Party uses One Belt, One Road
for both economic gain and political leverage.
Take the case of Greece.
Chinese state investment in Greek infrastructure
has skyrocketed over the past several years--
power grids, major ports, telecommunications.
Actually, in similar areas as Australia.
Two years ago,
after a controversial court ruling
on the South China Sea,
Greece-- coincidentally--sided
with the Chinese Communist Party.
They were one of only two EU countries
to do so.
Well, two countries plus Sam Dastyari.
We'll get to him in a moment.
Last June,
in another move that totally
had nothing to do with
the Chinese Communist Party's investments,
Greece stopped the EU from condemning
human rights abuses in China.
The Party's investments in Greece
and other European countries
have worried the EU--
enough that they now want to screen
Chinese investments that threaten
national security.
Things like, investing in power grids,
major ports, and telecommunications.
Using infrastructure investments
and corporate espionage,
the Chinese Communist Party's unrestricted
warfare
turns the West's economic interests
against itself.
Gaining political influence
is another important tactic
in China's Unrestricted Warfare.
As I've heard repeatedly since coming here,
Australia has the best politicians money can
buy.
ASIO has warned that "foreign interference...
on an unprecedented scale...
has the potential to cause serious harm
to [Australia's] sovereignty."
Since 2015,
ASIO has warned Australian politicians
to be wary of taking money
from Chinese donors with questionable links
to the Chinese Communist Party.
Thanks to some brilliant journalism
from Fairfax Media,
Four Corners, and others,
we know the Chinese Communist Party
has been very successfully
buying influence in Australia.
I also learned there are no laws
against foreign campaign contributions here.
Seriously?
Who thought that was a good idea?
I mean, besides the politicians.
Here's an example.
Chinese billionaire Huang Xiangmo
is linked to the United Front.
The Fairfax and Four Corners report
found that over 4 years,
he donated 2.7 million dollars
to Australia's three biggest political parties.
And he's had some pretty unusual dealings
with specific politicians.
Like the Labor Party's Eric Roozendaal.
He resigned in 2013,
but took an executive job
at a property development company
owned by Huang.
What happened to Roozendaal's
vacant council seat?
Why, just three weeks later,
it was nabbed up by a friend of Huang's.
Of course, Huang Xiangmo's
most well known associate
is Sam Dastyari--
known by some as "Shanghai Sam".
Huang gave Dastyari thousands
in campaign contributions.
Dastyari also got almost a million dollars
for the Labor Party from Huang.
Now we can't say for sure
what Dastyari's motives were,
but after that,
Dastyari did some rather questionable things.
Like pressuring the Labor
foreign affairs spokeswoman
to not meet with a pro-democracy activist
that Beijing doesn't like.
And in a 2016 press conference
to Chinese media,
Dastyari contradicted his own party's
stance on the South China Sea ruling,
siding with the Chinese Communist Party instead.
Oh, and when Dastyari found out
Huang was being spied on
by Australian security agencies,
he personally went to Huang's mansion
and warned him his phone was being tapped.
Now that's real friendship.
There are many other examples
I could give of Australian politicians
being bought off by the Chinese Communist
Party,
but I think you get the point.
The book Unrestricted Warfare says,
"social spaces such as the military,
politics, economics, culture,
and the psyche are also battlefields."
And the Communist Party effectively uses
the social spaces of Western universities.
ASIO has warned the Australian government
that it needs to be "very conscious" of
foreign interference in Australian universities.
And much of this interference
comes again from the United Front,
which calls "overseas students
a focus of United Front work."
One example is the Chinese Students
and Scholars Association,
or CSSA.
Most universities with large numbers
of Chinese students have CSSAs.
They're typically linked with
the Chinese Embassy.
And their job is to make sure
Chinese students toe the Party line
and to intimidate students who don't.
Chinese students have found things
they said in class in Australia
were reported back to the Chinese police
by other Chinese students.
Which is why all of their term papers
were titled, "Don't free Tibet."
The former head of the United Front,
Liu Yandong,
created the Confucius Institute.
For free, they'll set up classrooms
to teach Chinese language
and culture in universities.
Since 2004,
500 Confucius Institutes have been set up
in 140 countries.
There are 14 Confucius Institutes
here in Australia.
The Communist Party's former Propaganda Chief
called the Confucius Institute,
"an important part of China's
overseas propaganda set-up."
So what exactly do they teach?
Well, let's just say a little less
Tiananmen Square Massacre,
and a little more
China's rapid economic development!
But more and more universities
have been waking up to the nature
of the Confucius Institute.
Some universities have kicked them out.
And currently,
the FBI is investigating them.
In Australia,
the Chinese Communist Party's influence in
universities
has also become a national security issue.
The Australian Research Council,
using taxpayer money,
has given millions of dollars in grants
to Chinese professors working in Australia.
The problem is,
in some cases,
those professors are doing research
with the Chinese military,
on advanced military technology
that could one day be used against the West.
ARC has also given grants
to universities for projects
that involved China's leading
military aircraft manufacturer,
and the telecommunications company Huawei,
which also has ties to the Chinese military.
And I thought allowing foreign campaign contributions
was a bad idea.
Is this a problem?
Not according to UNSW's
pro vice chancellor
Laurie Pearcey.
He also happens to be the head of
the school's Confucius Institute.
He wrote a recent editorial called
"Let's not isolate ourselves
from the benefits of China."
In it, he confidently states that
"Beijing respects the quality
and independence of [Australian] institutions."
Yes, Beijing respectfully undermines
Australian institutions.
The Chinese Communist Party's unrestricted
warfare
has had a major impact on the West.
The Party uses propaganda
to promote a glittering ideal of its rule,
and censorship to silence opposition to it.
It steals intellectual property
from Western companies
while using investment to get
Western countries on its side.
The Party buys political influence
wherever it can,
however it can.
It uses CSSAs and Confucius Institutes
to stifle academic freedom at Western universities
while taking advantage of research done there.
Thus far,
the West has been unprepared to counter
the Chinese Communist Party's unrestricted
warfare.
So, what can be done?
Nothing.
Thanks for coming folks.
Okay...there are a few things we could do.
First, we need to understand
the nature of the Chinese Communist Party.
It's an authoritarian system
that uses "struggle" to preserve
and strengthen its own rule.
This will not change,
no matter who's in charge,
no matter what reforms are promised,
no matter how open the economy appears to
be.
For those of us living in liberal democracies,
it can be hard to understand the lengths
the Communist Party will go to.
We're not used to dealing with
a government like this.
As historian Frank Dikotter said
in Silent Invasion,
it's like a Boy Scout dealing with Don Corleone.
So I recommend we all re-watch The Godfather.
Not that it will help us with the Party.
It's just a good movie.
Second, we need to expose the actions
of the Chinese Communist Party.
One of the biggest reasons the Party
has been able to carry out
this unrestricted warfare
is that people have remained silent,
through intimidation or self-interest.
That's one reason why
what's happening in Australia
now is so vitally important.
As I said earlier,
Australia is one of the proving grounds
for the Communist Party's tactics.
But now, those tactics are being exposed.
And people are openly talking about
how to respond.
The Communist Party is going to fight back.
After the Fairfax/Four Corners investigation,
the Chinese Embassy called it
"filled with Cold War mentality"
and "typical anti-China hysteria and paranoia."
The Party and those it has influenced
will continue to cry racism
and cold war mentality
to every legitimate concern.
That's why we need to be very clear
that these are the Chinese Communist Party's
infiltration operations.
It's not about racism against
ordinary Chinese Australians.
They're the ones who are
the first targets of the Party.
The Party wants us to believe that
they represent all Chinese people.
If you're against the Party,
you're against the Chinese people.
But don't fall for it
when people play the racism card.
We need to clearly distinguish
between the Party and Chinese people.
This way, we both avoid racist undertones,
and demolish a key part of the Communist Party's
propaganda.
Third, we need to stand up
to the Chinese Communist Party.
Like most bullies,
they tend to back down when confronted.
The foreign interference laws
being debated in Parliament
are a good start.
Australia could also lessen their
economic reliance on the Chinese Communist
Party
by strengthening ties with other countries.
Australia, the U.S.,
India, and Japan
are in talks now to establish
an alternative to China's One Belt One Road
Initiative.
Australia is not alone.
The US, the EU,
and other Western countries
are also beginning to wake up
to the Chinese Communist Party's unrestricted
warfare.
Yes, Australia is on the front lines.
But if these tactics can be defeated here,
it will send a message to the Communist Party:
the West is not for sale.
Thank you for your time.
I'll now take questions.