On this episode of China Uncensoredm
get your Vault-Tec Vaults today
and prepare for nuclear fallout!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I'm your host Chris Chappell.
You know, when I hear that confrontations
in disputed territorial waters
could potentially spark a world war,
I think, hey,
we should put a nuclear power plant there.
Now I know, potential war zones,
or water,
is not the place you would normally think
is the ideal location for a nuclear power
plant.
But China begs to differ.
In their 13th Five Year Plan—
that's what the Communist Party's calls a
series of social and economic initiatives—
they rolled out this: the ACPR50S.
A floating nuclear reactor platform.
According to state-run People's Daily, the
reactor
"can ensure steady supply of electricity for
oil and gas exploitation,
and for islands development."
You know, islands development.
Like the artificial islands they're "developing"
in the South China Sea.
Now technically, this won't be the world's
first floating nuclear reactor.
That title would go to the United States'
fleet
of over a hundred nuclear powered vessels,
like submarines.
The difference is, China's will be used as
a nuclear generator,
not just for propulsion of the ship it's installed
in.
And to be fair, the US's nuclear fleet has
proven to be safe.
Slapping a made-in-China sticker on it though,
might be a different matter.
Construction will be in the hands of the state-owned
China General Nuclear Power Corp.
They aim to complete it by 2020.
Russia is expected to complete their own even
sooner, by 2017.
But China has even bigger nuclear ambitions.
China already has 30 nuclear power plants,
with 24 under construction.
By 2050, China hopes to increase its nuclear
energy generated by 100 fold.
China's nuclear push is probably not meant
to compete with its rival Japan
in the number of radioactive monsters...
But it's more an attempt to make China not
look like this.
Because everyone knows, if you want to protect
the environment,
nuclear energy is the clear winner.
What do you think of China's plan to build
a floating nuclear reactor?
And how do you feel about radioactive monsters?
Leave your comments below.
And please help support the creation of this
show on Patreon.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell, see you next time.