On this episode of China Uncensored,
China takes aim at guns.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
And this is 18 year old Liu Dawei.
He will be spending the rest of his life in
a Chinese prison.
Why?
Because the judge let him off easy for being
a teenager.
Even though he wanted to give Liu the death
penalty.
Wow, so what heinous crime did this young
man commit?
Terrorism?
Multiple homicides?
Dressing up like a giant purple dinosaur
and making up his own theme song to the tune
of a beloved patriotic classic?
Nope.
He ordered fake guns online.
Not real guns, replicas.
24 to be exact.
From a Taiwanese store.
But that shipment never arrived
because it was intercepted by authorities.
According to state-run People’s Daily,
police “identified 20 out of the 24 ‘replica
guns’ as real guns.”
And so this 18 year old kid was sentenced
to life in prison for arms trafficking.
And get this:
Those 20 real guns aren’t actually...real
guns.
It’s just that China has such crazy strict
gun laws,
that they include things no other country
would consider to be guns.
That was actually the defense Liu’s lawyer
used in court.
According to China’s gun laws,
anything with a barrel that can shoot an object
with a force of 1.8 joules per centimeter
squared is a gun.
That’s less than one-tenth of what is classified
as a gun
in that bastion of anarchy,
Taiwan.
Liu’s lawyer argued that’s pretty much
the same amount of force
he could produce throwing a “handful of
beans.”
After which he was promptly arrested for having...hand-guns.
“Please clap.”
Ok, that last part was a joke.
But it is true that in China,
an object that could shoot a projectile
with as much force as throwing a handful of
beans
is considered in the same league as a Magnum.
“Being that this is a .44 magnum,
the most powerful handgun in the world,
and will blow your head clean off,
you gotta ask yourself a question.
Do I feel lucky?”
Liu most definitely was not lucky.
And his plea to the judge to
“Shoot me dead with the guns I bought!
If I die, I'll admit I'm guilty,"
probably missed the mark.
Now, Liu was arrested in 2014.
His family has appealed the ruling,
and are awaiting a final verdict.
Their appeal was accepted for review by a
higher court earlier this month.
As I said, China has some of the toughest
gun control laws in the world.
Private gun ownership is banned.
And that includes rifles, pistols, and even
gun replicas.
Simply possessing a single gun can get you
a three-year prison sentence.
An actual gun crime typically means execution.
Of course, rule of law is a mercurial thing
in Communist China.
Liu got a life sentence for buying replica
guns.
But this guy only got 12 years for running
an entire online gun store.
Mao Zedong famously said “political power
grows out of the barrel of a gun.”
And so once they got political power,
the Chinese Communist Party made sure to take
those guns
out of the hands of the people.
But there’s one thing Mao couldn’t have
predicted:
a lot of Chinese people think guns are really
cool.
At least that’s if you go by the increasing
gun tourism industry
targeting Chinese travelers.
Umm, no pun intended.
For a change.
Chinese tourists flock to the United States
for a chance to shoot a live weapon at a gun
range.
Although according to state-run China Daily,
“some people have complained that Chinese
tourists at gun clubs
have not been careful,
taking pictures and pointing the guns at other
people.”
Well that's not very polite.
And although it’s super illegal to own a
gun in China,
it actually seems to be pretty easy to buy
one,
if you want to take that risk.
You can go to the dark web
and get guns shipped from overseas in pieces,
like this reporter found.
Or just Google it,
like this reporter did.
So how will the Communist Party handle the
increasing fascination with guns?
And what do you think of Liu Danwei’s sentence?
I know they smuggle bear paws into China as
medicine,
but should they have the right to bear arms?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.