On this episode of China Uncensored, How the
cure for malaria almost wasn't.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I'm your
host Chris Chappell. So what do you think
of when you hear 'secret communist plot?'
My guess is it's probably not
'Nobel Prize winning cure for malaria.'
In fact maybe you didn't even know there was
a cure for malaria. Every year, the US invests
millions of dollars into providing a life
saving malaria drug called Artemisinin. The
thing is, despite the drug being discovered
in the 70s, the World Health Organization
didn't endorse it until 2000, and it wasn't
until 2006 that it became widely available.
So how is it possible that a cure for a disease
that killed nearly a million people a year
existed for 30 years but was never used?
Partly because most malaria victims are poor
children in Africa.
And partly because the cure was discovered
in communist China.
It began as a secret project started by Mao
Zedong in 1967—one that just earned the
formerly unheralded Chinese scientist Dr.
Tu Youyou the Nobel Peace Prize for her contribution.
It was the Vietnam War! War, huh, good God,
y'all, what is it good for?
Finding a cure for malaria, apparently.
Communist forces in North Vietnam who were
fighting the Americans were dying of malaria.
So they asked Mao Zedong to help them find
a cure. No problem! I mean, except for the
fact that in China, Cultural Revolution was
raging out of control, the education system
was shut down, and Western trained scientists
were being persecuted and sometimes killed.
But Mao still managed to wrangle up 500 scientists
to work on the malaria cure. It was called
Project 523. And fortunately, he didn't interfere
when some of the scientists looked to traditional
Chinese medicine for answers.
Dr. Tu discovered a two thousand year old
recipe for treating malaria involving an herb
called sweet wormwood. She refined that traditional
recipe into a usable drug, and then adopted
the Western method of doing clinical trials.
For human experiments, she tested it on herself
first to see if it was safe. Patients with
malaria were cleared of the disease in about
a day with no major side effects.
Meanwhile, the anti-malaria drug being developed
in the West was less effective. Because in
addition to treating malaria, it also caused
nightmares, paranoia, and may have driven
several Special Forces to go soldiers insane,
making them kill their wives.
So why didn't this traditional Chinese cure
become available? Maybe it was the fact that
Mao died and China spent decades in political
turmoil. Maybe it was that patent laws didn't
exist under communism and no big drug companies
could make money off it. Or maybe it was because
Dr. Tu was never elected to the prestigious
Chinese Academy of Sciences—because most
of those positions were filled by phony scientists,
many of whom held high government titles.
Whatever the reason, an effective cure for
malaria languished for decades...as, according
to UNICEF, malaria killed one child ever 30
seconds. Not in time to help North Vietnam,
obviously.
And even though the drug became widely available
in 2006, it wasn't until 2011 that Dr. Tu
got the first recognition for her role in
its discovery, when she won the Lasker prize
for medical research. And in October this
year, she won the Nobel Prize.
Wait a minute! I think, I'm learning…some
kind of lesson here. That maybe when the East
and West work together in harmony, instead
of attacking each other, it's like…things
can be…good? Or something. No, I lost it.
But maybe you didn't! Did you learn a lesson?
If so, leave it in the comment section below.
And if you aren't, subscribe for more China
Uncensored. Once again I'm Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Speaking of strange things that happen under
communism, the Soviet Union once built the
most powerful nuclear bomb ever...and now
Russia is putting it on display.
Check it out on Seeker Daily.
Now everyone knows that “Made in China”
and “quality” go hand in hand. The same
way that “one more drink” and “good
decisions do.”