On this episode of China Uncensored,
China’s toilet revolution gets flushed.
Hi, welcome to
China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Chinese leader Xi Jinping
has been talking about a revolution...
a toilet revolution.
What a potty mouth.
Let’s just say,
toilets in China are not always in good shape,
like this one at a hotel my producer Matt
stayed at in Yunnan Province.
It lacks important features,
such as...a door.
Well, fear not, bathroom-goers!
Because Xi Jinping has a plan!
He wants to improve toilets across the country.
70,000 toilets have been built so far,
and 64,000 more are on their way.
You see, Xi Jinping is worried that
bad toilets can affect tourism.
So the obvious solution is a top-down mandate
that absolutely won’t be taken to ridiculous
extremes
by overzealous local officials.
Oops, spoke too soon.
Because “In an apparent bid to gain favour
with Beijing,
some officials have carried out
other over-the-top improvements,
including refrigerators packed with drinks,
microwave ovens, LCD televisions,
and automatic shoe polishers.”
Yes, there’s nothing I’d rather do in
a Chinese toilet
than microwave some food.
And want toilet paper?
In the past,
you usually had to bring your own
everywhere you went,
since people would steal
what was foolishly left unguarded.
Well now some restrooms
have face recognition toilet paper dispensers
that ensure you get the right amount.
The right amount depends on
whatever local officials think you need.
At least in China,
everyone gets an equal... small amount.
But some places are spending big
to show how enthusiastic they are
about Xi Jinping’s toilet revolution.
This restroom in Chongqing
cost over 120,000 dollars.
It’s become such a problem
that China’s tourism head official
has told everyone to just hold it.
“We don't need local governments
trying to outdo each other with ‘five-star
toilets’—
we just need to build practical public facilities.”
Exactly!
From now on,
officials should to just order cheap toilets
online.
Like this one from Alibaba.com.
What?
They’re only 250 bucks each!
So what do you think about
China’s toilet revolution?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
You know, considering that people
are actually buying Squatty Potties,
maybe China should embrace its squat toilets.
They could be a great place to catch up on
your favorite episodes of China Uncensored!
Just visit ChinaUncensored.tv
the next time you’re in the reading room.