The Chinese regime has teamed up with international
criminal cartels
to pump the West full of drugs
and dirty money.
And it’s all happening right under our government’s
nose
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
The Chinese Communist Party is at war with
the West.
This isn’t a 20th century boots on the ground
kind of warfare.
China has brought war into the 21st century
through a massive, coordinated campaign of
global terror, using links to triads and our
own politicians’ greed to undermine democracy.
Joining me today to talk about this is Sam
Cooper.
He’s an award winning Canadian investigative
journalist and author of the new book Wilful
Blindness: How a network of narcos, tycoons
and CCP agents Infiltrated the West.
Sam, thanks for joining me today.
Thanks for having me.
Your book is Willful Blindness: How a Network
of Narcos, Tycoons and CCP agents Infiltrated
the West.
So tell us, how did a network of narcos, tycoons
and CCP agents infiltrate the West?
It's a very complex story.
But to simplify it, really, this starts in
Hong Kong.
My a book gets into a corruption case that
happened in Canada's High Commission.
Tycoons that are very powerful and tight in
Hong Kong, and connected to drug and casino
money laundering triads, wanted to immigrate
to Canada.
They were able to allegedly corrupt Canadian
officials and immigrate and invest, especially
in the city of Vancouver.
Their connections were both to the Chinese
Communist Party at a high level, for political
reasons, and to drug traffickers.
They used casinos to launder money.
They used British Columbia casinos brazenly,
egregious money laundering.
We're talking bags of cash.
Hockey bags with from 500,000 to a million
dollars in $20 bills.
This was a way for corruption suspects to
get money out of China using organized crime
underground banking.
But there was also a scheme where intelligence
agents were using organized crime.
So you can see when money flows out of China,
it's not just corruption involved.
There was a level of espionage with the ultimate
goal of influencing Canadian politics and
using Canada's economy to get a foothold really
for Chinese state activity in the West.
This is the Chinese Communist Party actively
using connections to its business elite's
underground triads to pump money into the
West through drugs and human trafficking,
that's also part of this as well, and influencing
Canadian politicians.
That's right.
In a boiled down nutshell, organized crime
is working hand in hand with the Chinese Communist
Party.
My book showed examples of people who, on
the one hand, are alleged gangsters and also
involved in intelligence activity.
Also involved in, at least on the surface,
what is put forward as a legitimate business
activity.
So when you have people of great wealth that
have established themselves in Hong Kong and
are being used in a symbiotic sort of dark
alliance by the party in Beijing, this leads
to opportunities to influence Western politicians,
to donate money to Western political parties,
to try to control diasporic communities in
cities like Vancouver and Toronto to the extent
where you have people that are, to use a simple
term, being run through Chinese consulate
officials, working together with casino money
laundering gangs to rub shoulders with Canadian
politicians.
In the darkest cases, the same people I found
were harassing or politically opposing democracy
activists, Hong Kong Canadians, Chinese Canadian
dissidents, Uighurs, members of the Falun
Gong societies in Canada.
Not only does the Chinese government know
about this, but the Canadian government does
as well.
That's a difficult one.
On the casino money laundering and organized
crime side, what my book shows is, indeed,
there was willful blindness.
There had to be.
The police knew about these hockey bags of
cash coming into casinos.
They knew that it was coming through the hands
of persons who were loan sharks, persons who
were high-level drug traffickers under investigation,
while either lending money or themselves high
rolling inside, for example, the Richmond
River Rock Casino.
These are known high-level, organized crime
RCMP targets.
This was known by everyone, from people working
in the casinos, to police, to high-level government
officials.
It was known that this was seen to be by the
good investigators as high-level drug money
laundering using B.C. Casinos.
It was allowed to happen.
Is the intelligence side of this operation
allowed to happen?
My book didn't get into that level of willful
blindness.
But it's reasonable to believe that the people...
There are politicians in Canada that understand
that they're dealing with gangsters and people
from other governments asking them to act
against their country's interests.
So at some level, the intelligence organized
crime influence nexus is known in Canada among
politicians, among regulators.
How did you get started writing this book?
I got started writing this book, I have to
take a step back and look at the days when
I was a young journalism student, back in
2005 at Langara College in Vancouver studying
the craft of journalism.
I saw the downtown east side, which literally
is war zone conditions, where thousands of
addicts are clinging onto life.
They are in many cases, of course, on government
subsidies that unfortunately in many cases
are spent immediately on heroin or fentanyl.
I couldn't understand that scenario in Vancouver.
How is this happening in a Western city?
How has this open-air drug market allowed
to continue?
I couldn't figure it out.
Then I started to look at real estate in Vancouver.
Why were the prices just so far out of reach
of the average incomes?
Why is this the super capital, sorry, the
capital of super cars in North America, Lamborghinis,
Ferraris, McLarens, when people aren't declaring
incomes to compare with other big cities in
Canada or the United States?
And the answer was, this has become a medical
hub where there's so much narcotics flowing
in from offshore, so much addiction, so much
money laundering has to occur.
That had to have an influence on housing prices.
I looked into those issues.
Started to put them together.
And this is what led me to sort of these higher-level
later investigations where I saw that the
intelligence angle from other countries, such
as China and Iran, using organized crime in
cities like Vancouver and Toronto was very
present.
I imagine this must've been shocking for you
to uncover.
I never stopped being shocked, from those
moments in 2005, as a young student, looking
at the devastation of the downtown east side.
Look, paramedics are trained.
They take war zone training to work out of
ambulances in the downtown east side of Vancouver,
because this is the epicenter of death related
to heroin.
And now fentanyl.
I couldn't understand it.
That was shocking.
Real estate prices, I couldn't understand
it.
Going fast forward to 2015, hockey bags of
cash, $500,000 openly coming into the casino
night after night.
This doesn't happen, even in Las Vegas.
It doesn't happen in Macau.
Why is it happening in Vancouver?
Canada, a supposedly upright country with
the rule of law.
It didn't make sense.
So by 2017, when I'm starting to look at,
let's just say, a high-level People's Liberation
Army veteran, known to be a high-level organized
crime suspect, and yet meeting with Canadian
politicians, very chummy with Chinese consulate
officials, it doesn't make sense.
How is this happening on the west coast of
Canada, where we have this nexus of organized
crime and Chinese state actors?
How is this activity explained?
I still can't explain why this is occurring
in Canada.
I can say it is occurring.
The line is so blurry between triad member,
PLA member and Communist Party member.
I talk a lot about unrestricted warfare or
asymmetrical warfare.
And from everything you're telling me, this
really sounds like this is the kind of drug
warfare they're talking about, or even how
the housing prices are being through the roof.
It really seems like this is an aspect of
this sort of asymmetric warfare.
People have different levels of comfort looking
at the concept of gray zone conflict or hostile
state activity just below armed conflict,
kinetic war.
Do states, such as Iran and China, use these
asymmetric tactics?
I would argue that it's hard to argue a level
of total strategic control in countries such
as China and Iran.
But I do think there is the pattern of states
such as China using activities that are harmful
to other countries, perhaps allowing or not
cracking down on factories producing fentanyl,
because China is making so much money from
the production of pharmaceuticals.
There are a corrupt officials in China that
are doing business with drug gangs.
There are corrupt officials that are making
tremendous amounts of money in trade-based
money laundering.
China's economy, making so much money from
all of this rolled together, that why would
they crack down on it?
My sources in intelligence or the police would
say, "If they're not cooperating with Canada..."
When Canada goes to them and says, "Can you
work with us on fentanyl trafficking?"
And China says, "Well, maybe if you let us
put in our agents to go after our economic
fugitives, we'll work with you."
And Canada says, "I'm sorry, we can't allow
that covert fox hunt activity to occur in
our country."
And China says, "Okay, then no help on fentanyl."
What do we have here?
This is a hostage diplomacy-style of state
activity.
So are they directing those shipments of fentanyl
to cities in Canada and the United States,
Australia?
I don't know that level of direct warfare
is happening.
I do know an omission of enforcement is happening
to China and why.
What is being done about this problem?
Are Canadian officials doing anything now
that your book has come out?
Well, the book's only been out for less than
two weeks.
I can say that it's starting to make some
waves.
People in law enforcement and, of course,
intelligence are taking it very seriously.
Here's the rub.
Some would say Canada's government hasn't
been taking people in intelligence and law
enforcement themselves seriously.
This gets into the question of, why is the
concept of a 5G network run by Huawei still
a possibility in Canada, when countries such
as Australia and United States have completely
ruled it out?
I'm optimistic that my book, it has the chance
to open up the eyes of mainstream readers,
if you will, and for them to start talking
to their local politician and saying, "Why
aren't you acting on what looks like very
serious issues?"
You would hope once that starts to happen,
that politicians, high-level politicians,
in Ottawa, Canada's federal government, do
start to take actions.
But I have to say, we're in a position where
countries such as Australia and the United
States, I'm told they're about a decade ahead
of Canada in terms of dealing with this, first
of all, interference from countries such as
Iran in China, and this nexus of organized
crime working with state actors in countries
such as China and Iran.
I bet that really affects the security dialogue
between Canada and most of the other Five
Eyes countries.
That's undeniable.
My sources would say, "Canada is starting
to look like not a great partner."
It's not due to the police.
It's not due to CSIS.
When they're supported, when they have their
best leadership in place, these are leading
international agencies.
But Canada, for reasons that come from the
ground up, or maybe the top down, doesn't
seem to be pulling its weight in intelligence
and law enforcement internationally.
I think that's a huge problem.
Let me give you an example.
Canada's former top police intelligence official
is now being accused of working with some
of the worst gangsters and drug traffickers
in the world, profiting from helping them
evade detection.
This would be a form of protection of gangsters
that we might expect in a country like China.
It's happening in Canada, allegedly.
Was this person, Mr. Ortis, perhaps working
for hostile states as well to misdirect Canada's
policing investigations, to misdirect our
intelligence?
That's an open question.
His case remains to be tried.
Yet the allegations would, it just follows
that Australia and the United States would
start to hold on to their cards.
They'd start to hold on to their high-side
intel and not share with Canada.
So it's a problem.
Absolutely.
Well, Sam, the book is an absolutely fascinating
read.
I recommend it to anyone watching.
And I'll put a link below.
For anyone watching, where can they follow
you?
They can follow me on Twitter @scoopercooper.
And they can also watch for my stories online
on the internet.
Well, thanks, Sam.
It's been a pleasure talking to you today.
Thank you.
And thank you for watching.
If you want more, Shelley, Matt, and I had
Sam Cooper on our podcast for an hour—to
hear more of the crazy stories of what’s
happening with Chinese criminal gangs in Canada
and around the world.
So check out that episode of China Unscripted.
And also, you can now order Sam Cooper’s
book Wilful Blindness on Amazon.
The link is below.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next
time.