China has a shortage of women
And Chinese men are getting them from Burma
As the West retreats, China is rising
And that has some serious consequences
for the Burmese people.
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Myanmar.
The country formerly known as Burma.
And as you can see, it shares a border with
China.
And it’s full of women.
Or, you know, about 50% women.
Which is a lot more than China,
where decades of population control has resulted
in
30 million fewer women than men.
And that’s resulted in a thriving sex trade
between the two countries.
China and the United States have used Myanmar-slash-Burma
as a battleground of influence.
But with mounting human rights problems
and accusations of ethnic cleansing of the
Rohingya people,
the West is retreating.
And China is taking advantage.
At the 2019 Oslo Freedom Forum,
Shelley Zhang had the chance to sit down with
Esther Htusan.
She’s a Pulitzer Prize winning Burmese journalist.
And she shares with us what China’s influence
is doing to her country.
Thanks for joining us today, Esther.
Thanks for having me.
So how would you describe the relationship
between Burma and China?
Well, Burma had been under the military dictatorship
for about half a century
and during that period,
it was isolated from the rest of the world,
especially the western country.
China is one of the main country that support
Burma
so they had a very long, close relationship
between the two countries and China
was a long time investor in the country
when the rest of the world
would not even enter Burma,
so they do have this love and hate relationship
because sometimes the political conflicts
with China.
Then sometimes Burma has only China as the
only country
that they can rely on so there is this,
I would say it's a very close relationship
that has been a long standing with China.
There is some tension there, is what you're
saying?
Yeah, there were times when Burma felt like
China
was bullying them because they had no other
country
to rely on so there is some tension coming
up
and then it will ease again when China
had a better investment plan inside Burma
so it's just this on and off, love and hate
relationship.
So one of the things that might be
a little bit of a source of tension
is human trafficking in Burma, right?
The one child policy in China has left a lot
of extra men
who can't get wives and that's led to some
trafficking,
sex trafficking of women from Southeast Asia.
Is this something that's affecting Burmese
women too?
Absolutely.
Over the years there are just hundreds
of thousands of women who have been trafficked
inside of Burma
and then sold as brides in China and it has
become a very lucrative,
illicit trade cross border.
Not only just Burma but also
other Southeast Asian nations that border
with China.
So the biggest problem is that China initiated
this one child policy
a long time ago and to balance out their male
and female population,
it is going to take a long time because they
did it for so long
that they have imbalanced women.
There's something like thirty million more
Chinese men.
Exactly so they need more women for those
men to get married
because they don't have enough women so what
happens
is mostly Southeast Asian countries,
particularly the more poorer area that is
bordering China
like Burma for example,
Northern and Northeast Burma,
many women along this border have been trafficked
for many times
for example I did a few investigative stories
about women
who had been affected by Burma's internal
conflict
and then they were fleeing closer to China
border
and ended up getting trafficked and sold as
brides in China.
So it is a very regular incidence and it is
a very big issue
inside Burma at the moment.
So you said hundreds of thousands of women?
Over the years, right.
So is this something the Burmese government
is talking about
or is it more off-limits because it has to
do with China?
So when it come to human trafficking issue,
it is less political so there are things that
the Burmese authorities
try to stop but the problem with Burma is
the rule of law.
It has a very weak implementation of rule
of law
and particularly along the border region
there's no influence of legal protections
or there's no control over by the central
government
along the border so it's more difficult
for the government to implement trying to
stop human trafficking
or also the Burmese government has long been
famous for incompetence
to actually try to stop this kind of issue
so it's still ongoing.
They seem to be doing better job trying
to stop this kind of human trafficking
or even trying to get involved in going to
rescue women
who had already been trafficked
but the problem is the Burmese government
is not that willing
to really use the man power to rescue these
women
or to actually stop this issue because to
me as a journalist
it seems like the authorities don't really
care.
Is there a way for these Burmese women
to escape once they get to China?
Can they get back?
So we have women organizations inside
and also along the border of China
and these women organizations are amazing.
They are doing a great job.
They actually sent out people who can rescue
these women
in the middle of nowhere inside China.
It could take days, it could take months,
sometimes it take year but they don't give
up.
They actually go and try to rescue.
That's amazing that they can get these women
out.
Sure.
So we were talking about border issues with
Burma
and China and Burma shares a pretty substantial
border with China.
And you talked a little bit about people fleeing
conflicts.
Are there Burmese refugees that go into China
and how does China deal with that issue?
So as you said there's a substantial border
sharing
along Burma and China
and it is mostly in the East and Northeast
of Burma
and along this border we have ethnic conflict
that's ongoing for decades.
It's been ongoing along the border where ethnic
minority groups
have been fighting against the central government
for indigenous rights and self-determination.
Even since right after British Colonialism.
And China of course when there's conflict
along the border,
it produced quite an incredible number of
refugees.
Many people fleeing from conflict
and for many civilians along the border,
they don't feel safe to run into
the Burmese government controlled area.
For them, they rather flee into China
so most of them crossed into China.
But as far as I have seen.
The Chinese government had not done a more
sympathetic job.
Most of them are chased away by the Chinese
soldiers back to Burma
where they are airstrike bombing
or there are still active conflict ongoing
so they don't seem to have really sympathetic...
So they don't really seem to treat them as
refugees, basically?
No.
Because according to the U.N. charter
they should be accepting refugees.
Right.
So most of the displaced people
or people running as refugees are sent back
to Burma.
I read something about China actually supporting
militias
in part of Burma.
Is that true?
Yeah.
China has a very big influence,
not only just one ethnic group but quite a
lot of
different ethnic groups mostly along their
border so yeah.
Definitely.
They have a big influence and they have support
from some of those ethnic groups.
Can you tell me a little bit about what's
happening
with the militia groups in the Wa state
along the border with China?
So the Wa state, it was a self-administrative
zone
by constitution in Burma so it is part of
Burma,
it is Eastern part of Burma that borders China.
And because they have this really long,
good relationship with China,
later on they get the biggest support from
China
compared to many other ethnic groups in Burma
and later on this administrative region
had become a part of China.
When you go to this area,
you will feel like you are in China because
the currency
is in Chinese currency.
People are speaking mostly Chinese
and most people don't speak Burmese
so they have this very identical Chinese influence
as well as the enormous support that they
have from China.
This area also had a large number of Chinese
investments
on the extractive industries drug-trade route
because this region also is quite close
to other Southeast Asian nations
so it's kind of on the border with other countries
as well
so it's the perfect location for illicit drug-trade
and other sorts of investment.
So the Chinese authority is basically supporting
this area
because of the investments and things like
that?
Not just because of the investment
but also the Chinese government want a location
where they can actually be inside of Burma
but not as the central Chinese government
but as a state that they can completely control
and they can have their own armed forces,
they can have their own strength
which they can show against the Burmese authorities
as well.
So it's a very strange way to describe this
area
because it is Burma but it looks like China.
So is this not a conflict with the Burmese
government
if China is essentially supporting this self-administrative
but kind of separatist state that then
they are able to have a lot of influence over?
Definitely.
So in the very beginning of this armed groups,
they will attack quite a lot by the central
Burmese army
but later on when they get support from China,
they had the strongest armed forces among
any of the ethnic groups
so the central Burmese government
don't usually try to provoke this particular
group.
They feel like if they provoke this ethnic
group,
it will look like they are provoking the Chinese
authority as well
so that's just this very strange relationship
with this group,
with the central Burmese government.
That's interesting because with China,
a lot of what they talk about
is not interfering with other countries internal
affairs
because they don't want other countries
to interfere in their affairs
but then it seems that that is a pretty big
interference
in Burma's affairs
to kind of be supporting this other group.
Well, China always make this kind of rules
whenever they talk at the international level,
they say things only if they have interest.
They would tell the international organizations
that "we don't interfere what's going on in
Burma"
But when the conflict that is ongoing in Burma
is supported by China and there are just atrocities
ongoing just inside Burma
and because of these issues most talked in
the international level
and they would say "oh, it's nothing.
We don't really interfere Burma"
but on the other hand,
they are supporting in many different ways
to make sure
that there's conflict.
So China would come up with things based on
their interests.
So speaking of China's interest in Burma,
China has this one belt,
one road plan where they're investing in a
lot of countries
and I know with Burma, they have the China-Myanmar
Economic Corridor
which is part of the belt and road.
What are they investing in in Burma?
So most of the extractive industry like jade,
or amber, or gold,
they are mostly influenced by the Chinese
businesses
and then now they are trying to push for
one of the biggest hydropower dam in northern
Burma
and this is the most controversial project
inside Burma
and it really effects the internal politics
of Burma
because majority of people don't want this
project
but then the previous government
signed an agreement to implement this project
but now it's in limbo,
but anyway that's another project
and there's the deep water seaport as well
as gas pipeline.
So they actually crossed the gas pipeline
all the way
from western part of Burma into Yunnan province
in China.
That is pretty far.
That is pretty far and they have already built
this pipeline.
So its extracting the gas from western Burma
and taking it to Yunnan.
Exactly.
I want to ask about the hydropower dam.
What is so controversial about it?
Well so the problem is the Chinese company
did not come up a what if there is environmental
damage
that occurs in Burma when they build this
dam
because it will be in the most northern part
of Burma
and then if something happen, then thousands
of people
could die along the way, all the way down
to the south.
So people are really afraid that also at the
same time.
Most Chinese investments, so far that we have
seen,
it's not sustainable and people are afraid
of that
and also they don't usually care about environmental
damage.
They extract whatever they want
and then leave just the way it is.
So that's what we have seen along the way
throughout their investments
so people are afraid of the irresponsible
investments
and environmental damage so it's very controversial
inside Burma
and this project even could decide who wins
the election.
Really?
So China, in a way,
could have a huge effect on Burma's next election
is what you're saying?
Definitely.
Is this an issue that people talk about inside
Burma?
Like China's influence on Burma, these investments?
They do.
So, we have groups of civil society
who try to make investment responsible
or try to make development projects for local
people.
They just want the government
to make sure that the Chinese investments
are responsible
and also that benefits local people as well
but mostly it doesn't so people are really
angry
about most Chinese investments.
So how does the Burmese government react
to these civil groups saying
"we need to make sure these investments are
sustainable?"
Well the problem is they don't care.
For them, it is more important
to have a better relationship with China
than listen to civil society groups.
And probably the money is pretty important
too.
Definitely.
Particularly during the military government,
money is the main thing.
They had never used whatever they earned from
the country.
It all went to their pocket.
It was never really spent for the good of
the people for a long time.
So it still it's a habit.
It doesn't go away overnight but it is still
ongoing.
So let's talk about one of the things
that was really in the news with Burma lately.
The Rohingya issue.
And a lot of other countries had criticized
the Burmese government's treatment of the
Rohingyas
but what was China's stance on that?
Well as a long-term friend and a neighbor,
they of course always support the Burmese
military
or the Burmese government.
Well when you look at China,
China is not the best example of respecting
human rights
so of course for them when a bunch of people
get killed
or when nearly a million people fled to another
country
yet they don't want to criticize the Burmese
government
because they don't want to be friended with
the government
so they always protect the Burmese government
at the United Nations
or at any other level so it's very awkward
that one of those very powerful countries
would support really ugly atrocities.
So do you think China's support is giving
Burma
the ability to push back against other countries?
Absolutely.
Particularly the West.
The other problem with China is the reason
why they are protecting Burma is because
they don't want Burma to lean onto the western
countries.
For example, Burma opened up
a little bit more from military dictatorships.
In 2012, they opened the doors to the West
so that we started having western countries
coming into Burma and China did not like that
at all so for them,
they want to keep Burma to themselves as much
as possible
so by protecting the Burmese authorities,
who committed gruesome atrocities against
minorities in the country,
for them they know Burma will be on their
side
when they protect them on an international
level
when the whole world is criticizing Burma
so yeah.
So they are back to being Burma's biggest
friend then?
Exactly.
Thank you so much, Esther,
for talking to us.
Thank you.