On this episode of China Uncensored,
does Trump’s Secretary of State want
war with China?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Job interviews are just the worst.
You're overdressed,
sweaty,
and trying to answer difficult questions like,
"Where do you see yourself in 5 years?"
"If you were a brand,
what would be your motto"?
And of course the classic,
"Are you prepared to say that Vladimir Putin
and his military have violated the rules of
war
and have conducted war crimes in Aleppo?"
Ok, that last one was a question posed last
week
to Rex Tillerson,
Donald Trump’s pick for Secretary of State.
It was at his confirmation hearing
before the US Senate Foreign Relations Committee.
Think of it as a nationally televised job
interview.
One where you might make a slip of the tongue.
Like suggesting that maybe the US
should take military action against China
by blockading their activities in the South
China Sea.
We’re going to have to send China a clear
signal
that first the island-building stops
and second your access to those islands
is also not going to be allowed.”
He was referring to the Chinese regime
turning submerged reefs in disputed territorial
waters
into this.
The Secretary of State is the United State’s
top diplomat.
And who says diplomats have to be diplomatic?
Rex Tillerson,
or as I like to call him,
T-Rex,
used to be chairman and chief executive
of ExxonMobil.
But just because he’s into oil,
that doesn’t make him a dinosaur.
He’s a hawk,
and he’s going after China.
Building islands and then putting military
assets on those islands
is akin to Russia's taking of Crimea.
Comparing the Chinese regime to Russia.
Can China hack that?
Let’s see what they have to say.
Like the U.S.,
China also completely has the right to conduct
any normal activities in its sovereign territory,
and that is indisputable.
Because nothing is more normal
than building fake islands in disputed waters.
At least when those waters carry 5 trillion
dollars a year
worth of international shipping.
Oh yeah, and oil and natural gas reserves.
Now ever since Barack Obama’s Pivot to Asia,
the US has been increasing its naval presence
in the region.
But to suggest an actual blockade of Chinese
ships
from accessing their fake islands
is taking things to a whole ’nother level.
And while according to Reuters’ sources
the US has the military capability to do it,
the consequences could be huuuge.
Yes, no one wants a war!
I mean,
sure China is building military fortresses
in the South China Sea.
But they "highly value" peace and stability.
Something about those quotation marks makes
it seem sarcastic.
Anyway,
the Chinese regime’s, um, peaceful ambitions
in the South China Sea
have largely gone unchecked.
International pleas,
regular freedom of navigation tours by the
US navy,
and even rulings from the United Nations
have all failed to curb literally any of China’s
actions
in the South China Sea.
Last month,
the Chinese navy even stole a US research
drone
right in front of the US navy.
But hey, they gave it back.
So was T-Rex serious
about blocking China's access to those islands?
Or did he just get carried away
talking about a topic he's not that familiar
with?
Which I've never personally done in a job
interview,
but I, uh, hear it happens, sometimes.
Wait, what's that Shelley?
Oh, wow.
Apparently,
when Rex Tillerson was in charge of ExxonMobil,
the company signed deals with Vietnam
to drill in areas of the South China Sea
that overlap with China's territorial claims.
13 million acres worth.
That’s a lot of acres.
So I guess he does have some experience
with the South China Sea.
At the hearing,
future Secretary of State T-Rex
also echoed Trump on China issues
ranging from trade, intellectual property
theft,
and China’s “empty promises” on stopping
North Korea’s
nuclear ambitions.
Though he does seem to disagree with Trump
on some issues,
like that more nuclear weapons for our allies
is a good thing,
T-Rex wants everyone to have smaller arms.
Many politicians in the past on both sides
of the aisle
have favored a more nuanced approach
to US-China relations.
That has avoided military conflict,
but hasn’t been very effective at stopping
the Chinese regime.
This new more aggressive China policy by the
Trump administration
at least promises to be interesting.
So what does Xi Jinping think about all of
this?
Well, it's...hard to tell.
But he is in the middle of a massive purge
of political rivals,
and to survive, he needs to consolidate his
power quickly.
He can’t afford to look weak in his handling
of US relations.
Especially when it comes to third rail issues
like Taiwan
and the South China Sea.
So will T-Rex lead us to armed military conflict
in the South China Sea?
Only our future selves know for sure.
And since no time travelers have come back
to warn us
of imminent destruction in World War III,
I assume everything turns out fine in the
future.
Unless there’s no one left to come back
and warn us.
So what do you think about T-Rex’s idea
to blockade
China's access to their artificial islands?
And, if you were a time traveller,
what historical event would you try to change,
and how?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.