On this episode of China Uncensored,
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Wow, a bombshell has been dropped!
Check out what the Queen of England was caught
saying on camera
about the Chinese officials that recently
visited.
“They were very rude to the Ambassador.”
Chinese officials were very rude.
Now keep in mind,
the British are known for their subtly,
so let’s listen to that again translated
into American English.
“Those BEEP Chinese were BEEP to the BEEP
Ambassador.
BEEP.”
Now this is shocking.
Not only because of the so-called “golden
age” of China-UK relations that’s supposedly begun,
based around 62 billion dollars worth of new
business deals
but also because the Queen never comments
on anything.
How did China respond?
Well, to prove how not rude they are,
a state-run Global Times editorial called Western media “barbarians,”
who “will make progress” as they get more exposure to China’s 5,000 years of continuous civilization.”
Though in defense of Chinese officials,
which is not a phrase I ever thought I’d
say,
isn’t everyone rude compared to the Queen?
So what do you think about the Queen’s comments?
Leave your comments below.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next
time.