bjbj,(,( \ak5 China Uncensored-China Shows
the US How A Transition of Power is Done!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I m Chris
Chappell. You know, once again, China has
shown the US just how backwards it is. The
US Presidential elections are tomorrow and
the 18th Party Congress is Thursday, that
s when China has a once in a decade transition
of power. And you know, they just got it down.
They know how to keep things harmonious during
politically sensitive dates. I mean, just
today, I got in a cab, rolled the windows
down, went to the store and bought a ping-pong
ball. And it's the day before the election!
I mean, think of the damage you can do with
a ping-pong ball. Not to mention a taxicab
window you can roll down. That s why in Beijing,
you can t do stuff like that. They ve had
all the taxicabs rip out their window handles
and they ve banned the sale of ping-pong balls.
I mean, what if someone were to write reactionary
words on it and threw it out of a taxi. It
could go anywhere! Anyone could read it and
think who knows what kind of thoughts! But
the Chinese regime isn t stopping there. Officials
doing everything they can to ensure that they
aren t going to be bothered while they re
having their meeting. Want to buy a knife?
Too bad. A pencil sharpener? Who the hell
do you think you are? A remote controlled
air plane? Come on, really? And for all you
homing pigeon fans out there, don t think
they ve forgotten about you. No pigeons! Meanwhile
in the US, people are walking around with
sharp pencils in their pockets that could
write anything on anything. There are all
kinds of unsavory characters (like me) who
might be planning to release the 35 homing
pigeons they ve been training for the past
six months to carry Vote Herman Cain messages
strapped to their leg. I think its time we
all pack our bags and moved to China, cause
we re probably not going to have a country
by the end of the week if we just allow these
kind of shenanigans. Rapscallions with ping-pong
balls! Is that what George Washington killed
all those British people for? Think about
it America. Once again I m Chris Chappell,
thanks for watching China Uncensored Vote
Hermann Cain! [Content_Types].xml #!MB ;c=1
_rels/.rels theme/theme/themeManager.xml sQ\}#
theme/theme/theme1.xml G$$DA : BR \{i5@R V*[_X
,l\Y Ssd+r] 5\|E Vky- V4Ej 6NGU s?^V *<")QH
@\&> 7;wP EBU` 5VD GGHPXNT,
/M,W m2iU [[v _Xtl theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.rels
6?$Q K(M&$R(.1 [Content_Types].xmlPK _rels/.relsPK
theme/theme/themeManager.xmlPK theme/theme/theme1.xmlPK
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.relsPK
<a:clrMap xmlns:a="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/main"
bg1="lt1" tx1="dk1" bg2="lt2" tx2="dk2" accent1="accent1"
accent2="accent2" accent3="accent3" accent4="accent4"
accent5="accent5" accent6="accent6" hlink="hlink"
folHlink="folHlink"/> China Uncensored-China
Shows the US How A Transition of Power is
Done Chris Chappell Normal.dotm Chris Microsoft
Macintosh Word TXk5 PICT z+\}P o\{g9 g9kZZ kZo\{kZ^
kZo\{c g9g9c kZg9g9c o\{g9\{ o\{o\{s o\{kZo\{s o\{s
kZo\{o\{kZo\{o\{s kZo\{c o\{o\{s o\{o\{kZw kZkZw kZkZo\{o\
kZo\{c g9kZ g9,s o\{kZ^ g9g9kZc g9g9^ o\{g9c
g9g9c g9g9s kZg9 >g9^ kZo\{c g9kZZ g9o\{Z g9o\{o\{c
g9kZc g9kZo\{V kZo\{g9c o\{g9g9o\{o\{g9o\{kZc kZkZs
g9o\{o\{g9o\{s kZkZw g9"s kZkZc o\{kZs g9o\{kZs
kZkZs g9kZo\{o\{c g9kZZ kZo\{kZg9kZ o\{kZc o\{o\{s
%g9s o\{kZw kZo\{w kZo\{w g9kZw kZg9w o\{o\{s kZo\{s
o\{"s o\{g9o\{c o\{o\{s o\{kZs o\{kZkZg9kZkZo\{kZo\{kZw
o\{kZkZg9g9s g9kZ^ o\{g9s kZo\{s g9o\{kZ^ o\{g9g9kZ
"g9^ g9kZc g9kZc kZkZZ g9kZ g9g9^ g9o\{c kZg9Z
g9g9^ g9o\{kZZ kZo\{c kZkZo\{o\{g9s kZkZc g9kZ\{
o\{kZ^ g9g9kZs kZkZc g9o\{o\{c g9g9c g9o\{c kZo\{o\{c
g9g9s kZg9kZc kZkZc o\{o\{g9g9kZg9o\{c g9g9c
g9kZg9 =o\{kZZ o\{g9s g9g9Z g9g9c g9o\{kZZ g9g9s
g9g9^ o\{g9s kZg9^ o\{$Z o\{g9^ g9g9V g9g9c g9g9c
g9o\{^ kZg9^ o\{kZc o\{g9 kZo\{ o\{o\{s kZo\{s o\{o\{w
o\{o\
o\{kZs kZkZg9s g9kZs kZkZs o\{kZkZw o\{o\{s kZo\{g9o\
kZo\{o\{kZs 6kZs o\{o\{w kZo\{o\{s kZo\{s o\{kZs o\{g9o\{w
o\{kZs kZkZs g9o\{g9c g90s kZkZo\{o\{^ g9kZg9g9s
kZkZs g9o\{Z g9g9c g9o\{^ kZo\{Z .o\{c kZg9g9^
g9g9o\{kZZ kZg9s g9g9o\{c o\{o\{s o\{o\{s kZo\{o\{w
o\{o\{kZs kZo\{o\{w kZkZs kZo\{kZkZo\{kZ kZkZw g9kZo\{o\{s
kZkZg9kZc g9kZo\{s kZkZg9 kZo\{s g9o\{w o\{o\{s
kZkZ o\{kZo\{c o\{o\{s o\{kZo\{s g9o\{g9o\{w )g9^
g9g9\{ kZo\{g9g9^ g9o\{Z kZg9^ o\{kZ^ g9kZc China
Uncensored-China Shows the US How A Transition
of Power is Done Title ]ak5 Microsoft Word
97-2004 Document NB6W Word.Document.8