On this episode of China Uncensored,
China’s shocking military secret.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
Big news coming out recently.
And it’s upset a lot of people.
“Great Britain is breaking apart from the
European Union.”
No, it’s more upsetting than that.
“A shambolic performance by the national
team.
2-1 loss to Iceland last night will go down
as the worst moment in England's football
history.”
Well, not what I was thinking either.
Yes, China is killing millions of innocent
meditators for their organs.
Which is what a lot of people might call “genocide.”
This comes after this incredibly detailed
680-page report
revealed that as many as 1.5 million innocent
people in China
have been murdered for their organs.
And I’m not talking about this being done
by some
underground gangs or criminal networks.
I’m talking about official hospitals.
Including hospitals run by the Chinese military.
Like this one, the 301 Military Hospital in
Beijing.
It’s a place where a lot of high-ranking
Community Party members get treated.
The Chinese military is killing Chinese citizens
for their organs
on a massive scale.
And across China, other hospitals have been
following their example.
“The Chinese regime not only deprives its
people of their basic rights on a daily basis,
but literally steals their body parts for
a profit.”
Because there’s nothing more valuable than
a human life.
Now you’d think that this discovery should
be making major international headlines.
And to a degree, that’s happened.
The problem is that news, like comedy, is
all about…
…timing!
And the timing for this wasn't the greatest.
Hashtag Brexit.
But this story is still huge.
And the long-term implications haven’t even
begun to set in.
Eventually, I think it’s going mean more
countries will go from attitudes like this:
“I think this is going to be a very important
moment for British-Chinese relations
which are in a very good state,
something of a golden era in our relationship.”
...to attitudes like this:
“We recommend an international investigation
into forced organ harvesting in China,
and that the British government take a lead.”
Because it’s hard to have a golden era with
a regime
that’s currently committing crimes against
humanity.
I mean, once enough people know about it.
So, here’s what people ought to know about
it.
In most of the world,
it takes months or years to get an organ transplant.
But in China, it’s so easy!
“Patients typically must wait only a few
weeks for a donor organ.”
And they somehow perform a crazy number of
organ transplants there.
Officials say there's a total of 10,000 organ
transplants a year in China.
But this report finds that there are,
in fact, mega hospitals across the country,
each with thousands of beds,
performing thousands of transplants.
So many, that, according to the report,
many surgeons have simply
“lost count” of how many they performed.
Using data gathered from Chinese media reports
and the websites of individual hospitals,
the report goes on to estimate that between
60,000 to 100,000 political prisoners are
killed
—every year—
to supply China’s hospitals with fresh organs.
By contrast, the total number of transplants
in the US
in most years is less than 30,000.
Of course this raises the question:
If the Chinese Communist Party is killing
all these people for their organs,
where are these people coming from?
Wouldn’t, you know, people in China start
to question so many disappearances?
Well, not if the Party convinces you
that a certain group of people,
aren’t really people, and can be treated
however they want.
Is there...any group like that in China?
Falun Gong practitioners.
The people who are thrown into labor camps
for doing this.
That’s where the vast majority of the organs
are coming from, according to Bloody Harvest.
The report also says that other organ "donors"
include Tibetans, Uyghurs, and House Christians.
Note that one of the report’s authors is
David Kilgour,
who’s Canada’s former Secretary of State
for Asia-Pacific.
Bloody Harvest goes into detail about the
evidence behind their claim
that Falun Gong practitioners make up the
majority of organ harvesting victims.
Like how undercover investigators called dozens
of Chinese hospitals,
asking for those healthy Falun Gong organs.
And the doctors even boasted about it!
For example...
Doctor Dai:\h\h\h Let me tell you,
it should be OK to have liver transplant in
your case.
Investigator:\h\h\h I just want to know how
long we have to wait.
Doctor Dai:\h\h\h We have supplies everyday.
Today for example,
we are performing transplant surgery.
Investigator:\h\h\h Well, I mean not just
a fresh one.
We need one from live human body…
Doctor Dai:\h\h\h Sure, the organs we use
are all from live persons.
Investigator:\h\h\h What?
Doctor Dai:\h\h\h They are all live organs!
Ours are the best.
Yes, for the best live organs,
visit Jiaotong University Affiliated Hospital.
Investigator:\h\h\h So I want to know how
long you have been in operation.
I want to find out your skill level.
Doctor Dai:\h\h\h We’ve done this for 5-6
years.
We have performed such kind of operation for
5-6 years already.
Investigator:\h\h\h Then how many do you do
per month?
Doctor Dai:\h\h\h We have done 400 to 500
cases.
Investigator:\h\h\h What? 400 - 500?
Doctor Dai:\h\h\h Yes, that’s right.
Now the day after the Bloody Harvest report
was released,
a reporter in Beijing asked Chinese Foreign
Ministry Spokeswoman Hua Chunying about it.
Unsurprisingly, her response was that,
“such stories about forced organ harvesting
in China
are imaginary and baseless.
They don’t have any factual foundation.”
Which I can only assume means she didn’t
read the 680-page report,
the last 230 pages of which are filled with
all of their references,
because man, there’s a lot of facts.
But China’s Foreign Ministry had a better
solution
than reading the report and addressing the
facts.
It simply removed the reporter's question
and her answer
from that day's official press conference transcript.
Now no one will know!
Now although the update to the Bloody Harvest
report
just came out a couple weeks ago,
this story has been out for much longer.
The first press conference about it was 10
years ago.
And here’s someone you may know reporting
on it in 2011,
back when people still watched news on television:
"An investigation has raised the issue that
some Chinese organs
may have been taken from prisoners of conscience."
But like Leonardo DiCaprio,
the organ harvesting story has taken a long
time
to finally get the recognition it deserves.
In fact, the US House of Representatives
passed a resolution on June 13th this year
condemning China’s wide-scale murder
of Falun Gong practitioners for their organs.
Now that is shocking.
Democrats and Republicans actually agreed
on something!
But the biggest shock may come from inside
China.
Because now that this news is getting more
and more attention,
Chinese authorities will have to do more to
address it
than simply deleting all mentions of it from
the Foreign Ministry website.
And there’s some evidence that Chinese leader
Xi Jinping
is already taking steps to address it
but of course in a very roundabout way.
As I’ve mentioned before,
Xi Jinping’s so-called anti-corruption campaign
is really aimed at taking down his political
enemies.
One of his enemies is former Chinese leader
Jiang Zemin.
He’s the guy who originally orchestrated
the entire persecution of Falun Gong.
And he’s been controlling the military from
behind the scenes,
even after he stepped down in 2003.
Well, just a few days before the Congressional
resolution passed,
Jiang Zemin was allegedly taken into custody
by Chinese paramilitary troops
according to the Epoch Times.
So if the head guy responsible
for organ harvesting from Falun Gong practitioners
gets taken down,
does that mean Xi Jinping can make it stop?
And will he?
Perhaps we can gently nudge him towards the
right move
with a tremendous amount of international
pressure.
One thing you can do is sign this petition
calling for the UN to push China to stop killing
people for their organs.
The link is down below.
And like I said,
more people need to know about this.
So share this video with at least three people
you know.
And then they can share it with three people,
who can share it with three people,
and pretty soon the whole world will see this
video!
That's how YouTube works, right?
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
If you want to see the full Bloody Harvest
report,
the link is down below.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell. See you next
time.