On this episode of China Uncensored, eat your
heart out!
The world totally approves of China’s organ
transplant system.
But actually don't do that,
your heart is worth 130,000 dollars on the
Chinese market.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
Okay, we know China uses executed prisoners
as a source for transplant organs.
They even admitted it
...in 2009...many years after we already knew
they were doing it.
Which is like when Alex Rodriguez admitted
to using steroids.
The first time.
But the Chinese Communist Party
vowed to end the practice of using organs
from executed prisoners in 2012.
Sorry, they meant, in 2013.
Ok, for real on January 1, 2015.
Which is kind of like
when you keep asking for an extension on that
final college research paper
...the one you technically haven't started writing yet.
And the CCP has decided to just take an incomplete,
according to this massive report that came
out in July:
The one that alleges up to 1.5 million Chinese
organ transplants
have come not from executed criminals
—but from prisoners of conscience.
Because you’re only a criminal for doing
this in China.
So what does the top international transplant
organization
“The Transplantation Society” think of
China’s system?
Well, they just hosted their annual conference
in Hong Kong.
And they are big fans of China's transplant
system!
According to the people running China's transplant
system.
You see, they were invited to give a presentation
on China's new and improved system
at the conference.
As my favorite state-run newspaper Global
Times put it,
“Scholars say this special Chinese organ
transplant meeting
shows that the Chinese organ transplant world
has been truly accepted by the Transplantation
Society.”
And all the pro-communist newspapers in Hong
Kong agree!
Imagine that.
So what did the president of the Transplantation
Society
have to say about all the support and acceptance
he was giving to China’s organ transplant
system?
"It is important that you understand
that the global community is appalled by the
practices
which the Chinese have adhered to in the past...
Many people in the global community
are not persuaded that China has changed."
So that's what true acceptance sounds like.
As the New York Times puts it,
“Although Dr. O’Connell did not name any
groups,
he may have been referring to Falun Gong,
a spiritual movement that is outlawed in China
and that accuses the Chinese authorities of
extracting organs from its members.”
So that was awkward.
But not as awkward as this:
A Chinese liver surgeon, Zheng Shusen,
was originally scheduled to speak about
“a new era of liver transplantation in China.”
But then another Chinese surgeon was called
in to speak about it instead.
Well, that didn’t stop Zheng from pulling
a Kanye.
He just took the stage and talked anyway.
“Imma let you finish, but Falun Gong has
the best organs.”
After Zheng left the stage,
Dr. Jeremy Chapman, former president of the
Transplantation Society,
came up and was all like someone here,
not naming names,
presented research that included executed
prisoners.
Oh and interesting fact about Kanye wannabe Zheng
Shusen:
In addition to doing all kinds of liver transplants,
he's also the chair of an Anti-Falun Gong
association in China’s Zhejiang Province.
He’s also given scientific papers on liver-matching
in 24 hours
which is about as legit as guy on the street
selling Rolexes
that the previous owner “just didn’t want
anymore.”
In the US, it can take years to find a matching
liver.
Well, China’s former deputy health minister
Huang Jiefu
has responded to the claims
that the national organ transplant system
he runs
still uses organs from prisoners.
Unsurprisingly, he called those claims “ridiculous.”
He was also the guy who said China
would stop harvesting organs from executed
prisoners by 2015.
And 2013.
So is the Transplantation Society ready to
stop China’s appalling medical practices?
That's where things get interesting.
Because both Dr. O’Connell, the current
president,
and his predecessor Dr. Chapman
had undisclosed ties with a shady Chinese
hospital, according to the Epoch Times.
They both work at Westmead hospital in Australia,
which has ties to Third Xiangya Hospital in
China.
They even have one of those awkward Chinese
group photos together,
from when the doctors visited China back in
2013.
Third Xiangya Hospital is a "national research
base" for transplant technology in China
one that Chinese former deputy health minister
Huang Jiefu
promoted as a model hospital.
And according to a now mysteriously deleted
article from their website,
they once performed 17 transplants in only
one day.
Which is a lot.
Good thing so many people are “donating.”
So what do you think of China’s acceptance
by the Transplantation Society?
And if you want to know more about
the Chinese military’s secret involvement
in all this,
check out my episode “China’s Shocking
Military Secret Revealed!”
Leave your comments below.
Once again, I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.