On this episode of China Uncensored,
Ring ring. Mom?!
How’d you get me on the hydrophone?
Chinese fishermen are playing laser tag...
with US aircraft.
And finally, Xi Jinping says China won’t
give up
“even one inch” of Chinese territory.
Really?
How about half an inch?
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
A Chinese national has just been charged
with illegally exporting anti-submarine devices
to China.
According to the Justice Department,
he got his assignment
from the Northwestern Polytechnical University,
which is a a Chinese military research institute.
He stole “approximately 78 hydrophones.”
Approximately?
How can you steal approximately 78 hydrophones?
That sounds like a very precise number of
hydrophones to steal.
Ah well, probably something lost in translation,
a game of Chinese whispers,
or, if you will,
a game of hydrophone.
Hydrophones, by the way,
detect and monitor sound underwater.
The way modern telephones detect and monitor
when your mother is calling you,
so you can let it go to voicemail.
Unless you haven’t set up your voicemail
box yet,
which I swear I’m going to do soon, mom.
In other news, U.S. Defense Secretary Jim
Mattis
met with Chinese leader Xi Jinping.
And they must have been feeling the pain
of an awkward social situation.
Xi Jinping’s pants are too high.
Mattis’s tie is too long.
A bunch of Chinese military guys
are sitting around watching.
Also awkward:
That moment when Xi Jinping said,
“We cannot lose even one inch of the territory.”
Especially since Mattis had just announced
that
the US was going to send navy ships
through the South China Sea—
where China has built fake islands—
to demonstrate freedom of navigation.
Mattis also reminded Xi Jinping that no matter
what,
China is still going to lose one inch of territory
every year to natural erosion.
I think we all know who the real enemy is
here:
tides.
And how is the Communist Party going to fight
tides?
Are they going to control the moon?
Yes.
Yes, they are.
Meanwhile, militant Chinese fishermen
in disputed territories in the East China
Sea
have been flashing lasers at US military jets.
If the jets respond the same way to laser
pointers
as my cat,
China’s in trouble.
Over the last year,
there have more than 20 lasering incidents
perpetrated by the Chinese military—allegedly.
And like a game of laser tag,
it’s getting old pretty fast, guys.
Chinese police have already set up
more than 200 million surveillance cameras
across China—
mostly in big cities.
But now, they’re setting up what they’re
calling
the “Sharp Eyes Surveillance Project”
to cover small towns and villages, too.
Their goal is to achieve
“full coverage, network sharing, real time
availability,
and full control” by the year 2020.
Which just goes to show you,
the Communist Party believes that poor people
deserve equal opportunity...
to have their behavior monitored at all times.
And the Chinese Communist Party
may be trying to buy influence in Australia...
...but that’s no reason to worry about Chinese
phones!
Like Huawei, the Chinese telecommunications
firm
with close ties to the Chinese military,
the one that’s been banned by
some US government agencies.
Well Huawei’s Australian chairman assured
government officials there that Huawei
definitely wouldn’t give Australian users’
data to China.
That would be “completely illegal” he
said.
And we know they would never do something
illegal, right?
Just don’t let them near your hydrophones.
And now it’s time for another fan question
from a China Uncensored supporter on Patreon.
Pete Kuhns asks,
“Do you see signs/evidence of China physically
grabbing
more territory outside the 9-dash line?”
Yes.
The Chinese Communist Party is doing deals
to get control of land in a number of countries.
Military bases in Pakistan and Djibouti.
A 99-year lease on a port in Sri Lanka.
Using Chinese companies to buy up
20% of Cambodia’s coastline.
Setting up special economic zones
for Chinese state-backed companies in Vietnam.
The list goes on.
Plus, China wants to have influence in Antarctica,
where it announced it would be building
its fourth research base.
Now sure,
the Communist Party says that none of these
things
are about grabbing territory.
But if the Communist Party is willing to lie
about
its plans for the South China Sea,
trust me, it’s going to lie about
other territorial plans too.
Thanks for your question, Pete.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Hey, want the latest China news?
Subscribe to China Uncensored!
And turn that notification bell on
to make sure you find out
when new episodes are out.
We publish a brand new episode
every Monday, Wednesday, and Friday—
and sometimes Saturday.