On this episode of China Uncensored, no, you
can't play with LEGOs!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I'm your
host Chris Chappell.
So, you know what's hard about growing up?
Finding out that your beloved childhood icons
aren't what you imagined.
For example, I used to be a Hulkamaniac.
And who didn't love the Cosby Show?
But now, has the last plastic-bricked bastion
of my childhood been knocked down?
Chinese artist Ai Weiwei has slammed LEGO
for refusing to supply him with a bulk order
he wanted
for an upcoming exhibition on free speech
at Australia's National Gallery of Victoria.
And I know from personal experience, if you
slam LEGOs,
they really get stuck together and just impossible
to separate.
Ai Weiwei is well known for criticizing Chinese
censorship through his art.
And now he is accusing LEGO of censoring him
because of alleged pressure from the Chinese
regime.
So Ai Weiwei handled the rejection in the
mature, adult manner that one would expect
from the eccentric artist.
But does Ai Weiwei have enough of a case to
build on?
A LEGO spokesman defended their decision by
saying they never supply bulk orders for projects
with a political context.
Yes, LEGO stays away from politics.
That's why for LEGO's 50th anniversary in
2008,
when they had their ad agency create a series
of ads called "Making History,"
they picked only nonpolitical topics.
Like the Muhammad Ali fight. Or...
Wait, is that the fall of the Berlin Wall?
Well, I'm sure Chinese politics would be off
limits...
Oh.
Maybe it's just bulk orders.
Except that in preparation for Ai Weiwei's
2014 art exhibit on Alcatraz,
the group he worked with told LEGO from the
beginning that they were
"seeking LEGO bricks for a project... exploring
freedom of expression."
And then LEGO did sell to them in bulk.
That exhibition featured 176 prisoners of
conscience,
including many from China.
So come on, LEGO! Why the sudden change of
heart?
Oh.
So Ai Weiwei pointed out that LEGO's rejection
came on the heels this 300 million dollar
Legoland China deal.
But whether LEGO was right or wrong to deny
Ai's request, the Internet has clearly sided
with Ai.
He's set up several, uh, cars, where people
can donate LEGOs to him.
And this whole incident has made LEGO look
pretty bad.
In fact you could say it's making the company's
reputation fall to pieces.
But maybe we've been focusing too much attention
on Mr. Lego,
when maybe the real bad guy is this one.
It's not certain whether LEGO's decision was
a result of pressure by the CCP.
But if it were, LEGO would hardly be alone.
Because under the CCP, the price of doing
business in China is to play by their rules,
or face the consequences.
So what do you think?
Should LEGO have sold to Ai? Who's to blame?
Let me know what you think in the comments
section below.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell. See you next
time.
Starting recently, my new videos will have
optional Chinese subtitles.
You can access them a couple days after each
episode is posted, through that Closed Captions
button below.
Those are provided by Island Nation Translation,
based in Taiwan.
Next time you need your stuff translated,
give these guys a try.
They do a great job, work fast, and they won't
censor you.
Check out their Facebook page. The link is
in the description below.
The US guided missile destroyer the USS Lassen
sailed within 12 nautical miles of Chinese
territory...
as long as you consider artificial islands
built on submerged reefs part of China's territory,
which no one besides China does.