Who is driving the violence in Hong Kong?
Police or Protesters?
Is Hong Kong on the verge of collapse?
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I'm Chris Chappell.
Joining me today is Kevin Carrico,
a lecturer at Monash University.
His research focuses on China-Hong Kong relations.
Thanks for joining me today, Kevin.
Thanks for having me.
These protests have been going on for over
a hundred days.
How have they changed and evolved over that
time?
I think that we've seen a cycle of rising
tension
and mutual escalation between both protesters
and police.
When I was here June 12th,
the day that really started the current wave
of protests-
When the police fired all the tear gas.
Yeah.
It was the day that the extradition bill
was supposed to be passed,
and people were very eager to surround the
legislative council
to prevent that bill from being passed.
What I noticed at the time I think was on
the one hand,
there was still a very real emphasis
on being very I think peaceful,
very non-provocative in relations with the
police.
I think there was also a genuine fear of being
arrested.
What I think I have observed over the summer,
over the past three months is certainly I
think
a cycle of escalation wherein peaceful protest
has been met by the police with really disproportionate
force.
This has led protesters to, in varying ways,
fight back, setting up barricades.
In some cases, even throwing Molotov cocktails
or bricks
again in limited cases.
This has then led to the police just being
evermore aggressive
and evermore unreasonable and evermore violent.
This of course led to the ultimate escalation
on National Day
when police, after a warning that they may
have
to do to this at some point to,
actually used live rounds on protesters
in a situation in which that was,
in my opinion, completely unnecessary and
a criminal act.
Besides this obvious mutual escalation,
the point that really stands out to me is
that, sure,
regular citizens are scared of the police
when they show up.
I certainly am.
Yeah.
People are not scared of the protesters
despite the police portraying the protesters
as unlawful hooligans and things like that.
When people really get scared is when the
police show up.
I feel that I have noticed from June 12th
until October 1st,
I do feel like protesters are considerably
less scared of being arrested.
Being arrested in a protest used to be such
an exceptional,
such a rare event in Hong Kong,
but over the past three months,
we've literally seen thousands of people taken
in.
On the morning of October 2nd,
a total of 96 people appeared in court
related to charges of rioting.
This kind of massive,
expansive police violence and really indiscriminate
use
of politicized charges against protesters,
it's having the opposite effect of what's
intended
insofar as just making people first of all
less scared of repercussions,
and second of all,
more determined to fight back against this.
I know you mentioned that at the beginning,
these protests were focused on the extradition
bill.
That doesn't really seem to be the focus anymore.
I think the focus right now is really on
demanding some kind of police accountability.
This has been sadly completely lacking.
Carrie Lam keeps backing the police officers.
Yeah.
I don't know if Carrie Lam actually
has the power right to oversee or to I suppose
require
an independent investigation into police behavior.
Well, I don't understand.
Hong Kong is under one country, two systems.
Shouldn't the Hong Kong government have the
authority?
Is there perhaps some other power?
Yeah, there is another power.
We're not talking about Jesus, are we?
No, no we're not.
I think of course there's the power to the
north, Beijing.
I think there's also the power just a few
blocks over
from where we're filming, at the Wan Chai
police station.
I don't actually know if Carrie Lam
has control over the Hong Kong police force
any more at this point.
I don't know exactly what her intentions are.
If she actually for some reason wanted to
have
a real independent investigation into police
conduct,
of course, there's the issue of Beijing, but
at a deeper level,
I think there's the issue of police here
and whether police are any longer accountable
and under the control of the government.
I think we very much saw that on October 1st.
Speaking of October 1st, National Day,
we were both in Hong Kong on National Day.
That's the day that celebrates the communist
takeover of China.
Tell us about what you saw that day.
There are always I think far too many police
at these gatherings.
It's actually when the police arrive, of course,
that one begins to see violence unfortunately.
I participated in the illegal gathering,
walking from Causeway Bay all the way over
to Central
and a little bit beyond.
The protests, despite supposedly being illegal,
despite being unauthorized, was very orderly,
very peaceful.
People walked along the street,
voicing of course the five demands as well
as
their discontent with the Hong Kong government
and police.
That's a polite way to put it.
Of course, the central government.
I was in Central as people seem to be dispersing.
When I was walking at an intersection where
there's Cartier
and Louis Vuitton and things like that
and I was just doing a little window shopping,
going to get a new LV bag.
Somebody says to me,
"Oh sir, you better walk a little faster."
I didn't know quite what that meant.
That person seemed to be a protester.
Within a minute, the police had begun firing
teargas
I believe from inside an MTR station.
While the police escalated their use of force
in Central,
I made my way over to the legislative council
building
where at the time,
a fairly large crowd had gathered.
Perhaps around 500, 600 people on the street,
outside the legislative council and outside
of the PLA barracks.
I made my way out there just as of course
the police escalated their use of force there,
I saw at the legislative council,
the police firing teargas
from the top of the legislative council building
down on to the street,
which of course I think anybody can understand
is not a particularly safe way to fire.
No, I think that's actually not ...
You're not supposed to do it like that.
Yeah.
If I stood on top of the legislative council
building
and threw a can of Coke or a bottle,
that would be considered dangerous.
For some reason, when the police fire tear
gas rounds
indiscriminately from the legislative council
building,
this is considered okay.
I was happy to see that at least one teargas
round that I saw
seemed to have been picked up by protesters
and thrown into what appeared to be the PLA
barracks
next to the legislative council building
to great rounds of applause.
That was I think a really important
and wonderful gift for the PRC.
For the birthday.
Yeah, its 70th birthday.
Wow.
As we dispersed from the road
outside of the legislative council building,
people moved north to Pacific Place,
which is near where I am staying.
I saw literally thousands of young people
just set up on Queensway just outside of Pacific
Place.
That was actually the street
where I first really experienced teargas
on June 12th.
Special place for you.
Yeah, it has a lot of sentimental value for
me.
I watched actually from above,
from the lower block of the high court,
which is just maybe one level up from the
street.
As police proceeded down the street with the
big,
goofy water cannon providing them support
and basically just acted like rabid dogs
or some kind of angry, pissed off animals,
and just charging forward, yelling,
pointing their teargas guns indiscriminately
at people.
They pointed the teargas gun up at me as I
was watching.
You probably seemed like a threat.
Yeah, indeed.
That's me, very threatening as I watched from
above.
If that had happened three months ago, I would've
thought,
oh, well, they're just pointing it up.
They're not going to fire it.
At this point in the unfolding of this entire
protest movement
and the police response to it,
I was no longer confident that the police
weren't just going to randomly
just shoot a teargas canister at my head.
I of course backed away,
ducking down to watch as the police charged
forward,
randomly grabbing and beating people
and generally just acting in a way t
hat I suppose was a great gift to Beijing
on its 70th anniversary
to see that really the Hong Kong police have,
just like the PRC police,
essentially become just a political tool
for the oppression of the people living here.
Did this change how you view
the protests or the protesters?
I've always been, to put it lightly,
supportive of the protests.
I tend to disagree with a number of know-it-alls
and other analysts who have claimed that the
protest movement
needs to be more moderate,
needs to make some kind of compromise.
Really, what I saw on October 1st really
was just pretty straightforward suppression
of people's legally guaranteed rights under
the basic law,
using the most extreme forms of violence,
even including firing live rounds into teenagers'
chests.
For that reason,
I certainly feel that I not only support the
protests,
but I also support really any measure I think
that protesters use at this point
to push back against a violent and a repressive
regime.
I stepped away from October 1st,
moving from a pretty much no judgment zone
of protesters
to officially no judgment,
feeling that whatever happens,
it's important for people to continue to fight
back against
what I consider a repressive colonial regime
by really any means necessary.
You mentioned the protester
who was shot point blank in the chest by a
police officer.
How do you think that's going to affect the
situation?
Well, to put it lightly,
I don't think that's going to bring an end
to the protest.
No?
No.
I know that the police are stupid
and so they think that basically by using
live rounds,
perhaps they can scare people away,
and perhaps people won't come out.
Now, the decision to shoot a high school student
at point blank range in the chest,
it's a show of strong force,
a show of essentially willingness
to do anything to stay in power,
but it's also a demonstration
of a complete lack of understanding
for or rather complete disregard
of Hong Kong public opinion
insofar as everyone that I have spoken to
is outraged by and disgusted by this decision
to use that kind of live force.
Particularly when the policeman involved
had a rubber bullet gun in his other hand,
which I don't know about other people,
but if I was in that situation,
if I did fear for my life,
I would feel more comfortable,
if I had to, firing a rubber bullet
than firing a real bullet into a kid's chest.
It seems like the Hong Kong government,
their strategy or their hope has been that
eventually
the mainstream Hong Kong society
will turn against the protesters,
but that has not happened.
Why is that?
Because the government makes it so easy
to be opposed to the government.
They constantly miscalculate and mismanage.
As I said before,
if they had withdrawn this bill on June 12th,
none of this would have ever happened.
If they had shown some basic accountability
and done an investigation in the police violence
after June 12th,
this wouldn't have escalated further.
Really, basically, their response
to this entire protest movement,
if we use the metaphor of a fire building
up,
the Hong Kong government and the central government's
response
seems to think that, oh,
if we just pour another canister of gasoline
on this,
the fire will eventually burn out.
That's unfortunately not how things work.
While the government does seem to hope
that public opinion will turn against the
protesters,
every step of the way,
every stupid moment of bungling mismanagement
just pushes general public opinion
ever further away from the Hong Kong government
and of course the central government that
they represent
and leads to new concerns and new demands.
With the Chinese Communist Party
as the ultimate authority in Hong Kong,
how do you think these protests will end?
That's the thing.
I don't know how this will end.
I don't see any way that this will quiet down
or slow down.
These orthodoxies have faded away in the anger
and resentment
and disgust of this summer,
so that even if things do eventually quiet
down,
which is not something I actually see happening
anytime soon
but certainly could happen at some point,
I think the effects of this will be long lasting
and inerasable.
I don't really think Chinese rule over Hong
Kong
will ever be the same again.
Thank you so much for joining me today.
Be safe out there.
Oh yeah.
Thank you.
You too.
Thanks.