Trump singles out China at the UN
China is spreading AI Surveillance
And NASA fears China’s space aggression
That and more on this week’s China Uncensored.
This is China Uncensored. I’m Chris Chappell.
This week’s China news headlines!
A major confrontation at the recent UN summit!
A showdown we’ve all been waiting for.
No, not Trump and Greta Thunberg.
I’m talking about the showdown between Trump
and China.
We all knew it was coming.
On Sunday, before the start of the summit,
Trump’s Secretary of State Mike Pompeo denounced
the Communist Party’s attempts to erase
the mostly Muslim Uighur ethinc minority.
A Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman retorted
that the US has “slandered China’s policy
toward Xinjiang
and grossly interfered in China’s internal
affairs."
Trump himself singled out China on trade issues
and took aim at China’s claim to be a developing
country.
“The second largest economy in the world
should not be permitted to declare itself
a developing country
in order to game the system at others’ expense.”
Backing that call is the Australian Prime
Minister.
He also said that as a developed nation,
China must do its part to combat climate change.
Which I assume means Greta Thunberg
will soon be making a trip to Beijing
to protest climate change.
Where she will *not* be invited to give a
speech.
Meanwhile, back at the UN,
President Trump had a message of support for
Hong Kong.
The world fully expects that the Chinese government
will honor its binding treaty made with the
British
and registered with the United Nations
in which China promises to protect Hong Kong's
freedom,
legal system, and democratic way of life.
I’m sure Chinese authorities will get right
on that.
And in a final act of trolling,
the US invited Taiwan to the UN.
Specifically, to a UN meeting that the US
was hosting on religious freedom.
Taiwan has been trying for years to join the
UN,
and China has been trying for years to block
them
from joining the UN.
In fact, this religious freedom meeting
is the first time Taiwan has participated
in a UN event since 1971.
Also at the same meeting, the US invited the
daughter
of imprisoned Uighur scholar Ilham Tohti to
speak.
I think I know where this is headed.
And in another move that’s bound to make
Chinese authorities extremely uncomfortable,
a well-known lawyer has urged the United Nations
t
o investigate forced organ harvesting in China.
Lawyer Hamid Sabi from the UK
presented the findings of the China Tribunal,
which wrapped up in June this year.
The Tribunal concluded that Chinese hospitals
are “cutting out the hearts and other organs
from living,
blameless, harmless, peaceable people,”
mainly Falun Gong practitioners.
Falun Gong is a Chinese meditation practice
with exercises that look a bit like Tai-Chi.
Chinese authorities banned it in 1999
after it became really, really popular,
but refused to organize itself under Party
control.
The solution?
Arrest them and send them to labor camps!
Falun Gong practitioners say the practice
helps them stay healthy and fit.
Chinese doctors agree.
Their organs sure are healthy—
and ready to be forcibly transplanted!
Sabi said this organ harvesting
“constitutes one of the worst mass atrocities
of this century.”
China is preparing to celebrate the 70th anniversary
of the Communist takeover of China next week.
And by celebrate, I mean you’d better celebrate.
And Tibet is celebrating!
The holiest temple in Lhasa has put up this
banner that says
“May the great Communist Party live for
ten thousand years.”
And that still doesn’t motivate you to celebrate,
just like King George III,
Beijing will send a fully armed battalion
to remind you of their love.
“There will be 59 formations
and joint military band with 15,000 personnel.
160 planes and 580 sets of equipment
are taking part in the parade,
which will be the biggest military parade
in recent years.”
But Beijing faces serious threats
that make even 15,000 armed troops
quiver in their shiny boots.
That’s why they've banned the most dangerous
elements:
kites and pigeons.
Balloons too.
No, that’s not a joke.
The parade will pass along Tiananmen Square.
I personally can’t wait.
I don’t think I’ve seen so many tanks
in Tiananmen Square since...
never.
There were never any tanks here.
According to this study by
the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace
China
is supplying much of the world with AI surveillance
technology.
63 out of 176 countries surveyed used Chinese
AI tech.
At least 50 of those have gotten it from Huawei.
“There is also considerable overlap
between China’s Belt and Road Initiative
and AI surveillance—
thirty-six out of eighty-six BRI countries
also contain significant AI surveillance technology.”
And if you still somehow have doubts about
whether Chinese tech companies like Huawei
or Alibaba
are independent of the Chinese Communist Party,
don’t worry! The Chinese Communist Party
is working hard to erase your doubts.
Chinese officials in Hangzhou
“will assign government representatives
to work within 100 local companies including
Alibaba Group...
a new indication of the Chinese government’s
increasingly close monitoring of private companies.”
Bad news for Taiwan.
In less than a week after losing Solomon Islands
as a diplomatic ally,
Taiwan has now lost yet another one:
the island nation of Kiribati.
If you didn’t know, Kiribati is here.
Now sure, Kiribati only has a population roughly
the size of my apartment building in Queens.
But their pulling out means Taiwan now only
has
15 countries that officially recognize its
existence.
The Chinese Communist Party has vowed
to conquer Taiwan by 2020—
by force if necessary.
And as a Chinese Foreign Ministry Spokesman
said after nabbing Kiribati...
“What should happen will come sooner or
later.
Please remain calm, everyone should.”
Nice and cryptic.
According to the Congressionally funded
US-China Economic and Security Review Commission,
there’s been progress in the Trade War.
“The U.S. goods deficit with China totaled
$32.8 billion in July,
down 11 percent year-on-year.”
Meanwhile President Trump says the US is making
a lot of progress.
He said “the United States is taking in
billions
from tariffs imposed on Chinese imports,
and the total would soon reach $100 billion.”
Trade talks have resumed,
and the administration has lifted tariffs
on 400 Chinese goods,
things ranging from circuit boards,
to dog collars,
to miniature Christmas trees.
Trump says that’s because we’re winning.
But, depending on what media you read,
it's a sign we’re losing,
and “The administration is trying desperately
to reduce the pressure.”
So sometimes it’s hard to tell what’s
real from what’s fake.
Unless we’re talking about Impossible Foods,
the fake meat company.
They have plans to enter the China market
in the next year.
Which will be really confusing for the Chinese
Communist Party.
The typical modus operandi is to bring in
foreign companies,
steal their intellectual property,
and churn out a Chinese made knockoff.
But what will a knockoff of knockoff meat
look like?
On Tuesday, the head of NASA
accused China of aggressive space activity.
China has been developing anti-satellite technology
for years.
In fact, China was heavily criticized
for an anti-satellite missile test in 2007
that blew up one of their own satellites.
And created a giant cloud of space debris.
That’s something NASA’s head says they’re
going to fight.
“It’s important for people to understand
that we are not going to allow investments
that could potentially destroy space...
If we’re going to achieve what NASA wants
to achieve,
we can’t have people threatening to wreck
low-earth orbit.”
Perhaps most worrying of all was the new that
that’s no moon,
it’s a battle station.
And that’s it for this week’s China news
headlines!
And now it’s time for me to answer a question
from one of you—
a fan who support China Uncensored
with a dollar or more per episode,
by contributing through the crowdfunding website
Patreon.
Josiah faber asks,
“Have they stopped their belt and road initiative
since the trade war began,
as they have been losing so much money?”
Ah the Belt and Road lumbers on.
China has already invested a lot of money
around the world
through the Belt and Road Initiative.
Which means many countries still owe China
a lot of money.
As recently as March,
China nabbed its first G7 country, Italy,
for the Belt and Road.
But as countries around the world
have wised up to China’s debt trap diplomacy,
and as China faces more economic pressure
from the US-China trade war,
it’s been put on the defensive.
Since last year,
they’ve been talking about sustainable debt.
While also being forced to hold back money
from projects left unfinished.
But that doesn’t mean the Belt and Road
is over.
Not by a long shot.
Malaysia had become one of the toughest opponents
of the Belt and Road.
However, that changed in April this year.
“China has announced that it has persuaded
Malaysia
to resume a canceled rail project worth $10.7
billion.”
Because at the end of the day,
the Chinese Communist Party seeks world domination.
And the Belt and Road is a key part of that.
Thanks for your question.
And if you have a question for me
you want to hear answered on the show,
sign up to join the China Uncensored 50 cent
army,
by supporting the show with a dollar or more
per episode.
Again, YouTube is demonetizing us so much
we would have to shut down the show
if it weren’t for your support.
And to everyone, thanks for watching!
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.