China threatens to nuke Japan
Continuously
If Japan defends Taiwan
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
Last week, I told you Japan’s deputy Prime
Minister Taro Aso said Japan would go to war
if China invaded Taiwan.
By the way, that episode was not only demonetized,
but age-restricted.
Which was a shame because it got 1.5 million
views before YouTube decided to kill it.
The reason I bring this up is because there’s
a nonzero chance the same thing could happen
with today’s episode.
Since China has responded to Japan’s threat.
By saying it will nuke Japan.
And I’m able to bring you this story despite
YouTube shenanigans thanks to the support
of everyone watching who contributes to China
Uncensored on the crowd funding website Patreon.
Join us in the fight to expose the Chinese
Communist Party to the world with as little
as a dollar per episode on Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
So with the show’s basic survival out of
the way, here’s the story.
Right after this quick commercial break.
Just kidding, I’m not going to bother this
time.
So China has threatened not only to nuke Japan
if it defends Taiwan.
They threatened to continuously nuke Japan
if they send even just one soldier.
Here’s the video.
When we liberate Taiwan, if Japan dares to
intervene by force, even if it only deploys
one soldier, one plane, and one ship, we will
not only return reciprocal fire, but also
start a full scale war against Japan.
We will use nuclear bombs first.
We will use nuclear bombos continuously, until
Japan declares unconditional surrender for
the second time.
Now, when the Chinese Communist Party first
developed nuclear weapons, they promised never
to use them against a country that doesn’t
have nukes.
They said they would “unconditionally refrain
from using or threatening to use nuclear weapons
against non-nuclear-weapon states or nuclear-weapon-free
zones.”
Japan doesn’t have nukes.
But I guess the Chinese regime is making an
exception.
The video was first posted to a video sharing
platform called Xigua.
Xigua by the way is owned by Bytedance, the
same Chinese company that owns TikTok.
The video was posted by a military commentary
channel, “approved by the CCP and with close
ties to the People’s Liberation Army.”
Which wouldn’t have been such a big deal.
People say all kinds of idiot things on the
internet.
I should know.
But then it started getting shared and reposted
by local Chinese Communist Party committees.
So this went from being a video posted by
some quack on the internet, to being a message
approved by the Chinese Communist Party.
Of course, since this was posted by local
Party committees, the Central government has
plausible deniability.
Was this just some local Party official getting
a tad too patriotic?
Or is this a message the Chinese Communist
Party wants to send Japan?
Like I said, plausible deniability.
Now after this became international news,
the original video was deleted.
Obviously not before everyone made copies.
The channel also posted a second video that
talks about how China should invade Japan
and the aftermath of the nuclear war.
It was also deleted.
The video suggests that China and Russia should
simultaneously attack Japan, while North Korea
might want to use the opportunity to also
invade South Korea.
And after they’ve completely destroyed Japan
as a country, China will break up Japan’s
four main islands into four independent countries
under the supervision of China and Russia.
We certainly have a lot to look forward to
in a world dominated by the Chinese Communist
Party.
But in a twisted way, the CCP is actually
making the argument for Japan.
When Deputy Prime Minister Taro Aso said Japan
would fight if China invaded Taiwan, he was
arguing a Chinese invasion of Taiwan would
threaten the survival of Japan.
Yeah, kind of sounds like it.
Of course you could say, Chris you’re just
some idiot on the internet who’s blowing
this way out of proportion.
It’s not like this was an official video!
Right, it’s not like last year, when the
People’s Liberation army released this highly
produced video showing an attack on the US
air force base in Guam.
Huh, I wonder if we should actually listen
to what the CCP is saying about attacking
all of us.
Naw, probably should still invest in Chinese
bonds.
And now, as a thank you to fans who keep this
show alive by contributing on Patreon, I’ll
answer one of their questions.
JasCam asks, “Chris, would appreciate your
thoughts on whether an internal revolution
(aka Poland) or an international set of actions
(aka South Africa) have the best chance of
bringing the CCP down?”
Now that’s something I think about a lot.
It’s a really good question.
So on the one hand, the US still has tremendous
leverage over the Chinese Communist Party.
The Party is desperate for US dollars.
Recently I did a full episode about that.
I’ll put a link in the description.
Basically, without access to US dollars, the
Communist Party collapses.
Which is why the Party is desperately trying
to create its own international financial
system based on a digital currency.
Eventually the US will lose this leverage.
And sadly, it seems like the US elite are
too invested in China.
It would require completely decoupling the
US and Chinese economy.
They don’t want to do that.
And so likely, someday in the not too distant
future, China will decouple its economy from
ours when they no longer need us.
So how about an internal revolution?
It’s hard to know exactly how people inside
China feel about the Chinese regime, for obvious
reasons.
Certainly if the Party couldn’t promise
economic prosperity, people would rise up.
But that also depends on what the West does.
The Party has been pushing 30 years of patriotic
education to brainwash the youth of China.
It’s been pretty successful.
But the Party is also riddled with factional
infighting, corruption, and an incredibly
shaky economy.
What I think will ultimately happen is these
internal problems will cause the collapse
of the Chinese Communist Party.
And any Western country still tied to the
Chinese regime will suffer greatly for it.
Thanks for your question and your support
JasCam.
And thank you for watching.
As you can see, your support is so critical
for us to be able to continue making China
Uncensored.
So if you can, head over to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored
to learn how you can help.
You’ll get some cool perks, and I might
answer your question on the show.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.