Trump announces new tariffs...
10% on $300 billion in goods...
Because of China’s broken promises
and Beijing’s Seven Deadly Sins
Is there any hope for a trade deal?
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
President Trump is disappointed
that the Chinese Communist Party
has been dragging its claws on trade talks.
So last week,
Tariff Man said he plans to slap new tariffs
on China.
“The U.S. will start, on September 1st,
putting a small additional Tariff of 10%
on the remaining 300 Billion Dollars of goods
and products
coming from China into our Country.”
That would be in addition to the existing
25% tariff on $250 billion in Chinese goods.
And it would mean that basically ALL GOODS
coming into the US from China would now have
a tariff.
For American consumers,
there's good news and bad news.
Products that were spared in previous rounds
of tariffs
will now be hit.
That includes smartphones,
clothing, toys, and video games.
But fear not, Fortnite fans!
According to Trump’s trade advisor Peter
Navarro,
American consumers won't feel the pain
because China will absorb the tariffs
"by slashing their prices and by devaluing
their currency."
But would they really do that?
Well, on Monday,
China’s central bank set its exchange rate
at a weaker level than 6.9 yuan to the dollar,
for the first time since December.
And the offshore yuan sank to a record low.
That means the yuan devalued against the dollar,
which makes Chinese exports cheaper.
So even though there will be tariffs,
the cheaper cost of Chinese exports would
mean
the price American consumers pay will be essentially
the same.
Which means China is absorbing the cost of
the tariffs.
But the Chinese central bank can’t keep
that up forever,
or they will wreck their own economy.
But that’s a topic for another video.
Back to the tariffs, which Trump announced
on—
where else—
Twitter.
"Our representatives have just returned from
China
where they had constructive talks
having to do with a future Trade Deal.
We thought we had a deal with China three
months ago,
but sadly,
China decided to re-negotiate the deal prior
to signing."
US Treasury Secretary Steven Mnuchin
and Trade Representative Robert Lighthizer
had gone to Shanghai to breathe life into
the half-dead trade talks.
But apparently it was more like trying to
give CPR to a zombie.
Trump was maybe just being polite
when he called the talks “constructive”,
because insiders told the Wall Street Journal
that the Shanghai trade talks were "brief
and unproductive."
Which is at least better than “long and
unproductive,”
like getting a Master’s degree at NYU.
On the plus side,
while visiting Shanghai,
Lighthizer and Mnuchin probably got to eat
those those fancy little soup dumplings.
So America’s trade guys returned from China,
after being told essentially that the Chinese
Communist Party
would not agree to the US’s demands.
And then Tariff Man did what Tariff Man does:
He announced the new 10% tariffs.
On Twitter.
Trump is upset about what he feels are two
broken promises.
Back in December,
Trump had met with Chinese leader Xi Jinping
at the G20.
Afterwards, the White House said
China agreed to purchase a very substantial
amount of
agricultural and other products from the United
States.
This...did not happen.
The White House also said China
would stop the illegal exports of fentanyl.
That’s the synthetic opioid that’s played
a big part in America’s deadly drug epidemic.
Xi Jinping, “in a wonderful humanitarian
gesture,
has agreed to designate Fentanyl as a Controlled
Substance,
meaning that people selling Fentanyl to the
United States
will be subject to China’s maximum penalty
under the law.”
Well, there wasn’t much of a humanitarian
gesture, after all.
Fentanyl has continued to flow from China
into the US.
Although, to be fair to the communist regime,
if you read China’s official statements
from the G20,
China technically only agreed to “work to
open its market”
to US agricultural products
and “start working to adjust [fentanyl]
related regulations.”
It’s like when you tell your wife,
“I’ll start working on considering mowing
the lawn.”
She can’t prove you never started working
on considering it!
But technicalities don’t mean much to Trump,
since at the end of the day,
the Chinese Communist Party is still not buying
enough American goods,
and Chinese fentanyl is still killing Americans.
Hence, the new tariffs.
And that’s also why the enforcement mechanism
for any future US-China trade deal
has been a critical sticking point.
According to experts cited by the South China
Morning Post,
given the lack of transparency of the Chinese
economy,
and Beijing’s history of breaking previous
pledges,
the US side wants enforcement to be quote
unquote "painful."
At a February hearing of the House Committee
on Ways and Means,
Trade Representative Robert Lighthizer hinted
at
just what kind of pain the US has in mind.
“[We] are very aware of the history of
our trading relationship with China,
and the disappointments that have resulted
from promises that were not kept,” Lighthizer
said.
“The enforcement process will be very specific.
It will have layers,
it will have time frames,
it will have reaction.”
Experts say that the US wants to do
something called a “snapback.”
Which sounds like\h when you say “oh snap!”
while delivering a clapback.
But actually,
it’s a unilateral verification system.
The “snapback” option would let the US
review
whether China is keeping its side of the bargain.
Tariffs on Chinese goods would be removed,
but if China breaks the agreement,
the US would just snap them back into place.
For example:
A key goal for the US is to reduce its trade
deficit with China.
But if, let’s say, the reduction targets
are not met by a certain date,
the tariffs would automatically snap back
into place.
Now it should come as no surprise that the
Chinese regime
does not like this snapback option.
They’d prefer a trade dispute system like
the one
used at the World Trade Organisation—
where representatives from each side
have to agree on the enforcement.
You know, the same mechanism that’s been
in place for decades,
where the Chinese regime can keep cheating
with no consequences.
In fact, WTO dispute resolutions often drag
on for years.
And that's perfect!
Because in its trade talks with the US,
the Chinese Communist Party can just run out
the clock.
See,Trump only has at most 6 more years in
office,
but Xi Jinping gets to be presitator for life!
Which is why Trump is not likely to agree
to anything without strong enforcement.
And what needs enforcing?
Well, it’s what White House trade adviser
Peter Navarro
calls Beijing's “seven deadly sins.”
“Stop stealing our intellectual property,
stop forcing technology transfers,
stop hacking our computers
and steal[ing] our trade secrets,
stop dumping into our markets
and putting our companies out of business,
stop state-owned enterprises from heavy subsidies,
stop the fentanyl,
and stop the currency manipulation."
Of course, the Chinese Communist Party
doesn’t know about the Seven Deadly Sins.
They never went to Catholic school!
Or watched that weird Brad Pitt movie from
the 90s.
I suggest using a more awkward
Chinese communist propaganda name,
like the “7 Stops.”
Not that that would actually stop them.
In fact, in response to Trump announcing the
new tariffs,
Chinese authorities devalued their currency,
which makes it harder for US companies to
sell stuff in China.
And they ordered Chinese state-owned companies
to stop importing US agricultural goods.
And then China's UN delegate Zhang Jun
blasted Trump's tariff threat as “an irrational,
irresponsible act.”
“We do oppose that sanction decision has
been made,
and we definitely will take whatever necessary
countermeasures
to protect our fundamental right.”
Yes, the Communist Party has a fundamental
right...
to not be punished for cheating on trade!
Still, Trump is part carrot,
part stick when it comes to negotiating with
China.
Trump tweet-fed a bit of carrot,
saying he’ll continue positive dialogue...
and referring to Xi Jinping as his friend.
And the stick?
Well after the Chinese central bank let the
yuan fall,
which the central bank says totally had nothing
to do with the tariffs...
the US Treasury Department immediately did
what Trump had promised to do as his first
thing in office:
label China a currency manipulator.
Now practically speaking,
officially calling China a currency manipulator
doesn’t do much for now.
But it’s a heck of a snapback.
So what do you think about Trump's
new threat to impose tariffs on China?
Leave your comments below.
And now it’s time for me to answer a question
from one of you—
a patron who supports China Uncensored
with a dollar or more per episode
through the crowdfunding website Patreon.
Philip Conway asks:
“Did the Chinese Communist Party get a grip
of Italy
just so they can get hold of their ice cream
even though it's not quite as good as the
Russian type?”
The Communist Party wanted Italy to join the
Belt and Road—
not for the ice cream,
but for the political influence.
Also, the ports.
Italy is one of the world’s top 10 economies.
Plus, the Belt and Road is a great way for
Chinese regime
to make more European countries
more dependent on Chinese money,
and that gives them more sway over European
politics.
Also, I know that Xi Jinping enjoys his Russian
ice cream,
but I’m not convinced it’s better than
gelato.
I’ll have to try it next time I go to Moscow...
Or Brighton Beach.
What’s that, Shelley?
Oh yes.
Shelley is going to Italy in a month,
so if you have any tips on who she should
talk to
for information on China’s growing influence
in Italy,
email us at chinauncensored@gmail.com.
Thanks for your question, Philip!
And thank you to everyone who’s watching.
Your support of a dollar or more through Patreon
helps us keep this show going.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.