A Chinese stand-up comedian
says something “sexist”.
And it stirs a dangerous debate across China.
Welcome to China Uncensored. I’m Chris Chappell.
Amidst all of the chaos of this past year,
there has been one steadily rising power within
China. No, I’m not talking about Chinese
leader Xi Jinping’s pants. Although they
continue to be quite high.\h
I’m talking about China’s entertainment
industry. There’s a growing trend of TV
shows featuring singing competitions, dance
competitions, and even rap competitions.
Now, you might ask: How can you have artistic
expression under an authoritarian regime that
works to silence its people and squash the
slightest sign of rebellion? Too much freedom
of expression can be dangerous.
Well, don’t worry. Because glorious leader
Xi Jinping has figured it out.
In 2014, Xi gave a speech saying China should
be careful about what kind of foreign entertainment
gets promoted. He said, “Many art forms
from overseas, such as hip-hop, breakdance,
etc... should only be adopted if the masses
approve of them, while also endowing them
with healthy, progressive content.”
So basically... Xi Jinping Thought on Breakdancing
with Chinese Characteristics?
Well, kind of. What Xi Jinping actually meant
was that he wants to use foreign culture to
spread the Communist Party’s message. Which
is why we see things like this: A rap song
from Chinese state-run television about China’s
Reforms, featuring Xi Jinping!
“To rule the party strictly we must harden
our bodies, the judicial reform must be victorious”
“All corruption must be punished. Every
corrupt official must be prosecuted.”
\h“The reform group is two years old; it
has done quite a lot.”
Yes, how do you do, fellow kids?
So Chinese authorities are allowing foreign
art forms into China’s entertainment industry.
It’s a way for them to get the Party’s
message across to young, impressionable minds.
But there’s a potential pitfall: Young,
impressionable minds.
That’s why entertainment shows in China
are still closely monitored by the Communist
Youth League.
“Ultimately, the authorities still set China’s
cultural agenda, but the work of actually
realizing this agenda is increasingly decentralized.”
And as more producers and artists start opening
up this new market, it’s become less clear
what is and isn’t allowed on, say, a nationwide
broadcast. Or a nationwide streaming platform.\h
This is the case for stand-up comedy competition
“Rock & Roast”.
The show premiered on Tencent Video, a streaming
platform that belongs to tech conglomerate
Tencent.
Last year, one of the Rock & Roast finalists,
Yang Li, did a stand up comedy routine...for
which she was reported to China’s National
Radio and Television Administration. Why?
Well, here’s one netizen who reported her
for, among other things, “alleged acts of
sexism, many instances of hostile discrimination
against males, and incitement of conflict
among the masses.” And that is “detrimental
to the harmonious development of China’s\h
socialist society.”
￼
Well, I’ve got to hand it to this netizen.
They know the vocabulary.
So what did Yang Li say that was so detrimental
to the harmonious development of China’s
socialist society?\h
“Men are so wonderful and so mysterious.
You can never figure out what’s going on
in that little brain. Like, how can a guy
seem so average, and still have so much self-confidence?”
Well, I know she’s not talking about me.
Because I’m definitely not average.\h
Now her punchline doesn’t appear to be very
radical. It’s not even very funny.
Not that my jokes are much better. Which I
assume is why Tencent never invited me to
perform on Rock & Roast.
Now despite a rather unoriginal punchline,
it stirred up a big debate on Chinese social
media—over sexism. Clips of her standup
performance were shared across Chinese social
media, and it sparked a movement of women
speaking up about their individual experiences
facing sexism in Chinese society.
Obviously, something needs to be done to stop
these women.
But despite people reporting her to the higher-ups,
China’s National Radio and Television Administration
hasn’t done anything yet. Probably because
they don’t view Yang as a threat to the
Party’s agenda. But she is getting a lot
of blowback from Chinese netizens. Male netizens.
Including vicious attacks from people like
law professor Chu Yin at the University of
International Relations in Beijing.
You think you’re such a pretty princess.
You don’t have the life of a princess, yet
you have princess disease. You should get
that checked. It’s all a made-up fairy tale
from corporate minds commercializing on trends...You
think you’re a proud pretty princess, but
the reality is you’re just a corporate society
brainwashed leek.
Wow, that’s...really uncalled for. I’m
pretty sure the problem in China is not brainwashing
from *corporate* society.
Meanwhile, Yang isn’t afraid of the attacks.
She’s standing by her words.
“I can understand why people are lashing
out at me. Because they think a comedian’s
perspective is a reflection of their personality,
but that’s not it, I’m merely reflecting
what the audience is thinking. My comedy bit
got such a big response, only because it resonated.”
In response to one of her haters, she posted
on Weibo, China’s version of Twitter,\h“If
you don’t find it funny, then don’t watch
it, thank you. Try doing something more worth
your time. You have the guts to attack an
entertainment figure, but that’s just part
of the job. How about instead try to offend
people with power, offend the politicians,
offend the criminals.”
Is that an invitation or a death wish? Because
if someone went on television and actually
offended the people in power and the politicians...I
don’t think it would be just middle-age
professors attacking them.
Let’s just say Rock and Roast is not going
to roast Xi Jinping anytime soon. Or Rock
and Roast will quickly find themselves between
Rock and Hard Place.
But of course, making jokes about people in
power is the essence of good comedy. Some
people have even based their entire career
on that...(pause of self-reflection) I hope
it works out for them.\h
And that’s why people are warning Yang Li
to tread lightly—if she wants to veer into
socio-political topics. Who knows where this
will go?
Though for the most part, there has been a
positive response to Yang. People give her
career full support, saying that for there
to be a true stand-up comedy show in China,
the topics need to be more open.
But just how open can it be? It’s one thing
to talk about sexism. And sure, that attracts
a lot of attention on social media—because
that’s one of the things that people in
China *are* allowed to debate openly.
But if a person speaks her mind on political
topics, she might find herself whisked away
to get “re-educated.”\h
Of course, if everyone in China speaks their
mind, there’ll be no way to stop the tide.
I mean, how many re-education camps can there
be, right?
What’s that Shelley? There’s 500 in just
one region?!
OK, nevermind. It’s gonna be an uphill battle.
And now it’s time for me to answer a question
from one of our fans who supports China Uncensored
through the crowdfunding website Patreon.
You can support the show too at patreon.com/ChinaUncensored,
and I might answer your question at the end
of an episode.
Jon Gilmour asks “Are you going to SHAVE
YOUR BEARD OFF?”
Why would I shave my beard off? Sure, having
a beard means I may not look like a traditional
news anchor, but if that’s what the people
wanted, then Matt would be hosting China Uncensored.\h
That’s not what the people want. The people
want the beard. Wisdom springs from the roots
of this beard, Jon. Confucius had a beard.
Abraham Lincoln had a beard. Chuck Norris
has a beard.
I think you see my point here, Jon. And if
you don’t, I’m going to have to report
you to the National Radio and Television Administration
for hostile discrimination against my beard.\h
Thanks for your question. And thank you for
watching China Uncensored. Don’t forget
to like, subscribe, and hit the notification
bell so you'll know when we release the next
episode. Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.