China is sending a message to the US
It’s ready to fight for Taiwan
Plus the WHO’s China report is a disaster
That and more on this week’s China news
headlines
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
This week’s China news headlines.
The Chinese Communist Party has said for a
long time that it plans to invade Taiwan.
But when it does, the US will probably respond.
So now, the Chinese military is preparing
for that US intervention.
That’s according to Taiwan’s Deputy Defense
Minister.\h
This week, Chinese aircraft once again harassed
Taiwan.
That’s nothing new.
What is new is how they did it.\h
Radar readings showed different groups of
Chinese jets flew in a pincer pattern, surrounding
Taiwan on three sides.\h
And according to my favorite Chinese state-run
media, the Global Times, there’s a reason.
“The recent exercises show that the PLA
is...taking possible US and Japanese interventions
into consideration.”
Clearly, the flight plan of the Chinese jets
represented in yellow are to handle forces
coming from the US or Japan.
The Chinese fighters also happened to fly
over at the same time as the President of
Palau and a US diplomat were visiting Taiwan.
Wait, what if the Chinese Communist Party
is actually afraid of...Palau?
Maybe they are.
Because that US diplomat who traveled to Taiwan
was John Hennessy-Niland, the US Ambassador
to Palau.
And it’s the first time a US ambassador
has visited Taiwan in 40 years.
Which of course drew a “red line” warning
from China.\h
In other “angering China” news, last week
the US and Taiwan signed a Coast Guard Deal.
Which of course China denounced.
The deal means the US Coast Guard will be
working with Taiwan a little bit more.
It does kind of stretch the definition of
a Coast Guard.\h
Turns out “The U.S. has been deploying its
coast guard to the Western Pacific to help
allies enforce their claims in disputed waters.”
And the US Coast Guard even intercepted a
Chinese fishing boat illegally operating in
the waters of Palau in December.\h
Wait, Palau again?!
Be afraid, CCP.
Be very afraid.\h
But the latest group to offend the Chinese
Communist Party is: NASA.
They called Taiwan a country.
NASA has started a Send Your Name to Mars
campaign.
And in the “country” drop-down menu, you
could select Taiwan.
But obviously, the CCP is very sensitive and
this hurt its feelings.
So NASA changed it.
Now you select your “location” by picking
a country/region/territory.
NASA, if you’re going to cave to the Chinese
Communist Party, what are you going to do
when the aliens get here?
NASA has been banned from working with China’s
space program, since it’s run by the Chinese
military, and it could be a serious threat
to US national security.
And yet, recently NASA admitted they exchanged
data with China on Mars orbiters.
Ah well, it was a nice planet while it lasted.
But at least the US State Department is taking
a harder stance against the Chinese regime.
More on that after the break.
Welcome back.
The US State Department has released its latest
report on the state of human rights in China.
The state is: There are no human rights.
It calls the persecution of Uyghurs a genocide.
It also mentions allegations of forced organ
harvesting from Uyghurs and Falun Gong practitioners.
China responded by saying the hearts of all
Chinese citizens belong to the Party.\h
The State Department report comes a week after
Secretary of State Antony Blinken called on
NATO allies to join the US in countering China.
It also comes as the US successfully got its
allies to sanction China's abuse of Uyghurs.
And a Chinese professor has been caught on
camera revealing the secret to China’s success.
And by caught on camera, I mean he posted
this speech on Chinese TikTok.\h
“After reform and opening up, we let the
foreigners in.
They brought in their technology, their cars,
their money, their experience, their knowledge.
China couldn’t compete with the foreigners.
So what did the Chinese government do?
Let people start business partnerships with
foreigners.
And use the partnerships to learn to do it
on our own.”\h
“Now the factories, the equipment, the technology,
the patents, the products, the market, the
brands, are all ours.
The foreigners are completely gone.”\h
“So now our Yang Jiechi and Wang Li have
the status to be so tough in their talks with
the Americans.
“You are not qualified [laughter] to speak
to me like this.”
“For the last 40 years, all we’ve done
is plagiarize.
We’ve copied our way to the top.
We plagiarized wildly, copied wildly.
What intellectual property rights?
What patented technology?
We’ll get it first and deal with it later.”
That’s what the Communist Party calls forced
technology transfer.
We did a full episode about it, check it out.
Also, I’ve talked about this problem in
hundreds of China Uncensored episodes.
And yet, foreign companies keep throwing their
money and their intellectual property into
the China market.
What are you doing, Elon?!
The World Health Organization released its
report about the origin of the coronavirus.
And no one is happy.\h
Scientists say it only scratched the surface.
The White House says Americans deserve better
information.
The Wall Street Journal calls it the Wuhan
Whitewash.
That’s because the report is the result
of a close collaboration between the WHO and
the Chinese Communist Party.
And let’s just say, the Party might have
withheld some data.
Not that they have anything to hide.
A former head of the CDC says the coronavirus
mostly likely escaped from a Chinese lab,
accidentally.
But the WHO report says I don’t know, maybe
it came from animals?
Maybe not.
I don’t know.
We might as well have asked a Magic 8 Ball.\h
But as the WHO report came out, China also
announced they’re going to try to prove
it came from outside China.
You know what?
Let’s just all say it came from Taiwan.
Then China will either have to admit it began
in China, or admit that Taiwan is not a part
of China.
It’s perfect!
And after the break, guess which world leaders
now have the coronavirus?
Welcome back.
Both the president and prime minister of Pakistan
have contracted the coronavirus.
It was shortly after they both had their first
dose of China’s Sinopharm vaccine.
These are the things you sacrifice when you
ally with the Chinese Communist Party.
Sinopharm claims their vaccine is 79% effective,
although that has not been independently verified.
Until it is, I’ll believe it as much as
I believe the coronavirus data China gave
to the WHO.
The top Chinese diplomat in Brazil has taken
to Twitter, to mock Justin Trudeau.
As tempting as it is, I will not take the
Communist Party’s side on this.\h
The Chinese diplomat tweeted “Boy, your
greatest achievement is to have ruined the
friendly relations between China and Canada,
and have turned Canada into a running dog
of the US.
Spendthrift!!!”
Spendthrift?
There are way better insults than spendthrift.
Why not try Dunderhead?
I mean, Trudeau is a real Afternoon Farmer.
All hat and no cattle.
Am I right?
A real Gadabout.
He’s a galumphing milksop Rumbumptious sauce
box!
Now this may shock you, but a new study has
found that Chinese loans to developing nations
may pose some problems.
The study looked at 100 Chinese loan agreements
in 24 countries.
This is the first study of its kind.\h
Apparently, loans from the Chinese Communist
Party impose “unique conditions on borrowing
nations which could be giving Beijing undue
influence over their economic and foreign
policies.”
They also all contain confidentiality clauses
that prevent these countries from telling
the public what’s actually in the deal.
Transparency, with Chinese characteristics.
Meanwhile, in Hong Kong news, the Chinese
Communist Party has officially implemented
the terrible things we told you they were
going to implement.\h
Among other things, the Party now demands
that only people who demonstrate loyalty can
run for office, which makes it pretty much
impossible for pro-democracy politicians to
run ever again.
And as a fun bonus, the Hong Kong National
Security police will be the ones vetting potential
candidates for loyalty.\h
But most Hong Kong activists aren’t really
thinking about running for office right now,
because they’re just trying to stay out
of prison.
On Thursday, seven prominent activists were
convicted of unlawful assembly over a protest
back in 2019.
They included “Martin Lee, an 82-year-old
barrister known as the ‘father of democracy’
in Hong Kong; Jimmy Lai, 73, a media tycoon
and founder of the staunchly pro-democracy
Apple Daily newspaper; and Margaret Ng, 73,
a respected barrister and columnist.”
Clearly these people are a menace to society.
They each now face up to five years in prison.\h
And finally, the Chinese Foreign Ministry
loves to spread propaganda through Twitter.
Even though Twitter is banned in China.
Here’s an example.
After the US Congress passed a bill condemning
China for their treatment of Uyghurs,
China’s Foreign Ministry Tweeted that “Ethnic
minorities in China enjoy equal rights and
freedom in religion and culture.
China's ethnic policy is more successful!”
Yes, this is what I call a successful ethnic
policy.
Or when the US imposed visa restrictions on
Chinese officials over abuses in Tibet,
China’s Foreign Ministry again took to their
favorite propaganda tool, Twitter, to say
they would be imposing visa restrictions on
US personnel.
China’s Foreign Ministry Tweets about 100
times each month.
The tweets all have some propaganda goal,
whether it’s criticizing the West, or praising
the Chinese Communist Party.
And the CCP loves to use Twitter to troll
the rest of the world.\h
Twitter, of course, refuses to deplatform
this dangerous propaganda machine.
Which is fine, because it’s not Twitter’s
job to censor people.
But there’s a way you can fight back, and
use China’s propaganda against them.
Students for a Free Tibet has created this
website called Tweets for Tibet.
You can pledge, say 10 cents, per Foreign
Ministry tweet.
And the money goes to the Tibetan Freedom
Movement.
Every time China’s Foreign Ministry Tweets,
it raises more money to stand up to the Chinese
Communist Party.
Every Tweet they make, hurts themselves.
It’s a brilliant way to use the energy of
the CCP’s trolling against them.\h
Now to be clear: We don’t make any money
from this.
We just heard about it and thought it was
a great idea.
In fact, we signed China Uncensored up to
pledge $1 per Tweet.
So if you want to turn the CCP’s propaganda
against itself, check it out.
Go to TweetsForTibet.com.
And I’ll put a link in the description below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.