We all know America has the CIA.
Britain has MI6.
And Russia has the FSB.
But few people know about China’s three-letter
spy agency.
Hi, welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
Spy agencies.
A cloak and dagger world of mystique and mystery.
And with a little help from Hollywood, plenty
of glamor.
“It doesn’t bother you to kill all those
people?
“Well I wouldn’t be very good at my job
if it did.”
We all know about the spy agencies from Great
Britain...
and from the US
—or at least we think we do,
based on totally accurate Hollywood movies.
But China’s three-letter spy agency
may be the espionage world’s best kept secret.
It’s called the MSS—
the Ministry of State Security.
But whereas the is CIA
is restricted to spying outside the US—
which it...always sticks to—
the MSS doesn’t have that restriction.
It can spy anywhere!
Total freedom.
For the spies,
not for anyone else in China.
The MSS made headlines last December
after it detained two Canadians in China
on suspicion of “endangering national security.”
It was a move widely seen as retaliation
for Canada’s arrest of Huawei’s finance
chief
Meng Wanzhou.
Now for all the secret cloak and dagger stuff
that three-letter spy agencies get up to,
some, like the CIA,
can be surprisingly transparent.
Look, they have a website!
With career opportunities
And a library
And a Kids’ Zone
And an advice column?!
Anyway, you’re probably thinking, Chris,
having a website with job postings
seems like a low bar for transparency.
And that’s true.
Which makes it even more incredible
that China’s MSS doesn’t have a website
at all.
And it doesn’t have any publicly listed
contacts
or spokespeople either.
But at least it has a logo we can look to
for insight.
Let’s see:
Hammer and sickle.
So the Communist Party is obviously the top
priority.
Below that, the Forbidden City,
which means the government.
And at the bottom the Great Wall of China.
Which means...
repelling Mongolians?
Ok, I’m still working on it.
But the fact that the MSS
puts the Chinese Communist Party first,
that’s been established.
According to this report by China expert Peter
Mattis,
“China’s civilian intelligence and security
agencies are...
an integral tool for the preservation of
the power of the Chinese Communist Party.”
And since the MSS is “empowered to arrest
and to operate inside and outside China”,
it can used to help crush
dangerous subversive elements inside the country.
Like people who wear robes.
Or people who wear skull caps.
Or people who meditate.
But we still don’t know that much about
the MSS.
The only ad ever made public for a job at
the MSS
got posted on the career website of a Chinese
university.
But apparently that was a mistake,
because it was taken down immediately.
If you have good vision,
a “well-proportioned physique”
and are tall enough, the MSS wants you!
The post was for looking for grad students
with foreign language skills.
All sorts of foreign language skills.
Including Uighur,
which is spoken by the Muslim people
of China’s Xinjiang region.
Which, by the way, is, um,
absolutely not a *foreign* language,
it’s um, part of Chinese language since
ancient times.
Anyway, the MSS wants people who can speak
Uighur, ok?
Maybe they’ll help with the detention camps
in Xinjiang.
As one million Uighurs have been locked up
there
in re-education centers.
"They grabbed me and led me to another room
where they put me into a metal (chair-like)
device.
In this metal device you stand still and cannot
move.
Your arms are secured by the metal parts
and your chest is exposed.
After six hours in this device my whole body
ached.
Standing becomes uncomfortable after 10 minutes,
the iron rubs against your skin,
and after six hours the pain becomes very
strong."
Wow, that really makes you think:
Why would you need Uighur language skills
to torture people?
By the way, the MSS is also looking for people
who speak Tibetan, Mongolian, and Kazakh languages.
Anyway, another must-have skill
in the accidentally-posted job ad
was specialized knowledge in “information
security.”
You know, something that could be put to good
use
in missions of stealing other country’s
state secrets.
And commercial secrets.
Like in the case of two alleged MSS spies
Zhu Hua and Zhang Jianguo—
who were indicted in December
for cybercrimes in the United States.
The two alleged spies are accused of computer
hacking
of a wide range of American government agencies
and corporations,
including the Navy and NASA.
"The extent and types of data stolen by the
defendants
is shocking and outrageous.
As the deputy attorney general and the director
noted the defendants are alleged to have been
members
of a hacking group operating in China called
APT 10.
As alleged, these defendants engaged in their
hacking campaign
in association with the Chinese Ministry of
State Security.”
At a 2007 MSS recruiting event at a Chinese
university,
recruiters said they wanted applicants for
jobs
that promised “lots of travel”,
“tiring” work that was “mostly not dangerous”
and female students were basically not wanted.
Another closely guarded MSS secret revealed:
they’re not an equal opportunity employer.
Also, with a monthly salary of $600
and having to sign a fair chunk of your life
away
with a minimum 10-year contract,
the pay kinda sucks.
But the MSS spying efforts against the US
got an even more embarrassing outing
when the deputy director of the agency, Yanjun
Xu,
was arrested in Belgium and extradited to
the US.
He now faces charges of stealing trade secrets
from American aerospace companies.
It was a big deal also because it’s the
first time ever
that a Chinese official was hauled to the
US
on corporate espionage allegations.
According to this article,
the MSS deputy director allegedly lured scientists
from three American aerospace companies to
China
by inviting them to give talks at a conference.
He then allegedly offered them cash for blueprints.
But honestly,
I’m just distracted by that amazing headline,
“Oh no Xi didn’t!”
Definitely my pick
for best news headline of the year.
Anyway, former CIA head Michael Hayden
describes how this kind of MSS spying works.
“No one comes out and says:
‘Hey, here’s 50 million dollars,
you wanna spy for the Chinese?’
You begin a relationship
and then you begin to develop that relationship.
From that ‘I love your work,
can I read the paper?’
And then six months later.
I’m really feeling bad,
this has been so wonderful for me.
Tell you what,
let’s establish a consultancy relationship.
Let me begin to pay you.
You see where this is going, right?”
And speaking of relationships,
the MSS is no stranger to that staple of spycraft—
the honey trap.
They may not have many female agents,
but when they do...
For example, accused MSS agent Katrina Leung.
The FBI code named her “Parlor Maid.”
Parlor Maid was initially a high value FBI
informant
before they realized that she had provided
her FBI handler
“with misinformation for more than a decade.”
In 2003, she was indicted—
but defended herself.
“America is my home and I cherish it.
I know we will answer the charges
and that my name will be cleared.”
Katrina Leung was half right.
Her case was initially dismissed on a technicality,
but she later pleaded guilty to lesser charges.
And the honey trap part?
She “was a double agent who was sleeping
with not one,
but two, of the [FBI’s] top China agents.”
This is former FBI agent James Smith, one
of those, um,
“top China agents” she successfully honey
trapped.
He was charged with gross negligence
for giving her access to classified FBI documents.
According to the book “Tiger trap:
America’s secret spy war with China,”
Smith allegedly had a 20-year-long
romantic affair with Parlor Maid,
and apparently brought sensitive documents
to their...um...meetings.
But just how serious is the secret spy war
between America’s spy agencies and China’s
MSS?
"The threats we face have never been more
severe
or more pervasive
or more potentially damaging to our national
security.
And no country poses a broader
more severe long term threat
to our nation's economy
and cyber infrastructure than China.
China's goal simply put is to replace the
U.S.
as the world's leading superpower
and they're using illegal methods to get there."
So, yeah, you should maybe think twice
when a guy from China tells you
he really enjoyed your research paper
about supersonic engine design,
and would love for you to speak at his conference.
Or that pretty Chinese woman
who says she’d would love to show you her...
top secret intelligence documents.
So what do you think about China’s secretive
spy agency,
the MSS?
Leave your comments below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.