On this episode of China Uncensored,
China’s pouring money into its team of 16
in Europe.
Just to make sure that when it really counts,
somebody’s going to know which way to kick
the ball.
Wait, no, no!
Not that...way.
Hi, welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
You know, international politics and sports
are a lot alike.
You train hard, play your heart out,
and in the end…
the team with the most money wins.
Obviously everyone wants their team to be
the best.
And over the years, Europe has produced lots
of champions.
“Italy! World Cup champions...”
“Spain are the kings of world football.”
“That is it! Germany are the champions of
the world!”
Europe has also produced champions of human
rights.
“We recommend an international investigation
into forced organ harvesting in China,”
And more than once,
Europe was willing to address
one of the most difficult human rights issues
in China.
In July 2016, the European Parliament,
which represents 28 countries,
passed this declaration on stopping organ
harvesting\hfrom prisoners of conscience in
China.
And even before that,
Parliament passed this resolution,
which “expresses its deep concern
over the persistent and credible reports of
systematic,
state‑sanctioned organ harvesting” in
China.
And they called for the EU to investigate.
Well, to make sure this kind of embarrassing
exposé of their human rights problems
doesn’t happen again,
the Chinese Communist Party
is going on a spending spree.
To see if some players on team Europe
could “accidentally” fumble the ball sometimes.
Like Greece.
In our episode from December,
Shelley talked about how while the rest of
Europe
was busy squeezing Greece,
China showed up with cargo containers full
of cash.
And in a move that
was definitely in no way related,
Greece blocked an EU statement
on China’s human rights...
one that the EU usually makes every year.
Greece’s European pals were not impressed.
“The global human rights agenda
is best served when the EU speaks with one
voice,”
an EU spokesperson said.
Which is diplomat-speak for,
“Hey Greece, that was not cool.”
But China loved it.
So much, in fact,
that it wants to buy a whole team of players
like Greece.
It’s even got a name: 16 + 1.
That is, 16 Central and Eastern European nations,
plus one owner-slash-manager with deep pockets—
China!
11 of those 16 countries
are on the field with the EU,
and 5 are on the bench.
Team 16 is already getting lots of criticism.
Not just in Brussels—
the informal capital of the EU—
but across the entire continent.
One problem,
according to an unnamed European diplomat,
is that China is using Team 16
to change laws in Europe.
“Some of them are touching on
areas where there are already initiatives
between the EU and China.
And we only see the tip of the iceberg.”
Ah…the “tip of the iceberg.”
Don’t worry.
Icebergs are probably nothing to worry about.
But that warning seems lost on some countries.
“In Hungary Chinese Investment
is hailed as the ‘Eastward Opening.’
Serbian authorities see it as the glue
in a ‘reliable friendship,’
while the Polish government describes it as
a ‘tremendous opportunity.’”
An Eastward Opening?
Oh, I think I see one…go…go….oh…no!
That wasn’t supposed to happen.
Anyway, it’s obvious why
Team 16 wants China.
China is investing billions of dollars
in building infrastructure that will hopefully
spur other economic development in their countries.
In fact, since 2012,
Chinese companies have announced
15 billion dollars worth of investment.
It’s now all being wrapped into
China’s One Belt, One Road Initiative.
And roads are getting built.
In 2014,
Chinese state-owned power company and bank
agreed to build a 1.5 billion dollar to highway
in Bosnia.
And a year later, a different Chinese company
signed a 3.6 billion dollar deal
to build a highway between
Albania and Montenegro.
These are glorious, heady times.
At least until it’s time to repay
those billions of dollars in loans.
But they’ll cross that bridge
when they come to it.
Hopefully.
Of course,
the Chinese Communist Party is thrilled.
Because it stands to buy 16 players in Europe,
each willing to take one for the team.
And that starts to add up.
Like with Hungary—
which has been hungry for Chinese investment.
Last March, Hungary blocked an EU joint letter
that would have denounced the torture
of jailed rights lawyers in China.
And in July 2015,
Greece, Hungary, Croatia and Slovenia
managed to take out a direct reference to
China
in an EU statement about a court ruling
that struck down China’s legal claims
over the South China Sea.
Now that’s the team spirit!
Knocking some of the teeth out of
Europe’s “one voice” policy on China
is definitely part of the plan,
say EU officials.
“China’s strategy in Europe is divide
and rule,”
said Franck Proust,
a French Member of European Parliament.
“And it’s working because the 27 EU member
states
are incapable to remain in solidarity with
each other.”
But the bigger danger is that China could
use its influence to change laws inside Europe.
Already, China is suspected of using
its money and influence to change
an important EU initiative—
that is, EU-wide screening
of foreign investments.
The push for screenings comes as Chinese investment
skyrockets.
Which also makes countries
more dependent on Chinese money,
and less eager to criticize the Chinese regime.
But “China’s lobbying has already proved
effective
in diluting the proposed review process.”
Basically, the screening process
originally would have allowed the EU
to block Chinese investments
that threatened national security—
like CFIUS does in the United States.
But in the diluted version,
it merely “allows EU institutions
to give guidance.”
That’s like the TSA changing
its airport screening policy to a suggestion.
“We, uh, suggest that you take your laptop
out of your bag and walk through this metal
detector
and—and hey, hey!
Get back here, guys!
I was suggesting it for everyone’s own good!”
I mean, I’d like fewer airport screenings
too—
unless I found out the group lobbying for
it was ISIS.
So anyway,
the Chinese regime has made some progress
at weakening the power of the EU.
Some pro-EU politicians are worried
that Team 16 countries might use their
strong bilateral ties with China as leverage
with which to fight against Brussels.
And that has Sigmar Gabriel,
Germany’s foreign minister, very concerned.
He says, “If we do not succeed
in developing a single strategy towards China,
then China will succeed in dividing Europe.”
If true, this is bad news for fans of
a strong, united Europe.
Especially as the Chinese regime
takes advantage of Brexit
to further weaken the EU.
Pro-EU enthusiasts see
long-lasting peace and prosperity
as a major benefit of unification—
a benefit that’s shared among friends.
But, when it comes to high-stakes politics,
it may be like former Governor of Texas
Ann Richards famously said:
“In politics your enemies can’t hurt you,
but your friends will kill you.”
Especially if your friends are the kind of
people
who like buying soccer teams...
...and torturing dissidents.
So what do you think about China’s investment
in Europe?
Is China building a winning team,
or just making sure when push comes to shove,
it’s got someone to help them score?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Keep a close eye on
China’s checkbook diplomacy.
Visit ChinaUncensored.tv.
We upload full half hour episodes
you won’t see on YouTube.
Learn about interference from the Chinese
regime,
even before world leaders do!
ChinaUncensored.tv.