On this episode of China Uncensored,
nothing speaks to the glory of Tibetan Buddhism
like core socialist values.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
You know, no one cares as much about religion
as the officially atheist Chinese Communist
Party.
That is, they care about getting involved
with religion.
Whether it’s taking down Christian crosses,
banning reincarnation without government permission,
or supporting Tibetan Buddhism...
Wait, what?
Just last week,
the second highest figure in Tibetan Buddhism
held a 12-day ritual that hasn’t been performed
basically since a failed Tibetan uprising
50 years ago.
It’s called the Kalachakra ritual.
Kalachakra means wheel of time,
I learned from state-run Xinhua
that is reporting on it for
some reason.
The ritual is performed to activate dormant
enlightenment
for the 100,000 people,
including thousands of monks,
who were apparently allowed to freely gather
to practice Tibetan Buddhism.
It’s so extraordinary, you just gotta capture
the moment!
The ceremony was conducted by the Panchen
Lama,
basically the number two guy in Tibetan Buddhism
after the Dalai Lama.
As state-run CCTV puts it,
“The 11th Panchen Lama is the spiritual
leader of Buddhism in Tibet.”
In other words this guy is a big deal.
No, seriously.
Xinhua even interviewed a living Buddha about
it.
“Although the panchen Lama is only 26 years
old,
he has become a very great master in Tibetan
Buddhism.”
Wow, if a Living Buddha says this Panchen
Lama guy is so great on state-run media,
you know, there’s probably something really
wrong here.
And you’d be right.
This guy is not the real Panchen Lama
that is, if you go by the traditions of Buddhism
instead of communism.
The way it works in Tibetan Buddhism
is the Panchen Lama helps find the reincarnation
of the Dalai Lama and vice versa.
The previous Panchen Lama died in 1989.
Six years later,
the Dalai Lama named this boy as the next
one.
But the Chinese regime said,
naw, this is the guy
and the Dalai Lama’s chosen one conveniently
disappeared
along with his family
and haven’t seen seen since.
Don’t worry,
Chinese officials say they’re fine.
So now, the Communist Party loves to bring
this guy out
and show how much the Party supports Tibetan
Buddhism
and how much their appointed lama is beloved
and respected.
And what’s his message to Tibetans?
“I did not waste time studying over the
past two decades.”
That’s right, Tibetans,
stay poor and uneducated!
Great message!
What else you got?
“Core values of socialism,
such as harmony, honesty, and equality,
have their corresponding contents in Sutra.”
Ohhh hoooo man.
Yeah.
So how does the Dalai Lama feel about this?
Well, he doesn’t want it to happen to the
next Dalai Lama.
That is, he doesn’t want the Communist Party
to pick his successor.
That may be why he said he the lineage of
the Dalai Lama should end with him.
More specifically, he said,
“There is no guarantee that some stupid
Dalai Lama won’t come next,
who will disgrace himself or herself.
That would be very sad.
So, much better that a centuries-old tradition
should cease at the time of a quite popular
Dalai Lama.”
To which the Chinese Communist Party responded,
no you have to reincarnate.
Why do they care?
Don’t they consider the current Dalai Lama
a dangerous separatist?
Well, yes, but when he dies,
their Panchen Lama gets to pick the next Dalai
Lama.
And don’t be surprised if that one also
makes comparisons
between core socialist values and Tibetan
scripture.
So what do you think about Beijing’s Panchen
Lama
and the state-sponsored Kalachakra ceremony?
Leave your comments below.
And please, share this video with anyone who
may still think
the Chinese regime has eased up on religion.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you in the bardo.