bjbj,(,( On this episode of China Uncensored,
Thousand of Dead Pigs Found in Shanghai s
Drinking Water Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I m your host Chris Chappell. Some people
think, China will be free when pigs fly? Well,
how about when 6000 dead pigs go floating
down the river? Yes, take a look at one of
the biggest cities in the world s second largest
economy. Thousands of dead pigs have been
washing up along the Huangpu River outside
of Shanghai. Huangpu is of course Chinese
for yellow poo. Waves of pig corpses have
been washing up on the waves since late last
week. Okay, sure, it looks like some kind
of biblical plague. But I mean, it s not like
the rivers of China are turning red, right?
Now I know what you re thinking, looking at
all this water is sure making me thirsty!
Can I get a drink of that? Well you can. Since
this is one of Shanghai s major water sources
of drinking water, some people were a little
concerned. Needless so. Authorities say the
water is perfectly safe to drink. Sure it
contains a type of pig virus that Purdue University
researchers discovered has been mutating into
more deadly forms, but it doesn t affect humans.
So it s perfectly fine to drink the water
that 6000 dead pigs have been floating in.
And they say you can t trust Chinese media.
So where did all these pigs come from? Well,
no one is one hundred percent sure, but they
think that pig farms upstream in Zhejiang's
Jiaxing City were dumping the corpses of pigs
that died of disease after they were told
they couldn t sell that meat to the public.
That ll teach authorities not to tell people
what they can and can t sell. So needless
to say, the bloated, diseased, decomposing
corpses of 6000 pigs is not lending Shanghai
a particularly pleasing smell. But let me
again remind you this is perfectly safe to
drink. You know, I hear there s a new children
s rhyme going around Shanghai these days.
Row, row, row your boat gently down the stream,
merrily, merrily, merrily, did you hear a
pig scream? So would you ever drink water
that had 6000 dead pigs in it? Email me at
china uncensored at ntdtv dot com and tell
me what you think. Personally, I would only
drink water that had 100 dead pigs in it,
tops. If you liked the episode, please click
like and comment below, follow me on Twitter
and like China Uncensored on Facebook. And
as always, be sure to subscribe for more episodes
of China Uncensored. I m Chris Chappell, see
you next time. [Content_Types].xml #!MB ;c=1
_rels/.rels theme/theme/themeManager.xml sQ\}#
theme/theme/theme1.xml G$$DA : BR \{i5@R V*[_X
,l\Y Ssd+r] 5\|E Vky- V4Ej 6NGU s?^V *<")QH
@\&> 7;wP EBU` 5VD GGHPXNT,
/M,W m2iU [[v _Xtl theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.rels
6?$Q K(M&$R(.1 [Content_Types].xmlPK _rels/.relsPK
theme/theme/themeManager.xmlPK theme/theme/theme1.xmlPK
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.relsPK
<a:clrMap xmlns:a="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/main"
bg1="lt1" tx1="dk1" bg2="lt2" tx2="dk2" accent1="accent1"
accent2="accent2" accent3="accent3" accent4="accent4"
accent5="accent5" accent6="accent6" hlink="hlink"
folHlink="folHlink"/> jJ|! Chris Normal.dotm
Chris Microsoft Macintosh Word PICT%l |J^h
kZo\{g9^ g91^ g9g9Z kZg9c kZg9Z g9g9c kZg9^
kZg9g9Z g9g9kZ g9kZw o\{o\{w kZkZg9g9o\{s o\{g9o\{o\
kZkZNs^ g9g9^ g9kZc g9g9c o\{g9o\
kZg9g9c o\{g9c g9&s g9g9Z g9g9c g9o\{kZ^ g9g9s
kZg9g9c g9g9s g9kZg9g9^ o\{g9g9 g9kZs o\{kZo\{^
o\{g9w o\{o\{s kZg9kZ kZo\{w kZkZs o\{o\{g9s o\{g9c
g9g9c kZg9kZg9kZc g9kZ o\{o\{s o\{kZs g9o\
o\{o\{s o\{o\{kZo\{s kZo\{c o\{g9s g9g9Z g9kZkZg9g9s
g9g9o\{g9s g9g9kZc o\{o\{w g9kZZ kZg9R g9kZ 5g9s
g9kZg9c g9g9c kZkZo\{kZc g9o\{c g9kZ o\{o\{s o\{o\{s
g9o\{g9g9s kZo\{g9w g9kZZ kZg9 o\{kZ g9kZs o\{kZo\{w
o\{kZo\{w kZo\
o\{kZs g9g9c o\{o\{w kZ^ g9kZc @g9R NsNsZ o\{NsV
g9NsV kZg9R .g9Z g9o\{c kZg9Z g9kZg9^ o\{g9c
kZ7s o\{o\{kZs kZkZo\{kZw kZg9o\{kZo\{g9o\{kZkZ
o\{g9o\{^ kZkZc kZkZo\{o\{w kZkZc o\{g9kZkZ kZo\{kZkZs
o\{4g9w kZkZo\{o\{s g9o\{kZkZs o\{g9kZc kZg9\{ o\{kZs
o\{g9kZs g9o\{o\{c kZg9o\{s kZg9s kZo\{s o\{g9kZs
kZg9R o\{kZg9s g9o\{g9 o\{o\{w o\{o\{kZg9g9s o\{g9o\{s
kZo\{ o\{kZw o\{kZkZc kZg9g9o\{o\{^ kZo\{g9c o\{g9g9w
o\{o\{g9c o\{g9g9c o\{kZo\{g9^ kZo\{ /g9Z o\{g9^
o\{o\{ kZg9kZZ g9o\{g9Z kZkZ\{ -o\{kZZ o\{o\{V kZg9c
o\{g9V o\{g9Z g9g9R g9kZkZ^ o\{kZg9g9o\{c g9kZc
kZg9c o\{g9^ o\{o\{w g9kZg9\{ %kZkZo\{c kZo\{s kZo\{o\{c
o\{g9\{ g9kZo\{kZkZo\{c kZg9s o\{kZo\{s kZo\{g9o\
g9g9c kZg9g9 g9g9s g9g9w g9g9o\{kZkZg9g9kZo\{g9kZg9s
o\{g9o\{kZw o\{o\
o\{o\{s o\{kZs o\{o\{ o\{kZw kZkZ\{ g9o\{o\{g9g9w g9g9c
kZkZc g9kZ g9g9o\{c g9kZ kZo\{c kZg9c o\{kZg9^
kZkZc NskZV g9o\{ g9kZg9g9s g9g9^ g9kZ^ g9kZc
g9!kZg9c g9g9kZg9c o\{g9s g9kZV kZo\{g9c o\{o\{kZo\{s
kZo\{kZw o\{o\{w o\{kZs kZo\{w kZo\{w o\{o\{w o\{o\
o\{kZs o\{g9c kZg9o\{c o\{kZg9c o\{g9c g9o\{o\{c
kZo\{o\{kZkZg9g9 o\{g9c Bg9Z g9kZV kZkZc g9g9Z
o\{g9V o\{g9Z g9g9Z g9kZc kZg9s kZkZV o\{g9c
g9g9c kZo\{ o\{kZ o\{o\{s o\{o\{s o\{g9o\{s g9kZw
kZo\{o\{g9s g9o\{w o\{o\{w g9g9kZo\{c g9o\{g9c kZg9kZg9s
kZg9Z g9g9kZo\{g9g9kZkZg9s g9kZkZs g9g9o\{ Title
Microsoft Word 97-2004 Document NB6W Word.Document.8