On this episode of China Uncensored,
How do you celebrate a Communist takeover?
By going on vacation and buying lots of souvenirs!
The Chinese military wants you to know how
awesome it is.
And finally, the most expensive bowl in the
world.
It's worth its weight in Golden Grahams.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I'm your
host Chris Chappell.
The Chinese Communist Party knows how to get
on people's good side:
indoctrinate them from birth.
And also, give them time off work.
This week was Golden Week.
An eight-day national holiday
that kicks off with the anniversary of when
the Chinese Communist Party
liberated the people of China...
from their money...
and their lives.
This week also includes the Mid-Autumn Festival,
a traditional Chinese holiday celebrating
Chinese princess
Chang-e and her voyage to the moon.
Making it part of China's sacred territory
since ancient times.
And Golden Week isn't just about taking time
off work.
It's about travel.
700 million people,
half of China's population,
are hitting the road,
and spending about 90 billion dollars on it.
Did I mention half of all of China is travelling?
This is what that looks like.
From scenic spots,
to train stations.
Or just taking a selfie with that guy who
killed 100 million people.
And then there's that tourist spot north of
Shanghai
where folks can watch pigs dive into a river!
That's all it is.
Time to move on, folks.
And among the 700 million Chinese people on
the move,
more than six million will be going overseas.
The top three tourist destinations are Thailand,
Japan, and the US.
South Korea, however,
is no longer the hot tourist destination it
use to be.
I know what you're thinking,
but it's not because the Korean 24K gold snail
face masks
aren't as good as they used to be.
It's because the Chinese regime
is discouraging citizens from going there,
because they're super mad that the South Korean
government
installed that US missile defense system.
There's been a 20% drop in Chinese tourists
in the first half of the year.
But even during the holiday week,
some people were still hard at work.
Like this drug smuggler.
Police busted him carrying 99 grams of methamphetamine.
He was surprised after being arrested,
telling the police:
"I had thought that you all would be resting
because of the long holiday
and that I could take advantage of Golden
Week
to move some drugs."
How stupid can you be?
What, is this guy on meth or something?
And you know who else still had to work?
Apparently the people of Xinjiang.
Civil servants, government employees
and some teachers and students,
"had to cancel their holiday plans and work
through October--
including weekends--
while others were ordered to attend ideology
classes."
Yes, there's no better way to maintain peace
and order in an unstable region,
by forcing them to watch propaganda films
over the holidays.
Then again, I guess I do watch Independence
Day every Fourth of July.
And in a similar vein,
the Chinese Communist Party knows what people
really want
to do on their Golden Week Holiday.
Watch a documentary on state-run TV
about how awesome the Chinese military is.
Granted, the PLA might not be able to fight
off aliens.
But there's nothing like an eight-episode
documentary
produced by the Political Work Department
of the Central Military Commission
to get me excited for my Golden Week vacation.
It's better than a movie!
At least, a movie produced by the American
running dogs.
China only allows 34 foreign films a year
to be played inside China.
And those that do,
only get to keep 25% of their box office revenue.
Ideally.
But the Motion Picture Association of America
just audited ticket sales from China
and found they were coming up a little short.
"The audit found that the Chinese ticket sales
from 2016
were underrepresented by about 9%,
amounting to roughly $40 million in lost revenue."
But despite getting stiffed by China at the
Box Office,
Hollywood considers China a critical market.
Especially since in the US,
people seem to care less and less.
China is the second largest movie market in
the world
and can turn a flop into a success.
Take Transformers: The Last Knight.
In the US, it only earned 45 million dollars
on its opening weekend.
In China, 120 million.
But hey, even 45 million dollars in the US
isn't bad.
You can do a lot with 45 million dollars.
Like buy a 900-year-old Chinese bowl.
And still have money left over
to buy a giant house in the suburbs.
Or a tiny condo in Manhattan.
This bowl comes from the Northern Song Dynasty.
But...I still think it was a bit overpriced.
I mean, you could have gotten this one
from Bloomingdale's for just $12.99.
And then had even more money left over
to buy a huge mansion in the 'burbs
with swimming pools, tennis courts,
and a 12 car garage.
Or a 1-bedroom condo in Manhattan.
But supposedly what makes this Song Dynasty
bowl so great
is the ice crackle style used to make it.
That's where cracks form during the cooling
process.
I wish I had known about that in my high school
ceramics class.
Instead of getting an F,
I could have been a millionaire.
900 years from now.
What do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
You know how I'd spend my Golden Week?
By staying indoors and watching
full half hour episodes of China Uncensored
for free,
at ChinaUncensored.tv.
The best part is,
unlike Youtube,
our website's not censored in China.
Don't tell anyone.
And for your next National Day celebration,
go to ChinaUncensored.tv.