On this episode of China Uncensored,
If you go to a Chinese pop concert, hide your
face.
Trump wants you to know that everything with
China will work out fine.
Or maybe it won’t.
And, going to watch the new Avengers movie
in China?
One theater has a special tip for all the
ladies.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
China has gotten one step closer
to putting an unmanned spacecraft
on the far side of the moon.
On Monday, they launched a relay satellite.
It won’t actually land on the moon,
but it will help with the landing process
for a future craft.
China’s military-led space program wants
to be
the first to land on the far side of the moon.
It’s sometimes also called the dark side
because
that side always faces away from the Earth.
The new relay satellite would help solve the
issue of communication.
So, if China does manage to make it to the
dark side of the moon
later this year,
they’ll be the first to get a clear view
of when the Decepticons attack.
But Chinese technological breakthroughs
aren’t just going to the dark side of the
moon.
The dark side of technology has also arrived
in China.
Chinese authorities just arrested
a dangerous fugitive by the name of Yu
at the concert of famous Hong Kong singer
Jacky Cheung,
whose nickname is the God of Songs.
How did police find the man in that crowd?
Simple.
Facial recognition software picked out his
face
as his entered the venue.
Local police wrote on their WeChat account,
“Wearing a smile as he came to see his idol,
he hadn’t realized that he was already being
watched.”
Hahaha.
Haha.
Ha.
That’s not creepy.
They’d been watching for him for 3 years.
And get this—this is the third time in two
months
that a fugitive was caught this way...
at a Jacky Cheung concert.
Wait a minute.
Is Jacky Cheung a secret crimefighter
known as the God of Songs
whose superpower is luring criminals to his
concerts?
That would explain so much.
So what was the heinous crime Yu committed
that got him arrested at the concert?
He owed almost 20,000 dollars...
on unpaid potatoes.
That’s no small potatoes.
Ah ha ha.
Wait,
what use could anyone have for 20,000 dollars
worth of potatoes?
Perhaps it’s the God of Songs’ archnemesis...
Chairman Potato Head?
Anyway, these kinds of arrests using facial
recognition
will happen more and more.
The Chinese Communist Party has invested heavily
in AI-powered surveillance cameras.
Within three years,
they plan to add 400 million new cameras
capable of recognizing and tracking citizens.
They will also be able to identify your car
and your friends.
Here’s another fun fact about China’s
facial recognition surveillance program.
They’ve started installing it in schools
behind the blackboard
to see how much kids are paying attention,
tracking every movement of students’ pupils.
I know, that sounds disturbing,
especially if you’ve ever fallen asleep
in class.
But don’t worry,
the system can be fooled.
In other news,
Burkina Faso has severed diplomatic relations
with Taiwan,
reminding the world that Burkina Faso still
exists.
The US and China are continuing trade talks.
Last week, Liu He, China’s vice premier
and top economic adviser to Xi Jinping,
met with US President Donald Trump.
Liu gave a good presentation.
According to Larry Kudlow,
the head of the National Economic Council,
“President Trump was very engaged.”
I bet.
One of the main issues was the nearly 400
billion dollar trade deficit
the United States has with China.
President Trump wants that reduced by half.
US officials say China has proposed achieving
that by buying more US goods.
But it seems that President Trump doubts the
trade talks will work out.
"Will that be successful?
I tend to doubt it.
The reason I doubt it is because China has
become very spoiled.
The European Union has become very spoiled.
Other countries have become very spoiled,
because they always got 100 percent
of whatever they wanted from the United States.
But we can't allow that to happen anymore."
He also tweeted this week that the trade deal
would need a different structure to succeed.
Speaking of different structures,
President Trump has cancelled the Singapore
summit
with North Korean leader Kim Jong Un.
That comes after North Korea had made
increasingly harsh statements,
including one that threatened a “nuclear
showdown”
and called Vice President Mike Pence a “political
dummy.”
To which the White House strenuously objected,
because quote,
“only President Trump gets to call Mike
Pence a political dummy.”
Last week, Trump had already thrown some doubt
on the summit,
while maybe possibly blaming China for things
going wrong.
I think things may have changed a little bit
when they met with China a second time,
as you know Kim Jong Un had a second meeting
with China,
which was a little bit of a surprise meeting...
but there has been a big difference since
they had
this second meeting with President Xi ,
with that said,
my attitude is, whatever happens, happens.
Could there be trouble in bromance paradise?
Only time will tell.
Avengers: Infinity War.
It’s called that because it will go on forever.
And it’s out in China!
And one theater in Inner Mongolia had a very
special message
for the ladies in the audience.
“You should do nothing but eat your popcorn
silently.
Don’t mess with your man while he is worshipping
the silver screen.
If your man gets really excited while watching
the movie,
please pretend to be interested.
And based on his facial expressions,
you should say things like ‘yes’ and ‘totally.”
But before you go crying “sexism,” yes,
there was a message to the men in the audience
as well.
“Don’t try to explain the characters to
your women
in the middle of the movie.
They won’t be able to recognize them
just like you can’t differentiate between
lipsticks.
Get them some popcorn, soda,
and snacks to keep their mouths full.”
A Communist utopia!
And finally, Zhao Kangmin has passed away
at the age of 81.
You may not know his name,
but I bet you know the thing he’s famous
for.
No, he wasn’t a terracotta warrior.
He was the archaeologist who discovered the
terracotta warriors.
Or more accurately,
he pieced together tiny fragments of pottery,
until they formed the terracotta warriors.
The Terracotta Warriors were made some 2,000
years ago
by Emperor Qin Shihuang,
the first emperor to unite China,
and they’ve become perhaps one of the most
recognizable symbols of ancient Chinese heritage.
But get this, at first, Zhao and his colleagues
were afraid of announcing the find.
Because it was during the middle of the Cultural
Revolution,
where across China, Mao Zedong had directed
people to destroy anything from China’s
cultural past.
Fortunately for everyone,
the terracotta warriors were treated better
than all those teachers and intellectuals
who were killed.
Maybe that’s because Mao Zedong admired
Emperor Qin who made them.
Qin was the emperor who himself bragged about
killing hundreds of Confucian scholars
for having traditional beliefs.
Fortunately, his dynasty only lasted 15 years.
And before we wrap up, here’s a question
from…
Jeppe Christensen
If China is to get rid of the ccp
and become a democracy,
and maybe unite with Taiwan again,
where do you see the push for change to come
from in China?
Interesting question!
This is something I’ve thought a lot about.
One scenario that could happen is that the
CCP
would start to lose control of some of the
southern provinces of China.
Particularly Guangdong and Guangxi.
Those are Cantonese speaking provinces,
which aligns them culturally and linguistically
with Hong Kong.
And we know Hong Kongers love to dissent.
Plus, Guangdong is where Shenzhen is—
the city that manufactures all your electronics.
As the Communist Party loses its grip in power,
it would focus its energies on maintaining
control over Beijing
and the surrounding regions.
Now this doesn’t have to be violent revolution.
In fact, across the world,
the vast majority of political change in the
past two decades
has come through nonviolent resistance.
In fact, the data shows nonviolent resistance
is actually more effective.
But of course that’s just one way things
could go down.
Maybe Presistator Xi Jinping does such a good
job,
they decide to just get rid of the Communist
Party
and let him rule for life.
Thanks for you question.
Remember, if you want to leave a question
for me,
sign up to support China Uncensored on the
website Patreon!
Link is below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Thanks for watching.
Want to make China Uncensored even better?
Of course you do.
Click this orange button to support China
Uncensored on Patreon.
Join our 50-Cent Army.
Click here to see what cool perks you’ll
get.