On this episode of China Uncensored,
China will do anything to "meat" market demand.
Including...
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I'm your host Chris Chappell.
If you're like me,
you want answers to the questions that matter
most.
"Where's the beef?"
Where's the beef indeed.
If you answered,
"On a farm,"
haha, that's so cute.
No, the beef is in Tianjin, China,
where the world's largest animal cloning facility
is under construction.
Chinese genetics company BoyaLife wants to
be the first to take animal cloning to an
industrial scale.
BoyaLife's 31 million dollar cloning plant
will go into production in 2016.
It will start by producing 100,000 cloned
cows per year,
eventually reaching one million.
Holy Cow!
Their goal is to provide 5 percent of the
meat eaten in China.
You know, the meat that's not rat meat falsely
labeled as lamb.
Mmm, my mouth is already watering.
So how does this cloning work?
"A DNA strand like me is a blueprint for building
a living thing."
Actually in that case I believe it worked
like this.
But here's a better explanation.
"Cloning is where you take all of the genetic
contents from one cell and move them somewhere
else and reproduce them."
Helping BoyaLife is a joint venture partner:
South Korean company Sooam Biotech.
It's run by a man once known as the "king
of cloning"
until he was fired from the Seoul National
University for
"research fraud and
gross ethical lapses in the way he obtained
human eggs for his experiments."
So this new Chinese cloning plant is in good
hands.
As for practical concerns like
how will they manage to feed so many cattle?
and what will the environmental impact be?
Well, that was somehow left out of the BoyaLife
press release.
Also left out of the press release: all the
ethical concerns.
Cloned animal meat is a hugely controversial
topic in many countries.
A topic BoyaLife dismissed with a single vague
sentence.
In Europe, it's illegal to sell cloned meat.
Parliament voted to ban it because of human
health and animal welfare concerns.
Which is why people freaked out when a lamb
crossed with a jellyfish was sold for meat
in Paris.
What's the big deal?
It's like lamb with mint jelly, but all in
one.
Now the long-term health affects of eating
cloned meat are unknown,
though there is some evidence that cloned
animals may die earlier.
In the US, the FDA says cloning can improve
the quality of animals and approved cloned
meat for human consumption.
No special labeling is required.
So are you already eating cloned meat if you
live in the US?
Well, since no special labeling is required
for cloned meat,
how would you know?
But according to the Guardian, most cloned
animals are used for breeding,
not for food.
Is there such debate in China?
Well, the Chinese people might have concerns,
but who cares?
The government gave it thumbs up,
so no debate.
And why worry?
BoyaLife’s chief executive said cloned beef
is
"the tastiest beef I've had."
And I'm sure he's totally unbiased.
The US doesn't import beef from China.
But that's because of concerns over quality.
But as BoyaLife's chief executive said,
"We are going [down] a path that no one has
ever traveled."
And I'm sure everything will work out just
fine,
like it always does in China.
But for now, I think I'll stick to a burger
made in the traditional way
by grinding together 1,000 cows from five
different countries.
I'm sorry!
I'm lovin' it!
So would you eat cloned beef?
Let me know what you think in the comment
section below.
And please like this video and subscribe to
my channel.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell, see you next
time.