Ah, college.
Living on your own.
Doing what you want, when you want.
Letting it all hang out.
And for tens of thousands of students from
mainland China
studying here in Australia,
they finally are out from under
the watchful eyes of their parents,
and can take a big old hit of academic freedom.
The issue is the academic freedom they have
in Australia,
even though they are in this free county,
it's quite limited.
It's more like what they'd actually experience
studying in China,
I sat down with Chinese Australian Alex Joske,
a freelance journalist and student at Australian
national university
Well, why not?
Do they have some kind of prudish RA
who’s against getting a higher education?
No.
So why don't Chinese students
want to explore their political philosophy?
I think they've been growing up
in China
with what's known as patriotic education
and, I wouldn't say they're brainwashed,
but they've certainly been brought up
in a certain way that encourages them
not to criticize the Party.
And that same attitude carries over
when they're in Australia.
Oh yeah, we all have that political ideology
we were dating back home that we say we'll
be with forever,
but I mean, come on,
it's college.
You get over that.
I don't think they've managed to
dump the Party quite yet.
Clearly these Chinese students need to loosen
up.
These kids can benefit from my years
at a small liberal arts college.
So I donned the robes
symbolic of Greco-Roman philosophy and debate.
Toga! Toga! Toga!
What are you studying?
Accounting.
Master of Statistics.
Master of International Management.
Finance.
Actuarial.
Software engineering.
Both of you, software engineering?
Yeah.
Have you guys ever considered taking an art
class?
Uh, maybe ... not.
Art class?
Yeah.
Art class.
Art class?
Yeah.
No, I didn't take art class.
How about you?
Art? Have you ever taken an art class?
No!
And what's the craziest political party you've
been to?
Sorry?
Political?
Political party, yeah.
Party?
I think I don't know any one.
what's been the craziest political party you've
been to?
Party?
Oh.
Have you ever experimented with democracy?
Democracy?
Have you voted on something?
Not yet.
Democracy?
Yeah, democracy.
What's democracy?
Democracy.
Democracy?
And have you guys ever experimented
with democracy while you're out here?
I'm sorry, what is democracy?
Democracy, you know.
We do not know it.
What is democracy?
You don't know democracy?
Yeah.
That's okay.
Well, we can go on to the next question.
What do you say or do if you hear someone
say something critical or bad about China?
It is interesting to exchange some ideas
but I don't think I have the responsibility
to tell them,
"You need to think in that way."
At first, I may feel a bit angry when somebody
talks
some bad things about your mother countries.
Yeah, maybe I want to argue with him and ask
him
why he feels not good about my country.
I will try to convince him there are many
good things in China.
Some people will say something about Tibet
and Xinjiang problems—like this.
And kind of, we often think that you shouldn't
have bring up such ideas.
I think many people love China.
Yeah, but to understand, they say something
bad on China,
I think if they're right, I think it's okay.
It's okay?!
Yeah.
I think if it’s a fact, you can talk something
bad
and I think it can make us make progress.
I think better say some good thing to them.
Let them know China is a good country.
Yeah.
Ahh youth.
You never forget your first liberal democracy.
But it still felt like there was something
holding them back.
So, there were some serious inhibitions that
need to be explored.
Why do these Chinese students have all these
hangups?
One major part of that is the Chinese Students
and Scholars Association,
which basically functions as the Chinese government's
ears and eyes on campus.
It's kind of like a frat?
Not quite.
It's a rich kid frat.
I know how to handle these people.
It’s locked.
No one’s home.
Is this a Communist Party or what?
Well, they wouldn't let me in.
Can you get me in?
No.
Why not?
Last time I interacted with them,
they followed me and tried to kick me out
of the venue.
What's their deal?
I'm not really sure.
Yeah, well they just saw me going in and followed
me
and had people sit around me and my friend,
and watched us for the whole evening.
And then
when we went to the bathroom,
they followed us, too,
and tried to have us kicked out.
Why did the CSSA target you?
I'd previously reported on and investigated
their ties to the Chinese government,
and also their attempts to censor free information
critical of the Chinese government on campus.
And for that reason,
they're extremely hostile towards me.
And is it just you,
or do they harass other students?
I was there with a friend who is a political
dissident from China,
and they were definitely targeting him as
well.
And I think it's not just something at this
university.
It's not just
the CSSA at ANU, it's CSSAs all across the
globe
that would be willing to engage in these kinds
of activities.
What are some of the ways the CSSA
monitors Chinese students abroad?
Well, it's believed they're in regular contact
with the embassy.
There have been a couple of cases of Chinese
students
or lecturers making comments in class critical
of the Chinese Communist Party,
and then these comments being reported back
to the Chinese government.
So, it's quite likely that CSSAs are involved
in those cases.
How can we tell the CSSA to be cool and stay
the heck out of school?
I think it's important for universities to
send a message to CSSAs
that they're not ever going to be endorsed
by universities.
They won't be allowed to use university facilities,
and the universities
should really encourage alternative Chinese
Student Associations
that don't have these kinds of intimate ties
with the Chinese government.
So, how can Chinese students be encouraged
to come out of their shell a bit more?
Yeah, universities really need to make sure
they're spread out across the university.
That they don't form enclaves,
that they have ample opportunities to interact
with non-Chinese students
and really make the most of their experience.
What you're saying is, we need to throw a
party?
That's not what I meant.
The mother of all parties.
I'm on this.
Just like college…
Chug, chug, chug!!!