China is testing President Biden
With the most aggressive action against Taiwan
yet
How will the Biden Administration Handle China?
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
This episode is sponsored by Surfshark Alert.
It helps detect if your private information
has been leaked online, or is part of a data
breach.
So, just days into Biden’s Presidency, the
Chinese Communist Party issued its first military
challenge—by flying warplanes close to Taiwan.
Just a few days after US President Joe Biden
took office, Washington and Beijing are battling
in a show of force in the South China Sea,
following reports from Taiwan of a large incursion
of Chinese warplanes for the second straight
day.\h
This weekend marked an escalation.
China dispatched fighters and bombers, rather
than reconnaissance aircraft, as had generally
been the case.
This was a major challenge to Biden by the
Communist Party.\h
It comes after the Trump Administration offered
unprecedented US support for Taiwan,
from weapons sales
to high level diplomatic visits.
Pompeo even reframed the entire US Taiwan
relationship.
But was it really a trap for Biden?
In a sense, yes.
The Trump Administration basically put Biden
in a position where he either carries on US
support for Taiwan, angering Chinese leaders,
or he changes course, and sends out signals
he’s going soft on the Chinese Communist
Party.\h
The Biden Administration started with an important
foreign policy signal by inviting Taiwan’s
de facto ambassador to the US to President
Biden’s inauguration.
It was the first time that a Taiwanese official
had attended an inauguration since 1979.
The Chinese Communist Party also tested Biden
almost immediately with their aircraft incursions
over Taiwan.\h
And in response to the Chinese aircraft incursion,
Biden’s State Department said, “Our commitment
to Taiwan is rock-solid.”
And also this:
A U.S. aircraft carrier group has entered
the South China Sea, the U.S. military said
on Sunday...
The carriers entered the South China Sea on
Saturday, the same day Taiwan reported a large
incursion of Chinese bombers and fighter jets
into its air space in the vicinity of the
Pratas Islands.
This comes after more than a year of the Chinese
military ramping up pressure on Taiwan.
“Chinese jets violated Taiwan’s airspace
about 380 times in 2020 and have continued
to carry out such incursions on a nearly daily
basis this year, according to Taiwan’s Ministry
of National Defense.”
We did an episode a few weeks ago about how
these incursions are part of the Communist
Party’s “gray zone” war tactics against
Taiwan.\h
Those are tactics designed to exhaust the
Taiwanese military and make it harder for
Taiwan to defend itself against the Chinese
Communist Party.
According to a former Pentagon policy chief,
Taiwan will be a flashpoint for the Biden
Administration.
Will the Biden administration continue to
stand up for Taiwan?
I hope so.
Because if Taiwan falls, where else am I going
to get those tasty little pineapple cakes?
Meanwhile, China’s Communist leader Xi Jinping
spoke at the World Economic Forum in Davos.
Where he called for unity.
And global cooperation.
Because if we don’t cooperate, there could
be a new cold war.
Of course, we’re already in a new cold war,
one that the Chinese Communist Party started.
But that’s not the point.\h
The point, according to Xi’s speech, is
that we should “all join hands and let multilateralism
light our way toward a community with a shared
future for mankind.”
That’s exactly the kind of message that
the World Economic Forum eats right up.
And it really worked last time Xi gave a similar
speech at Davos, back in 2017.
But now it’s 2021.
And no one can join hands to do anything anymore,
because of the coronavirus.
Which initially spread around the world thanks
to a coverup by the Chinese Communist Party.
So while Xi Jinping used all of the right
words at Davos, where people love to talk
about how great multilateralism and global
cooperation are, people are a little more
skeptical this time.
And they should be.
Because “Xi essentially proposed a multilateralism
with Chinese characteristics—designed to
ensure that international interactions be
conducted in accordance with China’s perspectives.”\h
Basically, Xi Jinping’s message was that
China is strong, and the rest of the world
had better cooperate.
Which is also what he said back in 2017, but
the rest of the world might actually be listening
now.
Speaking of Xi Jinping’s speech at Davos
back in 2017, guess who was listening in the
audience?
Then Vice-President Joe Biden!
Back in 2017, Xi might have still called Biden
an “old friend” as he did in 2013.
But are they still old friends in 2021?
Well, the Chinese Communist Party hopes so.
They’re using diplomatic back channels to
push for a high-level meeting to ease tensions
with the US.
They’re offering to cooperate with the US
on issues like climate change and the coronavirus
pandemic.\h
So where does the Biden Administration stand
on this?\h
Secretary of State Anthony Blinken has said
that it’s possible the US and China could
cooperate on issues like climate change.\h
Although he also reaffirmed that he believed
that China is committing genocide against
the Uyghurs.
So, kind of mixed messages there.\h
Meanwhile, the Biden Administration has signaled
that they’re in no rush to meet with Chinese
officials.\h
At a press briefing over the weekend, White
House press secretary Jen Psaki announced
the Biden Administration China policy— “strategic
patience.”
I can hear Xi Jinping trembling.
Patiently.
If strategic patience isn’t entirely reassuring
to America’s allies in Asia, the new U.S.
Defense Secretary Lloyd Austin did reaffirm
the US commitment to Japan to defend islands
disputed with China.
In Japanese, these are called the Senkaku
Islands.
And if the US doesn’t defend its allies
from the Chinese Communist Party, those alliances
amount to Sen-kaka.
The Biden Administration is also under pressure
from Republican lawmakers to maintain a tough
on China approach.
Senators Marco Rubio, Ben Sasse, Tom Cotton,
and Mitt Romney even wrote a letter to Biden’s
Secretary of the Treasury Janet Yellen to
do just that.
The letter says, “As a key advisor to President
Biden on national security issues that involve
the most powerful and sophisticated tools
of economic statecraft, it is critical that
you demonstrate to Congress that your decisions
will be informed by a clear-eyed view of the
threats posed by the Chinese Communist Party
(CCP) to the United States.”
This comes after Yellen’s opening statement
at a confirmation hearing before the Senate
Finance Committee.
She did not mention China or the Chinese Communist
Party.
Republicans and Democrats then challenged
her on China.
She said the Biden Administration will address
China’s “illegal, unfair and abusive”
practices.
And said, “China is clearly our most important
strategic competitor.”
So in addition to strategic patience, the
Biden Administration seems to be carrying
on the Trump Administration's designation
of China as a strategic competitor.
Under Obama, China had been called a strategic
partner.
Michael McCaul, the top Republican on the
House Foreign Affairs Committee, also called
on Biden to stick to his promises to be tough
on Chinese social media companies like TikTok.\h
Biden did agree with the Trump Administration
that TikTok was a genuine concern.
So basically, between Chinese military incursions
in Taiwan and Republican pressure at home,
everyone wants to see how Biden handles China.
So far, so good.
But really, President Biden should just come
on China Uncensored and make his stance known.
The Philippines are protesting a new Chinese
law they’re calling a verbal threat of war.
“China’s Coast Guard Law, which was passed
on Friday, empowers the force to ‘take all
necessary measures, including the use of weapons,
when national sovereignty, sovereign rights,
and jurisdiction are being illegally infringed
upon by foreign organizations or individuals
at sea.’”
So... now the Chinese Coast Guard can just
shoot or capture foreign ships in disputed
waters.
Which sounds pretty scary, since the Philippines
and China have a lot of disputed waters.
But has the Philippines tried strategic patience?
I’m going to go out on a limb here and say
the South China Sea is about to need a whole
lot more patience.
And possibly more US aircraft carriers.
And this episode has been sponsored by Surfshark
Alert.
Big data breaches happen all the time.
Like the 2019 Capitol One breach that affected
100 million Americans.
Or the 2017 Equifax hack that exposed data
of nearly 150 million Americans.
Whether these hacks come from China or elsewhere,
your private information can be exposed—like
your credit card number, bank account balance,
social security number, and more.
If you’re concerned about data breaches,
identity theft, password leaks, or hackers,
you should use Surfshark Alert.
Surfshark Alert will notify you if your data
is compromised.
This way, you can change your passwords, close
exposed accounts, or switch to new companies.
And for a limited time, you can save 75% off
of a 1-year Surfshark Alert plan PLUS 3 extra
months and a free Surfshark VPN subscription.
This special offer makes your subscription
just $47.88 for the year.
To get this deal, go to “Surfshark-dot-Deals
slash UncensoredAlert” and use the code
UNCENSOREDALERT.
Take control of your online security.
Monitor your credit cards.
Guard your email passwords.
Go to surfshark.deals/uncensoredalert to learn
more.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.