On this episode of China Uncensored,
China’s is building a dystopian future
straight out of 1984.
I hope their handcuffs
look like hot pink leg warmers.
Chinese troops are amassing
at the border near India.
I assume they’re in line for that new
take-out curry place.
And finally,
Agent Smith goes to Washington.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
1984.
Brave New World.
Fahrenheit 451.
Grim dystopian visions of a future gone wrong.
But if you’re the Chinese Communist Party,
it's just really research material.
Remember renowned science fiction author
Philip K Dick’s short story,
The Minority Report?
Okay, remember the Tom Cruise summer
blockbuster movie Minority Report?
Crime is predicted before it happens.
And nothing goes wrong.
Well now the Chinese regime
wants to try its hand at precog justice.
Chinese companies are developing facial recognition
software
that analyzes hair color, facial dimensions,
and skin color to predict criminal behavior.
Well they don’t need computers to do that.
They could just ask my racist Uncle Ted.
What’s that, Shelley?
Oh, they’re just analyzing those things
to identify individuals.
And then they’re going to use it to predict
crimes.
That’s still terrible.
I mean, the Chinese Communist Party
has already been doing a pretty good job
of arresting people who haven’t committed
any crimes.
But with this technology,
they’ll be able to arrest people
before they haven’t committed any crimes.
China has also been setting up
a “nationwide ‘social credit’ system
that will rate every Chinese citizen
by collecting big data on financial,
legal or social misdeeds.”
And almost 7 million people
have already been punished.
If only they had that facial recognition software
earlier
they could have punished those 7 million people
a long time ago!
According to the Supreme People’s Court,
they were guilty of not repaying their debts.
Now, they’re banned from flying
or taking high speed rail.
And if they happen to live in Jiangsu Province,
they might get this added bonus.
If they owe the local court money,
everyone who calls them will get a message
that they owe money.
That’s ridiculous!
Don’t they know about WeChat?
Who actually calls people these days?
And speaking of our hand-held computing devices,
aka, mobile phones,
Big Brother is always watching.
Especially if you’re in Xinjiang in western
China.
The residents of Xinjiang’s capital Urumqi
are being forced to install a surveillance
app
on their mobile phones.
The app is called…
Web Cleansing.
Making our internet clean of any harmful information.
The app is designed to track everyone
all the time,
and make sure they’re not involved
in dangerous activities.
Like visiting dangerous websites
or having religious beliefs.
And if you don’t install the app voluntarily,
police officers at checkpoints may stop you
and force you to install it voluntarily.
Speaking of religious beliefs,
don’t get any ideas
if you’re a Communist Party member.
Because China’s top religious affairs regulator,
yes, that’s a thing in China,
says that if you want to be in the Communist
Party,
you have to give up your religion
or face punishment.
Of course,
you’re not forced to join the Communist
Party.
But if you want to practice religion in China,
you are forced to belong to a state-run church
or temple,
which is under the authority of the Communist
Party.
Unless of course,
you join the Communist Party,
in which case
you just directly belong to the Communist
Party.
But hey, maybe you’re concerned
the Chinese regime’s dystopian policies
aren’t reaching far enough.
Well don’t worry,
because they’re about to reach
just a bit farther.
The Hong Kong government,
under totally no pressure from Beijing,
has decided to lease part of a new
high-speed rail station in Hong Kong
to mainland China.
This way,
Chinese police can enforce Big Brother’s
laws
inside Hong Kong.
Pro-democracy lawmakers have expressed
concern about it,
but as I reported last week,
enough of them have already been purged
so that pro-Beijing lawmakers
can do pretty much whatever they want.
And to ensure that Chinese people can watch
the latest dystopian hits,
China has built a new movie theater.
Right here on an artificial island
China built in the disputed waters
of the South China Sea.
Because everyone knows
when you’ve built a movie theater,
that means you’ve won the territorial dispute.
But don’t worry,
moviegoers will be able to
eat their popcorn in peace,
because this island is defended by female
soldiers
known as “The Fighting Sunflowers.”
Oh wait, my mistake,
they’re actually called,
“The Most Beautiful Sunflowers.”
Here they are,
striking fear into the hearts of China’s
enemies,
with their...accordions.
I’m sure Vietnam is now running scared.
Moving on to more serious matters,
as we mentioned a few weeks ago,
the Chinese regime is in Djibouti.
That’s where they’re building China’s
first overseas military base.
Their Djibouti base is so big,
you can see it from space.
It’s even bigger than we expected.
These satellite photos from Stratfor
show they’ve been literally drilling into
Djibouti
to expand their military base underground.
Speaking of the Chinese military,
closer to home they seem to be preparing for...
whatever it is that’s going to go down in
North Korea.
They’ve been, “establishing a new border
defense brigade,
24-hour video surveillance of the mountainous
frontier
backed by aerial drones,
and bunkers to protect against nuclear
and chemical blasts .”
There’ve also been reports about
amassing troops along the border.
US officials have said military action
is on the table to deal with the North Korean
regime,
and North Korea just said
if the US tries anything,
this time they really will launch a nuclear
strike
at the US.
For reals.
Yes, they will, quote,
“strike a merciless blow at the heart of
the US
with our powerful nuclear hammer.”
But the joke’s on Kim Jong-un.
You’ll never destroy down the real America!
We have hundreds of Cracker Barrels!
And finally, China has banned Justin Bieber
for inappropriate behavior.
Although the Chinese regime gave no specifics,
it can safely be said that this
makes up for anything the Communist Party
ever did or will do.
OK, not everything.
But maybe—I don’t know—
the Anti-Rightist Movement.
And coming up after the break,
a border dispute between China and India
is heating up.
And neither side wants to back down.
I’m sure everything will be fine.
For the media.
You know you love me,
I know you care.
Just visit China Uncensored dot TV
and I'll be there.
Baby, baby, baby oh—
you can watch the full half-hour episode
right now if you just click here.