China is fighting the coronavirus
With a brand new test
You might feel a slight pinch
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
China has a new coronavirus test.
And it’s a real pain in the butt.
Now I don’t want to taint your view of China’s
anal swab test.
Some Chinese experts claim it’s way more
effective.
One specialist told CCTV, “If we add anal
swab testing, it can raise our rate of identifying
infected patients.
But of course considering that collecting
anal swabs is not as convenient as throat
swabs, at the moment only key groups such
as those in quarantine receive both.”
Sure, it’s not as convenient.
But if you’re going to be forced into a
Chinese quarantine center you might as well
have a little fun, right?
So how does the test work?
Don’t worry, they’ve made diagrams!
You only have to put the swab in about 1-2
inches deep.
Of course, it’s also helpful to know what
the heck is happening.
Apparently “some residents in China’s
northern regions...have been subjected to
the swabs with little warning.”
Surprise!\h
This new test couldn’t come soon enough.
It’s almost Chinese New Year.
That’s the biggest travel holiday in China.
An estimated 3 billion trips happen during
a normal year.
That’s not good during a pandemic.
Already more than 22 million people are under
lockdown.
And so “More than 1,000 schoolchildren and
teachers in Beijing were given anal, throat
and nose swabs last week.”
I hope not all at once.\h
On the plus side, I can’t wait for the next
New York Times article praising how well China
is handling the pandemic.
Those reporters can be the first ones to try
out the test in America.\h
Of course, one expert told Bloomberg, “I
don’t understand why Beijing added anal
swabs.”
Well, they don’t call it a Communist *Party*
for nothing.
While a couple of studies have shown that
in some cases the coronavirus is still detectable
in stool samples even after it doesn’t show
up anymore in nose or throat swabs, it’s
not clear that means anything when it comes
to spreading the virus.
“There’s no evidence that virus transmission
is any more common among patients who test
positive in the anus area.”
All I know is, I do not envy the scientists
who have to run that study.\h
China doesn’t have any nationwide policy
about the anal swab.
So that leaves its use in the hands of overzealous
local officials—who will implement any policies
that might stamp out the coronavirus.
Or even policies that just make it look like
they’re stamping out the coronavirus.
No one wants to be in charge of the next Wuhan.
As the Washington Post puts it, “Since the
beginning of the pandemic, China has been
willing to take draconian measures to halt
the spread of the coronavirus, even at enormous
inconvenience to its population.
In the early days of lockdowns, health officials
sometimes sealed apartment buildings to keep
people from leaving.
Millions were rounded up for overnight flash-testing
drives, with people forming lines in the streets
in darkness.”
In darkness?
Why, that’s the perfect environment for
an anal swab!
And the problem is, now that anal swabs have
become a thing, unless someone in the central
government comes out and says to stop, more
and more areas will implement them, regardless
of whether they actually help.
That’s how it works in China’s communist
system.
Another example of this is the problem that
China is having now with food imports.
In their eagerness to blame the coronavirus
on any other country that’s not China, Chinese
state-run media have been running a propaganda
campaign about how the virus may have come
from imported frozen foods.
Meanwhile the US Centers for Disease Control
and the World Health Organization have both
said that there’s no evidence that anyone
has gotten the coronavirus from frozen foods
or food packaging.
But people in China are now scared of buying
imported food, and frozen food is just sitting
at Chinese ports for weeks, causing a huge
backup in the global food supply chain.
Some areas in China are also now dealing with
food shortages and skyrocketing food prices
due to lockdowns.
People aren’t happy about high food prices.
But they’re even less thrilled about the
anal swabs.
Obviously people are concerned about government
overreach.
Or would this be under reach?
But really, to help protect the public from
the coronavirus, is there anything you wouldn’t
let the government do to you?
Or are you a monster?
Anyway, no matter how bad things get in America,
let’s just say, they got it a lot worse
in China.
And this kind of penetrating, deep China coverage
would not be possible without the support
from viewers like you.
I call them the China Uncensored 50 cent army,
fans who contribute a dollar or more per episode
through the crowd funding website Patreon.com/chinauncensored.
As a thank you, I’ll answer your questions.
Today’s question comes from TheOKWoodsman.
“With all the money and efforts into the
many military and ‘civilian’ island building
projects, isn't the CCP worried about sea
level rise due to climate change?”\h
Now that’s a good question.
If you don’t know, China is aggressively
expanding its territory in the South China
Sea.
They’ve built artificial islands and then
call them Chinese territory.
How do they get away with that?
Well, first they militarize them.\h
And then they have Chinese citizens move in.
For example, Sansha City—built back in 2012
on the Paracel Islands.
It now has a population of almost 2,000 people.
But as you say OKWoodsman, what if the ocean
levels rise because of climate change?
Helped along by the insane number of coal
plants China has.
Well, that’s why China is also building
secret villages along the China India border.
Those are way up in the Himalayan Mountains.
So you see?
The Chinese Communist Party plans for any
contingency.
That’s why they hate to be the butt of jokes.
Thanks for your question OKWoodsman.\h
And thank you for watching.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next
time.