The CCP Coronavirus
Has changed the world
Here’s how
This China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
Well folks, we’re all suffering because
of the Chinese Communist Party.
The CCP Coronavirus has turned into a deadly
pandemic
that has people all over the world cowering
in their homes,
hoarding toilet paper.
Shelley, how’d you get that photo?
It’s embarrassing.
I’m not wearing a suit.
Anyway, since this is the Chinese Communist
Party’s fault,
I’ve started calling the coronavirus the
CCP Coronavirus.
I hope you’ll join me in doing the same.
But a picture is worth a thousand words.
So I’m about to show you many thousands
of words worth of
how the CCP Coronavirus has changed the world—
in a series of photos from before and after
the CCP Coronavirus pandemic.
And now the question is, will life ever be
the same again?
Personally, I hope not.
I hope we all approach the Chinese Communist
Party
with a good deal more skepticism now
and maybe start manufacturing medical supplies
inside the United States instead of China.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
stay safe out there.