On this episode of China Uncensored,
kids do the darndest things.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
Check this out.
It was posted a couple weeks ago
on Chinese social media.
This three-year-old kid picks up a steel pipe,
like he’s gonna fight off a bunch of police
officers.
What a riot!
Even the police officers are filming it.
The video is so cute that China’s state-run
People’s Daily
posted it to their YouTube channel.
Wait…
the People’s Daily has a YouTube channel?
YouTube is blocked in China.
But I guess there’s no harm in showing the
rest of the world
how cute Chinese toddlers can be, right?
Haha, look at that!
Wait…
it sounds like he’s screaming,
“Don’t bully my grandma!”
Dang! He seems genuinely angry.
And these police,
well, they’re not really police.
They’re called “chengguan” or “urban
management.”
Chengguan are the taskforce that’s supposed
to enforce city laws
related to street vendors, traffic, and so
on.
But they have a reputation for being corrupt.
And brutal.
Like that time in 2011
when chengguan beat a one-legged fruit vendor
to death.
Or in 2013,
when chengguan beat a watermelon vendor to
death.
Or in 2014,
when chengguan assistants beat a 70-year-old
man to death.
I mean, he did criticize them.
But clearly,
a three-year-old couldn’t have read those
articles.
No, he just intrinsically understands that these
chengguan are bad guys.
And if they’re after his grandma,
it’s worth taking the most extreme action
to stop them.
And the videos of this kid have become online
sensations in China,
getting millions of views.
Although there’s not much info on who this
kid is
or what the chengguan were doing to his grandma,
it seems every netizen has an opinion.
This weibo user writes:
“His grandmother is so blessed.”
This user said:
“...This proves that from a child’s perspective,
chengguan have a bad image. Thought-provoking.”
And this user writes:
“This little boy has gone mad...
and the adults don’t know how to restrain
him.”
There was even an online survey that got more
than 100,000 responses.
47% said “The kid’s just protecting his
family,
that’s all.”
35% said “First, I need to know if the chengguan
had roughed them up prior [to the video].”
And 18% said “It’s a bit troubling
a child this young is resisting the law.”
I feel like this survey might be more of a reflection
on what Chinese people think of standing up
to authority in general.
And authorities better watch out.
Because someday, this toddler
might become the next Ip Man.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And be sure to check out our Facebook page
for more content.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.