On this episode of China Uncensored:
Bathing in the purple rain?
Sounds like Beijing pollution has gotten really
bad.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored. I’m your
host, Chris Chappell.
Unless you’ve been living in a cave,
you know that the artist known as,
then formerly known as,
then once again known as Prince,
was found dead at his estate on April 21.
Last Thursday, the coroner’s report revealed
the cause of death:
an overdose of fentanyl.
What is fentanyl?
“It’s the strongest opiate based painkiller
on the market.
It is 50-100 times stronger than morphine
and 25 times to 50 times stronger than heroin.”
“It can go by the street name China White,
or China Girl.”
China Girl?
Now we’re dragging David Bowie into this?
Yeah, this year sucked.
Now we don’t know how Prince got his fentanyl,
whether it was prescribed by a doctor or he
got it some other way.
But fentanyl is a big problem in the United
States.
According to the US Drug Enforcement Administration,
fentanyl was involved in 14% of drug overdose
deaths in 2014,
and it's getting worse.
In other words, fentanyl is killing more people
than heroin in some parts of the country.
And a lot of it comes from China.
In fact, buying it is as easy as doing an
online search for “buy fentanyl.”
Don't do that.
And it’s not just fentanyl.
Dangerous synthetic drugs of all sorts are
flooding into the United States from China.
China supplies the raw materials
and drug dealers create the finished product.
With fentanyl, dealers often “cut” it
with other drugs
that means they add a bit of it to a drug
like heroin.
Or they make pills that look like more expensive
drugs, like oxycontin.
Users may not know this
if they’re buying it off the streets.
And the big problem is,
it’s 50 times stronger than heroin,
so that makes it super easy to overdose.
Recently, US Senator Pat Toomey called on
the Obama Administration
to pressure the Chinese regime into stopping
exports on fentanyl and other synthetic drugs.
A reasonable request if you assume Chinese
labs
were somehow unwittingly supplying perfectly
legal compounds that got misused down the line.
I mean, who could predict that some guy ordering
raw fentanyl, and a pill press,
might use it to make illegal drugs?
And the Chinese regime has taken action in
the past.
Last year, it made it illegal to export a
type of fentanyl called acetyl fentanyl.
In fact, the Chinese government has technically
banned the export of over 100 different synthetic drugs
But then…
Chinese labs just changed the recipe to make
a new type of fentanyl,
one that wasn't on the US’s controlled substances
list yet.
So what can the Chinese regime do to stop
the influx of synthetic drugs
that are killing Americans?
I guess the question is whether that’s something
they want to stop.
Senator Toomey found out that apparently,
the Chinese law enforcement officials can’t
prosecute labs for shipping these drugs.
Think about that.
The Chinese regime can detain people for remembering
the Tiananmen Square Massacre,
but not for shipping potentially deadly compounds?
You really think they couldn’t crack down
on labs if they wanted to?
Maybe, they don’t.
In 2014, a U.S. Army Special Operations Command
report
discusses the reality of the “unconventional
warfare” China is waging on the United States.
It quotes a top Chinese colonel Qiao Liang
as saying,
“the first rule of unrestricted warfare
is that there are no rules, with nothing forbidden.”
Part of that includes “drug warfare.”
National security analyst Joseph D. Douglass
wrote a book called Red Cocaine.
In it, he writes communist regimes,
“have been using narcotics for several decades
as a decisive weapon in the ongoing low-level
warfare
they are waging against Western civilization.”
According to the DEA,
90% of meth in the US is made by Mexican cartels.
But they get 80% of their ingredients from
China.
By the way, according to this report by the
Department of Justice,
the main source of illegal firearms in Mexico
is also China.
So maybe the Chinese regime knows exactly
what’s going on
and maybe that’s why they’ve done so little
to stem the flow of synthetic drugs.
In fact, there’s been a big surge
in the number of new psychoactive drugs in
the last few years
not just fentanyl.
And a lot of them come from China.
So what do you think about about the Chinese
regime’s drug warfare?
Leave your comments below.
And if you like the show,
consider supporting us on Patreon.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell,
thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.