Is China run
By a Transnational Criminal Organization?
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
In China today, there are concentration camps.\h
Minorities are used for slave\h
labor—after getting forcibly sterilized.\h
People of faith get their organs\h
harvested in state-run hospitals.
And yet, Wall Street elite keep pushing investment\h
in this same government. Here’s a recent article\h\h
from JP Morgan Chase, “Focused on opportunities:\h
Why invest in Chinese Government Bonds now?”
And human rights concerns didn’t stop\h
a major EU-China investment agreement.
The Chinese Communist Party has\h
repeatedly broken international promises:\h\h
Like its agreement with the\h
World Trade Organization.\h\h
And its agreement with the UK that Hong\h
Kong would get to keep its freedoms.
The problem is, governments\h
and countries around the world\h\h
treat the Chinese Communist Party\h
like a legitimate government.\h
But that may change. There’s an effort going on\h
right now to label the Chinese Communist Party\h\h
a Transnational Criminal Organization.\h\h
For more on that, I spoke with Hong Kong\h
businessman and political commentator Elmer\h\h
Yuen about how the world can hold the Chinese\h
Communist Party accountable for their actions.\h
Mr. Yuen, thank you for joining me today.
All right. So thank you for inviting me.
Of course, you initially came to the\h
US to advocate for Hong Kong before\h\h
Beijing passed the National Security Law.
Yes.
What do you think of what the\h
US government has done so far\h\h
to counter the Chinese Communist\h
Party's actions in Hong Kong?
When I arrived back in middle of June,\h
they were not really prepared. I mean,\h\h
[inaudible 00:00:51] spoke a lot\h
about standing with Hong Kong,\h\h
but that's only words. In action, they are totally\h
unprepared, and the overall, the State Department,\h\h
as you know, is not very anti-China at all, they\h
are pro-China overall, over the years. It's always\h\h
been, they, after most of these guys retire,\h
they look to have some business with China.
China is a big business market. So\h
anyway, nobody's quite prepared,\h\h
and it's more spoken support instead of\h\h
action. I hear these words about measured\h
response against China, against CCP.
You've proposed that the US government\h
should label the Chinese Communist\h\h
Party as a transnational criminal\h
organization. What does that mean?
Everybody says China is a big country, big nation.\h
In fact, the nation itself, the word, "Nation,"\h\h
is really a facade. In essence, it's the CCP in\h
total control, complete control. It's really not a\h\h
nation. Almost behind every government official or\h
even behind every business, even small business,\h\h
you can see the CCP controlling behind. As you\h
know, China has over 90 million CCP members,\h\h
over 90 million. Then you have lots\h
of young people after kindergarten,\h\h
they start joining this Young Pioneers. So,\h
yet they have unlimited supply of a very\h\h
well educated, the best they have, the\h
brightest they have, to join the party.\h\h
So overall, the CCP is very much like\h
the mafia, the mafia organization, right?
On top, you have about 50 families, very\h
powerful families, from the Long March,\h\h
or from the high officials. We call them The\h
Red, second generation or third generation,\h\h
and then The Official, second or third generation.\h
They have accumulated huge amount of wealth.
As you can see in all the major cities, the\h
most expensive apartments or properties,\h\h
bought up by them, the prime real estate.\h\h
They have been using companies, shell companies,\h
investing in all kinds of Fortune 500 companies.
You don't know them, because they use company\h
name. So they are really controlling this\h\h
company behind the scene, and also working\h
with them. All right, China is working with\h\h
all of these big corporations on the\h
surface. So this, as you can see.\h\h
But the control behind the back, the equity\h
control is something people don't talk about.
So this is the organization, 50 families,\h
90 million members, which are like gangs in\h\h
the mafia. Then they have 1.3 trillion people to\h
exploit. Very much like, you remember the New York\h\h
movies? You have the mafia families, and then you\h
have the gangsters, and then you have the people\h\h
on the street, that they go and collect protection\h
money. Very much, that's the system. It works.\h\h
So the word, "Nation," it's really, we always\h
consider it as nation, as the legal nation. So\h\h
we deal with them, with the policy, and then make\h
contracts with them. Then the British ruled this,\h\h
Sino-British Joint Declaration, about\h
Hong Kong, treating them like a nation.
But as you know, criminals have no understanding\h
of law, right? The minute they can break, they\h\h
will break. As long as they are making money, they\h
let it go on, and as long as they don't make any\h\h
money, they will break the contract, any contract.\h
So Hong Kong is a typical example. They find that\h\h
Hong Kong people want too much freedom,\h
rule of law and democracy, so they have\h\h
decided to take over Hong Kong. And then forget\h
about the Joint Declaration, British-Chinese\h\h
declaration. So they've decided to do that, and\h
suddenly Hong Kong become part of China. So Donald\h\h
Trump says, "It's no longer a one country, two\h
system, it's become one country, one system."
So what happened to me, I've really not been\h
involved with politics. I realized, but I know all\h\h
about China, because I deal with every level of\h
them. I lived in China 20 years, I live in US 20\h\h
years and Hong Kong 20 years. So I know all these\h
countries quite well. So I've decided I know what\h\h
all the crimes they've committed in the last\h
71 years, where the People's Republic of China,\h\h
they named the country, which is really not, they\h
don't respect it. There's no people, you never see\h\h
the people. It's not a Republic, and it's really\h
not Chinese culture. What they are exercising,\h\h
is very much like the Soviet, no, even more\h
closer to the Fascist-behavior. Chinese are not\h\h
Fascism, even though we have emperors, but\h
the emperor normally leaves the people alone.
So, anyway, I decided to come to expose\h
their crimes. Over, I mean, at least 70\h\h
million people died of abnormal death, since 1949,\h
from starvation, from cultural revolution, people\h\h
committing suicide and all kinds of political\h
struggle. Every family has been, has suffered\h\h
from the political persecution. So I\h
decided to come to the States, to lobby\h\h
your Congress about the Chinese being a criminal\h
organization. In the beginning, I was thinking\h\h
about using the RICO law. I'm sure you know about\h
the RICO law against a gangster. And which means\h\h
every party member is in fact, the criminal,\h
if you belong to this criminal organization.\h\h
Then we discovered, there's even a better law,\h
called the Transnational Criminal Organization.\h\h
They use that law against South American drug\h
cartels, and also use it against the Hezbollah.
And of course, China is a much bigger scale of\h
criminal organization, so that suits very well. So\h\h
we have Congressman Scott Perry, he is combining\h
three different laws. One is the transnational\h\h
criminal organization, one is the RICO and\h
also as you know, there was old McCarthy law,\h\h
the Communist Control Act. So he's combining all\h
three, and he is trying to legislate and designate\h\h
the CCP as the TCO, and also a RICO, violation\h
of the RICO and the Communist Act. These laws are\h\h
already in place, so we don't need to go through\h
legislation. It's only a matter of designation.
Well, so practically speaking, what\h
would it mean for the international\h\h
community and businesses if the CCP\h
were labeled a criminal organization?
If you are a businessman, would you sign\h
a contract with a criminal organization?
Would you sign a contract with a\h
mafia organization? It's exactly that.\h\h
I wouldn't even shake hands. If you're normally in\h
US, a legitimate company, you normally have your\h\h
lawyer to check the other side, to see how good\h
is it? The minute you discover it's a criminal\h\h
organization, no executive in their right\h
mind would sign a contract or even negotiate.\h\h
So suddenly you have to isolate it. You force\h
them, takes time, right? You force them to give up\h\h
this CCP and become a normal country. This is\h
in long-term, this is what I expect. But step\h\h
number one, you must label them, because\h
most people don't know. They think, "Oh,\h\h
I'm going to China. It's a huge market, 1.4\h
billion people. I can make a lot of money."
That's everybody. Same thing with the\h
Ivy League or the professor, "Oh, Chinese\h\h
great culture. They are inviting me there,\h
pay for my tickets and hotel, everything."\h\h
And then, "Oh, I must go. There's is a lot to\h
study. And I can write paper and write books."\h\h
This is what happened to the corporatists, to\h
Hollywood, "Wow, how can I let go of 1.4 billion\h\h
movie tickets, for a good movie?"\h
So all NBA, everybody, is really,\h\h
they thought about this huge market and forgot who\h
they are dealing with. They're not dealing with\h\h
the people, they're dealing with the communist\h
party. That is the problem. So I want to label\h\h
them. So people are aware of who they are dealing\h
with. Criminals, they're dealing with criminals.
It's very important, and you cannot expect them\h
to keep their promise. In the end, they will\h\h
do anything, because criminals obviously have no\h
sense of law. They will do anything, for their own\h\h
good. And communism means they want to take over\h
all the private ownership. Global, not only China,\h\h
global, that's what One Belt, One Road. That's\h
why they're in US. They have infiltrated, almost\h\h
everything, including your White House,\h
your state department and your presidency.
So you were basically saying that the US should\h
sanction the entire Chinese Communist Party?\h\h
But the CCP is already fighting US sanctions by\h\h
saying that if international\h
companies follow US sanctions,\h\h
they're going to get in trouble in China. So\h
does that mean US sanctions wouldn't work.
You'll have to decouple with them,\h
and forget about the near-term profit,\h\h
honestly. Because if you still want to do\h
business with them, then the trouble would\h\h
never end. Right now, of course, if you look at\h
Wall Street and Silicon Valley and Hollywood,\h\h
NBA, and the Ivy leagues, they love to do business\h
with China, right? Because China treat them well,\h\h
they know how to take care of them. So\h
they don't want to cut off. But in reality,\h\h
we know we've been dealing with them,\h
from Hong Kong, we know how they behave.\h\h
They always win, in the end, they always win. So\h
I believe that you have to decouple with them, and\h\h
not only US, the whole world has to isolate them\h
and make sure they change back to a normal nation.
Then you can deal with them, China\h
business will be five times better,\h\h
if you're dealing with a normal nation. Right now,\h
they're stealing your technology, they're stealing\h\h
everything. And they have very cheap labor,\h
cheap land and cheap executive. So they can\h\h
undercut the price. Basically you can't\h
compete with that. They have the mass,\h\h
they have their domestic market to have\h
the scale, economy of scale. So in a way,\h\h
you cannot compete with them fairly,\h
unless they become private enterprises.
So you're arguing that it is\h
in the economic interest of\h\h
the international community, Hollywood, Wall\h
Street, to actually view China, the Chinese\h\h
Communist Party as a criminal organization?\h
That that is in the long run, better for them?
In the long run, but I think people should also\h
try to understand the evilness of this whole\h\h
regime of this party and that what's happening in\h
Xinjiang is more serious than what the Nazis have\h\h
done to the Jews, more serious in Xinjiang.\h
And people can also compare Hong Kong now,\h\h
with Hong Kong before. Everybody loves\h
Hong Kong, whoever has been to Hong Kong,\h\h
they love Hong Kong. Now suddenly you can talk\h
to any Hong Kong people coming out of Hong Kong,\h\h
and they will tell you, "It's disaster." It's\h
basically, it's like taken over by the fascists,\h\h
and that they are arresting people. They don't\h
go by the law, they give them whatever sentence\h\h
they want, and they don't care about the charges.\h
Suddenly our whole ecosystem is out of the window.
Well, thank you very much for joining me today,\h
Mr. Yuen, it's a fascinating thing to try and\h\h
label the Chinese Communist Party as\h
a transnational criminal organization.
As they understand more about CCP, and as the\h
personal damage from the COVID and economics,\h\h
and also the cyber-warfare that they are\h
attacking US, I think, I hope people will wake up\h\h
and it takes time. It may take time, but\h
this is what they are. Thank you, Chris.
Thank you.
And thank you for watching. Do you think the\h
CCP should be labeled a Transnational Criminal\h\h
Organization? Let me know in the comments below.\h
Once again I’m Chris Chappell. See you next time.