Tibet has been occupied for 60 years
The Chinese Communist Party has waged a systematic
campaign
To wipe out Tibetan Culture
Will there ever be a Free Tibet?
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
It’s been 60 years since the Chinese Communist
Party liberated Tibet.
From its freedom.
But first, Mao Zedong tried different tactic:
Making friends with the Dalai Lama.
You know, to get him to see how good
Buddhism with Chinese characteristics could
be.
Obviously, that did not work out.
In 1959, the Dalai Lama fled Tibet.
He would go on to establish a democratic Tibetan
government
in exile in Dharamsala, India.
Meanwhile, the Chinese Communist Party would
go on to destroy
most of the Buddhist temples in Tibet,
while massacring 1.2 million Tibetans,
according to some observers.
International calls for Free Tibet died down
as Western businesses and officials
eagerly sought out the Chinese market.
Which of course worked out so well for them.
Karma is a...well you get the idea.
So what is the future of Tibet?
I sat down with Dorjee Tseten,
a member of the Tibetan Parliament in Exile.
He’s also Executive Director of Students
for a Free Tibet.
Thank you so much for joining us today.
Thank you, Chris.
So it's been 60 years since, well,
the Communist Party says it liberated Tibet,
how are things in Tibet?
So for us, for the Tibetan and for people
around the whole Tibet,
it's a 60 years of occupation,
and it's 60 years of resistance inside Tibet,
and we need to understand that Tibet is colonized
by China,
and it's under the military occupation right
now.
Despite the 60 years of occupation,
Tibetan has continued to resist for their
freedom,
and we're seeing growing resistance inside
Tibet,
especially by the new generation in this difficult
time.
Mm-hmm.
Do you mean inside Tibet or abroad?
Yeah, inside Tibet, outside Tibet.
So one example that I can give, one of the
recent
like most landmark historic uprising in 2008,
that has capture the imagination of the international
community,
and China was also like shock,
it was led by the Tibetan new generation.
Almost 70 percentage of people who joined
the uprising,
and that took part in like hundreds of cities
and villages
around the whole Tibet was led by the new
generation.
So we can see the new generation of Tibetans
are taking
the responsibility of the movement in the
resistance.
I'm curious, why do you think the Chinese
Communist Party
is so interested in Tibet?
So Tibet is a strategically very important
for China
to spread its control in Asia.
And when Tibet was occupied, Tibetan movement,
the leadership,
we have been telling to the international
community
that China's aim is not just Tibet,
it want to control the Asia and the global
community.
So what we are seeing right now,
now China's expansion,
this idea is not limited to Tibet.
We are seeing in Asia, threat in South Asia,
East Asia.
So Tibet is really,
really strategically important place for them,
and Tibet has a very, very rich mineral resources,
and like any other colonized country,
it is important for China to take away the
resources,
and they're doing the mining, they're [...] the
river.
So on that part, China is gaining a lot, and
for them
the continuation of Tibet,
and also the population they can transport
into Tibet,
which now we as concerned that Tibetans are
becoming
a minority in our own land.
So all those are the reason that China continue
to occupy Tibet.
The Chinese Communist Party has been pushing
Tibetans
to be less religious and spend their time
learning Mandarin,
why is the Communist Party so concerned about
changing the culture of Tibet?
So Tibetan language and Tibetan culture,
Tibetan religion is the core of Tibetan national
identity,
and what China want to do is to wipe out Tibet
from the map of the world,
and Tibetans inside Tibet to forget their
culture,
their identity, so that they can control the
Tibetan people.
But Tibetans are continually resisting by
using their culture
as a mean of resistance,
which is really, really unique,
and new things that we're seeing in the resistance,
how Tibetans are using culture and language
as a tool to resist.
And China, the sinicization program that is
going on,
not just in Tibet, but other part of like
occupied territory,
like in East Turkestan.
Basically they'd want to the new generation
to forget everything,
and what we are seeing is new generations
are taking up ...
courageously taking the risk to keep their
identity and fighting back.
Well, I was going to ask about that.
Do you see any parallels between what has
happened in Tibet,
and what is happening with the Uyghurs in
Xinjiang or East Turkestan,
as you call it?
Yeah, so the current situation inside East
Turkestan is very,
very difficult, or one point ...
or one or two million Tibet,
I mean, Uyghurs are under the concentration
camp which is unbelievable,
and the person who has implemented this policy,
the current party secretary in East Turkestan,
the Uyghur Autonomous Region, the Chen Quanguo,
Chen Quanguo,
he was the party secretary of so-called Tibet
Autonomous Region.
So when he become the party secretary of Tibet
in 2011,
he had implemented such a policy,
a new policy on security which undermine
and which repress the Tibetan religious freedom
and right of the people,
and under that policy, he implement a grid
system,
urban grid system, and introducing biometric
security,
and then it has really, really impact a lot,
caused a lot of challenges for the Tibetan
people inside Tibet.
So what we are seeing right now happening
to the Uyghur people,
the Tibetans has gone through that.
Because it was the same guy running the show.
Yes.
He's the same guys who's doing that,
and for Tibetans despite such difficulty,
we continue to resist,
and we continue to find different ways of
like engaging
and protecting our culture.
So I think ... I mean, we have our solidarity
with Uyghur people,
but we need to understand that this is not
just one place happening,
it's happening all over the ... It's a kind
of strategy that China
is implementing to the Chinese people
and to all the occupied territories.
I know the Communist Party has gone so far
as to even create laws regulating reincarnation.
How likely do you think it is,
we're going to see a new Dalai Lama someday
that's party approved?
So I think that's what China want to bring
again in the discussion,
but His Holiness Dalai Lama is the soul of
the movement,
and His Holiness Dalai Lama had made it very
clear
that the reincarnation will be chosen by the
Tibetan people
and China has no business in it.
And basically it is funny that Chinese government,
which repress religion for over last 60 years,
and now finding interest in choosing next
Dalai Lama,
and not only that, this is not a new thing,
there's I think a ...
form a new law, I mean, a law in 1995 which
under Order No. 5,
they decide that Chinese government has the
right to choose
any reincarnation in Tibet, which we have
protest,
and now international community is also understanding
that.
Recently there was a resolution in the Congress,
US also saying that it's a Tibetan people
right,
and China cannot decide on that.
So on that part, those are the legal thing,
but basically it is most important that reincarnation
and the religion is so deeply related to the
heart and belief,
no matter what China do.
If Tibetan doesn't believe, they cannot do.
They can make rules, they can put people behind
the bars,
but they cannot force people to believe.
So on that part, I mean, recently we observed
the 30th birthday of His Holiness The Panchen
Lama,
the Panchen Lama, Gedhun Choekyi Nyima,
and he has been missing for the last over
24 years,
and China tried to do that.
But the China appointed, the so-called Panchen
Lama,
nobody respect, nobody respect inside Tibet,
nobody respect outside.
So I think it shows that it failed.
If China wanted to do again, it won't work,
but then like most important thing is His
Holiness
has devolved the political authority to the
elected leader
of the democratic institution in exile,
and I think that is really key critical here.
So possibly there will be two Dalai Lamas,
but the Tibetan community will know which
one
is the one they support?
So I think if China does that,
it won't definitely make any sense to the
Tibetan community.
And what I'm saying is more important is the
political struggle,
and movement of Tibet will continue.
And His Holiness Dalai Lama under his leadership,
he has established a democratic institution
in exile
which represent both Tibetan people inside
and outside.
In early 60s,
His Holiness first establish the Tibetan parliament
in exile,
and now we have an elected Tibetan president
of Tibetan government in exile.
So I think those are key important that how
movement will sustain,
and it is the legacy of His Holiness.
Even though we still hope that His Holiness
will return to Tibet in this lifetime,
but His Holiness has shown the vision that
how Tibet
should be a democratic institution, and the
exiled government
that based in India is really important in
that whole picture.
And it's interesting as you say,
that there is this democratic institution
that's been created,
because one of the pieces of propaganda the
Communist Party
uses is to say that the Dalai Lama was like
a feudal slave-owning oppressor of the Tibetan
people,
but clearly he has established a democratic
institution.
Mm-hmm.
Even before the Chinese invasion,
even when His Holiness was very young,
he try to introduce new changes,
and basically bringing changes in the Tibetan
government and system,
but at the same time even before China's invasion,
Tibetan people are free,
Tibetan people have a government,
of course, His Holiness was the leader.
Tibetan has a system where no matter what
kind of system we have,
but we have food to eat, there was no famine
like the way after Chinese invasion, like
Tibetian,
so many Tibetan faced a lot of challenges,
and right now under occupation.
And His Holiness has always,
has this vision to have the people the power,
and to form the democratic institution.
So that's why when His Holiness first escape
and then came to exile,
the first thing he did was forming that democratic
institution.
So China, there's no basis on China's claim
that
His Holiness wanted to go back and establish
the same system,
there's no basis this for that, and basically
for Tibetan,
we want to have a system which decide our
own future
by the Tibetan people.
You mentioned the United States government,
and one thing I find very encouraging is that
when it comes to Chinese Communist Party,
this is one of few things that is always bipartisan,
it's something both Democrats and Republicans
can agree on.
What has been the support for Tibet and to
Tibetans abroad?
Throughout the Tibetan freedom struggle,
U.S. government and people,
most importantly, has support Tibet issue,
and of course supported His Holiness, Dalai
Lama.
Recently, there was a bill passed in congress
called
Reciprocal Access to Tibet,
which actually seek reciprocity.
Because China, right now, rules Tibet under
complete lockdown,
so they don't allowed any people from outside
freely.
Even more difficult for the Tibetan Americans
who have a right to go to Tibet and also like
the American journalists or leaders.
This act demand China to have this reciprocity.
Those people who implement such law,
such restriction will be also bar from United
State,
to visit United State.
So it is supported unanimously as a bipartisan
support in the congress,
and it is passed as a law last December,
which is a historic support,
which will make China accountable.
Then the Tibetan government, and Tibetan Exile
Government,
and Tibetan settlements in India for the education,
for the school, for the community,
United State government has been very supportive
throughout the years.
Especially the American people has been supportive
for the Tibet movement.
The organization I work right now, Students
for Free Tibet,
was established in United State 25 years ago.
We have so many American members and supporters,
along with Tibetan members,
so we have a grassroot people support for
this movement
from this country and around the world.
I know a few years ago there was a big Free
Tibet movement in Hollywood.
You had actors like Richard Gere promoting
it,
but you don't see that much anymore.
What happened?
Richard Gere is still one of the most important
supporter
and friend of His Holiness, Dalai Lama.
He continue to advocate the rights of Tibetan
people.
What we are seeing right now there is a strong
influence from China.
Any stars or Hollywood actors or film makers
keep relation with Tibet or Tibetan leader,
like His Holiness, Dalai Lama,
are barred from visiting China.
So what we were seeing right now,
the depression and the situation that Tibetan
people
face inside Tibet is no longer in Tibet.
The influence, the censorship, is now coming
to the rest, as well.
So because of that, of course,
it is sometime difficult for people to stand
for issue of Tibet.
But no matter that, there are many,
many other key people who has shown their
support
despite the consequence they face from China.
But of course, it is our responsibility, now,
especially for Tibetan and American
also to protect our rights here,
how we fight back the censorship.
Because this is a land of free.
This is not China.
But how people still fearful,
because China may punish the companies,
the corporation that try to make business
with China.
Undermining the human rights issue,
basic principle of what United States stand
for.
So I think this is also a fight that we,
as the Students of Free Tibet,
and also many other groups and people are
engaged ... Yeah.
What is the larger Tibetan community outside
of Tibet doing?
For the last 20 years,
many Tibetans has moved to the West.
Of course, Tibetan from inside Tibet,
as well as like [...] Tibetans in India.
What we have form now, unlike in the past,
Tibetan community has become integrated into
the global community.
So like in North America, we have around like
18 to 20 Tibetan community centers.
Tibetan community try to pass on the culture,
and language, and identity to our new generation.
So through this community center,
which directly operate independently,
but also in relation with our exile government
to protect our culture, language,
so the new generation can take the movement
forward.
The organization I work, Students for Free
Tibet,
as it was established 25 years ago,
along with the political campaign we do, we
do lot of trainings
to the new generation leaders.
Last year, we organize like 12 trainings
engaging almost like 500 participants,
basically to train them as the new generation
leaders
and activists about campaigning,
about media communication, about leadership.
Also about online security,
how to be safe from the China's threat
now we are no longer safe anywhere.
All those things, like we are building the
movement,
both the community and the global Tibetan
movement.
We have over like 180 Tibetan groups around
the world
still campaigning for Tibet, even after such
a long time.
You currently are an MP in the Tibetan parliament,
correct?
Yeah.
I'm a member of Tibetan parliament in exile
What is being an MP in a government-in-exile
...
What does that entail?
As we struggle for our freedom, His Holiness,
Dalai Lama,
has established the Tibetan Exile Government
and Tibetan parliament early '60s.
As we fight for our freedom,
we also want to create our own vision and
system.
What kind of system we want to create?
So this democratic institution is really important.
As I said, now Tibetans are in almost 30 countries.
But the institution we have, Tibetan Exile
Government,
also known as Central Tibetan Administration,
our president is being elected by people around
the 30 countries.
Our member of parliament also represent all
those people,
especially Tibetan people inside Tibet.
So every five year when we do election,
when Tibetan people in exile,
because when people inside Tibet cannot vote,
so Tibetan people in exile represent the movement.
By representing the movement, when we form
our government,
it is a direct challenge to Chinese government
that what kind of system we want.
We don't want a repressive regime that China
is right now
implementing in Tibet.
That is, I think, key.
His Holiness, Dalai Lama,
he has voluntarily stepped down from the political
responsibility in 2011.
Since then, even the exile government role
has become much more important.
Even though we hope that we will go to Tibet
soon,
but it might take time, because any resistance,
any movement take time.
So how we pass this knowledge and experience
to new generation?
I, as a Tibetan born in India, I'm engaged
in the movement
because of that vision from our elder generation.
That's why the democratic institution in the
exile community
as Tibetan Government-in-exile,
also known as Central Tibetan Administration,
is key.
What China claim about His Holiness
and about Tibet is completely baseless.
What we want?
Tibetan people to be free.
Tibetan people can decide their future.
That's why we have a really healthy democratic
system in exile
and now Tibetans across the globe in almost
like 30, 40 countries.
Especially like recently,
we mark the Tibetan National Uprising Day,
60 years of Tibetan National Uprising Day.
That was held in almost hundred cities around
the world on same day
by Tibetans and supporters.
So you can see the strength of the movement,
how it's being passed generation after generation.
I think that is key to the movement.
No longer how much it take,
we will continue to resist until we gain our
freedom.
This is something the young Tibetans care
about.
That's completely true, both inside and outside.
Where do you see Tibet in the next 10 years?
As I said, I think it is really critical time,
because of His Holiness age and because of
what is happening right now.
As much as we, Tibetan, care for our freedom,
it is now a time for international community
to care for their democracy.
Because what we see…
the expansionist kind of approach has now
crossed Tibet or…
It has reached beyond Asia and also in the
West.
Our democracy, our open society,
our freedom is under threat.
I think it is key for Tibetan.
This 10-year is completely important,
especially for new generation.
Also like Tibetan inside and outside,
how we continue our movement.
For that, we need to invest in the movement
to new a generation.
For the global community, I can see now the
governments or leaders
and the community are awakening.
We have been telling international community
long back like,
"You cannot trust China."
But people thought by doing business,
by opening of China,
there might be a trickle-down democracy,
Chinese might change.
But now things has gone from bad to worse.
The Human Rights Watch report said things
have much more critical, has gone bad, since
like 1989.
We are marking the 30-year of Tiananmen Massacre,
right?
Mm-hmm.
So I think it is time for Tibetans and also
global community
and people who care for freedom to really,
really think and to stand for Tibet issue.
I think Tibet issue is a litmus test,
because for last almost 60 years,
underneath His Holiness, Dalai Lama's leadership,
we had practice nonviolence as a mean to resolve
our issue.
If this movement fail,
of course it will caution the matter of nonviolence.
But as I said, not only from the religious
point of view,
but new generation leaders are, in smart and
strategic way,
see nonviolence movement as impactful and
practical,
and we are doing that.
But for that, we need global community support.
Mm-hmm.
Well, thank you so much for joining me today.
It was fantastic to have a chance to talk
to you.
Thank you so much, Chris, for having me.