On this episode of China Uncensored
Party on dude!
The Communist Party wants to be
the strongest party.
And the Catholic Church and the Communist
Party -
They go together like peas and cyanide.
Plus, is it a Titanic sequel?
Or a Titanic mistake?
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
A 7.0-magnitude earthquake
hit China’s Sichuan province
Tuesday night.
Hundreds were injured,
and at least 20 people were killed.
Fortunately, the area hit the hardest
was a relatively unpopulated nature preserve
called Jiuzhaigou.
But it is a popular tourist destination,
so 50,000 people had to be
evacuated from the area.
But don’t worry, everyone.
Chinese state-run media was there
to cover the important news,
like reassuring the world
that the pandas are ok.
Oh, and the foreigners are fine, too.
You know a lot of times
we focus on the Chinese Communist Party.
But really, we should be focusing
on the Chinese Communist Party!
It’s been a wild year.
The 90-year anniversary of the Party’s military.
A big Party Congress later this year.
And like every really good Party,
there’s been lots of purging...
of corrupt leaders.
Yes this Party can’t stop,
won’t stop.
And now, they’ve announced a new mission:
“to be the strongest party in the world.”
Good thing this week was
World Baijiu Day—
where they drink the strongest alcohol in
the world.
Oh yes, the purging has only begun.
Now, when you think of the Trump administration,
you might think of tin foil.
And for good reason.
The US Department of Commerce
has put a levy on Chinese tin foil—
technically aluminum foil.
Apparently some Chinese foil companies
were getting unfair subsidies
from the Chinese government.
Which makes me realize something.
In China, the government really is
watching you all the time.
And if they’re supporting the tin foil industry...
Oh my gosh!
It was a government conspiracy all along!
Anyway, speaking of conspiracies,
the Grammys.
A secret plot to make you excited about
musicians you never cared about
in the first place.
Well now the Grammys want to go to China,
to do a tour showcasing
some of their nominated artists.
One small problem.
Some musicians think they should be allowed
to have opinions about China haha.
No.
Already last month,
China announced Justin Bieber
wouldn’t be allowed to perform in China
due to undisclosed “bad behavior.”
Which left me torn.
Which do I dislike more?
Justin Bieber or the Chinese Communist Party?
But it’s not just Justin Bieber that’s
banned.
Less-terrible musicians are affected too.
Like Lady Gaga,
Bon Jovi,
and Selena Gomez.
They’ve all had concerts canceled in China
because of things they’ve said about
the Dalai Lama or Tibet.
So the Grammys have
“pledged to bring only well-behaved artists
to meet Chinese censors’ demands.”
Remember artists:
You can say whatever you want
about the American government.
Just don’t criticize the Chinese Communist
Party.
On another note:
the Catholic Church.
It has no official diplomatic relationship
with the Chinese Communist Party.
But the chancellor
of the Vatican's Pontifical Academy of Sciences
was in Kunming this week
attending an organ transplantation conference.
You know,
a conference held in a country
where the authorities are definitely not killing
political prisoners by harvesting their organs.
Now it seems that some officials in the Catholic
Church
are trying to build a relationship
with the Chinese Communist Party—
despite its ongoing crackdown on Christians,
and on religion in general.
Because they’re tired of the Party
picking all the bishops
and forcing believers to belong to
the Chinese Patriotic Catholic Association,
where, you guessed it,
patriotism is more important than God.
Anyway, as part of building that relationship,
earlier this year,
the Vatican held a conference
about organ trafficking and invited China.
Specifically, the guy in charge of
China’s organ transplant system—
the system that’s murdered
thousands of innocent people
to sell their organs
like a Wal-Mart for body parts.
Which is kind of like inviting the Big Bad
Wolf
to a conference on the structural integrity
of pig houses.
The Vatican defended their decision.
I believe their spokesperson called it
an eye for an eye,
a liver for a liver.
Speaking of bad decisions,
a Chinese company is building
a replica of the Titanic.
It’s meant to be a tourist attraction.
Now you might think,
this is a risky venture.
Every Titanic in history has sunk!
The original from 1912,
and the remake in 1997.
But to ensure that this boat will go on,
they’ve decided to built it in Sichuan Province,
600 miles from the nearest ocean.
At least you can stand on the bow and yell,
“I’m Chairman of the world!”
Thanks for watching.
Sadly, you’re still missing out.
This is only part of our weekly show.
The whole half-hour show is available now
if you visit China Uncensored.tv.
We publish our show there
every Friday afternoon.
See you there.