The Chinese Communist Party
Doesn’t want you to watch this video
But are they controlling YouTube?
Welcome to China Uncensored. I’m Chris Chappell.
The Chinese Communist Party has been very\h
successful at censoring Americans, even\h\h
inside America. Usually by leveraging corporate\h
interests that want to do business in China.
From the NBA banning Americans\h
protesting in support of Hong Kong...
To Zoom sending American user\h
data to the Chinese Government...
To CBS censoring its own shows for\h
criticizing censorship in China.
Yeah, that was ironic. Sorry, I meant tragic.
But what about Google?
Google has been trying to get back in\h
the China market for years. It tried\h\h
to secretly create a censored search\h
app for the Chinese Communist Party.\h\h
One US general has said that Google’s work\h
in China is benefitting China’s military.
So what does that mean for YouTube,\h
which is owned by Google—and\h\h
for channels on YouTube that talk about China in\h
ways the Chinese Communist Party might not like?
Joining me today to talk about that\h
is Matt Tye, better known as LaoWhy86,\h\h
who runs his own YouTube channel on China.
Matt, thanks for joining me today.
Hey, thank you so much, Chris.
So in a recent video, you suggest YouTube may be\h
compromised by the CCP. Why do you think that?
Sure. Well, I've had a really big problem\h
between all three of our channels. I mean,\h\h
I run Laowhy86, which is my own, I run ADVChina\h
together with Winston over on SerpentZA\h\h
and then we collab on each other's channels all\h
the time. Also we run the ADV Podcasts and all of\h\h
them are surrounding China content, China-based\h
content particularly they're recently about\h\h
the Chinese government. And although we've had\h
videos demonetized or suggested for limited ads\h\h
basically, it's their nice way of saying it.\h
We've had a recent problem where videos are\h\h
getting manually reviewed. So what that means\h
is in the past YouTube kind of decides, okay,\h\h
this video is limited ads. So you're not going to\h
get monetization on this, and there's nothing you\h\h
can do about it. But so many people complained and\h
they kind of changed the way they do things to be\h\h
more transparent about why you're not getting\h
ads or how they came up with that decision.
And what they suggest now is that you upload\h
your videos ahead of time so that they can\h\h
actually have a physical reviewer. Now, I don't\h
know if this works on smaller channels, but on\h\h
bigger channels, they'll have a physical person,\h
a real human being to watch your video and say,\h\h
this is okay, so that it won't get affected in the\h
future. It can't get flagged, it won't get taken\h\h
down. It's already manually reviewed by YouTube.\h
So what's recently been happening and I have three\h\h
concrete examples on my video on Laowhy86,\h
I made a video called Taiwan is a Country,\h\h
even if you wish it really wasn't. And basically\h
what happened was it was manually reviewed by a\h\h
human being as being totally fine so I was getting\h
ads on it. And then all of a sudden it was again\h\h
demonetized. It was demonetized after it had been\h
manually reviewed. So I was very confused because\h\h
when I went into this new transparent YouTube\h
system about how they kind of come up with this\h\h
conclusion, it said that that video had been\h
demonetized because of video game violence.
Now, my channel has nothing to do with video\h
games, obviously, no, I wasn't playing like\h\h
a Taiwan video game simulator and GTA V\h
or anything. This had nothing to do with\h\h
actually what the content was about. So I was very\h
confused, I went on to the live chat on YouTube,\h\h
and of course they bumped me up to their internal\h
team, the good old YouTube internal team,\h\h
which they looked at the video and quite\h
quickly said, "Oh yeah, it's totally fine.\h\h
Congratulations, good news your video is\h
monetized again." And that got me thinking\h\h
why not pursue this and see what\h
their decision-making process was?
So I said, you know what's going on? It was\h
flag what was the decision making process\h\h
that made this originally fine but then\h
another manual reviewer came in and said,\h\h
it's not fine? And they just completely\h
avoided that conversation and said, "Yeah,\h\h
thanks for your cooperation. Thanks for\h
your feedback. That's great." There was no\h\h
transparency involved. So they've effectively\h
made this transparent system to say that your\h\h
videos are monetized or demonetized for a reason,\h
but then they won't actually tell you that reason,\h\h
even after it's already been falsely\h
accused is something that it's not.
What are the consequences of\h
a demonetized video for you?
So this is something I think YouTube likes to\h
deny. They like to say that the monetization of\h\h
a video has nothing to do with its performance,\h
right? The thing is when a video gets demonetized\h\h
across all three of our channels or all four\h
of our channels, actually what we'll see is\h\h
that the performance of a video will spike\h
when it's monetized and it will be very,\h\h
kind of very stable. It won't really grow if it's\h
demonetized, if it has that yellow check mark.\h\h
And that's just our evidence like on our end,\h
but I've also heard other channels for example,\h\h
I heard something from Ethan Klein on H3 Podcasts\h
talk about how they've proven that basically you\h\h
could watch the spike of the graph. If a video\h
gets demonetized like halfway through its life,\h\h
it will stop getting views basically.
There's no incentive for YouTube to want to\h
recommend content that isn't making them money.\h\h
Especially if it's content that's getting\h
falsely flagged for reasons that they\h\h
might perceive as being offensive, or they\h
don't want to offend their audience, right?\h\h
If YouTube is caught recommending a content that\h
someone might deem offensive according to all the\h\h
flags that they're getting, then at the end of the\h
day, YouTube might be complicit in that content.
And so you think how you got flagged for\h\h
a video game violence, that was like\h
something somebody purposely did?
So this is my theory is that if you go\h
onto the Chinese side of the internet,\h\h
on the other side of the Great Firewall of\h
China, if you are searching things in Chinese,\h\h
you can find forums about both me and SerpentZA\h
and there's entire basically walkthroughs\h\h
and there's thousands of pages of this stuff, but\h
walkthroughs on how to use a VPN, get on a VPN,\h\h
go to YouTube, find our content, I saw\h
your content on there, Chris, as well.
Oh good.
Of course, to go on our content and\h
then to flag it for different reasons,\h\h
how to actually flag it, how to change your\h
browser into Chinese when you go to YouTube,\h\h
you know how to do all these things. And\h
the reason being is that they're voluntary\h\h
wumaos, voluntary fifty-cent armies that would\h
like to take our content down. And this is one\h\h
of the only ways that they can conceive of doing\h
this. Now, we've also found Western YouTubers,\h\h
American YouTubers doing the exact same thing,\h
following that same playbook, showing how to go\h\h
onto all of our content and flag us as this\h
and this and this, whether it's for racism,\h\h
whether it's for bullying, whether it's for\h
harassment, video game violence, or whatever.
What I think happened and this is what happened\h
on our ADVChina video for the Tiananmen Square\h\h
monument that we visited and paid tribute\h
to, is that they found that maybe the YouTube\h\h
reviewers are very lax on the whole video game\h
violence thing. Maybe they'll just say, yeah,\h\h
it's video game violence because there's a\h
ton of that out on YouTube and just kind of,\h\h
oh, whatever. Yeah, let's demonetized after\h
it's been flagged for that reasoning. Or the\h\h
other theory is that there's someone in there\h
that's constantly getting flags on our content\h\h
because we know that that's happening. We know\h
that, for example, on one of SerpentZA's video,\h\h
he did a video on the century of humiliation\h
and that's kind of what spurned the whole\h\h
tutorial thing. So we know that basically\h
they'll find any reason to report a video.
In that case, it was an old man who walked into\h
the camera, like into the shot and then they\h\h
flagged that for bullying an old man, the video is\h
completely removed. Now, in that case, it wasn't\h\h
even demonetized it's just removed. So we think\h
that there's probably either someone sympathetic\h\h
to that within the YouTube moderation sphere,\h
which you know that the idea is really difficult\h\h
to prove but the same time, how can somebody whose\h
job is to manually sit down and watch a video,\h\h
say, "Yes, this has been flagged for video game\h
violence. And yes, I'm going to approve this."\h\h
Certainly that's all traceable within Google,\h
the people who moderate there's a trail,\h\h
there's a paper trail of the moderators that\h
are actually flagging content. So it wouldn't\h\h
be impossible to prove, but it would be\h
impossible to prove without someone to\h\h
be able to go in there and look at the content and\h
see who was moderating and why they clicked that.
And has YouTube responded\h
in any way to your concerns?
No. So I put that video out and concern I wanted\h
to bring attention for people like yourself\h\h
people like SerpentZA, people like me. I wanted\h
people to understand that this is different than\h\h
a normal video that someone might find offensive.\h
This is potentially thousands and thousands\h\h
of flags coming at these channels, which is\h
going to do whether they ignore them or not,\h\h
it's going to do something in the whole\h
zeitgeist of how the content system works,\h\h
moderation system works in YouTube. If you're\h
seeing constant barrages of flags on a certain\h\h
type of content, eventually something's going to\h
happen and that we're starting to see that now.\h\h
I'll admit that the whole mass demonetization\h
has gotten a little bit better since they made\h\h
the whole human moderation process a thing. But at\h
the same time now we're seeing people physically,\h\h
actively okaying flags on these videos that\h
are not... They're completely irrelevant to\h\h
the content. And what we've noticed is that\h
it's always on very, very sensitive topics.
So if we look at the three concrete examples\h
that I have Taiwan is a Country, I mean,\h\h
chairman, she literally says, "Taiwan is our most\h
controversial issue." If we look at the Tiananmen\h\h
Square, the monument video, the video is\h
literally called the Chinese Government's\h\h
not Going to like What we Found in the Desert,\h
very sensitive issue for China, The Century of\h\h
Humiliation on SerpentZA's video, incredibly\h
sensitive issue. It's never stuff about,\h\h
you know maybe it's stuff that pokes fun\h
or maybe satire. It's never that kind of\h\h
stuff. It's always very, very cutting and\h
very, very sensitive topics that get hit.
Well in your video, you say\h
the Chinese Communist Party\h\h
is winning the propaganda\h
war. Why do you say that?
I say the Chinese Communist Party is winning the\h
propaganda war I mean, partially I'm referring\h\h
to the soft power that they put out there\h
on YouTube. And what I mean by winning is\h\h
that there's not a mass army of people in other\h
countries that are reporting their content. To\h\h
me for someone that has actually been affected by\h
the Communist Party of China and sees the absolute\h\h
atrocities that they commit, for me to see the\h
Chinese Government able to post freely on the\h\h
Western internet to try and sway opinion in the\h
Western World or in other countries to me that's\h\h
offensive to me. But I'm not going out there\h
reporting their content and you're not finding\h\h
thousands or millions of potential people getting\h
paid or voluntarily going to report their content\h\h
either. So when I say they're winning, they're\h
actively using Western platforms and freedom\h\h
of speech that they themselves ban in their own\h
country to spread their own oppressive message.
And I just find that kind of ironic because you\h
have numbers on your side. So when someone like\h\h
me or you, or Winston tries to put out content\h
and information and stuff that we truly believe\h\h
about the Communist Party of China,\h
and we get mass attacks, mass flags,\h\h
not to mention the death threats and all that\h
other kind of stuff that I'm sure you're very\h\h
familiar with, they don't have to deal with\h
that. So from that aspect, they're winning,\h\h
they have the platform and the tools to do that,\h
the money to do that and the audience to do that.
Why is the Chinese Communist Party so concerned\h
about what YouTube shows have to say about China?
Well, I think there's a couple of reasons. One\h
thing that really bothers the Chinese Communist\h\h
Party is that they're worried that when a Chinese\h
person does in fact use a VPN, maybe it's an\h\h
English savvy person. When they go over to the\h
other side of the internet, they want to make\h\h
sure that they have enough content for them\h
to consume, to confirm their internal bias. So\h\h
we know how the Chinese brainwashing system works\h
and the education system of Government of China.\h\h
People are, if they're a little bit curious,\h
I'm not talking about dissidence or anything,\h\h
if they're a little bit curious and they want\h
to hop over to the English speaking internet\h\h
or a place where they can freely express\h
their opinions or consume other opinions,\h\h
they want to make sure that there is enough\h
domestic type media there. So you got CGTN,\h\h
you have pro-CCP Western YouTubers that are\h
definitely a huge force right now in terms of\h\h
attracting Chinese nationalist audiences\h
on the other side of the internet.
And they want to make sure that it's kind of\h
a safe place. So it's just people like us,\h\h
our dissenting voices are actually kind of drown\h
out in that whole mess, but there's also the other\h\h
thing is that China has a huge prerogative\h
to want to sway Western opinion to make\h\h
its own system look good. So when you hear all of\h
this news, let's say, or opinions from us about\h\h
how oppressive freedom of speech is, the freedom\h
of religion and all these issues that China\h\h
has really horrible track record with.\h
When you hear about all these things,\h\h
but then you hear a ton of other opinions that\h
kind of drown that out, or kind of make that less\h\h
reliable and you see other people able to post\h
on YouTube on these supposedly websites that\h\h
are blocked in China, Facebook and YouTube,\h
but how do these people get away with it? How\h\h
does this person walk around with a camera\h
in China and just say whatever they like?
It starts to create questioning in people's minds\h
and when you have mainstream media here in the\h\h
U.S. that really just preys on the insecurities\h
of people and really likes to big up chaos and\h\h
all kinds of busy clickbait media, when you have\h
this kind of zeitgeist, but then you see this\h\h
bastion of stability that China likes to portray.\h
It all of a sudden becomes a little bit more\h\h
palatable in authoritarian system like China.\h
Number two, you have China's prerogative of\h\h
just wanting to have soft power throughout the\h
world, whether it's financially benefiting them or\h\h
diplomatically as well. So it's not just Americans\h
that are watching the Chinese media stuff.\h\h
It's not just their prerogative to... I'm trying\h
to formulate here, but our channels for them are\h\h
dangerous because it offers a differing opinion\h
to something they dumped millions and millions\h\h
of dollars and man hours into trying to portray.\h
It flies in the face of all that. So if we have a\h\h
big enough audience, that's a big threat to their\h
hegemony. It's a big threat to their influence.
So moving forward, what are you guys going to do?
I mean, honestly, like an interview like\h
this, where we're talking about it openly,\h\h
we're all in the same boat here. We'd like\h
to see YouTube actually be a little bit more\h\h
transparent I'd like them to reach out to me\h
[inaudible 00:13:47] and tell us why content is\h\h
being flagged. I want to know is the concept being\h
flagged, what is being flagged for and why someone\h\h
would manually review that content as something\h
that it's not? I don't want a reply in this email\h\h
chain to be like, "Oh, we thank you for\h
your cooperation." I want to know why?\h\h
When I ask why I expect a reason why. As a content\h
creator, we're putting our intellectual property,\h\h
we're putting our ideas and hard work out\h
there. I expect to know why something happened.
I understand that I, you and Winston are using a\h
platform that has community guidelines and rules,\h\h
but those community guidelines and rules\h
haven't been broken in these videos that I'm\h\h
referring to. So I'd like to them to\h\h
not just say that they're being transparent\h
with these new tools of human moderation,\h\h
but telling... Giving concrete reasons as to why\h
content is still being demonetized or removed.
Well, thanks for joining me today\h
and sharing this story with us.
You're welcome, Chris. Thank you for having me.
So at this point I think it’s pretty important\h
to like and share this episode so more people\h\h
can know about how the Chinese Communist Party\h
is influencing what you can watch on YouTube.
Also, coming out today is the 100th\h
episode of the China Unscripted podcast,\h\h
and I had both Matt from Laowhy86 and Winston\h
from SerpentZa (Corner Box both) on for an\h\h
incredible interview. Check\h
out the link below for that.\h
I’ve also put a link to Matt’s episode below,\h\h
be sure to check it out and\h
subscribe to his channel as well.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next time.