Two million people took to the streets of Hong Kong.
They're calling for Hong Kong chief executive Carrie Lam to resign.
Have these protesters changed the future of Hong Kong?
This is China Uncensored, I'm Chris Chappell here in Hong Kong.
On Saturday, Carrie Lam said the Hong Kong government
was going to postpone the controversial extradition bill.
But as you can see by the massive protests all around me,
that may not have been enough for the people of Hong Kong.
What you're looking at is a lot of very, very mad Hong Kongers.
It's over a proposed extradition bill.
If passed, it could allow the Hong Kong government
to extradite people in Hong Kong
to mainland China for trial.
And Carrie Lam, the Hong Kong chief executive,
did not seem to understand how upset people were.
This is what she said a day before the protest:
I feel deep sorrow and regret
that the deficiencies in our work
and various other factors
have stirred up substantial controversies.
But she didn't stop at that stunning apology.
She also said the Hong Kong government would postpone voting on the extradition bill.
But is that enough for the people of Hong Kong?
Well, let's ask them!
Uh, not quite, because
she still said that people do not understand
why this bill has to be passed.
But I don't think so.
I think it is
a difference in value.
I think it's a wise decision to postpone and review the ordinance
and make more of a social awareness that the people of Hong Kong need.
Also extremely important, it's the lack of faith in Beijing.
Beijing must show more good faith
not just to Hong Kong but Taiwan, the Philippines
and the general neighborhood.
As you can see, Carrie Lam is kind of screwed.
Lam had called previous protests over the extradition bill "organized riots."
And called this a very "restrained" response by police.
Police used 150 cans of tear gas in a single night.
By comparison,
in the entire 79 days of the 2014 umbrella movement,
they only used 87 cans of tear gas.
I guess Carrie Lam isn't good at saying "stop."
One of the themes of today's protest was "suspend your mother,"
referring to Carrie Lam.
It's sort of a Cantonese pun that invovles lots of swearing.
Any way, protesters were demanding Lam stop labeling the protests as "riots,"
and release students who were arrested.
They also wanted her to fully withdraw the extradition bill.
And, oh yeah, resign.
But since the protest was on Father's Day
it was also a fun event for the whole family.
Why did you choose to spend your Father's Day like this?
It's not my choice. It's the government's choice to push us together to do the protesting.
And I think we're doing the right thing, definitely.
We think this is a good sign to show that we support
the students and the rest of the protesters.
How do you feel being here with your whole family?
I'm proud of them because I think they understand
what to do, why they should be here,
and what they are fighting for.
It's a nice feeling to be here with my dad
and to know that I'm not the only one
the only part of my family that agrees with me on these things, these ideals
Why'd you come out here with your family today?
Because it's important to let the other
the next generation know about these events.
This law has to be cancelled.
Because I want my next generation to have a better life and more freedom.
And how do you feel to be here?
I'll interview you again in a couple years.
Protesters came from all parts of Hong Kong society.
There were so many of them, they spilled over into other streets.
Organizers said there were almost 2 million protesters.
Double last Sunday's protest.
Hong Kong only has 7 million people.
Which would make this the largest protest in Hong Kong history.
But police said there were just over 300,000 people.
Maybe the police need some help with counting.
Nobody expected this many people.
And in response to this unprecedented protest,
Carrie Lam issued an apology.
...written in the third person.
"The chief executive apologizes to the public, and promises that she will accept criticism in the most sincere and humble way."
Problem solved...
After one of the biggest protests in Hong Kong history,
clearly, the people of Hong Kong have woken up.
They will not go quietly into that good night.
Well, except for these people. It has been a long day.
Once again, Chris Chappell here in Hong Kong.