Which of these two maps is correct?
It depends who you ask.
Most countries don’t recognize China’s
territorial claims.
But China is trying to change that.
By slowly changing the maps you see around
the world.
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
This episode is sponsored by MOVA Globes.
This is the coolest globe you’ll ever own.
But there’s one thing that most people buying
it won’t notice...
but China Uncensored viewers will.
And some of you already have.
It turns out, there’s no single, standard
map of the world—
at least not from the perspective
of the world’s roughly 200 countries.
Not every country agrees on where the borders
are.
For example, India has border disputes
with both Pakistan and China,
so each of those countries
has its own version of the world map.
And most notably, the People’s Republic
of China
thinks they own the entire South China Sea.
That’s why, on China’s official maps,
they draw this Nine-Dash Line.
Everything inside belongs to China...
including the entire country of Taiwan,
which is also claimed by the People’s Republic
of China.
Plus, China’s map claims this giant chunk
of India’s
Arunachal Pradesh state.
China calls it “South Tibet.”
The important thing here is that while
this is China’s current official map,
pretty much no other country’s government
agrees.
In fact, in 2016, an international tribunal
in The Hague
rejected China’s claims to the South China
Sea.
That made it official.
Except that China rejected the Hague’s ruling...
and then ramped up its own plans to
quietly change the rest of the world’s maps.
That’s why when you look at a map printed
in China,
it looks like this.
Here’s a closeup.
As you can see, this globe has the Nine-Dash
Line,
and Taiwan is the same color as mainland China.
So wait...why is China Uncensored sponsored
by a company
that prints China’s version of the map on
its globes?
Turns out, it’s a crazy story.
It all started a few months ago.
Shelley, Matt, and I were at a museum in Norway.
And we saw these MOVA Globes in the gift shop.
I thought, “Cool, that’s our sponsor!”
And then I looked more closely.
On each globe, I could see China’s Nine-Dash
Line.
I was surprised,
because *this* is the globe MOVA had sent
us before,
when they sponsored America Uncovered.
It does *not* have the Nine-Dash Line.
Some of our viewers also contacted us
and said they noticed the Nine-Dash Line on
their own MOVA globes.
So we emailed MOVA and asked them what was
going on.
And they told us their fascinating story
of Chinese censorship and crippling fines.
MOVA International is an American company
based in San Diego.
But their globes use a lot of complicated
high-tech parts
that are not available in the US.
So, and this may sound familiar,
they set up shop in China,
by contracting with a local factory.
That way it was easier and cheaper
to get the parts they needed.
They began making globes in China in 2008.
By 2017, MOVA was doing
more than 80% of its manufacturing in China.
MOVA makes dozens of designs, including earth
globes,
the moon, other planets, even a Van Gogh painting.
MOVA has always focused on the technology
of their globes.
They’re not an educational company.
So they were never concerned with the politics
of maps.
MOVA purchased their map designs from a Chinese
vendor,
and then had a local company do the physical
printing.
That includes their 12 globe designs
that have political maps of the world.
And it turns out, Chinese government regulations
require that all maps sold in China,
or printed in China but sold abroad,
have to have China’s official version of
the world map.
And since MOVA had its maps printed in China,
it had no choice but to comply with Chinese
law.
Over the years,
and especially since the 2016 Hague ruling,
the Chinese government has strengthened its
map printing rules.
As my favorite Chinese state-run media The
Global Times put it:
The goal is to “make the [Chinese] government’s
position on territory
clear to the international community.”
And this is important,
because “Problematic maps... will confuse
the international community
about China’s territory and the government’s
position,
or even be hyped by those with ulterior motives,
seriously damaging national interests and
the government’s image.”
And while most normal people would consider
this to be... ludicrous...
the People’s Republic of China takes it
very, very seriously.
And they literally have inspectors check every
single Chinese factory—
including foreign companies’—
to make sure their maps are politically correct.
Here’s another example.
Shelley got this map as a Christmas gift.
You can scratch off the countries you’ve
been to.
It’s sold by a UK-based company.
It, too, has China’s Nine-Dash Line.
Guess which country that map was printed in?
And when Shelley scratched off China and Taiwan,
they were the same color.
Sorry, Shelley, you only get credit
for visiting *one* country now.
Even digital maps of China are affected.
While Google Maps looks like this...
Chinese-owned Baidu Maps looks like this.
It has China’s version of the border with
India,
the Nine-Dash Line,
and Taiwan is labeled like a province of China,
not a separate country.
And artwork has been affected, too.
Last year, Chinese students protested
at the London School of Economics
because a giant upside-down globe sculpture
showed
Taiwan as an independent country.
As you can see from this photo,
Taiwan is clearly pink while China is yellow.
After an international controversy,
the London School of Economics solved the
problem
in the most academic way possible:
They added a footnote.
And the map controversy has hit retail stores,
too.
Last year, clothing company GAP
was criticized by Chinese authorities
for selling a T-shirt with the “wrong”
map of China.
This is what GAP’s shirt looked like,
And this is the map it was “supposed”
to have.
GAP wrote an apology so pathetic it’s almost
unreal.
They said: “Gap Inc. respects the sovereignty
and territorial integrity of China.
We’ve learned a Gap brand T-shirt sold in
some overseas markets
mistakenly failed to reflect the correct map
of China.
We sincerely apologize for this unintentional
error.”
Other companies that have recently
apologized to China over maps include:
Versace...
Christian Dior...
And Audi...
Just last month,
following that NBA-Hong Kong debacle,
sports broadcaster ESPN showed this graphic
of China—
complete with Taiwan and the Nine-Dash Line.
All this is to say,
that a huge number of companies that print
their products in China,
or simply have a business relationship with
China,
have felt pressure to make their world maps
conform to China’s official version.
And that includes the maps they use in products
sold in the rest of the world.
And given that most maps are made by companies
that are not educational companies—
like GAP, ESPN, et cetera—
those companies don’t really care.
Many of them are not even aware of the politics
surrounding maps.
And it’s much easier to just do what the
Chinese government requires,
than to take a stand against
the world’s most powerful authoritarian
regime
on what—for them—is a minor issue.
The United States and other free countries
don’t have these kinds of map restrictions.
So in the US, Canada, Europe, et cetera,
you can show any map you want.
Like Shelley’s scratch-off map—shipped
to the US
by a UK company that just happens to print
its maps in China.
See, it doesn’t matter if it matches
the US or UK’s official world map.
That’s called freedom of the press.
And the Chinese Communist Party
is taking advantage of *our* freedom of the
press.
Their plan is to get the rest of the world
to recognize their territorial claims.
I’m not exaggerating.
They literally say that in state-run media.
So the Chinese Communist Party
is slowly infiltrating all the maps everywhere,
by controlling the printing inside China,
and pressuring Western companies outside China.
But this cloud has a silver lining.
Not every company is a coward like GAP.
Which brings us back to MOVA Globes.
The management at MOVA told us
they hadn’t even noticed the Nine-Dash Line
until we pointed it out to them.
But now MOVA *is* aware.
And MOVA has stopped production in China.
I’d like to say it was our message to MOVA
that convinced them to pull out.
But it wasn’t.
It was something even crazier.
See, this is MOVA’s Antique Terrestrial
map.
It’s based on an Italian world map from
1790.
In 1790, China was ruled by the Qing Dynasty,
and the map of China looked very different.
But guess what?
China’s communist authorities
don’t recognize that map,
because China was labeled in Italian.
Chinese inspectors had approved
all MOVA Globe designs since 2008.
But things seem to have changed in 2017—
right as China was strengthening its map printing
rules.
That’s when Chinese government inspectors
entered the factory—
the one MOVA had contracted to make their
globes.
The inspectors saw this antique design,
and told them they couldn’t print it—
because it doesn’t match China’s guidelines.
That’s crazy!
But it gets crazier.
The inspectors stopped the presses,
and issued steep fines for, quote,
“not being in compliance with China’s
rules and regulations.”
This applied to the antique designs,
plus a number of modern designs.
All in all, MOVA was forced to pay
more than 40,000 US dollars in fines.
So what was MOVA to do in this kind of
highly politicized environment?
They closed up shop,
and moved all their manufacturing to Taiwan.
Well, they didn’t actually close up shop
themselves.
The Chinese government did.
Officials boarded up the factory,
and forbid them from accessing it until they
paid up.
They had to pay,
because that factory still housed
a lot of MOVA’s expensive internal components,
like solar cells and magnets.
And it’s those components
that make MOVA globes spin magically like
this,
without any wires or external batteries.
This unique technology is the core of their
business.
So the Chinese government essentially forced
MOVA
to pay more than 40,000 dollars
just to go into the factory and collect their
own components.
All in all, it was a very expensive form of
censorship.
As of 2019, MOVA does 100% of its printing
and assembly
at its own facility in Taiwan.
And since Taiwan is a free country,
MOVA can now print whatever they want with
no restrictions.
And now that the US has a 30% tariff on certain
imports from China,
it’s actually less expensive to manufacture
in Taiwan.
But like many companies,
even after pulling out of mainland China,
MOVA is still facing pressure.
See, even though MOVA’s map designs are
now printed outside China,
each globe uses highly specialized Low-Light
Solar Cells,
and a Low Friction Motor.
And there’s only one country
that manufactures those components:
You guessed it, China.
Which is why MOVA’s willingness
to even work with China Uncensored is so courageous.
Very few companies have the guts to do it.
And that’s why I can proudly say that
this episode is sponsored by MOVA Globes.
And for the record,
we approached them about sponsorship.
And, get this:
MOVA still had some of those Nine-Dash Line
designs in stock—
the ones printed in China.
I asked them to send me this one,
because it’s a limited collector’s item
now.
I mean, who else gets to own one of these
awesome
self-spinning globes that has the Nine-Dash
Line?
And until supplies runs out,
you too can get one of these Nine-Dash Line
globes.
This model is called “Political Map Blue”.
A link with our tracking code is in the description
below.
And when you buy one of these MOVA Globes,
you’ll not only have a great story to tell
your friends.
You’ll also be directly supporting China
Uncensored.
And trust me,
we’re not going to be sponsored by GAP any
time soon.
So click the link below and check out MOVA
Globes.
And wherever you are in the world,
if you see one of China’s Nine-Dash Line
maps in a store,
in a magazine, et cetera—let us know.
Send us a photo on Facebook messenger
or to ChinaUncensored@gmail.com.
Then we can all see how widespread this phenomenon
is.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.