Is the Coronavirus plague warfare?
China is charged in one of the biggest hacks
in history
And Chinese jets harass Taiwan.
That and more on this week’s China news
headlines.
This is China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
This week’s China News Headlines.
First up, the coronavirus,
now known as COVID-19.
Currently, it’s believed the virus spread
from this wet market in the Chinese city of
Wuhan.
However, that might not have been the original
source.
Therefore, there’s only one logical explanation.
IT WAS A BIOWEAPON THAT ESCAPED A CHINESE
LAB!
Yes, I’m channeling Alex Jones,
but that’s not his conspiracy.
Maybe he believes it.
But he didn’t come up with it.
It’s actually a widely popular theory
spreading almost as fast COVID-19.
So much so, that Fox News anchor Maria Bartiromo
actually asked that question
to White House trade adviser Peter Navarro.
“They knew that coronavirus had happened
back in December.
They sent a delegation to the White House
to shake everybody’s hand.
They knew that they had this virus that had
started with the 'phase one.'
Then, they sent the largest delegation ever
to Davos.
And now, the ambassador to China
was on one of the Sunday shows this weekend,
and he did not deny that coronavirus could
have started,
could have started in a weapons lab.
“Do we know if this started in a research
lab?
And how come they won’t allow the CDC in
there
to better understand how this started,
because if they started this in a weapons
lab,
that’s evidence that they are developing
or trying to develop
weapons of mass destruction, biological weapons.”
Wait, is Maria Bartiromo asking if Chinese
authorities
were using the coronavirus to *infect* US
officials
and rich and powerful people at Davos?
I mean, she was talking kind of fast
but I’m pretty sure she’s implying that
the coronavirus
could be plague warfare.
That is giving Alex Jones a run for his money.
Look at poor Navarro’s face.
Pro tip: If you’re going to ask your interview
guest a leading question,
at least give him a chance to *answer* your
leading question.
On to another conspiracy theory—
one that turned out to be true.
Remember that massive Equifax hack back in
that stole the personal information of 145
million Americans?
At the time there were rumblings
that maybe Chinese state-sponsored hackers
were behind it.
Well, the US just charged 4 members of the
Chinese military for the hack.
Don’t worry, 145 million American who were
affected by their actions.
The Chinese military only gained access to
your name,
address, Social Security number, driver’s
license number,
and a few other minor details.
And anyway, the Chinese military says they
didn’t do it.
Why is America such a big bully?
The US Justice Department has been busy.
Besides charging Chinese hackers for the Equifax
hack,
they also charged 5 people in New York and
Texas
for selling sanctioned Iranian oil to China.
They managed two shipments of oil per month
worth a profit of 28 million dollars.
But they now face 25 years in jail.
Partially because, you know,
China buying Iranian oil is funding Iranian
terrorism.
The Pentagon submitted its 2020 budget proposal.
The focus is on keeping pace
with high tech weapons developments in Russia
and China,
including “boosting hypersonic missiles,
nuclear modernization, 5G technologies, and
missile defense,
as well as the newly-minted Space Force.”
A big part of that is ship killing missiles.
It comes at a time when China is rapidly building
up its Navy.
I’m sure there’s no connection though.
Meanwhile, the State Department is hammering
China’s military
for crossing into Taiwan airspace.
Yes, while the Chinese regime
should be dealing with the outbreak of a deadly
virus,
they put resources into military drills and
harassing Taiwan.
Surely the world will be successfully distracted!
Except now the US is flying bombers near Taiwan
to show that they’ll stand by Taiwan’s
side.
2020 is the year everything goes wrong
for the Chinese Communist Party.
So what do you think?
Let me know in the comments below.
Be sure to like and subscribe
for more of the China news that impacts you.
And as you may have heard me mention,
YouTube has refused to run ads
on most of our episodes about the coronavirus.
Which means we can’t afford to keep covering
it.
Except for one thing:
We have the support of viewers like you,
whom I call the China Uncensored 50 cent army.
Through your contributions on the crowdfunding
website Patreon,
China Uncensored can keep paying our staff
and our expenses,
so we can keep letting you know about important
China issues,
like a deadly global pandemic.
So as a thank you to supporters,
I answer a question from them at the end of
some of my episodes.
Today’s question comes from rswaggs
“What is the Supreme People's Court?
Doesn't Xi interpret all the Chinese's laws?”
Good question!
Well, the Supreme People’s Court
is the highest court of law in China.
Which is kind of an oxymoron since China
doesn’t really have rule of law.
But since the 1980s,
China has built up a structure that looks
a lot like a legal system.
The difference is, the Communist Party uses
the law
to go after people it wants to go after—
but not everyone is treated equally under
the law—
if you’re rich, if you have connections,
and especially if you’re a Party member.
Unless you’re a Party member who makes a
big mistake.
Keep in mind,
the Chief Justice of the Supreme People’s
Court once said,
“China’s courts must firmly resist
the Western idea of judicial independence
and other ideologies that threaten
the leadership of the ruling Communist Party.”
So does that mean Xi controls the courts?
Not directly.
The Communist Party is like the world’s
most nightmarish bureaucracy.
Xi definitely has a lot of power now,
but he still has to guard his back
from all the other Communist Party members
who would love to see him gone
and maybe themselves put in as replacements.
This means there’s a lot of compromise
that goes on behind the scenes.
They’ve called it the collective leadership
of the Party.
But even if Xi Jinping doesn’t have the
final word,
you can be sure it is still the will of the
Communist Party
coming through on any sensitive verdict.
Thanks for your question.
And if you’d like to join the China Uncensored
50-cent army,
head over to patreon.com/chinauncensored to
learn more.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.