On this episode of China Uncensored,
does Xi Jinping have the soccer balls
to fight corruption?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Xi Jinping.
Paramount leader of the Chinese Communist
Party.
Chairman of the Central Military Commission.
And huge soccer fan!
And it’s not just Xi Jinping.
Soccer,
or football as some people erroneously call
it,
is pretty popular in China.
But for the country that invented the sport
2,000 years ago...
...it’s surprisingly bad
at producing soccer champions.
But that’s going to change.
Because Xi Jinping is a baller.
And he wants to maker soccer huge in China.
He’s said his “Biggest hope for Chinese
soccer
is that its teams become among the world’s
best.”
Because in Communist China,
the Party tells you what sport to like.
Xi Jinping has a nationwide soccer plan.
Because to get people to truly love soccer,
you need the kind of top down,
centralized approach you can only get
under authoritarian regimes.
In fact, the State Council even released
a Chinese soccer reform and development directive.
Because when you want to promote a sport,
the first question is,
what kind of guiding communist ideology
do you need?
Like the theories of Deng Xiaoping,
or the Three Represents.
Or the Five Defensive Kicks.
The directive also states that 50,000 schools
need to specialize in soccer by 2025,
up from 5,000.
It also wants to more than sextuple
the number of soccer fields—
from 11,000 now to 70,000
by the end of 2020.
Ping pong diplomacy was so Cold War.
And guess what?
When the head honcho
says soccer is very important,
government officials and influential business
leaders
at all levels decide
they, too, love soccer!
And they’ve been going to crazy lengths
to outdo each other,
proving how much more they love the game
than the other jerk,
in hopes of hitting a homerun with Xi Jinping.
What’s that Shelley?
Oh sorry, wrong sport.
Make a slam dunk with Xi Jinping.
Thanks, Shelley.
Take for instance this 167-acre campus
containing 50 soccer fields
and a squad of soccer coaches from Spain.
It’s part of the world’s largest soccer
academy,
owned by the Evergrande Group,
run by Chinese property tycoon Xu Jiayin.
At the top of China’s soccer pyramid
is the Chinese Football Association Super
League,
also known as the Chinese Super Friends
League of Justice.
Since Chinese scientists have not yet perfected
soccer playing robots,
the Chinese Super League
is coughing up huge sums of money
to recruit players from around the world
to come to China
to play and teach.
They’re even outspending the English Premier
League
by more than 100 million dollars.
That's quite a full-court press.
They recently turned this Argentinian soccer
star
into the highest paid player in the world.
He has a $40 million dollar contract
with Shanghai Shenhua,
a Chinese soccer club I’d never even heard
of
until this week.
And it’s not just him.
China has 4 of the top 10 highest paid soccer
players
in the world.
The number two guy gets paid over 25 million.
Next at number 5, over 20 million,
number 9, 16.5.
That’s sad.
Only 16.5 million dollars?!
What can you even buy with that?
Anyway, why is Xi Jinping so focused
on reforming Chinese soccer?
Well let's recap.
Soccer in China involves: Big Government,
Big Business,
and lots and lots of money.
Would you be surprised if I told you
soccer in China is riddled with corruption?
Yes it turns out soccer in China
is somehow even more corrupt than FIFA.
And it's been corrupt for years.
So corrupt, that in 2008 state-run CCTV
refused to broadcast soccer matches
for more than three years.
They cited Chinese soccer’s
“lack of professional ethics.”
Which is a pretty rich coming from CCTV.
It’s like Lindsay Lohan calling Miley Cyrus
not very professional.
So in China,
match-fixing and bribes are rampant.
China’s top referee, Lu Jun,
used to be called the “golden whistle.”
In retrospect, it was a good name,
because he was making
so much money in bribes.
But he finally got put in the penalty box
when he was sentenced to five and half years
in jail
for taking 128,000 dollars in bribes
to swing the outcome of 7 games in 2003.
And remember that giant soccer academy
built by Evergrande Group?
Well, it also owns one of the major soccer
clubs
in the Chinese Super League.
And one of its coaches was caught paying
almost 300,000 dollars to a rival coach
to ensure his team won.
Maybe it’s more like the League of Shadows.
Since gambling is mostly illegal in China,
a huge 600 billion dollar underground gambling
syndicate
sprung up to handle illegal sports betting.
By comparison, all of Macau,
the only place in China where gambling is
legal,
brought in only about 28 billion dollars in
2016.
But after Xi Jinping came to power in 2012,
he started applying his anti-corruption campaign
to soccer.
CCTV even started broadcasting the game again.
Maybe it was just so Xi Jinping
could have his photo op with David Beckham.
Or maybe it's because companies
were using soccer to launder money.
You see, there's one big issue
that Chinese authorities
have been struggling to control.
And that's the massive amounts of money
people are trying to move out of China.
It's almost like they don't think it's safe
there.
Coincidentally, Chinese companies
have been spending a lot of money
to buy foreign soccer teams.
According to Quartz,
Chinese buyers have invested over two billion
dollars
in 14 European soccer teams since 2015.
And not just bargain basement teams.
Big names like AC Milan.
But some of these deals might just be a way
for investors to get their money out of China.
In fact, China’s top Foreign Exchange regulator
“accused Chinese firms of moving assets
overseas
under the cover of deals
that don’t make good business sense.
In particular...
the acquisitions of foreign soccer teams.”
What a curveball.
So with all the spending—
and massive, massive corruption—
you’d at least think China would be
an up-and-coming soccer world power.
But according to the current
FIFA/Coca Cola World ranking,
China comes in at 86th,
which is below Montenegro.
I don’t even know where that is,
but I looked it up,
and apparently that entire country
has a smaller population than most
third-tier Chinese cities.
But it still has a better national soccer
team.
And without some kind of Hail Mary,
China's national team is less and less likely
to qualify for next year's World Cup.
It looks like the China soccer dream
still has a long way to go
before it can knock one out of the park.
So what do you think of Xi Jinping’s plan
to turn the world’s most corrupt soccer
league
into champions?
Now, that’s a movie idea if I ever heard
one.
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored,
once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.