On this episode of China Uncensored,
what’s the greatest threat
facing the Chinese military?
Apparently it’s
“Up, up, down, down, left, right, left right,
B, A start.”
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
China may have the biggest
standing army in the world,
but its troops are a little distracted these
days.
So distracted, they can’t fight.
At least according to the official newspaper
of China’s army,
the People's Liberation Army Daily.
And it all has to do with this.
It’s a Chinese mobile phone game
called King of Glory.
Also known as Honor of Kings or Strike of
Kings.
And it’s so addictive
The PLA Daily says it could sap
the fighting power of soldiers.
I mean who wants to fight a real war
when you could be pretending
to fight a war instead?
PLA Daily said,
“The game has already infiltrated
the daily lives of some soldiers and officers,
affecting [their] physical and psychological
health
on a certain level.”
Well that’s simple enough to deal with.
Just don't play that level.
King of Glory is a fantasy role playing
mobile phone game
based on Chinese historical characters.
Like the famous poet Li Bai.
Sorry, he looks like this in the game.
He’s an assassin.
And there’s also the famous doctor Bian
Que.
In the game, he kills people with poison.
And let’s not forget famous hero...
Mulan?
Mushu the dragon looks
a little bigger than I remember.
I actually agree with state-run People’s
Daily
when they say the game
might be slightly misrepresenting history.
Fortunately, the English version of the game
fixed that,
by adding a more
historically accurate character:
Batman.
I’m not making this up.
For some reason,
they added Batman.
And King of Glory is not just
super addictive for Chinese soldiers.
It’s become the most popular
mobile game in the world
with 200 million active users.
That’s about one out of seven people
in China.
It’s made by
the Chinese company Tencent.
Remember that name,
because we’ll come back to Tencent
later in the broadcast.
Anyway, as I said,
the game has become so popular
it’s become a distraction.
Last month, Party Mouthpiece People’s Daily
called it a “poison”
and a “drug” for teenagers
“That [article] caused the market value
of Tencent
to plunge by US$17.5 billion at one point.”
Tencent responded by putting time limits
on how long people could play.
Which is good because Internet addiction
is becoming a major problem in China.
And you do not want to be sent to
one of China’s Internet addiction boot camps.
And finally, Big Brother is watching.
So could you be a little more entertaining?
In China, everyone is being filmed all the time.
Cameras are everywhere
They even have special police buses for it.
So what do you think of the effect
King of Glory is having on Chinese troops?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode
of China Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Sorry Mario,
but your princess is already watching
the full length episode of China Uncensored
on our website ChinaUncensored.tv.
Every Friday,
we upload a new half hour episode
free of charge.
So you could have seen this episode earlier.
Don’t be a goomba.
Visit ChinaUncensored.tv.