Chinese leaders announce new solutions...
to fix the crisis in Hong Kong.
There’s just one problem:
They’ve already tried them before.
And guess how that turned out?
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Another weekend of pro-democracy protests
in Hong Kong
left dozens of people injured,
and one man in critical condition.
In one shocking incident,
a man shouting pro-Beijing slogans
slashed four people with a knife.
And then he bit off part of the ear of a pro-democracy
politician.
Somebody’s been picking up tips from watching
old Mike Tyson fights.
It’s gotten so bad,
journalists even wore hardhats
to a police press conference in protest of
police violence.
Stop.
Police.
Lies.
Get it?
The police did.
But the only thing they stopped was the press
conference.
Anyway, the Hong Kong crisis is clearly in
need of a solution.
Fortunately, someone’s finally going to
step in and solve everything:
These guys.
I’m sure it’s going to be the perfect
solution.
Last week was the Fourth Plenum.
It sounds like some weird astrological thing.
But it’s actually the annual super secret
meeting
of the Chinese Communist Party’s Central
Committee.
During that meeting,
top leaders put their noggins together,
and came up with three brilliant proposals
for Hong Kong.
The first of the three proposals is that Beijing
will support Hong Kong’s efforts to quote
unquote
“strengthen law-enforcement capabilities.”
That’s not exactly a new idea.
It’s actually a lot like the anti-subversion
law
they proposed back in 2003.
It was called Article 23.
Article 23 was designed to prohibit
“any act of treason, secession,
sedition, and subversion”
by the people of Hong Kong.
Basically, it would mean that a bunch of things
that were illegal in China but allowed in
Hong Kong,
would now also be illegal in Hong Kong—
things like criticizing the government.
The only problem was,
the people of Hong Kong didn’t like Article
23.
They were afraid it would be used to crack
down
on pro-democracy marches and undermine the
rule of law.
I wonder where they got that idea.
So they protested.
Actually, half a million people protested.
And the Hong Kong government backed down,
and withdrew Article 23.
That’s why, as one expert puts it,
with last week’s proposal,
the Chinese leadership “is just re-doubling
its efforts
to implement more strenuously a policy
that caused the problems in Hong Kong in the
first place.”
Ok, so the first idea might not work.
But don’t worry.
Chines leaders have a second proposal, too.
See, as any good Maoist will tell you,
the best way to get people on your side is
to brainwash them.
That’s why the new proposal calls for patriotic
education in schools,
to help kids understand from an early age...
that they should love the Chinese Communist
Party.
The only problem is,
they tried a similar scheme back in 2012.
And it didn't go well.
People protested.
School students led the protests.
That included weeks of sit-ins,
and massive street demonstrations.
Finally the Hong Kong government got the message
that the kids don't need no thought control.
Though a bit of education in spelling wouldn't
hurt.
So that patriotic education proposal
that fell through seven years ago?
It might not work so well this time, either.
So the first and second ideas might be a bust.
But don’t worry!
Because the brilliant Party leadership
has a third great proposal.
They plan to change how Hong Kong’s Chief
Executive
is appointed and removed.
What does that mean?
“There was no elaboration.”
Oh.
So they could mean that Hong Kong’s leader
would be removed in the middle of the night
to an undisclosed location.
Ok, probably not.
But it does smell a lot like the proposal
they had back in 2014.
See, in 2013, the Hong Kongers
had been promised universal suffrage.
That is, they would get to directly elect
their Chief Executive.
But then in 2014,
Beijing modified that promise, saying,
“Yes, you can elect your Chief Executive...
but first we get to pick the candidates.”
Which is like saying,
“As I promised, you can have anything you
want for dinner.
Choose between broccoli, cauliflower, or brussels
sprouts.”
By the way, for anyone watching
who finds those options delicious,
you’re wrong.
The joke is that they’re all terrible.
Anyway, Beijing’s proposal about getting
to pick
Hong Kong’s candidates was massively unpopular.
Hongkongers didn't like it, and protested.
The police met the protesters
with some light tear gas and pepper spray.
And so protesters pulled out umbrellas to
use as shields.
This was the start of the Umbrella Movement.
People were so upset that the CCP
tried to rig the election that they continued
to protest.
They set up tents, and occupied three main
Hong Kong thoroughfares.
It lasted 79 days.
Eventually, police came in and cleared them
out.
And arrested a bunch of people.
Oh, and Hongkongers never got the right
to elect their Chief Executive.
Just a guess here,
but Beijing’s new plans last week
to “change how Hong Kong’s leader is appointed
and removed”
...probably don’t include giving the people
universal suffrage.
All this is to say, that the Chinese Communist
Party’s
newest solution to end the current Hong Kong
protests
involves three proposals—
that are just like proposals that all *caused*
massive protests in the past.
So is this one of those things where,
“If at first you don’t succeed, try try
again”?
Or is it like,
“The definition of insanity is doing the
same thing
over and over again
and expecting different results”?
My guess is it’ll be more like,
“Putting out a fire by pouring gasoline
on it.”
Which is either stupid...or evil genius.
If their proposals push the protests to spiral
out of control,
Beijing will have no choice
but to send in the People’s Armed Police
to “restore harmony.”
After all, according this video
purposefully released by state-run media,
they’ve been training.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And now it’s time for me to answer a question
from a fan who supports episodes like this
by contributing through the crowdfunding website
Patreon.
Anders Andersson asks:
“How comes the Hongkong Police
[are] so loyal to CCP to quell the protestors
(and violent)?
Are they mainlanders?
Good question, Anders.
I’ve had the distinct...pleasure, let’s
call it...
of being in Hong Kong during the 2014 Umbrella
Movement...
and then later during the recent,
um, 2019 Tear Gas Movement.
The police changed in five years.
In 2014, the police officers were mostly polite.
There were a few clashes,
and there were a few police groups that were
more troublesome.
But the main body of police just tried to
protect everyone.
When I was in Hong Kong last month,
it was completely different.
The police are out of control, and violent.
Yes, there are rumors that some of them
have been brought in from mainland China.
That might explain why they’re acting like
mainland thugs.
But so far, those are just rumors.
But either way, Hong Kong police commanders
have pretty much given the officers carte
blanche
to do whatever they want.
Plus, they’re wearing masks but no ID badges,
and there’s a law against doxxing them.
So they have the protection of being anonymous.
On top of that, they’re overworked and stressed
from five months of continuous protests.
This is a recipe for disaster.
It doesn’t even require loyalty to the CCP.
Thanks for your question, Anders.
And thank you to everyone who’s watching.
Go to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored
to learn how you can be like Anders and support
the show.
If you pledge a dollar or more per episode,
you’ll even have a chance to get your own
question in the hat.
Plus your support helps us pay our staff,
travel to Hong Kong,
and keep making episodes like this.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.