Hiding Behind a mask
Protesters fight for justice
Against a police force
that can no longer be trusted
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
On Wednesday, June 12,
teachers and students showed up in force
around the seat of the Hong Kong government.
Their demand:
End a controversial extradition bill
that could allow the Hong Kong government
to send people from Hong Kong
to mainland China for trial.
You know, where people tend to get killed
for their organs.
The police responded with a kind of brutality
rarely seen in Hong Kong.
They fired 150 cans of tear gas.
They fired bean bags and rubber bullets,
hitting one man in the face.
He was later arrested at the hospital,
since police can access people’s information
directly from hospital records.
It was a horrifying night that left many traumatized.
And helped spark a 2 million person strong
march
only a few days later.
Now protesters wear masks
to hide their identities from the authorities.
Fighting for justice,
while hiding in the shadows.
Like Batman.
But with less weapons,
and more public support.
During Sunday’s 2 million strong march,
I spoke with two protesters
who were there the night of June 12.
Why were you out on the streets
protesting on Wednesday night?
On Wednesday night,
I just feel like Carrie Lam can not hear our
voice,
and our voice of being neglect.
1.03 million ordinary citizens like myself,
went onto the streets,
and our voice was crystal clear.
We want the government to withdraw
their extradition bill to China.
So, what did you see that night?
Actually, I was not there at the afternoon.
I just came back home to dress up
and clean up myself and I opened the television
and I saw the very shocking picture.
The people was shot by the police.
They very clearly to see the people shoot
to the heart.
This is really shocking.
And they attacked the journalists,
the riot police rush over there
and the people keep going, keep going, moving,
everywhere is tear gas and I feel very, very
shocked.
I hesitate a while and dress up again and
go out again.
So you were initially kind of scared to go
out there?
Yeah, really scared.
But I just don't want to fight alone.
What happened when the police turned violent?
Protestors sent out a clear message to Carrie
Lam.
They need to withdraw the bill by 3.30 on
Wednesday,
otherwise we'll occupy the Legislative Counsil.
However, our voice was not heard,
so students and protestors surround the Legislative
Counsil,
and police just like burst out tear gas, with
batons.
Of course, there are some chaos
in between protesters and police,
but the majority of the students there
were protesting very peacefully.
Suddenly I heard bam,
and people were screaming,
“Someone got shot!
Someone got shot!”,
so I was furious and curious at the same time.
And I saw the medics carry injured person
out
with a big wound all over his face,
with really thick blood.
The blood was so thick and it leave
a big stain on the ground.
So the police force just sent out,
it's called Special Tactical Squad, STS, AKA
Raptors.
So, the Raptors just keep beating up students
in the front line.
And that one protestor was hit with a rubber
bullet, correct?
The one who got hit by the rubber bullet
was unwarned before they opened fire.
To me, this is against human rights,
and I think this a war crime.
What do you think of the police response?
I don't have much emotion to police
because I realized that after the Umbrella
Movement,
I just think that they are just like machine.
Just follow the order.
I can't believe the police want to shoot our
head,
must be someone ordered them to do so
and just follow the order.
So when you were there on Wednesday night,
and the police were firing rubber bullets
and tear gas,
how did you feel?
I feel furious.
I feel disappointed.
Right after the Special Tactical force
beat up students in the front line,
Protestors were not doing anything provocative,
and we were not provoking the police.
While protestors were being squeezed in between,
like sandwiches,
the Raptors just kept throwing tear gas into
the crowd.
I see a lot of families,
a lot of young students,
like five foot little girls were there.
I mean, Hong Kong police force, ask yourself,
you've got families,
how can you do that to ordinary citizens,
and tax payer like us?
So, what do you think of Carrie Lam
calling it organized riots?
To be honest,
they are just ordinary students,
from my observation.
Many of them are high school or students in
university.
I don't see how ordinary students like them
could be an organized crime.
We are not talking about triads
or any terrorist organization.
So, Carrie Lam,
you should really watch your word.
For those watching,
why do you want to keep your face hidden?
Because now the police said this event is
riot, yeah?
And this is a very serious crime,
several years of this, so I have to-
In jail.
So I have to cover our face
and every Hong Kong people very shocked
because we just want to go to Tamar Park to
assemble.
Maybe some people want to charge,
the police want to storm the building,
but most of them is just sitting there.
They got the family,
they got adult,
so many teenager,
most of them is very peaceful.
And the police tried to shoot us,
do the tear gas,
and also came this as the riot.
I can't accept that.
So why do you want to hide your face?
I want to stay anonymous because Hong Kong
right now
is fill of white terror.
The hospital assisting the police
to make arrests in emergency room,
so people need to be really careful,
and the police are start making a lot of arrests
now.
So I want to stay anonymous because I'm afraid.
What do you think about Carrie Lam
saying she's postponed the Extradition Bill?
Is that enough?
She lie, of course.
She lied.
I just think she is not the someone
to decide to go this bill,
but she have to listen to order from someone.
I don't know what is someone.
Maybe the country, maybe someone, the leadership.
But her response really, really, really show,
yeah.
So you're not satisfied with Carrie Lam saying
they're going to postpone the extradition
bill?
There's a big difference between postpone
and suspend.
Are you worried about the future,
both for yourself and Hong Kong?
Of course.
We are quite disappointed at this place.
After everything you saw on Wednesday night,
are you afraid to be back here today?
Of course.
Of course, I scared, everybody's scared.
We just citizen, we have no power.
We are not armed, but we have to.
We just have to.
And are you nervous being here again today,
after everything that happened?
I am really panicked.
I am paranoid.
And what are your feelings about the future
for Hong Kong and for yourself?
To be honest, if it keeps going,
if it keeps progressing this way,
I don't see no future in Hong Kong.
I feel like the police,
the government are trying to end our future.
Students are our younger generation
and we need to protect them, educate them,
but not forcefully spoon-feed them what they
think
we should learn.
It's all about critical thinking.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thank you very much for joining.
And thank you for watching.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell,
reporting from Hong Kong.