Welcome back to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
If you were living under a brutal, authoritarian
regime,
how would you change things?
Would you rally your fellow citizens to take
up arms
against the tyrant?
Or would you use nonviolent civil resistance?
I’m willing to bet you already have a strong
feeling about
which way you would go.
But what if I told you that according to historical
data,
the most likely way to make meaningful change
is through nonviolent resistance?
You might not believe me.
But I sat down with a man who wants to convince
you otherwise—
Dr. Peter Ackerman,
founder of the International Center for Nonviolent
Conflict.
Nonviolent, conflict?
Sounds like an oxymoron.
But his organization has advised dissidents
in dozens of countries
on how to create lasting regime change without
using violence.
Thank you for joining me today, Dr. Ackerman.
So, why nonviolent resistance?
Well, why totalitarian rule?
It's a response to totalitarian rule,
to the kind of rule that people feel oppressed
under,
that makes their lives miserable, and puts
them under threat of death,
pestilence, bad education, injustice.
All the horribles that one can think of for
humanity
correlate with tyrannical rule,
and one of the responses to tyrannical rule
that I believe
has been effective for decades if not millennia
is civil resistance, o
r nonviolent resistance, or people power,
when understood
and used with the most strategically sound
methods.
But can nonviolent resistance really stand
up to a bloodthirsty dictator?
Remember, a bloodthirsty dictator can't shoot
everybody with his own gun.
He can try.
Yeah, but even he doesn't try.
What he can, what he must do,
is he must have people who will do it for
him.
Even Hitler had people who had to do it for
He has to muster an army, a police,
and not all these organizations remain loyal.
Sometimes, the more bloodthirsty you are,
the more brittle you are, because the bloodthirstiness
carries over to your own military.
Remember, the newest head of North Korea took
his uncle,
put him on a fence post, and shot him with
an artillery round,
in front of the cadets on graduation day,
as I understand it.
Look at how solid True Korea is.
Yeah, it's as stable as you can imagine.
The American Revolution was a violent revolution,
and America's the greatest country on Earth,
so how can nonviolent revolution be better
than violent revolution?
Well, there were important nonviolent tactics
used,
like the tea party.
The Boston Tea Party was a nonviolent tactic.
No one is saying ...
We can't be absolute.
No one is saying that violent tactics
linked into a strategy can't be effective.
It was against the British,
but there are also factors that were not military
in character
that also impacted the outcome.
An occupation is a difficult thing from across
an ocean.
Now, we have done a study of 323 insurrections
between 1900 and 2006.
They were divided into two kinds of insurrections,
those dominated by violent tactics, guerrilla
warfare, insurrection, terrorism,
whatever you might want to think of,
and those that are dominated by tactics that
maintain nonviolent discipline,
strikes, boycotts, mass protests.
There's hundreds of them, bank holidays, consumer
boycotts.
Where people stop supporting the system.
Or disrupt the system.
Disruption.
What we found was that of the two-thirds
that were dominated by violent tactics,
based on their own goals as articulated,
they reached their goals 26% of the time.
With respect to campaigns of civil resistance
or people power movements,
those goals articulated by them were reached
53% of the time,
and the transfer of power that occurred was
10 times more likely to be
democratic after a civil resistance movement
than a violent insurrection.
You're saying nonviolent resistance is actually
a more effective means at achieving democracy.
That data would suggest just that.
Wow.
People like to use the term nonviolence and
confuse it with nonviolent conflict.
When you think about nonviolence, you think
about people who are there to
basically convince you of the error of your
ways,
to sit cross-legged with incense and say,
"Beat me until you basically have sympathy
of my views
so you'll change your ways."
It has a component that's very moral in its
impetus,
which is a wonderful thing,
but it doesn't overthrow dictators.
Because I have yet to meet a dictator,
or hear about one, when he's asked to give
up some of his power,
he says back, "Would Tuesday be soon enough?"
They don't give their power up. It has to
be taken,
so nonviolent conflict is the act of disruption
that leads to defections that undermines the
legitimacy of a dictator
or an authoritarian.
You're saying this is an aggressive form of
nonviolent conflict.
No. All nonviolent conflict is aggressive.
It's just that nonviolence,
which is peaceful, tranquil, has nothing to
do ...
It's not a strategy.
It's a morality.
It's a fine morality.
Now, one of the things that confuses people
is,
what about Gandhi and King?
They both were committed pacifists, true,
but nobody would care about Gandhi if, in
1930,
he didn't leave his ashram, walk 210 miles
to Dandi Beach,
pick up a handful of mud, throw it into a
pot of boiling water,
turn it into salt, which was illegal to make,
and have 250 million people follow him,
do the same thing,
and then read from the viceroy of India that
if this disruption continues,
and the local constabularies around India,
if only 100,000 basically defect,
we're going to have to leave.
This is basically a targeted strategy of regime
change.
Power shifting. It may lead to regime change,
or it may lead to a new mode of coexistence
between the tyrant and the opposition,
but it's a power shifting,
a dramatic power shifting to restore human
rights,
to restore justice, liberty, property rights,
the things that basically advanced societies
have a lot of and enjoy.
What are some of the tactics that you encourage
dissenting groups around the world to use?
We don't give advice about what tactics to
use,
but we try to make them understand that there
is
a tremendous variety of tactics.
Let's take in Poland,
it was the Gdansk shipyard strike.
In South Africa, it was the boycott in Port
Elizabeth.
In India, it was the salt march.
We did the story of the Nashville lunch-counter
boycott
in the civil rights movement.
In Chile, it was a referendum that undid Pinochet.
He thought he was going to win.
He didn't.
He told the military, "Please, let's forget
we ever had a referendum."
The military says, "You're done." Remember?
I do.
He wants to shoot them. They won't shoot.
They're in big trouble. In Ukraine, it was
a protest in Maidan
for a month that basically led to a military
defection.
In Egypt, which is I think yet to be successful,
we had Tahrir Square, which was that eruption.
Let's shift over to China.
Then of course Tiananmen in China.
...that didn't exactly go so well.
Now, when you say it didn't go well,
that tactic alone didn't get the job done,
but there's a difference between tactics and
strategy.
A strategy that works is when you knit a series
of tactics together.
It went very well if you measure the tactic
in terms of
successfully disrupting the status quo.
It certainly did that.
The question wasn't about that tactic,
but what would come next.
The only way you know what comes next is if
you're trained
to think about how to link tactics into a
strategy,
and that's what the International Center on
Nonviolent Conflict does.
Our site is very rich. We help dissidents
around the world.
We don't tell people who we're helping,
but we've now helped probably dissidents in
70 countries
over the last 15 years.
That's what we do.
It's a coaching mechanism to make people think
strategically
about the campaign of civil resistance.
How do you coach that?
Because in the Tiananmen protest as well as
many other grassroots movements around the
world,
the question is always, who is in charge?
Who is making these decisions?
Now, often, they end up shooting themselves
in the foot.
There's a lot of different ideas.
First of all, who's shooting who in the foot
in a nonviolent conflict?
Themselves. It's a metaphor.
Did they shoot them? Yeah, it's a metaphor,
okay, but there's a lot there that needs to
be unpacked.
A nonviolent resistance movement done badly,
people will shoot themselves in the foot,
but they won't shoot themselves in the foot.
They might shoot themselves in the foot,
but it might hit the little toe.
A violent insurrection that screws up,
they shoot themselves in the head.
There's no coming back from it.
We have data to show that a civil resistance
movement
that even is not successful lays the seeds,
potentially, for another one four, five, or
six years later.
That's exactly what's happening in Iran today.
Or like in Hong Kong,
where they had the Umbrella Movement in 2014.
Even though that did not necessarily achieve
all of their goals,
that movement is still alive.
Exactly.
In a country like China,
how can the population that is under so much
propaganda ...
The Communist Party has this thing called
patriotic education,
where from a young age, people are taught
that the Party
is there for them,
that they have to love the Party,
that the Party is China. In an environment
like that,
how can people decide to begin a nonviolent
resistance movement?
Well, let's answer this by referring to Natan
Sharansky,
who was the great refusenik in the Soviet
Union,
where that ideological indoctrination was
just as intense.
He asked a very interesting question.
How was it that the people in the gulags,
the people who basically were under the most
pressure,
lived the most miserable\hlives,
were able to predict the end of the Soviet
Union
where all the intelligence agencies of the
world
and all the smart people who were Russian
experts couldn't?
Because they knew something that's profoundly
true,
that in every authoritarian regime, there's
four kinds of people.
There's the population that's apathetic and
just doing nothing.
Then, there's the part of the population that's
willing to dissent.
Then, they're in opposition to the third group,
which is the true believer,
who basically is at the very top and believes
the ideology,
whatever ridiculous justification it may have
for mistreating people
the way they do.
Then you have the latent double-thinker,
who is a normal human being,
who hates to see the collateral damage of
what the true believers
are trying to inculcate.
They become disillusioned.
That's exactly it.
Double-thinkers are the subject of disillusionment,
exactly.
Perfectly expressed.
So, the strategy is for the activists to convert
the double-thinkers,
or make them go from latent to active.
Yes. Now, China, we know there's lots of double-thinkers,
and they're latent.
The question is, how do they-
Take action?
First, how do they expose themselves safely
to find other double-thinkers,
and then take action? The disruption, like
I told you in India,
and I don't think there was 250 million people
saying before that,
"I want the Raj over," but as soon as the
guy made salt,
it was easy for people to say that that's
what they wanted.
People need to see that they can win.
They can win, or more importantly, it's that
they can express
their double-thinking without fear of terrible
reprisals.
They're always afraid of being the one head
that's above
the other that gets chopped off.
One of the tactics I know you talk about is
signage.
What do you mean by signage?
One of the questions I've been asked all the
time is,
"Won't the Internet make all this right?"
The answer is it may or it may not.
The Internet is interesting in terms of its
ability to
distribute information individual to individual,
but it's also a problem,
because it basically allows people to be tracked
individual to individual.
You can have granularity of communication,
granularity of tracking.
The Chinese Communist Party is especially
good at using social media.
So I'm told, yeah.
Now, the one thing that's interesting,
that I've been trying to tell people to think
about,
is stop this obsession with the Internet,
because the Internet is great,
but it's also a choke point.
Unless they're watching this show,
in which case they should still be on the
air.
Then you're unclogging the artery that's been
clogged,
and thank you for doing that, but the one
thing, people have to go outside.
There have to be buildings, and lots and lots
of signs expressing dissent
have a virtue of being out there.
They show that people are not in control,
that they claim to be.
They can offer directions. They can interact
with the Internet.
You know, "Click here." We haven't done nearly
enough technologically
to make sign-making instantaneous and hard
to track as to who is doing it.
If you want to say about the Internet, "Go
here," like in Tahrir Square,
everybody thought it was a Facebook revolution,
because people always refer to things based
on
what they're experiencing at the moment.
Facebook was taking off, but the fact is that
6% of the population
only were Internet-savvy, Internet-connected,
and the Internet was shut off
before Tahrir Square, but we don't want to
get into those facts.
It may be a choke point, but it may be an
addendum to something,
a form of communication that's not a choke
point,
but becomes a magnifier to something that
already exists.
That's what signage can be.
I wonder if this would count.
One of the largest groups of nonviolent resisters
in China right now
is practitioners of Falun Gong.
I know one of the tactics they use is to write
messages on Chinese money
and pass that around.
Same idea.
What can groups like that in China do to effect
change?
If we're talking about the logistical support
of
nonviolent tactics through signage,
one of the things we also have to realize
is that Facebook is not a strategy.
You've got goals, and you've got tactics,
boycotts, strikes, and then you have
a strategy that knits them together.
Then you have logistics that support a strategy.
Facebook is communications logistics.
It's nothing more than that.
We get enamored with Facebook and think it's
secure for everything,
but it's just a logistical tool.
We need to understand that.
Then we say,
"What other logistical tools can achieve the
same things?"
Once you basically sharpen your logistical
tools, your knives,
for the tactics you're going to use, that's
all they're used for.
Then there's the selection of tactics,
and the selection of tactics is far more important,
because the disruption you create will lead
to
a certain level of repression.
It might lead to obedience,
or it may lead to a certain level of disruption.
That may lead to defection.
The authoritarian regime wants to have as
much obedience
with as little repression as possible.
Of course.
The nonviolent resistance-
The civil resisters want to have as much defection
with the least amount of disruption.
That's where the competition is,
because if you have too much disruption and
too little defection,
the public will become apathetic.
If you have too little obedience with too
much repression,
the repression will backfire, and then-
People will defect.
the authoritarian has lost his main tool.
things the authoritarian wants you to stop
doing,
like a protest or a march,
and stop doing things they want you to continue
to do,
which is what you're talking about here.
The most important thing I would do is think,
what else can we do in combination?
Because it's the combination of tactics that
create a strategy.
Tactics on their own is not a strategy.
The power is in the combination.
At the end of the day, it's a game of chess
between
the authoritarian regime and the resisters.
Right.
Each using their tactics to try and defeat
the other.
Each using their tactics to create the best
strategy.
To create a strategy.
What the authoritarian is most worried about
is that the opposition
will actually have a strategy,
because what they want to do is disrupt that
possibility.
That's their best. They want to basically
make sure nobody unifies.
They want to make sure that nobody's thinking
about
different ways to disrupt.
They want to make sure nobody's planning.
Eisenhower said that plans are useless, but
planning is everything.
The ability to constantly think about how
to piece together a string of tactics,
always thinking about that, is very, very
powerful.
My son's a wrestler.
You don't just bull-rush an Olympic wrestler.
You have to basically pull his arm,
pull his head, touch his knee, and it's called
chain wrestling,
until basically if you do it properly, he'll
fall over.
You cannot talk about a tactic in isolation.
Let me say one thing.
A tactic in isolation, or a tactic combined
with another tactic,
or a tactic combined with a second tactic,
that first tactic has completely different
outcomes
depending on whether you combine it and what
you combine it with.
So that's the danger of violent resistance,
because it's very easy to just not think,
attack.
Yes. The real danger, why I think violent
tactics
and violent strategies are generally a loser,
is because the people who start with the guerrilla
movement
basically start with an inferior military
position.
The only way they can right that position,
which is a key to their having any hope of
success,
is to kill enough people on the other side,
who are mostly authoritarians.
But before that,
the people they're killing also are seeking
protection,
so they will go and basically strengthen
their relationship with the authoritarian
for protection.
They won't want to defect.
So, they won't want to defect.
I think a violent insurrection tends to work
against itself,
and that's why the data has shown very low
incidences of success.
Do you think we'll see a nonviolent resistance
movement
taking down the Chinese Communist Party?
I don't know what “taking down” means.
I know that a violent insurrection will never
have a meaningful impact.
I think it's a loser,
but remember the point that taking down is
a loaded phrase.
Do I think that over time, a nonviolent resistance
movement
is likely to create a complete new compact
of power
between those at the top and citizens?
I think there's a good chance of that.
Whether it means regime change or it comes
in a different form,
where the current practices are embedded with
other,
more democratic practices,
and individual rights are basically protected,
I can't say what the endgame is.
I know that civil resistance, if persisted
on, is highly likely,
over a 50% chance of creating a better,
more democratic endgame,
but we also know that violent ...
This is an interesting fact.
A violent insurrection takes nine years, on
average,
a civil resistance movement, three years.
If people can plan and persist for three years,
there will be a change.
That's what they need to know.
That's what we're in business to tell them.
I see what you mean about the importance of
language,
because taking down implies violence.
Really, what you want is a conversion.
A transfer of power.
That's brilliant.
Thank you very much for
joining me today.
A pleasure being with you.
Thanks for watching.
Want to see more interviews like this?
Leave your comments below about who or what
kind of person
you’d like to see on China Uncensored next.
And remember you can watch our full half-hour
episodes
on www.ChinaUncensored.tv.