Are US Allies joining President Biden
In countering the Chinese Communist Party?
Plus: New sanctions for Uyghur persecution
That and more on this week’s China news headlines
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
This episode is sponsored\h
by Surfshark Alert. It helps\h\h
detect if your private information has been\h
leaked online, or is part of a data breach.
This week in China news...
From the start of his campaign,\h\h
President Biden said he’d work with US allies\h
to counter the Chinese Communist Party.\h\h
And now for the first time, it seems like\h
that strategy might be bearing fruit.
The US, Canada, UK, and EU joined together\h\h
to sanction China for its\h
treatment of Uyghur Muslims.
The sanctions target current and\h
former officials plus a paramilitary\h\h
organization involved in the mass\h
detention of Uyghurs in Xinjiang.
The officials targeted will have their\h
assets frozen and be banned from travel.
This is honestly surprising\h
considering this is the first time\h\h
Europe has used sanctions against China\h
since the 1989 Tiananmen Square Massacre.\h
It’s even more surprising considering the\h
EU signed a preliminary trade deal with\h\h
China at the end of December, in which human\h
rights and US concerns didn’t factor in.
The US had led the way with sanctions on China\h
under the Trump Administration. The US had also\h\h
labeled the Uyghur persecution genocide. However,\h
this coordinated sanctioning under the Biden\h\h
Administration is new. Is Biden making good on his\h
promise to work with US allies to counter China?
Earlier this month, Biden also\h
met with leaders of the Quad,\h\h
an alliance of India, Japan, Australia,\h
and the US aimed at countering China.
But if you’re a US ally who’s\h
wondering whether you’ll have\h\h
to choose between the US and China, don’t worry.
This week Secretary of State Antony Blinken\h
also said the US won’t force allies into an\h\h
“us or them” choice between the US and China.
“The U.S. wants to out-compete with China,\h
not simply seek to defeat it, Blinken said.”
When asked to respond to Blinken’s comment,\h\h
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesperson\h
Zhao Lijian attempted to say something\h\h
about America’s decline, but instead just\h
laughed uncontrollably for five minutes.\h
And after the break, I’ll tell you how China\h
has responded to America and its allies.
Welcome back.
The new sanctions on Chinese officials are\h
no laughing matter for the Communist Party.\h\h
In fact, they’ve responded with\h
their own sanctions on the EU.
Those sanctions included\h
“blacklisting 10 European lawmakers,\h\h
as well as several think tanks and academics”.
The EU sanctions China for\h
crimes against humanity,\h\h
China sanctions the EU for\h
sanctioning them. Makes sense.
Of course, that may mean that fancy new\h
trade deal with Europe might be doomed.
That’s because several of the European\h
lawmakers the Chinese regime sanctioned\h\h
are members of the European Parliament—which\h
has to approve that trade deal.
And as a result of the sanctions,\h
the European Parliament cancelled\h\h
a meeting that was supposed to discuss that deal.
The US and China had also signed\h
a trade deal in 2020. That was\h\h
right before the coronavirus\h
became a global pandemic.
And this may surprise you, but China\h
hasn’t been holding up its end of the deal.
So if that deal also goes down\h
the drain...boo frickin’ hoo.
And now, to punish the US, the Chinese\h
Communist Party has been running a nonstop\h\h
propaganda blitz. They’re accusing the US of\h
racism, inequality, and a poor pandemic response.
You know they say we criticize in\h
others the things we see in ourselves.
Despite the draw of the China\h
market, the rest of the world\h\h
is beginning to wise up to the risk\h
posed by the Chinese Communist Party.
Take Canada, which is also\h
part of the recent sanctions.\h\h
China has kidnapped two Canadian citizens,\h
Michael Korvig and Michael Spavor.\h\h
Well, in the last week, both Michaels\h
were secretly put on trial for spying.
In both cases, the verdict hasn’t been\h
announced. But China’s justice system is\h\h
very efficient. Everyone put\h
on trial is found guilty!
Foreign journalists and diplomats were banned\h
from the trials. But in a show of support,\h\h
“More than two dozen diplomats representing\h
several countries, including Canada and the United\h\h
States, tried to gain access to the courtroom,\h
only to be turned away by security personnel.”
Hey, do you think the Chinese Communist Party’s\h
hostage taking might actually be backfiring?
More on that after the break.
Welcome back.
There are more signs that the\h
Chinese Communist Party’s aggression\h\h
is turning the world against it. NATO is now\h
looking to build partnerships with Japan,\h\h
South Korea, Australia, and\h
New Zealand to counter China.
And another US Admiral is warning\h
a Chinese invasion of Taiwan\h\h
is closer than most people think.
Of course, he’s obviously not talking about\h
most people who watch China Uncensored.
But as the Uyghur genocide continues to turn\h
people against the Chinese Communist Party,\h\h
the Party is striking back.
Facebook recently caught Chinese hackers\h
creating fake profiles to attack Uyghurs abroad.
The hackers would pose as activists or journalists\h
supporting the Uyghurs. They would send targeted\h\h
Uyghurs links to compromised websites. They\h
even created fake prayer apps for Android.
Meanwhile, the Chinese regime\h
has launched a boycott of H&M\h\h
for criticizing the treatment of Uyghurs.
In this statement last year, H&M said, Ohh,\h
I guess that page doesn’t exist anymore.
Hmm. But nothing is ever\h
really gone from the internet.\h\h
Here’s their original statement, which said,\h
“H&M Group is deeply concerned by reports\h\h
from civil society organisations\h
and media that include accusations\h\h
of forced labour and discrimination of\h
ethnoreligious minorities in Xinjiang.”
They also said they’d stop buying cotton from\h
Xinjiang, since it’s made with Uyghur slave labor.
Nike also released a statement on Xinjiang,\h
saying they’re committed to ethical and\h\h
responsible manufacturing. And that they\h
do not source products from Xinjiang.
Even though they lobbied against a\h
Uyghur slave labor bill in Congress.
And now Nike might be next\h
on China’s boycott list.\h\h
“On Wednesday, Nike was at the top\h
of Weibo’s ‘hot search’ list. Some\h\h
users were furious that Nike had joined\h
the boycott of cotton from the region.”
Never thought I’d see boycotts\h
against companies for *opposing*\h\h
genocide and slave labor. But that’s\h
the Chinese Communist Party for you.\h
And this episode is sponsored by Surfshark Alert.
Big data breaches happen all the time. Like\h
the 2019 Capitol One breach that affected\h\h
100 million Americans. Or the 2017 Equifax\h
hack that exposed data of nearly 150 million\h\h
Americans. Whether these hacks come from\h
China or elsewhere, your private information\h\h
can be exposed—like your credit card number, bank\h
account balance, social security number, and more.
If you’re concerned about data breaches,\h
identity theft, password leaks, or hackers,\h\h
you should use Surfshark Alert.
Surfshark Alert will notify you\h
if your data is compromised.\h\h
This way, you can change your passwords, close\h
exposed accounts, or switch to new companies.
And for a limited time,\h\h
you can save 75% on a 1-year Surfshark Alert\h
plan. Plus you’ll get 3 extra months free,\h\h
and you’ll get a free Surfshark VPN subscription.\h
All of this for just $3.19 per month.
To get this great deal, go\h
to “Surfshark-dot-Deals slash\h\h
UncensoredAlert” and use the code UNCENSOREDALERT.
Take control of your online security. Monitor your\h\h
credit cards. Guard your email passwords. Go to\h
surfshark.deals/uncensoredalert to learn more.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell. See you next time.