Chinese jets get aggressive against South
Korea.
There’s evidence China is killing innocent
people
for their organs.
And a top exec overseeing Google is in the
hot seat.
This is China Uncensored.
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
South Korea is having problems with China,
problems of the military variety.
Chinese military aircraft have been repeatedly
entering
South Korea’s Air Defense Zone.
Now that’s not quite the same as Korean
territorial airspace.
Airspace is covered under the United Nations
Convention
on the Law of the Sea.
Even though this is the air.
It’s defined as 12 nautical miles from a
country’s shoreline.
The Air Defense Zone is bigger
and not defined by treaties.
But still, it’s common practice to notify
a country
if you’re going to fly your planes into
their zone.
But the Chinese military didn’t.
In fact, it’s been getting more and more
aggressive.
“According to the South Korean Air Force,
the number of Chinese military aircraft
entering its identification zone is rising.
In 2016, there were about 60 incursions,
70 in 2017
and 110 were reported up to September this
year.”
It’s likely the Chinese Communist Party
is concerned about a US, South Korea, Japan
alliance,
a sort of Asian NATO, as some have called
it.
In 2016, South Korea and Japan
agreed to an intelligence sharing treaty.
China’s military criticized it as part of
a cold war mentality.
Of course, flying your jets through
another country’s air defense zone
in no way could be considered a cold war mentality.
Not at all.
China is on trial!
For some serious crimes against humanity.
Over the weekend in London,
an independent people’s tribunal was held
to examine
evidence that the Chinese Communist Party
is killing people for their organs.
People’s tribunals are typically set up
by victims of a serious crime,
when governments are unwilling to investigate
an issue.
After all, what government would want to
offend the Chinese Communist Party?
Do you know how much business we can do in
China?!
“The charges are that many groups including
Falun Gong practitioners,
Uighurs, some Christians, and some Buddhists,
have been taken as prisoners, checked on a
regular basis
whether they are medically fit, and then,
when the time comes, their organs are removed.
Some stories say without any anesthetics,
in a very horrible way—
and immediately transplanted into an organ
visitor.”
Many of the witness who testified were labor
camp survivors.
They had stories of extreme torture or sexual
assault—
but also strange medical tests.
Tests very similar to what would be needed
to match an organ.
According to Freedom House,
“The organ transplant industry in China
remains
enormous and growing,
even as the number of judicially executed
prisoners
has declined over the past decade.”
So where are they getting the organs?
The Tribunal’s chair,
former English Judge Geoffrey Nice QC,
said the tribunal unanimously found beyond
reasonable doubt that China has been committing
forced organ harvesting from prisoners of
conscience.
There will be more hearings early next year,
followed by a report.
And with any luck,
the issue might start actually getting
some attention from the mainstream media.
Of course, I think what they really need as
a publicity stunt.
How about a re-release of The Oregon Trail—
but set in China?
The CEO of Google’s parent company, Alphabet,
was asked to testify before the US House Judiciary
Committee on Tuesday.
There were a lot of issues on the table,
but a key one was how Google has been accused
of
secretly working on a censored search app
for the Chinese market.
Internally, Google gave it the codename Project
Dragonfly.
But the CEO stuck pretty closely to the talking
points
Google has been using since these accusations
came to light this summer.
"Right now, we have no plans to launch in
China.
We don't have a search product there.
Our core mission is to provide users access
to information,
and getting access to information is an important
human right.
So we are always compelled across the world
to try hard to provide that information."
Basically, he’s saying Google hasn’t launched
any search engine in China.
But he didn’t specifically say Google
won’t launch one in the future.
And really, what’s the point of giving your
project
a cool codename if you’re not planning to
launch it?
Now Amnesty International, Human Rights Watch,
and the Committee to Protect Journalists
all signed a letter urging Google not to go
into China.
But they weren’t the only ones.
Another signator,
coming all the way from Russia,
was Edward Snowden.
Have you ever stayed at a Marriott hotel?
Well, you might be one of the 500 million
people
whose personal information was taken by mysterious
hackers
back in September.
And I know this may surprise you,
but guess which country these mysterious hackers
were from?
It’s China.
The revelations come as,
“The Trump administration is planning actions
targeting China’s trade, cyber and economic
policies,
perhaps within days...
[and] also plans to declassify intelligence
reports to reveal
Chinese efforts dating to at least 2014
to build a database containing names of executives
and American government officials with security
clearances.”
We’ll keep you updated on those moves by
the Trump administration.
Remember a couple weeks ago how I told you
about
the Chinese scientist who claimed to have
created
genetically engineered twin babies?
Well, he’s missing.
Have authorities detained him because
his Frankenstein experiment made Chinese science
look bad?
Or did they just kidnap him for a secret project
to genetically engineer super soldiers?
I guess we’ll find out in World War III.
Speaking of abductions,
100 Christians have been abducted by Chinese
authorities,
some in the middle of the night.
They were all members of an underground Protestant
church.
Underground churches are ones that aren’t
approved
by the Chinese Communist Party and don’t
have state-approved pastors.
This is part of an escalating persecution
of Christians in China.
According to Bob Fu,
founder of the US-based Christian rights organization
China Aid, “
There were more than 10,000 cases of detention
of Christians this year,
compared with just over 3,000 cases for the
whole of last year.”
And it’s not just Christian worshippers
that have been targeted in China.
Authorities in Shandong Province noticed people
in one small village
had begun worshiping a giant stalk of sorghum.
They believed that since it had grown unnaturally
large,
it was most likely endowed with supernatural
qualities.
Obviously, any kind of non-atheist belief
like this
is a serious threat to China’s social harmony.
So police came and chopped it down.
Chinese police also announced a new policy
where all local imaginary friends will be
rounded up for execution.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And before you go,
it’s the time you’ve all been waiting
for,
when I answer questions from a member of my
50 cent army,
fans who support China Uncensored
through the crowd funding website Patreon.
San Son asks,
“I plan to leave Patreon.
Do you have an alternative support processor?”
Ah, I’ve been hearing this from several
people recently.
Some of you are concerned about Patreon as
a platform
after they banned a few YouTubers.
I understand where you’re coming from.
I would like to say that by abandoning Patreon,
it definitely hurts China Uncensored
more than it hurts Patreon.
And it also hurts you,
because Patreon gives us a platform
to easily provide all the perks to our supporters.
But even though we still prefer to use Patreon,
there are other ways you can contribute to
China Uncensored
if you want.
If you go to chinauncensored.tv/support,
you’ll see other options,
including direct PayPal contributions.
I’ve also heard from some of you I should
look into
Patreon alternatives like Subscribestar.
I’ll take a look at that platform and any
others you recommend.
Either way,
I would like to thank you for the support
you’ve given
and hope you’ll find ways to continue,
even if it’s not on Patreon.
But for all of you still on Patreon, remember,
you get to submit questions to me that I’ll
answer on the show!
So leave your questions for me there.
And to everybody,
thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.