On this episode of China Uncensored,
James Bond villains have some pretty frightening
technology.
And the Chinese regime is a quick learner.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I'm your host Chris Chappell.
You know, when I hear the Chinese regime is
working on plans for a supersonic submarine,
mining the moon,
or developing hypersonic nuclear missiles,
I can't help but wonder,
maybe the Chinese military has been spending
a little too much time watching James Bond
movies.
And then it hit me.
Of course they have!
The new James Bond movie Spectre is one of
the few foreign films allowed in China this
year.
On opening weekend alone, it raked in 48 million
dollars.
So it makes sense the Communist Party is learning
from a franchise with a proven track record.
So here are 8 James Bond Villain Technologies
Used by China.
Number 8: Space Lasers
The cornerstone of any evil mastermind's plan
for world domination surely involves space
lasers.
Like in or Die Another Day.
But what you might not know is that China
is building its own space laser!
It's the "largest ever space project."
The satellite will use massive solar panels
to gather solar radiation and convert it into
lasers to be shot down at Earth.
But it's totally not a weapon.
It's a "space solar power system."
You see China has a bit of a pollution problem,
and this alternative energy source is clearly
the most efficient solution!
Did I mention it's not a weapon?
Number 7: Space Station
Who could forget that magic moment when James
Bond tried to be Star Wars?
Moonraker has that Gravity movie beat hands
down.
This is the secret space base of the movie's
villain Hugo Drax,
who wants to wipe out life on Earth.
China's pollution is already doing a fairly
good job of that,
so of course a space station is in order.
Meet China's Tiangong-1 Space Lab,
launched in 2011.
China doesn't participate in the International
Space Station.
It has its own version.
And it will launch new ones in 2016 and 2022.
Obviously, this has nothing to do with vying
for control of space.
It's just for scientific purposes.
Number 6: Intellectual Property Warfare
Remember James Bond's View to a Kill?
Christopher Walken's character is the result
of a genetic experiment by Nazis.
And boy, does he have a real microchip on
his shoulder
"I propose to end the domination of Silicon
Valley,
and leave us in control of that market."
He wants to literally flood Silicon Valley
to eliminate competition for his microchip
company.
Now the Chinese regime basically has the same
plan.
Only instead of literally flooding Silicon
Valley,
they're just figuratively flooding the market--with
cheap knockoffs of Western technology.
According to the chairman and CEO of BLACKOPS
Partners Corporation, Casey Fleming,
intellectual property theft from China costs
the US 5 trillion dollars every year.
And James Bond was written by a man named
Ian Fleming.
Coincidence?
Yes.
Number 5: Tanks in the shape of monsters
Normal tanks might be fine for a boring old
army like America's.
But when you want to terrify the likes of
James Bond,
you need something with a little more flare.
In case you couldn't tell,
that was a dragon tank.
China wants to take it a step further,
and build a giant spider tank.
And it will look like this.
Number 4: Claiming Islands in the Middle of
the Ocean
Take a look at the secret island base occupied
by the villain from Skyfall.
Look familiar?
Tiny island in the middle of the ocean?
Used as a secret military base?
Well China is building its own islands in
the South China Sea-
and using them as military bases
I mean, uh,
for totally peaceful purposes only.
Number 3: Satellite Killer
Once again lets go into space.
In You Only Live Twice,
the main villain, Dr. Evil,
I mean Blofeld,
has found a unique way to take out spacecraft.
Well, China's got anti-satellite weapons,
too.
According to U.S. Air Force Lieutenant General
Jay Raymond,
"Every satellite in every orbit will be able
to be held at risk" by China's anti-satellite
abilities.
Now China wouldn't do it exactly like the
movie.
They have anti-satellite missiles.
They tested the first one last year.
Number 2: Underground Bases
Check out this underground base from You Only
Live Twice.
And guess what?!
It's full of ninjas.
Well China has scores of underground military
bases,
reinforced and almost impossible to destroy.
And its soldiers totally know kung fu.
Which is kinda like ninjitsu...?
Though apparently,
Chinese soldiers are no longer going to do
kung fu.
From now on,
they'll just shoot people with guns!
And Number 1: Surveillance of Everyone
If you've watched the latest James Bond movie,
Moriarty is back!
I mean, Spectre is back.
And this time, it wants global leaders to
share intelligence data so it can spy on the
world's population.
"Do not let them tell you we need less surveillance.
We need more.
Much more."
And guess who else is into massive surveillance
of its citizens?
Yep.
China.
And foreign companies even helped them do
it.
And let's just say it might not all be for
fighting terrorism.
Anyway, those are just a few things the Chinese
regime has done that they surely learned from
watching James Bond movies.
What do you think?
Leave your comments below,
and be sure to check out our Facebook page.
Once again, I'm Chris Chappell.
See you next time.