On this episode of China Uncensored:
Taiwan, China...
what's the difference?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I'm your host, Chris Chappell.
I’ve never been to Kenya,
and I certainly haven’t been arrested there.
But I hear their jails are great!
Or at least, I presume they must be.
That would explain why these 15 Taiwanese
citizens
in Nairobi, Kenya attempted to barricade themselves
in a jail cell.
Unfortunately, their delightful detainment
wasn’t to last.
A few moments later,
Kenyan police busted the door down,
grabbed them, and put them on an airplane.
And deported them to China.
This China, not this China.
Even though they’re from this China.
And if you’re not familiar with the “One
China” policy
that says that both of these regions are China,
watch this video.
And if you are familiar with the “One China”
policy,
you know why this awkward
sending-Taiwanese-citizens-to-mainland-China
thing
is such a big deal.
Here’s what happened:
These 15 people are part of a group of 45
Taiwan citizens
who faced charges in Kenya for telecom fraud.
They had been accused of defrauding people
in mainland China
of more than $93 million dollars in a series
of scams.
I can only assume they pretended to be African
princes
seeking to "transfer funds" to unsuspecting
victims.
Anyway, I'm not saying they didn't commit
fraud.
But they were acquitted by the Kenyan court.
That is, not guilty.
Yet the government of mainland China insisted
that Kenya send these Taiwanese to mainland
China for “investigation.”
As Kenya's Interior Ministry spokesperson
put it,
"They came from China and we took them to
China.”
Now it’s not that Kenyan officials are too
dumb to realize
that being from China and being from Taiwan
are not the same thing.
They just want to respect the "One China”
policy,
where Kenya only recognizes the CCP, and not
the Taiwan government,
as the legitimate rulers of all China.
As a Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesperson
put it,
"Countries which follow the 'One China' principle
are worthy of approval."
But while Kenya may get a gold star from the
CCP,
they're actually violating their own policy.
Because the Kenyan court issued an order to
not deport these people.
So why would they do it? Could it possibly
have to do with...
money?
Now I'm not saying these Taiwanese citizens
didn't commit fraud.
You may be innocent unless proven guilty in
America.
And in Kenya.
And in Taiwan.
But in mainland China, you're only innocent
until you're forced to confess on state-run
television.
Because that’s actually what happened.
And if this case is any indication,
now it could potentially happen to any Taiwanese
citizen
accused of a crime overseas—
even if they’re found not guilty.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments—or confessions—below.
And please support this show on Patreon.
Once again, I'm Chris Chappell. See you next time.
OK, so what do you need?
Suits. Lots of suits.
Wait...
Who is this?
Mania.
Official clothing sponsor of China Uncensored.
www.maniasuit.com