China wants Malaysia to pay $20 billion
For a new rail line
But Malaysia is fighting back.
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Malaysia.
A country that's truly...what's the word for
it?
"The soul of Asia,
the essence of Asia,
it's truly Asia…
That’s it, truly Asia.
Talk about a songwriter reaching for the low-hanging
fruit.
Not so for Malaysia's Prime Minister Mahathir
Mohamad.
He’s reaching for the sky.
Now 93 years old,
Mahathir holds the Guinness World Record
for being the world’s oldest Prime Minister.
And that’s a record he’s likely to hold
onto for a while.
At least until our planet
is run by an immortal artificial intelligence.
On the plus side, I’ll have also been upgraded
by then.
But the real reason to keep an eye on this
93-year-old
is that he’s just dodged a bullet...
at least when it comes to China’s Belt and
Road.
The Belt and Road Initiative is the massive
infrastructure plan
to build trade corridors between China and
the rest of the world.
It’s also known as One Belt,
One Reason to Not Go into Debt.
That’s because it has been a convenient
way
for the Chinese regime to saddle some small
countries
with debt they can't pay back.
So in exchange,
these countries have to sign over
valuable resources or assets to China.
The poster child for this is of course, Sri
Lanka.
When you can go from sun-kissed
to mountain mists in only four hours,
that’s so Sri Lanka.
When dolphins and whales swim around you all
year,
so you can visit them at any time?
That’s so Sri Lanka.
And when you take a giant Chinese loan
to build a deep water port,
can’t pay the loan back,
and then have to give the port to China on
a 99-year lease,
that’s so Sri Lanka.
The list of countries at risk
of falling into China's debt trap is long.
It includes places like Djibouti
Kenya
Pakistan.
And it looked like Malaysia, too…
But then came Malaysian Prime Minister Mahathir
Mohamad.
After taking office in 2018,
he right away suspended 22 billion dollars
worth of
China-backed infrastructure deals.
He also scrapped three China-backed pipeline
projects
worth 3 billion dollars.
And there was also a railway project
called the East Coast Rail Link.
It was supposed to be built by
China Communications Construction Company—
for a price tag of nearly 20 billion dollars.
He scrapped that, too.
But he still wanted some of the infrastructure.
Just not at that price.
So he re-negotiated the price of the East
Coast Rail Link—
from $20 billion to down to only about $11
billion.
Because the “economics of the original deal
did not make financial sense.”
As Mahathir's office said in a statement,
“This reduction will surely benefit Malaysia
and lighten the burden on the country’s
financial position.”
Yeah, it’s a *bit* lighter of a burden now.
Like $9 billion dollars lighter.
I wonder if the same negotiating strategy
can be used for student loans.
Anyway, given Malaysia’s crushing debt load,
any breathing space is a sigh of relief.
A year ago,
everyone thought that Malaysia was around
$170 billion in debt.
But when Mahathir took office last year,
he discovered, nope!,
Malaysia was actually $250 billion in debt.
How did this happen?
A few months ago,
I spoke with investigative journalist Clare
Rewcastle Brown—
who exposed the previous government’s
massive 1MDB corruption scandal.
She says the previous prime Minister, Najib
Razak,
needed money to cover his tracks,
after he’d allegedly stolen around 700 million
dollars.
And there’s not a lot of guys you can go
to help you fill a 700 million dollar hole.
Except China.
“What happened, because of Najib’s financial
difficulty,
he nearly dropped his rich and independent
country
like a ripe plum into the lap of China
because he needed someone to secretly
bail out his debts on 1MDB.”
The Chinese Communist Party:
The guy you call when you need to bury a body.
Or 700 million dollars.
Najib is now accused of wide-scale corruption
that includes skimming billions of dollars
off China-backed projects.
Najib went to trial last week in the first
of
what is expected to be multiple trials.
He faces four counts of corruption.
Each one could land him in jail for up to
20 years.
And if he lives to see the end of it,
he could win the Guiness World Record
for the world’s oldest former Prime Minister
in jail.
Anyway, after Mahathir Mohamad
won the election against Najib in 2018,
one of his first tasks was to be to pull Malaysia
back from the brink of a Chinese debt trap.
"He’s made it clear that he intends to revise
some of these deals that were made to bail
out Najib.
And Malaysia has been looking
very critically and openly and frankly
at the corrupt nature of these deals
and challenging Chinato back off
given these deals were clearly laced with
corruption."
It turns out, Najib had made a deal with China
that Malaysia would overpay for the East Coast
Rail Link,
and then China would secretly top up the cash
Najib stole.
Um, allegedly.
So Mahathir has begun to resolve this issue
by renegotiating the price of the project
with China.
But Mahathir is doing more than that.
He’s also taking his
“beware of bad Chinese deals” show on
the road.
On a recent visit to the Philippines,
he warned President Rodrigo Duterte to beware
of China's debt trap—
saying “the Philippines should
‘regulate or limit influences from China.’”
But Mahathir is also making some people nervous.
That is, some people connected to the Chinese
Communist Party.
Wang Yiwei, a professor at Renmin University
of China in Beijing,
worries that "it sets a bad example for other
projects,
that China can just lower the costs."
He says it could encourage other countries
to push China to cut prices on debt trap projects.
That would be terrible!
It would completely defeat the purpose of
a debt trap.
And Malaysia’s new attitude is even pushing
the Chinese regime to re-evaluate its own
actions.
“With pressures mounting at home and abroad,
Beijing has started to adjust its approach
to the Belt and Road Initiative —
trimming spending on projects and toning down
what it says.”
So the Communist Party has really got to tone
it down.
Or at least seem like they’re toning it
down.
So what do you think?
Could this be the beginning of the end for
some of the more worst Belt and Road debt
traps?
Leave your comments below.
And before I go,
now’s the time for me to answer a question
from one of you—
who supports China Uncensored
through the crowdfunding website Patreon.
Steve Wilson asks,
“Chris, with your education in music composition,
do you have anything to do with the music
that's played with China Uncensored videos?”
Good question, Steve.
I do have a Masters degree from NYU
in Classical Music Composition.
But the main thing that’s done for me is...
get me to move to New York,
where I ended up having the opportunity
to create China Uncensored.
I didn’t personally create the awesome Chinese
music
that we use in the episodes.
They were created by a friend of mine,
who’s a professional music composer and
audio engineer.
There are in fact 9 unique tracks
that belong to China Uncensored.
You’re listening to one of them right now.
And for all of you who contribute $5 or more
per episode through Patreon,
you get special access to download these tracks
so you can listen to them anytime.
So while I didn’t directly create
the music using my Masters Degree,
I do have the knowledge to appreciate
all the work that went into them.
Thanks for your question, Steve.
And thank all of you who support China Uncensored.
If you visit Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored,
you’ll see that we have increasing rewards
for different levels of support.
For example, depending on your pledge,
you can get my private monthly newsletter...
behinds the scenes stuff...
the awesome Chinese music...
your name featured at the end of episodes...
or at higher levels even dinner with me,
Shelley, and Matt.
So click the orange square button
at the end of the episode
to check out our Patreon page.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.