On this episode of China Uncensored,
China Sells Killer Drones to Iraq
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I'm your host Chris Chappell.
Earlier in the year,
China sold an "unknown number" of combat drones
to the Iraqi military.
The Iraqi Ministry of Defense released this
video showing one of these Chinese-made drones.
Here, it's firing an anti-tank missile at
what is allegedly an ISIS target.
Ahhh, ISIS: bringing the world together...against
you.
These Chinese drones,
the CH-4B model,
have a range of more than 3,000 miles.
And they can fire on targets up to 3 miles
away.
And if a few of them get shot down, who cares?
They were made in China.
Actually, the purchases from China are part
of a broader effort by the Iraqi military
diversify their suppliers.
Over the past year,
Iraq has also bought weapons from Russia and
Iran.
It seems they don't want to just rely on the
US.
Well that's some thank you for all that liberation
and freedom we gave them.
But this is also a move by the Chinese regime
to grab a bigger share of the,
I guess you would call it,
killer drone market.
China is already the world's largest manufacture
of drones,
a realm of technological warfare that used
to be the sole domain of the US and Israel.
China's success is in producing cheaper, lower
tech models.
According to an analysis by Air Force World,
their drones follow the same concept behind
the AK47
instead of going for high tech,
they go for what's simple and easy to use.
And, of course, cheap.
Now drones have become the weapon of choice
for counter terrorist operations.
ISIS doesn't have much in the way of air defense.
So drones can easily cross international borders
and attack targets.
Which is of course one reason why they're
the subject of so many thorny diplomatic and
human rights questions.
So what do you think about China taking a
piece of the armed drone market in Iraq?
Will China's drones replace US drones?
Leave your comments below or on the Facebook
page.
And remember to subscribe to this channel.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell.
See you next time.