On this episode of China Uncensored,
China supports President Trump’s sanctions
on Iran.
In fact, maybe they support the sanctions
too much.
Kim Jong-un goes back to China...
for a second helping of Xi Jinping.
And finally,
an official who could have become
one of China’s top leaders
gets purged by Xi Jinping.
Bet he never saw that one coming.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
On Tuesday,
US President Donald Trump announced
he was re-imposing sanctions on Iran.
Perhaps no country was as supportive
as the People’s Republic of China.
Mainly because they’re going to ignore the
sanctions.
My favorite Chinese state-run media,
the Global Times, wrote,
“Chinese companies doing business in Iran
will remain in the country.”
China is the second biggest
consumer of oil in the world,
just behind the United States.
And this year,
a third of all Iranian oil shipments have
gone to China.
And US sanctions could actually benefit China.
As CNN says,
“If the new sanctions cause European nations
to cut back or even stop buying Iran’s oil,
it would leave more crude for China to buy,
possibly at a discount.”
And it’s not just Iranian oil.
The Chinese Communist Party has been
doing business with Iran for over 30 years.
And US sanctions are less likely to bother
Chinese state-run companies
that do business there.
Let’s just say,
they have some workarounds.
But there was an even bigger news story
from this week.
How big you ask?
Kim Jong-un big.
So big you can barely see
that island in the background.
“China's state-run media revealed on Tuesday
that Kim Jong Un had visited Chinese President
Xi Jinping
the day prior,
what would appear to be the second secretive
trip
across that border by Kim in the last two
months.”
Kim apparently told Xi that,
“He hoped relevant parties would take ‘phased’
and ‘synchronized’ measures to realize
denuclearization.”
Phased synchronized parties?
Kim Jong-un: Vaporwave aficionado.
This comes ahead of the eagerly anticipated
meeting
between Donald Trump and Kim Jong-un.
And remember how the Chinese Communist Party
somehow managed to arrest or kill a dozen
CIA operatives
inside China 6 or 7 years ago?
Well, it turns out,
the Party may have gotten their information
from this guy.
He’s a naturalized US citizen
and a former CIA field agent.
He has now been charged with conspiracy
to commit espionage on behalf of China.
If convicted,
he could be spending the rest of his life
inside a US prison cell.
But it could be worse.
It could be a Chinese prison cell.
And it’s time for another chapter
in the ongoing soap opera of political infighting
in the Chinese Communist Party.
Sun Zhengcai was once pegged to be
one of the next top leaders of China.
But he was arrested for “bribery”
and has just been sentenced to life in prison.
And let’s be honest, he does look like a
“bad guy.”
But, you might think,
“By Communist Party standards,
bribery is not that bad!
Why was he jailed for life?”
Well, as with most of the arrests
in Xi Jinping’s so-called anti-corruption
campaign,
the real reason is that Sun Zhengcai
was close allies of Xi Jinpings’s rival,
former Chinese leader
and professional Dr. Kamikazi impersonator,
Jiang Zemin.
And oh yeah Sun allegedly tried to stage a
coup.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
And it’s time for me to answer
another fan question!
Coralline Algae asks:
“A while back there were many stories
about China's ghost cities.
Can you give us an update to that situation?
Has China stopped building them,
or are people finally moving into them?”
Great question, Coralline.
The most famous Chinese ghost city is Ordos.
They started building it in about 2005,
but one moved in.
But now, 13 years later,
it appears a few hundred thousand people are
there.
You know, with space for another million or
two.
Incidentally, Ordos is home to
one of China’s biggest Bitcoin mining outfits—
because, you know, land is cheap.
So maybe in another 15 years,
Ordos will be a proper city.
But who knows?
And yes,
local Chinese governments are building
more ghost cities all the time.
At least ghosts will always have cheap rent.
Remember, if you support China Uncensored
with a dollar or more per episode or per month,
you can join our official 50-Cent Army—
and I’ll answer your questions
at the end of my next episode.
Click this orange button to support the show.