On this episode of China Uncensored,
China brings you Sonic Attack 3!
This one’s not much fun, though.
Welcome back to China Uncensored,
I’m Chris Chappell.
The pen is mightier than the sword.
But sound can be an even more dangerous weapon.
Just ask anyone who’s been to karaoke with
me.
Near, far…
Wherever you are…
Yes, sound can be a weapon.
And some people are concerned that US diplomats
in China
have fallen victim to sound weapons,
or sonic attacks.
At least two Americans tied to the US consulate
in the southern Chinese city of Guangzhou
have been evacuated due to mysterious ailments
that came after they heard odd sounds.
A US State Department Spokeswoman said Wednesday
night
that the Department has sent a number of individuals
for further evaluation in the United States.
A US official spoke to ABC news,
saying the evacuated Americans were,
“being brought for testing to the University
of Pennsylvania.”
It follows this health advisory from the US
embassy in China,
warning that, “If you experience any unusual
acute auditory
or sensory phenomena accompanied by
unusual sounds or piercing noises,
do not attempt to locate their source.
Instead, move to a location
where the sounds are not present.”
Which seems like the plot to a bad 1950’s
B-movie.
“The Sound from Space.”
One US consulate employee was diagnosed
with a “mild traumatic brain injury.”
And that followed a similar incident last
year in Havana, Cuba.
24 US Embassy employees reported symptoms
similar to a concussion after, “some sort
of ‘acoustic element,’
such as a ‘high-pitched beam of sound’
or a ‘baffling sensation akin to driving
with the windows partially open in a car.’”
“US believes that several state department
employees
at US embassy in Havana,
have been have been subjected to acoustic
attack?
What does that even mean?”
That’s exactly how my college girlfriend
reacted
when I told her I was starting a baroque metal
band
called Acoustic Attack.
Back to China.
The New York Times uncovered the identity
of one of the two most recent evacuees
from the US consulate in Guangzhou.
And apparently,
he had complained in an email to the entire
consulate
that they were lied to about how serious the
situation was.
That’s why he and his wife
didn’t report their symptoms right away.
His symptoms included “dizziness,
headaches and an inability to concentrate.”
Wait, that just sounds like a normal day at
the office.
But in all these cases,
victims report hearing a strange sound
before suffering physical symptoms.
No one knows for sure what’s behind it.
One explanation is it’s a sonic attack.
I know what you’re thinking,
I haven’t had a sonic attack since 1991.
Yeah, the original game was from 1991.
You are old.
But weaponizing frequencies is very real technology,
not just some crazy scheme by Dr. Robotnik.
There are three types of sonic weapons.
The first type is simply playing
music or sound really, really loud.
Like a Limp Bizkit concert.
Now that’s a sonic attack.
Another type of sonic weapon
is called an infrasonic weapon.
It blasts loud, low frequency sounds
that can’t be heard by the human ear,
but can be felt.
This technology has been used to,
I kid you not,
fight off pirates.
And everyone knows that pirates
are just like diplomats.
But it’s unlikely infrasonic weapons are
the culprit.
They’re typically pretty bulky—
not something you can hide in a consulate.
The effects include excruciating headaches,
ear pain, and even involuntary defecation.
That’s not what the consulate employees
reported.
But then again,
would you tell your boss if you had involuntary
defecation?
The third type of sonic weapon is ultrasonic
weapons.
Those are frequencies too high to hear.
They can cause nausea and headaches—
which is like the symptoms the US diplomats
suffered from.
But there are problems with this theory.
Ultrasonic emitters are very short range.
Like, if you’re standing on the other side
of the room,
that’s too far,
kind of short range.
Then there’s the fact that,
“Ultrasound is also highly directional.
Precise alignment in millimetres would be
needed to steer
an ultrasonic ‘beam’ to hit someone from
across a room.”
It’d be like if Goldfinger said,
“I expect you to die, Mr. Bond. J
ust uhh...that bench doesn’t have chains,
so...stay right there.”
OK, so probably not ultrasonic weapons either.
So...are there any other theories?
Yes, actually.
These might not have been ultrasonic weapons,
but rather just sloppy ultrasonic spying.
You see Ultrasound is also used in motion
sensors.
And studies have found it can even be used
to read
a person’s mouth in noisy rooms,
or even whispering.
Ultrasonic frequencies can also be used to
take over
voice-controlled devices like Amazon’s Alexa.
Alexinator: Rise of the Machines,
available now on Amazon Prime Video.
But then the problem is,
if that ultrasonic emitter is trying to target
your Alexa
on the other side of the room,
and you walk right in front of it,
the strength could be thousands of times greater.
Even short exposure could cause damage.
And if there are several ultrasonic spy devices,
if you get in just the right position where
all of them
are directly focused on your brain,
your head explodes.
Okay, not really,
but it could cause the kind of damage we’ve
seen
with US diplomats in China and Cuba.
This might make more sense.
Trying to spy on diplomats,
well everyone does that.
Attacking diplomats with experimental sonic
weapons
on the other hand, that’s kind of raising
the bar.
Like going from Sonic, to Tails.
Either that, or it was the aliens all along.
Before you go,
now’s the time when we answer questions
from fans who support China Uncensored
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
J R Harrison asks:
“What do you plan on doing once the CCP
collapses?”
One final episode, and then a long snooze
on the beach.
But until then, I’ve got work to do.
Speaking of work, Shelley,
on the next China Uncensored karaoke night,
it’s you, me, and A Whole New World.
What’s that?
What do you mean, you’re busy?
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Leave your comments below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
A whole new world
That's where we'll be
A thrilling chase
A wondrous place
For you and me