China’s first space walk
hides a dark secret.
China’s space ambitions
are a global threat.
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
China made history this week with its first
ever space walk.
Hundreds of miles above earth, China made
history on Sunday with the first spacewalk
outside its Tiangong station...He and two
other astronauts are on the first of four
high-stakes missions to complete China's space
station by the end of 2022.
And the space station, Tiangong, which means
Heavenly Palace, is just the beginning of
China’s ambitious space program.
In just the past 7 months, China has put a
rover on the moon, and one on Mars, becoming
the second country in history after the US
to land a rover on the Red Planet.
They also plan to send humans to the moon
in the 2030s.
So these Chinese astronauts must have some
really inspiring words for mankind.
We will obey orders and instructions and keep
calm while meticulously carrying out the mission.
One small step for man, one giant leap for
Big Brother.
You see, China’s space program has a dark
secret.
It’s not run by a civilian agency the way
NASA is.
China’s space program is run by the People’s
Liberation Army, which is the armed wing of
the Chinese Communist Party.
Yes, in communist China, the army belongs
to the Communist Party, not the government.
Speaking of belonging to the Communist Party:
“All three astronauts are party members,
and they and other space officials repeatedly
credited [Xi Jinping] or the party for the
country’s feats in space.”
And if you’ve seen the recent celebrations
for the Chinese Communist Party’s 100 year
anniversary, that kind of cult-like worship
should have you pretty worried.
Especially because China is rapidly looking
to replace the US in space.
Without new funding, the ISS could be decommissioned
in 2024.
Which means the Tiangong could be the only
space station left in Earth's orbit.
Foreign astronauts are certainly going to
enter the Chinese space station one day.
There are a number of countries that have
expressed a desire to do that.
If the Chinese Communist Party is able to
control access to space, that means China
could cut off access to any nation that’s
unwilling to do this.
According to US Intelligence, China is already
building space weapons to blind US satellites.
Say goodbye to your GPS.
That would be devastating for the US military.
And for me when I try to use Google Maps to
navigate to the nearest Cracker Barrel.
The Chinese Communist Party has an iron grip
on science in China.
If you have any questions about that, just
look into how the Communist Party has silenced
scientists who don’t toe the party line
on the coronavirus.
But here’s a more recent example.
A Communist Party official connected to the
state-owned China Aerospace Science and Technology
Corporation “allegedly attacked two prominent
space scientists -- including an 85-year-old
woman.”
Funny, because Xi Jinping has been saying
how much the Party supports scientists.
Because science is the main battleground with
the West.
But it’s the Party and politics that really
rule China.
“The Party Secretary attacked the two scientists
after they refused his request to be recommended
for membership of the International Academy
of Astronautics.”
And by attacked, I mean he broke the spine
of an 85 year old woman.
But it’s not just that a Party secretary
attacked Chinese scientists.
It’s that this happened in early June.
And the Party covered it up for weeks.
And many Chinese netizens were curious why
it took so long for the story to come to light.
And why the Party secretary hadn’t suffered
any consequences.
Well, I can tell you.
The Party was gearing up for its 100th anniversary
and the space walk, and didn’t want people
to know.
After a huge public backlash, the China Aerospace
Science and Technology Corporation finally
put out a brief statement saying the party
secretary was drinking at the time, and now
he’s been suspended.
But you can see why the Communist Party is
so interested in space.
In space, no one can hear the people scream.
And now it’s time to answer a question from
a member of the China Uncensored 50 Cent Army,
fans who support us and our efforts to expose
the truth about the Chinese Communist Party,
by contributing through crowd funding website
Patreon.
Ian Jackson asks, “Chris, there is room
here for your channel to do a 1 hour time-line
documentary on the origins of this starting
2009 up to 2020.
Do it as a proper docco, not just a news item.
At the very least it will really annoy the
CCP
Ah, Ian is talking about the origins of the
coronavirus.
This is actually something we’ve been thinking
about.
Maybe not quite a full documentary, but an
explainer that breaks down everything we know
about the Wuhan Institute of Virology, their
coronavirus research, especially with human
animal chimeras, US funding for the lab, and
the timeline of the coverup—both what the
Chinese Communist Party did, and what US scientists
and media did to convince Americans the lab
leak hypothesis was a racist conspiracy theory.
It also reminds me of another idea we had.
To do more explainer episodes—like a quick
rundown of historical things like the Cultural
Revolution, or what a wumao is, things like
that.
So is that something you’d be interested
in watching?
Let me know in the comments below.
Thanks for your question and your support,
Ian.
And a big thank you to everyone who supports
China Uncensored on Patreon.
We could not do this show without you.
So thank you for joining us in the fight to
expose the Chinese Communist Party to the
world.
If you’re interested in joining, head over
to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
You’ll get a bunch of cool perks, including
the chance to have me answer your question
on the show!
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next
time.