On this episode of China Uncensored,
Xi Jinping solidifies his grip on the military
police.
The hottest viral sensation in China is Ice
Boy.
And finally, you can buy your own half-built
skyscraper...
it’s a bit of a fixer-upper.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Protests broke out recently in Iran
over the poor economy.
And that has China worried.
According to this article from Radio Free
Asia,
...China’s propaganda department told state-run
media
not to report on the Iranian protests.
For some reason they don’t want Chinese
people
learning about a popular uprising
against an authoritarian regime
started by people upset over economic hardship.
Plus, online forums discussing
anything to do with Iran
are being monitored.
And let’s just say,
they’re open to the idea of detaining people.
That’s the way to stop protests from getting
started.
Preemptive detention.
Before on the show,
I’ve talked about how there’s a political
battle
raging between current Chinese leader Xi Jinping
and a faction tied to former Chinese leader
and Jabba the Hutt’s personal mini-me,
Jiang Zemin.
To be the Master Blaster of Chinese politics
it’s important to control two things—
the military and the police.
Well, Xi Jinping has spent years
purging the military of Jiang Zemin’s cronies
and getting himself named Commander in Xi-ef.
Now he’s after the police.
Specifically the paramilitary police.
One of the big things Xi did at the end of
was to have the paramilitary police report
directly to
the Central Military Commission.
Which Xi is in charge of.
Xi’s speech to the paramilitary police
follows another speech he made last week
to the actual military.
He told soldiers not to fear death.
Inspirational words for soldiers
who fight on the front lines.
But for soldiers who are still in training,
fearing death is a good thing.
It could save your life
if you’re bad at, say,
grenades.
Just throwing that out there.
Why the big speech?
Xi Jinping probably just felt the army
needed a little kick in the rear.
Apparently they’ve wasting time
building snowmen.
Can we zoom out a little on that tank one?
Well, someone’s getting preemptively sent
to detention.
But as impressive as the PLA is
at building snow propaganda,
they can’t compete with the the annual
Harbin Ice Festival.
10,000 people worked for months
crafting this winter wonderland that will
be seen
by an estimated 1.5 million people.
Sadly none of them will be me.
Of course the cold isn’t fun and games for
everyone.
This little boy has become something of a
national hero
after this photo of him went viral.
His hair is coated in frost after his daily
three mile walk to school in a thin jacket.
Wow, his hands look like he’s been
working in a coal mine
for the last 50 years.
But he got a 99 on his test!
His name is Wang Fuman,
and people are calling him Ice Boy.
The rural school he goes to doesn’t even
have
heat in the winter.
He and his sister are left behind children—
their father is a migrant worker
trying to earn money in the city,
and only comes home every 4 or 5 months.
Their mother abandoned the family.
The good news is that his photo
has inspired people across China
to donate winter clothing to a local youth
charity.
And the school has received
over 15,000 dollars in donations so far.
Which means Ice Boy finally gets gloves.
Plus, someone offered his dad
a construction job close to home,
so he can actually see his kids.
Someday Ice Boy will be able to tell his children,
with complete honesty,
when I was your age,
I had to walk 3 miles to school everyday,
in the snow,
uphill,
both ways.
And here are the viral videos to prove it.
And his kids will say,
“What’s a video?”
In other news, ever want to own a skyscraper?
Well now you can!
A court in Shanxi is trying to dump this beautiful,
39-story skyscraper on Taobao,
China’s version of Ebay.
You can own it for just 84 million dollars.
Basically, the builders ran out of money
before it could be completed
and it’s just been sitting there
ever since 2010.
Now the first auction
was not the most successful.
Zero people bid on it.
But don’t worry,
you haven’t missed your chance!
The Shanxi court has a new plan.
Another auction!
What do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
You know, you don’t have to
walk uphill both ways in the snow
to watch China Uncensored.
Just visit us at ChinaUncensored.tv.
There you can watch full half hour episodes
of China Uncensored you won’t see on YouTube.
And if you like the show,
consider supporting us on the website, Patreon!
Click here.