On this episode of China Uncensored,
don’t look a gift from the Communist Party
in the mouth.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
This woman committed a terrible crime.
She married a writer.
You’d think that would be punishment enough.
But that isn’t just the punchline of a bad
joke.
Artist Liu Xia was kept under house arrest
for 8 years
because she was married to prominent Chinese
dissident,
writer, and Nobel Peace Prize winner, Liu
Xiaobo.
That’s it.
That was her crime.
“Her only crime was that she never gave
up on her late husband,
and she paid a dear price for her love for
Liu Xiaobo,
who died last year of lung cancer, while still
in custody.”
And if 8 years of house arrest doesn’t sound
that bad to you,
imagine being locked in your house for 8 years,
in a country with no Facebook, YouTube, Twitter,
or Netflix.
Now that’s torture.
But what am I saying?
Liu Xia has been free this whole time,
according to the Communist Party.
Doesn’t she seem like a free woman,
whispering in a reporter’s ear about how
the authorities
can hear everything in her apartment?
But now, after tons of international pressure,
the Communist Party has allowed Liu Xia to
leave China for Berlin.
Obviously they didn’t let her leave because
of international pressure.
China’s foreign minister gave a different
explanation.
“China’s Foreign Ministry said Liu Xia
had travelled to Germany for medical treatment.”
Oh, that makes sense.
Because there are no hospitals in China.
Now correlation doesn’t always mean causation...
but that top level Communist Party official’s
visit to Germany
just maybe had something to do with Liu Xia’s
sudden freedom.
Germany has been pushing for Liu Xia’s release
for a while.
In fact, German Chancellor Angela Merkel personally
brought it up
with Chinese leader Xi Jinping.
Apparently told her “maybe”,
if she kept it hush-hush.
Well, they did finally release Liu Xia.
And it comes ahead of an EU-China summit next
week.
You see, the Chinese Communist Party is dealing
with
the US-China trade war.
And making nice with Germany and the EU
might provide the Party the economic lifeline
it needs.
As Quartz puts it, “Given the troublesome
relations with the US,
China needs to put effort into winning over
Germany...
Allowing Liu [Xia] to travel to Germany was
a concession
from a China that wants to be recognized
as a responsible global player.”
And really, don’t you think we should applaud
the Chinese Communist Party for doing the
right thing?
It’s so generous of them to let Liu Xia,
who did nothing wrong in the first place,
leave the country as a gesture of goodwill
during their talks with Germany and the EU.
The same talks where Chinese officials will
try to convince
Germany and the EU to stand with China,
against the US.
Such compassion.
But wait!
“Chris,” you ask,
“Now that Liu Xia is free,
won’t she become an outspoken dissident?”
Ah, that kind of simple thinking is why you
are not
in charge of your own Marxist-Leninist authoritarian
state.
See, Liu Xia’s brother is still in China.
Although he tried,
he was not allowed to leave with her.
And if Liu Xia knows what’s good for her
brother,
she’ll keep her fool mouth shut.
And in case you thought Liu Xia’s release
means the Chinese Communist Party
is turning over a new leaf,
well, the next day,
they sentenced a democracy activist to 13
years in prison.
The Party wouldn’t want you to think they’re
getting soft.
So what do you think about the Communist Party’s
generous release of Liu Xia?
Leave your comments below.
And before you go,
it’s that time when we answer questions
from fans who support China Uncensored
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
SciNerdGirl asks
“Have you ever eaten ‘Stinky’ Tofu?
Does it really smell as bad as they say?”
Ah, the tough questions.
Have I eaten stinky tofu?
Yes, and I’ll never forget it.
For those of you who don’t know,
stinky tofu is fermented tofu.
Meaning...it’s stinky.
Some people really love it.
Not me.
I had it for the first time in Shilin Night
Market in Taipei.
That’s the capital of Taiwan province, China.
There were many strange foods there I really
enjoyed,
like giant deep fried squid,
and even pig blood sausage.
But the stinky tofu?
Well, let’s just say I’d prefer durian.
What’s that, Shelley?
Stinky tofu is amazing?
We’ll have to agree to disagree.
Thanks for the question SciNerdGirl.
By the way,
if you’re really a sci-nerd,
I recommend reading the Three Body Problem.
Excellent Chinese science fiction.
And for all of you, remember,
China Uncensored is supported mainly from
viewers like you.
If you want us to keep making great episodes,
and have a chance to get your question answered
on air,
become a supporter on Patreon.
The link is below.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Hey, want the latest China news?
Subscribe to China Uncensored!
And turn that notification bell on
to make sure you find out when new episodes
are out.
We publish a brand new episode
every Monday, Wednesday, and Friday—
and sometimes Saturday.
So check back frequently.
But I’ve heard from many fans
that YouTube won’t notify you,
even if you have notifications on.
Come on Google,
that’s not nice.