On this episode of China Uncensored,
I think Shelley’s been wiretapping me!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Chinese state-run media report a lot of fake news,
complete and utter fabrications
that Western media report as true.
Like that China’s GDP is really strong,
when, in fact, even the guy in charge of China’s economy
said he doesn’t even believe the GDP data.
Or that China is going to stop harvesting organs
from executed prisoners.
No matter how many times they say,
this time it’s for real.
While also ignoring the organs are coming
mainly from executed prisoners of conscience—
not even regular prisoners.
And who could forget the classic,
the Chinese government is a meritocracy.
Ha ha ha.
It just happens that the most capable leaders
are the sons and daughters of the
Communist revolutionary elite.
Who just also happen to control
most of the businesses.
But while Chinese people in the know
may secretly laugh at us in the West
for eating up their fake news as truth,
we in the West can at least laugh at Chinese media
for eating up our fake news.
I mean stories like this one from last week,
about how US President Donald Trump
has been wrapping every phone in the White House
with tin foil to stop Barack Obama
from wiretapping him.
Many Chinese netizens were shocked...
that state-run media did not pick up on the fact
that story was a satire piece in the New Yorker.
And this wasn’t a one-off slip.
In 2013,
state-run Xinhua and People’s Daily republished verbatim
a satire piece written by the same author
saying Amazon CEO Jeff Bezos accidentally
bought
the Washington Post.
Then there was the time they picked up the
Onion story
about Kim Jong-un being named Sexiest Man Alive,
and ran a 55-page photo spread about him
as a tribute.
Or the time my favorite state-run media the
Global Times
ran this story,
about former would-be-president Hillary Clinton’s
memoirs revealing her secret bisexuality.
That story’s source?
The National Enquirer.
I hope they never discover the Weekly World
News.
No, no on second thought,
I hope they do.
So why does this keep happening?
Well, think about this.
In the Kafkaesque world that is China,
they call air pollution “fog.”
And they say ethnic minorities
enjoy unprecedented religious freedom.
And even that the capital of Tibet
is the happiest place in China!
It makes perfect sense!
The Chinese Communist Party is the
ultimate performance artist,
and we’ve been getting trolled all along!
Maybe during the National People’s Congress
at the end of this year,
Xi Jinping gets up in front of everyone and
is like,
“The Aristocrats!”
And then he and Jiang Zemin hug,
Andy Kaufman walks on stage,
and they all go to Mao’s mausoleum
to give him a mummy makeover.
But there’s probably another,
slightly more likely explanation.
In a country where the atheist Communist Party
actually claims it has the authority
to control reincarnation...
In a country where there are
actual internet police...
And in a country where former high-ranking
Party member
Bo Xilai actually did wiretap leader Hu Jintao...
It wouldn’t be that hard to believe
that a president would wrap his phones in
tin foil.
Or that Americans think Kim Jong-Un
is the Sexiest Man Alive.
I mean, have you seen the guy on a horse?
So what’s your favorite piece
of Chinese Communist Party performance art?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.