On this episode of China Uncensored,
wouldn't China make a better friend?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Well, the US and the Philippines are just
wrapping up
joint military drills.
And it’s a bit bittersweet.
Like the last days of high school.
You and your girlfriend tell each other
you’ll totally stay in touch.
That nothing can keep you apart.
But deep down,
you both know it’s over.
Because let’s face it,
the US and the Philippines are drifting apart.
Times have changed.
And you’ve coupled together for the last
time.
I think the Philippine Defence Minister said
it best.
Maybe we should re-assess (the relationship).
Are we benefiting,
are we getting what we should be getting
from the alliance or the Americans as well?
Is it time for us to look at other source
of our materials?
It is part of this growing up.
It’s part of growing up.
Sure, some harsh words have been said.
And there’s been regret.
He regrets that his remarks to the press
have caused much controversy.
But also, forgiveness.
I don't take these comments personally...
so I’ll think it seems to be just a habit,
a way of speaking for him.
And then some more harsh words.
Mister Obama,
you can go to hell.
Because the Philippines is seeing someone
else,
and it seems the relationship with the US...
is over.
I will break up with America.
I would rather go to Russia and to China.
Grr, China!!!
Yes, under their new president Rodrigo Duterte,
the Philippines is cozying up to China.
Because China is sooo much more supportive.
Well, whatever.
The US is totally fine with it.
I mean,
if you love something,
let it go, right?
But this period of experimentation and self-realization
may not turn out too well for the Philippines.
Because if you hook up with China,
well,
Xi ain’t gonna treat you right!
So why is President Duterte leading the Philippines
towards this risky—
if exciting—new relationship with China?
It’s related to two major issues in the
Philippines right now.
One is the territorial dispute in the South
China Sea.
This is the Scarborough Shoal.
The Philippines and China both claim it.
And they have nearly come to blows over it.
The Chinese coast guard has at times blocked
Filipino fishermen
from the region.
Even fired their water cannons on them.
Then China alleged Filipino fishermen
threw firebombs at their ships.
The Philippines did recently win a major victory,
though.
In July,
a UN Tribunal ruled in favor of the Philippines,
saying China has no right to a large part
of their claim
in the South China Sea, including the contested
Scarborough Shoal.
And US President Barack Obama
had the Philippines’ back.
Before the ruling,
Obama had warned the Chinese leader of serious
consequences
if China reclaimed land at Scarborough Shoal.
But after Duterte became president...
Mister Obama, you can go to hell.
And ahead of Duterte’s upcoming trip to
China,
he said he’s not even going to bring up
the Scarborough Shoal.
Why?
Because the Philippines, “can’t win.”
Why the 180?
Well,
it has to do with the second big issue
in the Philippines right now:
Duterte’s war on drugs.
In an attempt to rapidly solve the Philippines’
drug problems,
he’s gone after both drug dealers and users.
More than thirty-three hundred people have
been killed
in just a few months.
Of course, some drug users are being rehabilitated.
For example,
by organizations having them build…
coffins!
If they did not change their former way of
living,
they might be the one using the caskets,
but it's just a joke.
Ha HA!
What a joke!
Obama isn’t laughing, though.
The US has been one of many governments
expressing serious concern over the extrajudicial
killings
of not just drug dealers,
but also drug users.
And Duterte has not taken the criticism
of his anti-drug campaign well.
I would like to just give an advice
to all the human rights (groups)
who are shouting now,
local or international.
I said you can all go to hell.
So yeah, he doesn't like criticism.
Look,
the Philippines does have a very serious drug
problem.
The previous president wasn’t able to do
anything about it.
That could be one of the reason why Duterte
is so popular
inside the Philippines.
And I get why distancing yourself from the
United States
has appeal.
For years,
the Philippines was basically a US colony.
My favorite Filipino dish,
sizzling sisig,
basically exists because the only meat people
could afford
were discarded pig heads
sold by US troops.
Pig heads it turns out,
are delicious.
But China is a bad alternative.
China and Russia are also carrying out
joint military drills in the South China Sea.
And while China might agree to let Filipino
Fishermen in...
...doesn’t that sound more like they’re
granting Filipino fishermen
access to Chinese territory?
And as for war on drugs,
well, President Duterte,
you said it yourself.
But most of the materials,
all of the machines and the boilers are from China,
what does that mean?
It means Xi ain’t gonna treat you right.
So what do you think of the President Duterte
“breaking up” with United States for China?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.