On this episode of China Uncensored,
Taiwan—Donald Trump’s trump card!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Donald Trump has now been in office for...
okay, well, he’s still a month away from
assuming office,
but he's already making
ch-ch-ch-changes!
Yes, turn and face the strain.
Because for one,
it looks like he might change 40 years
of US diplomatic policy in regards to Taiwan—
policy created in part to avoid having a war
with China.
On Sunday,
Trump questioned the “One China” policy.
That's the policy where both China and Taiwan
agree that there's only one China,
but disagree on which one that one is.
And the US has its own one China policy
where it also agrees that there's only one
China,
but unlike China's version,
the US doesn't recognize China's authority
over Taiwan.
Whew.
You know what?
Let's just call it the Highlander policy.
For clarity.
Anyway, let's recap.
Two weeks ago, Trump took a phone call
from Taiwanese president Tsai Ying-wen.
That’s the first time in 40 years
a US president has spoken directly
with a Taiwanese president.
And that left many with mixed feelings.
Not the Chinese regime though.
They were very clear on how they felt.
But even though they consider Taiwan
just a breakaway province,
they decided to just play it cool with Trump.
Agree to disagree.
There are indeed some disagreements and differences
of opinion,
this has been the status quo of U.S.-China
relations.
Vice President-Elect Mike Pence also said
it wasn’t a big deal.
The waters here seem like a little bit of
a tempest in a teapot.
Haha, well, now it’s tea time.
I fully understand the one China policy,
but I don’t know why we have to be bound
by a ‘one China’ policy
unless we make a deal with China
having to do with other things, including
trade.
Here's what China's foreign ministry spokesman
said in response:
There can be only one!
Or to quote him more accurately,
China has noted the report
and expresses serious concern about it
Upholding the one China principle
is the political basis for developing China-US
ties.
If this basis is interfered with or damaged
then the healthy development of China-US relations
and bilateral cooperation in important areas
is out of the question.
Expressing “serious concern”
may not sound like the strongest language
out there.
But the Chinese Foreign Ministry always maintains
an air of decorum and self restraint.
Because the Chinese regime has state-run Global
Times
to express how it really feels.
Trump is “as ignorant as a child” it says.
And “In response to Trump's provocations,
Beijing could offer support,
even military assistance to US foes.”
and may even start a war to retake Taiwan.
Of course,
the Global Times is like the New York Post
of Chinese state-run media.
So while amusing,
we shouldn't read too much into what it says.
It would be like freaking out every time a
politician
says something on Twitter.
People in Trump’s camp
have balked at the idea
of having to make concessions to the Chinese
Communist Party.
Stephen Moore,
a former economic adviser to Donald Trump
and chief economist of the The Heritage Foundation
had this to say in a recent radio interview.
Too many namby-pamby people
in the foreign policy shop
are saying “Oh my gosh
we can’t do this,
we might insult the Chinese.”
Taiwan is our ally, John.
That is a country that we have backed
because they believe in freedom.
We ought to back our ally,
and if China doesn’t like it,
screw ’em.
And despite what President-Elect Trump says
about the call with Taiwan being something
he only heard about an hour before the call,
reports from Trump’s transition team
seem to show the call was actually months
in the making,
thanks to lobbyists like former U.S. presidential
candidate
Bob Dole,
who may have been paid by Taiwan.
Meanwhile, the Taiwanese government has no
comment
on Trump’s remarks.
Taiwan is in a tricky situation here.
Trump seems to view the One China policy
as a bargaining chip that the US can use
to get China to cooperate on trade and other
issues.
Meanwhile, the Chinese Communist Party
views the policy as non-negotiable.
And while Taiwan may welcome more recognition
and stronger support from the US,
the country-slash-region is at risk
if the boat gets rocked too much.
In fact,
a majority of Taiwanese want to keep the status
quo
with China forever.
Sure, they may not be formally recognized
as a state right now,
but at least those 1,600 missiles pointed
at them aren't firing.
So what’s next?
Is Trump leading the US to war with China?
Or is he standing up for Taiwan?
And should we just rename the One China policy
the Highlander policy instead?
Tell me what you think in the comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.