A scandal on a Chinese airplane
A promise to Taiwan
And new video game regulations
That and more on this week’s China Uncensored.
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
This week’s China news headlines!
This, for some reason one of the most trending
stories
about China this week.
Truly worth of international headlines.
A pilot of Air Guilin let this woman sit in
the pilot’s seat
during a flight so she could take the selfie.
The selfie went viral on Weibo,
basically China’s version of twitter.
Which is apparently as much of a dumpster
fire as our Twitter,
because people freaked out.
The airline fired the pilot for potentially
putting
all the passengers in danger.
Of course, he can still go get a job
with another Chinese airline.
And I really don’t know what the big deal
was.
I mean, co-pilot was there in case anything
went wrong.
And now to Canada,
where Prime Minister Justin Trudeau’s party
recently won reelection.
And you know what that means.
A gentle reminder from Chinese authorities
to release the CFO of Chinese telecom giant
Huawei.
“We urge the re-elected Canadian government
to seriously treat China's solemn stand and
concerns
and immediately release Meng Wanzhou,
and bring the China-Canada relationship back
on track
by taking real actions.”
Meng Wanzhou is the Huawei CFO and daughter
of Huawei founder.
Aww, it’s a family business.
She was arrested at the end of last year on
charges
of violating US sanctions on Iran.
And the Chinese Communist Party
still hasn’t quite gotten a grasp
of how this whole rule of law thing works.
Canada can’t just release Meng as a favor
to China.
That would be a scandal.
And Justin Trudeau doesn’t need another
scandal.
The Chinese Communist Party is saying it will
fully respect
Taiwan’s way of life after it inevitably
takes over.
Now for some reason,
people are scoffing at that.
I don’t get it.
The Chinese Communist Party *promised*
it would respect Taiwan’s way of life.
Just like it promised in Tibet.
Or Hong Kong.
Speaking of places where everyone’s rights
are upheld: Xinjiang.
Uighur women there are getting sterilized
and sexually abused in the Chinese regime’s
internment camps.
And if you’re not in an internment camp,
the Chinese regime will just assign a strange
man
to come and sleep next to you in your home.
I really don’t get why Taiwan would be nervous
about being part of the People’s Republic
of China.
So the abuse of the Uighur Muslims may *sound*
pretty horrifying.
But the Communist Party is working on improving
the situation.
By paying Facebook and Twitter to spread anti-Muslim
propaganda
to justify its actions in Xinjiang.
That’s according to reporting from the Intercept,
and this one from Buzzfeed news.
Now this story broke back in August,
but it’s still important to talk about.
So what happened was essentially this.
Chinese state-run media,
including my personal favorite the Global
Times,
would pay Twitter or Facebook to promote their
posts.
Posts specifically about how those internment
camps for Uighurs
are actually wonderful vocational education
and training centers.
Here’s a video from Global Times Editor
in Chief.
“They smeared the vocational education
and training centers established to help people
avoid extremism by calling them mass detention
camps.”
Wow, I had no idea!
I’m glad social media giants
and accept money in exchange for getting this
message
to hundreds of millions of people.
Now Twitter has said it will no longer allow
that.
Facebook...still allows it.
Some good news for the Chinese Communist Party:
The NGO Freedom House has for the fourth year
in a row
awarded China the...dishonor...
of being the world’s worst abuser of internet
freedom.
I believe the award looks like an Oscar,
except it’s Al Gore in handcuffs.
Because Al Gore says he invented the Internet.
And so…he’s in handcuffs…anyway
Congratulations!
The Chinese Communist Party would like to
thank the academy,
and also God...
wait, sorry, I mean Chairman Mao.
And finally, China has put a curfew on video
games.
Users younger than 18 won’t be allowed to
play games
between 10 p.m. and 8 a.m.
And only for a maximum of 90 minutes on weekdays,
and three hours on weekends and holidays.
This is also part of Xi Jinping’s push
to combat poor eyesight in China.
And thus all the problems in China have been
solved.
And that’s it for this weeks’ China news
headlines.
But before I go,
it’s time for me to answer a question from
one of you—
a fan who support China Uncensored
with a dollar or more per episode,
by contributing through the crowdfunding website
Patreon.
Franky asks,
“How can I support the Hong Kong protesters
(the peaceful ones)?
I can't really share on social media because
of my work,
and I support your channel and once supported
the HK Free Press....
which is the only way I could come up with,
even though it is indirect.
(Foreigner living in rural Japan.)
Glad you want to help.
And I can tell you that means a lot to the
people of Hong Kong.
So, if you don’t want to talk about Hong
Kong on social media,
you can always talk to people face to face.
Especially in Japan,
I know people are concerned about
the Chinese Communist Party’s influence.
Japan is definitely a target of the regime,
so I’d imagine people would be pretty open
to hearing about
what’s happening in Hong Kong.
You can also find resources online,
like this recently updated Reddit thread
with many ways to help Hong Kong protesters.
We’ll put a link to it in the description
below.
But it’s a good question.
So I’d like to open it up to everyone:
brainstorm some ideas and leave your comments
below
about ways we all can help the situation in
Hong Kong.
Maybe we all can do a little bit of good.
Thanks for your question, Franky.
And thanks to everyone for watching.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.