bjbj,(,( On this episode of China Uncensored,
Hit and Run Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I m your host, Chris Chappell. In my recent
episode, China declares war on the Chinese
people, I said that China s vast array of
standard, secret, and military police officially
get more money than the Chinese military.
So rather than existing to protect and serve
the Chinese people, the police in China are
an extension of the Chinese Communist Party
and function more as a means of making them
obey the Party. Here s an example. I hope
they see that ped. Oh. And the police drive
off. There s no word on whether or not the
pedestrian survived, but if they did, I m
sure they ll rest comfortably knowing that
China s police are absolutely dedicated to
fighting crime, and they ll crush anyone in
their way to do so. So yeah, the police suck,
but I mean, the driver of this car didn t
stop either. Come on, where s the love for
your fellow man? Actually, this is a problem
in China, something contemporary Chinese social
critics have been pointing out for years,
that while China has developed materially,
it s come at the cost of its spiritual civilization.
It reminds me of a similar thing from 2011.
Yueyue was only two years old when. Well,
we don t need to see that. But get this. Over
the next ten minutes, 18 people walk past
without doing a thing to help, before ultimately,
she s run over by another van. She died two
weeks later from her injuries. It was a huge
story in China. The China Youth Daily, the
official Communist Party paper for youth,
did a survey and 88% of respondents said Yueyue
died because of growing apathy in China toward
other people. Amazingly, another 71% thought
all those people just walked by Yueyue because
they were afraid of getting in trouble themselves.
That s because good Samaritans in China often
find themselves getting blamed for the crime.
The most famous example is from 2006, when
a 65 year old woman fell while exiting a bus.
While others passed by, a 26 year old student
named Peng Yu stopped, helped her to a hospital
and even paid part of the bill. The woman,
of modest means, thanked Peng by suing him
for 7,000 dollars, saying he pushed her. The
case went to court and the judge famously
said it was common sense that the only reason
someone would help another person was if they
had a guilty conscience, and ruled against
Peng. That s proved a grim lesson. In 2009,
a 75 year old man also fell after disembarking
a bus. No one dared touch him until he shouted
it s nobody s fault. I fell by myself. Then
everyone nearby helped him out. But here s
the kicker. Six years after the Peng Yu case
enraged the country, some newly disclosed
documents from the trial that hadn t been
made public came to light. Apparenlty, Peng
confessed to pushing the old woman, then solicited
local media and online forum moderators to
paint him as a martyr. On top of that Peng
and the 65 year old grannie were in cahoots,
and they had already agreed to a financial
settlement. And on top of that, law enforcement
officials had testimony and evidence that
Peng knocked the old woman down, and didn
t say anything. So for years people have been
afraid of helping each other because of this
crazy lawsuit case that was a total sham.
That s just. That s, I can t even really wrap
my head around that one. Which kind of begs
the question, if that whole thing hadn t happened,
would someone have helped Yueyue? So what
do you make of all this? I mean, it seems
to me like people in China want to help each
other, but they ve been made too afraid to
do anything. Share your thoughts by either
commenting below, or you can follow me on
Twitter of like China Uncensored on facebook.
And as always be sure to subscribe for more
episodes of China Uncensored. Thanks for watching,
I m Chris Chappell. See you next time. [Content_Types].xml
#!MB ;c=1 _rels/.rels theme/theme/themeManager.xml
sQ\}# theme/theme/theme1.xml G$$DA : BR \{i5@R
V*[_X ,l\Y Ssd+r] 5\|E Vky- V4Ej 6NGU s?^V
* 7;wP EBU` 5VD
GGHPXNT, /M,W m2iU [[v _Xtl theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.rels
6?$Q K(M&$R(.1 [Content_Types].xmlPK _rels/.relsPK
theme/theme/themeManager.xmlPK theme/theme/theme1.xmlPK
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.relsPK
<a:clrMap xmlns:a="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/main"
bg1="lt1" tx1="dk1" bg2="lt2" tx2="dk2" accent1="accent1"
accent2="accent2" accent3="accent3" accent4="accent4"
accent5="accent5" accent6="accent6" hlink="hlink"
folHlink="folHlink"/> hw~\ Chris Normal.dotm
Chris Microsoft Macintosh Word PICT'h kZo\{g9^
g9g9Z kZg9c kZg9Z g9g9s o\{o\{s >kZZ o\{g9g9kZc
kZg9Z g9o\{o\{^ g9g9^ o\{g9c kZo\{Z o\{g9c g9g9^
kZg9 g9kZZ g9kZkZc (o\{c g9o\{^ g9kZ^ o\{o\{w
o\{kZc o\{kZw kZg9g9kZkZo\{^ kZkZg9 kZ(o\{o\{s
kZo\{kZkZg9\{ kZo\{g9s kZg9o\{s kZo\{g9o\{w kZkZo\{kZc
kZo\{o\{g9kZg9 kZkZg9g9o\{g9w kZg9o\{g9s g9g9kZw
kZo\{kZs g9kZw o\{kZo\{kZo\{g9\{ o\{kZ^ g9kZkZg9o\{
o\{o\{s o\{g9 o\{kZw kZkZ kZg9c o\{g9^ g9kZc g9NsZ
g9NsZ $o\{kZs kZo\{g9s kZo\{s g9kZ CkZg9V kZkZ^
o\{g9NsZ g9kZg9Z !kZZ g9g9V o\{g9c g9g9c g9kZ^
o\{kZZ o\{g9s g9o\{V g9o\{w kZkZs o\{o\
o\{o\{s kZkZc kZkZo\{w o\{g9o\{s o\{o\{s o\{o\{s kZ(g9g9kZs
g9o\{s kZg9kZg9^ o\{g9c kZo\{o\{^ g9kZZ g9g9o\{kZw
kZg9V g9kZR !o\{c g9kZs o\{g9g9c g9o\{c g9kZ
o\{o\{s o\{o\{w kZg9^ o\{g9g9^ o\{g9^ g9g9^ g9kZg9^
g9g9 g9NsZ kZg9 "o\{c g9kZV o\{kZc o\{g9g9Z kZkZ^
o\{o\{w AkZg9V kZg9c NskZV g9g9c g9g9V g9g9c
o\{kZZ kZg9kZkZc o\{kZ^ g9kZkZZ g9kZ^ g9g9s
o\{g9o\{g9g9kZg9g9s g9g9\{ o\{kZo\{kZ o\{o\{^ o\{kZ
o\{o\
g9g9kZkZg9g9c kZg9c g9kZ kZkZg9c g9g9kZg9g9s
kZo\{g9o\{w o\{o\{ o\{!w o\{o\{s o\{o\{w o\{o\{s o\{o\{kZc
o\{o\{g9kZo\{s o\{o\{s o\{o\{s g9kZs kZo\{o\{g9\{ kZg9s
g9kZg9o\{o\{g9s o\{o\{c kZg9g9kZg9R g9"s kZg9g9c
g9kZg9c o\{o\{kZg9c kZkZg9g9^ g9g9\{ g9kZc kZg9R
o\{kZ g9g9c kZkZV o\{g9^ g9o\{kZo\{o\{s o\{2kZc
o\{g9o\{o\{kZs g9kZkZs g9g9o\{kZkZg9o\{kZ^ o\{kZkZs
o\{o\{w kZg9c o\{o\{kZc kZo\{o\{kZc o\{g9kZkZ kZg9s
o\{g9kZc o\{g9s kZg9s g9g9s g9g9kZg9kZkZg9 kZg9kZV
kZg9c g9kZg9o\{kZkZ kZo\
o\{g9kZc kZo\{^ Nsg9Z g9g9^ g9kZg9^ o\{o\{kZs
o\{o\
g9g9c g9o\{c o\{o\{ AkZkZR g9g9Z @kZZ kZg9^ g9g9Z
kZg9 g9g9kZg9Z o\{kZ o\{o\{kZs kZo\{ 3kZkZV g9kZV
o\{kZs g9kZV g9g9^ g9o\{g9c kZg9c g9g9Z o\{o\{w
o\{o\
NB6W Word.Document.8