China launched a propaganda war
taking advantage of the Israel-Palestine conflict
saying China is the savior of the world’s Muslims
Welcome to China Uncensored. I’m Chris Chappell.
Eleven days of fighting between\h
Israeli and Palestinian forces\h\h
ended on Friday with a ceasefire. It had\h
been the worst violence there since 2014.
But every heartbreaking conflict\h\h
is also a great opportunity—for a\h
Chinese communist propaganda drive!
You might be arguing with people over who the\h
real bad guy is in this long-standing conflict.\h\h
Israel? Hamas? No. The real bad guy is...America!
During the fighting, Chinese state-run media came\h
out with article after article about how the US\h\h
is part of the problem, but\h
not part of the solution.
The US stands opposite to international justice.
And the US is the one really\h
harming the world’s Muslims.
The Israel-Palestinian conflict has been a godsend\h
for the Communist Party. International pressure\h\h
has been mounting on the Chinese regime for\h
its genocide of Uyghur Muslims in Xinjiang.
But with the recent fighting in Israel and Gaza,\h\h
the Communist Party can now use one of its\h
favorite propaganda tactics—the switcheroo.
You see, the US is over-concerned about Muslim\h
Uyghurs, but what about Muslim Palestinians?
Get a load of this. State-run China Daily says the\h
US is “pretending to be friends and well-wishers\h\h
of Muslims, but they have been caught red-handed\h
this time. Because they are clamoring for the\h\h
human rights of Muslims in China, but quite\h
silent about the killings of Muslims in Palestine.\h\h
Thus their hypocrisies have been\h
revealed to the world once again.”
Wait, does that also mean China\h
is being hypocritical by saying\h\h
they care about the Muslims in Palestine,\h
but not about the Muslims in Xinjiang?
Of course not, because what the US claims\h
is happening in Xinjiang are all lies.
Chinese Foreign Ministry Spokeswoman Hua Chunying\h\h
said, the US “joined with a few of its allies\h
and attempted to organize meaningless meetings\h\h
on Xinjiang-related issues based\h
on lies and political prejudice.”
Because the reality is human rights in\h
Xinjiang are great! There’s an economic boom!
Granted, that economic boom is mostly felt\h
by the Han Chinese people that have flooded\h\h
Xinjiang in recent years, displacing the Uyghurs.
But what’s important to remember is...look\h
at all that happy ethnic dancing!
Clearly China is the real\h
friend of the world’s Muslims.
“Muslims are well aware that the US allies\h
are pretending to come out as their friends\h\h
by shedding crocodile tears\h
for Uyghurs in Xinjiang.
“Muslims think that the [US] is using the\h
Xinjiang issue as a shield to hide their\h\h
long history of oppression in Muslim countries.\h
Since actions certainly speak louder than words,\h\h
Muslims know who are their genuine and\h
bonafide friends around the world.”
It’s China. China is their bonafide friend.
Which is why it’s so evil that “The US has\h
been pressuring Arab countries [to criticize]\h\h
China's human rights and sabotaging the\h
China-proposed Belt and Road Initiative.”
Yes, please ignore whatever the US\h
says about China’s genocide of Muslims,\h\h
and continue to do business with China!
Which is why the state-run\h
Global Times suggests that,\h\h
“only human rights views of developing countries\h
such as China should be more listened to.”
And you know, since you asked, the\h
Chinese Communist Party does have\h\h
some ideas about how to solve\h
the Israeli-Palestinian conflict.
I’ll tell you what they are after the break.
Welcome back.
Yesterday’s ceasefire was\h
brokered largely by Egypt.
Which, I can’t understand. After\h
all, China had also offered to help!
But don’t worry, because there *will* be more\h
conflict in the region at some point. And then\h\h
the Israelis and Palestinians can turn to China.\h\h
Because China knows all about\h
how to create peace and harmony.
For example, China said,
“To avoid a humanitarian catastrophe, Israel\h
must fulfill its obligations proposed by\h\h
relevant UN resolutions, completely\h
lift its lockdown in the Gaza Strip,\h\h
ensure the safety and legal rights of\h
Palestinians in the occupied territories,\h\h
and facilitate the entrance\h
of humanitarian assistance.”
You know, like China does in\h
Xinjiang. Or it would if there was\h\h
actually a problem but there\h
isn’t so there’s no need.
China is also suggesting a two state solution.
What a great idea! Why hasn’t\h
anyone thought of that before?\h\h
Oh wait, they did. And the\h
Palestinian side repeatedly said no.
But the important thing is—China doesn’t need\h
to offer actual solutions. They just need to\h\h
seem like they’re the rational good guy,\h
while making the US look like the bad guy.
The reason China supports a two state solution\h
is because that’s been the UN’s stance. A very\h\h
unsuccessful stance, but that doesn’t matter.\h
The Communist Party likes to pretend it's\h\h
a responsible international player by saying\h
oh yeah, we totally follow the UN. Especially\h\h
because China has tremendous control\h
over the UN. And can stop it from\h\h
say...criticizing what China is doing in Xinjiang.
Meanwhile, Chinese state-run media\h
has used the Israel-Palestine conflict\h\h
to criticize the US for being on the\h
opposite side of international justice.
And the Chinese Communist Party is also taking\h
advantage of political divisions in the US.
It blamed the crisis on both Trump and Biden.
It’s Trump’s fault because,\h
“What Trump did in the past\h\h
years has sowed the seeds for the\h
current conflicts and bloodshed.”
So if you’re on the left in the US, you\h
might agree—Trump is a total monster.
But it’s also Biden’s fault, because “Biden\h
is unlikely to make any concrete moves\h\h
in de-escalating the confrontation, at most\h\h
making certain gestures in diplomatic\h
language that do not mean anything.”
So if you’re on the right in the US, you might\h
agree—Biden is a weak, ineffectual president.
The Chinese Communist Party\h
really knows how to play us.
Of course I wouldn’t want you to\h
think China is just blaming the US.\h\h
They’re also blaming the Jews! You\h
see, spokesperson Hua Chunyingsays\h\h
this conflict is intertwined\h
with the Iran nuclear issue.
So Chinese state-run media say “Israel doesn’t\h
want to see the US and Iran reach a deal\h\h
so the conflict in Gaza will add difficulties\h
to the talks between the US and Iran.”
You see, Israel has a secret\h
plot to muck up the US-Iran Deal.\h\h
Which is why they got Hamas to fire\h
rockets at them so they could fire\h\h
back. And if that sounds like a crazy\h
conspiracy theory, listen to this.
“The US bore an undeniable responsibility\h
[because] its policy in the Middle East has\h\h
long been kidnapped by its Jewish community\h
that serves the interest of Israel.”
That’s right. Chinese state-run\h
media is blaming the current conflict\h\h
on a cabal of Jews controlling the US government.
Israel has been criticizing blatant\h
antisemitism in Chinese State-run media.
A recent Chinese state-run CGTN broadcast\h
questioned what was really behind US support\h\h
for Israel. The host said, “some people believe\h
that U.S. pro-Israeli policy is traceable to the\h\h
influence of wealthy Jews in the U.S. and the\h
Jewish lobby on U.S. foreign policymakers.”
“Jews dominate finance and internet sectors.\h\h
So do they have the powerful\h
lobbies some say? Possible.”
Stay classy Chinese state-run media.
And now it’s time to answer a question from a\h
member of the China Uncensored 50 Cent Army,\h\h
fans who support us and our efforts to expose\h
the truth about the Chinese Communist Party\h\h
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
\h
Jason Oehring asks, “Question, has the CCP done or\h
said anything about moving the great firewall of\h\h
China so that it covers HK as well?”
(\h
That’s an excellent question.\h
For those of you who don’t know,\h\h
the great firewall is essentially the massive\h
censorship apparatus the Chinese Communist Party\h\h
uses to cut off China from the global internet\h
and control what people in China can see online.
Now, ever since the Chinese Communist Party\h
implemented the Hong Kong national security law,\h\h
Hong Kong’s freedoms have\h
increasingly been restricted.
Protesters have been arrested for\h
holding up blank pieces of white paper.
Hong Kong legislators need to make\h
patriotic oaths to the Communist Party.
Reporters are attacked in broad daylight.
Many are concerned it's just a matter of time\h
before the Great Firewall comes to Hong Kong.\h\h
Technically, Hong Kong still has\h
freedom of speech and the press.\h\h
But new fake news laws have a lot of\h
people worried about press freedom.
And earlier this year, a\h
pro-democracy website was blocked.\h\h
Which got a lot of people\h
thinking about the Great Firewall.
Last year, “The Hong Kong government\h
enabled police to censor online speech\h\h
and force internet service providers to hand\h
over user information and shut down platforms.”
So really, it’s only a matter of when, not\h
if, the Great Firewall comes to Hong Kong.
Thanks for your question Jason and your support.
And a big thank you to everyone who supports China\h
Uncensored on Patreon. We could not do this show\h\h
without you. So thank you for joining us in the\h
fight to expose the Chinese Communist Party to\h\h
the world. If you’re interested in joining, head\h
over to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored. You’ll get\h\h
a bunch of cool perks, including the chance\h
to have me answer your question on the show!
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next time.