On this episode of China Uncensored...
Wait, a story about Hong Kong
that’s actually hopeful?!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Finally some good news on the show!
It seems rare these days, doesn’t it?
Hong Kong activists Joshua Wong,
Alex Chow and Nathan Law
have had their prison sentences overturned.
Two years ago they had been sentenced
to community service for unlawful assembly
for their role in the 2014 Umbrella Movement.
That’s when tens of thousands of Hong Kongers
staged a mass protest against the Communist
Party
for going back on its promise
to give Hong Kong universal suffrage.
Then last year they were resentenced
to prison for the same crime,
because the “Hong Kong government”
decided that their sentences
weren’t harsh enough
to deter other people
from protesting in the future.
Now they’ve all served time in prison,
so I’m not quite sure how the courts
will give them that part of their lives back,
unless they’ve discovered time travel.
Of course, time travel is illegal in China.
It’s not all good news for protesters, though.
On one hand,
Hong Kong’s chief justice said,
“It would be inappropriate to retroactively
apply harsher penalties to the three.”
But on the other hand,
the judge also suggested that
from here on out,
the courts will be doling out harsh sentences
to anyone who gets out of line.
We wouldn’t want the young people
getting any more ideas.
But it will be hard to keep these things low
profile.
Because 12 US Congresspeople
have nominated Wong, Chow, and Law,
as well as the entire Umbrella Movement,
for the Nobel Peace Prize.
Led by Senator Marco Rubio
and Congressman Chris Smith,
the lawmakers praised the Hong Kong activists
for boldly challenging the Chinese regime’s
erosion of the one country,
two systems model—
the model that was supposed to
protect Hong Kong from the CCP.
In response,
Chinese state-run media decided to maintain
a dignified silence on the issue.
Just kidding.
They called it “ludicrous” that they would
nominate
those dangerous “rabble rousers”!
Yeah, you rabble rousers!
Get off China’s lawn!
China’s Foreign Ministry even wrote a statement
to Reuters
calling the Umbrella Movement illegal from
head to toe.
Yes, Joshua Wong...illegal from head to toe.
And on Wednesday,
everyone’s favorite pro-Beijing group,
Voice of Loving Hong Kong,
showed just how much they love Hong Kong,
by protesting the Nobel Prize nomination
in front of the US and Norwegian consulates.
Now at first,
you might think that’s a dumb place to protest.
The government of Norway
does not have a say
in who wins the Nobel Prize,
even though the Nobel organization
is headquartered in Norway.
But you see,
groups like the Voice of Loving Hong Kong
tend to be closely linked to the Chinese Communist
Party,
so you know, it’s hard for them
to understand that in free societies,
the government isn’t actually secretly controlling
everything.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Hey, did you know I was there
for the Umbrella Movement in 2014?
If you head over to our website,
ChinaUncensored.tv,
you can see all the cool adventures Matt,
Shelley, and I have had making China Uncensored.
So grab your favorite umbrella
and head on over to ChinaUncensored.tv.