A classical Chinese dance show.
The Chinese Communist Party hates it
And they’ll stop at nothing to shut it down
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Shen Yun.
It’s a classical Chinese dance show.
You’ve seen Shen Yun advertisements everywhere.
Everywhere.
And I do mean everywhere.
Why so much advertising?
In part, because the Chinese Communist Party
has spent enormous resources
trying to suppress the show—
threatening theaters,
slashing tour bus tires,
denying visas, and much more.
Why does the Communist Party consider this
show
such a threat?
Matt Gnaizda sits down with Shen Yun
Master of Ceremonies Leeshai Lemish to learn
more.
Leeshai, thanks for joining me today.
My pleasure.
So the Chinese Communist Party really, really
does not like Shen Yun.
They, for example, sent thugs to slash tour
bus tires.
.I mean, what's up with that?
Yeah, so Shen Yun is a performance of traditional
Chinese culture,
but it's based in New York.
That's the first thing they don't like.
Here is a celebration of Chinese culture and
it's not under
the Chinese Communist regime's monopoly.
Second, our mission is to revive traditional
Chinese culture.
So this is 5,000 years of civilization stories,
history,
different virtues that are brought out through
the stories.
And this is a culture that they spent decades,
about 80 years,
trying to destroy.
Cultural revolution, killing off different
people,
smashing statues, burning books.
And here we are,
"Hey, this is a celebration of this culture
that you destroyed.
Let's bring it back so people can experience
what traditional Chinese culture really was
about."
And this is really intimidating to them, because
if people reconnect with that culture,
be it in China or people outside of China,
realize what Chinese culture really was about
all this time,
then all of a sudden have some major legitimacy
questions,
because they brought in a regime that's Soviet,
it's Marxism, atheism, Darwinism, Maoism,
all this stuff.
Xi Jinping thought on socialism that Chinese
characteristics-
Chinese characteristics, very different from
these ideas,
like in Journey to the West of a spiritual
elevation.
And so-
Right.
Yeah, exactly.
Which is really a metaphor for our spiritual
path.
And also fighting bad guys.
Fighting bad guys is good.
Anybody can connect with that.
We actually get a lot of correspondence from
China,
people in China, wanting us to perform there.
So here we are a company that's celebrating
Chinese culture and we can't perform in China.
And not only that, they're trying to stop
us from performing outside of China.
It's interesting you talk about the culture,
because there's this article I read in the
Chinese state-run Global Times,
and it basically claims that Falun Gong is
using Shen Yun to push some sort of propaganda,
which was funny because the Chinese Communist
Party
has been in recent years trying to use Chinese
culture to push their propaganda.
Right, they have.
Are they jealous?
Well, they have all these Confucius Institutes,
they do all these different things,
and the reality is, and you probably have
talked about this before,
Confucius institutes, in the name of Confucius,
which was considered number one bastard during
the cultural revolution,
and so they spent all this time smashing Confucius
statues,
and just slandering him-
The whole criticize Confucius thing.
Yeah, like propaganda.
Yeah.
It was a big deal.
And they're like,
"Oh yeah, we're all into Confucianism."
But what they actually teach there is there
wasn't really a Tiananmen massacre,
Falun Gong, they're really anti-China, and
oh, by the way,
this is what Chinese characters are.
It's not traditional taste characters, it's
a simplified version,
so it's easier for you and lacks any content,
but that's okay.
So they'd been trying to do this whole propaganda
blitz
and really have a monopoly on Chinese culture.
And it's very different type of Chinese culture
that they're talking about
then what you guys in Shen Yun are doing,
right?
Right.
So Shen Yun was established about 13, 14 years
ago, end of 2006,
with the mission of reviving the real traditional
Chinese culture.
It started off because Chinese New Year would
come around,
usually during the winter, January, February
and people would want to have a performance.
And there was this performance that was done
in China
and on CCTV television, or in the embassies
here outside of China,
and these are just propaganda blitzes of,
"Hey, the Communist Party is great."
And everything was literally red.
It was all about how great China is under
the Communist Party.
And so Chinese people overseas would go like,
"This does not represent us, or our culture,
or celebrating anything.
Let's have our own show."
And so they would start their own performance.
And this grew, and the first one was here
in Madison Square Garden in 2004 and in 2005,
and Radio City 2006 was my first time hosting
the performance.
And eventually we said,
"Well, let's have our own performance and
really bring this culture back to life."
And so doing that through classical Chinese
dance, and music, and so on.
And so this is really an idea, like let's
go back into 5,000 years of civilization
and bring any story, any literary figure,
any character, be it [inaudible]
or the real story of Mulan, who by the way,
did not speak English it turns out or-
Really?
Yeah, it's amazing.
And she didn't have a pet lizard dragon also.
Really?
Yeah, yeah.
Well, it's shocking what you discover when
you actually go into.
But yeah, stories from Journey to the West,
Outlaws of the Marsh, Romance of the Three
Kingdoms, the creation,
Legends of the Creation [crosstalk].
So these are all being brought into Shen Yun
as different performance?
Right.
So Shen Yun is saying let's revive this and
bring this back.
And so it has the effect of first, people
outside of China,
no matter how familiar with Chinese civilization,
they get a sense of, okay, this is a very
different perspective on Chinese culture
and this is actually something you can go
back and you can read [inaudible] poems
from the seventh century and get a sense for
this.
We actually have a story about a famous poet
from that period and how he got inspiration.
You have novels like Journey to the West,
and Romance of the Three Kingdoms
and the characters there, and it's not just
stories.
You have a lot of good versus bad, and action,
and warriors,
and even supernormal abilities, and magic,
but you also have the virtues and the values
behind them.
Ideas of loyalty, and integrity, and faith,
and compassion, tolerance-
Whoa, whoa, whoa.
Integrity, compassion, these are not-
It's a little different from the Confucius
institutes.
From Communist Party culture, right?
Yeah, a little different.
So I can see why they're sort of intimidated
by Shen Yun.
Yeah, and the Falun Gong is another part of
that.
So Shen was started by Falun Gong practitioners.
A lot of our artists...
So Falun Gong was practiced all throughout
China.
You had people in every sphere.
Certainly you had workers,
and farmers, and different professions, but
then you also-
Right.
In the 1990s it was like you go to China
and there's just people practicing Falun Gong
everywhere.
Yeah.
And you even had people who were top party
members,
so they didn't see any conflict between being
a Falun Gong practitioner
and being a Communist Party member.
Like you could be a Republican or a Democrat
and practice say yoga or pilates.
It's just funny to think about that, like
from today's perspective.
Absolutely, yeah.
But they were also artists.
So you had choreographers, and composers,
and leaders of some of the best orchestras
in China.
And some of them came outside of China, and
they said,
"Well, we have these skills.
What do we do with them?
Because we'd like to bring back this culture.
We like to tell people the story of what's
happening to Falun Gong in China,"
so this company was founded.
And so these people brought this together,
and then also as part of the performance alongside
the stories are the traditional culture part
and ethnic dances, folk dances and so on.
You also have stories on what's happening
to Falun Gong practitioners in China today.
There's maybe a couple of pieces.
We have about 20 stories every year, 20 different
dances.
Maybe a couple of them are about the Falun
Gong story,
and you have a sense of, okay, so these are
people meditating in the park,
and that maybe is how the story starts, or
it's a family, and then boom,
they get pounced on, there's persecution that
erupts seemingly out of nowhere.
And then they get thrown in jail and it's
basically
a battle of their faith in the face of the
persecution,
and finding inner courage, and finding eventually
hope.
And so this story is now a story they've been,
the CCP, Communist Party,
has been trying to hide all these years, now
20 years of persecution.
They said, "Oh, this is not happening.
Just a small group of people, and we're treating
them very nicely,
and this is all made up."
And here we actually have it on stage at Lincoln
Center,
Kennedy Center, all over the world, and we
have VIPs, CEOs,
congressman in the audience, and they say,
"Oh, this is actually," and it's depicted
very beautiful.
Well but this is your problem, because you're
taking
traditional Chinese values and making them
relevant to today.
Absolutely.
And it's-
Right?
This is the worst possible thing you could
do
from the Communist Party's perspective.
Yeah.
Because there's a sense that also this is,
in a way...
A big part of this is like, oh, this is what
human culture really was like a long time
ago,
not just in China, but around the world.
Yes, it has this Chinese flair to it, and
Chinese costumes,
and all the stories, but these ideas of loyalty,
integrity, compassion,
these are things that are common universally.
And so I think people are surprised when they
come to see
the performance that it's not just a journey
into Chinese culture and history,
but actually there's something really deep
that resonates with people,
and inspires them, and uplifts them.
So I want to get back to what the Communist
Party
has done to stop Shen Yun.
And one of the things actually in the same
Global Times articles,
They said that they wanted the Shen Yun performers
names to be
“made public so they will be expelled from
mainstream Chinese communities.”
Basically they want overseas Chinese,
like here in America,
to dox Shen Yun performers and cancel them.
Like, is this actually happening?
Yeah, to actually ostracize them or even blacklist
them,
not allow them to get jobs.
Yeah.
So for example, the Chinese Student Scholar
Association, CSSA,
they're in Columbia, they're in every big
university across the country and around the
world,
they have been very active under the auspices
of the Chinese Communist Party's embassies
and consulate.
Actually, the head of the CSSAs in these universities
actually kind of a liaison
with the embassy and they get directives from
them.
So they'll bring them out to welcome a leader
and maybe get paid to do so,
and they'll go and protest Shen Yun,
and maybe they're getting paid to do that.
And so they actually have been very active
in trying to target Shen Yun and trying to
stop us.
Now, not some-
So they get the Chinese student groups to
protest like a Shen Yun performance?
They get Chinese students who are here, have
to go back to China,
have family back in China, maybe even got
a scholarship to be here, and they say,
"We are representative of China.
You have to follow our orders.
Here's what you're going to do or else you
are going to be in trouble."
But-
I'm just imagining some foreign governments
trying
to get people to protest Hamilton.
Right?
Like that's crazy, right?
No, I've never heard of that happening,
but for us it's kind of a reality.
From day one when we first started in 2006
we've had all these various phenomena.
So one thing that they do is that kind of
a protest.
Not very common anymore because it's really
not successful.
Another thing they do is they try to pressure
family members
of performers who are still back in China.
So for example, my MC partner.
I'm on stage, I introduce the pieces,
there's a lady who introduces them with me.
She was from Beijing, and her parents were
still in Beijing,
and they would get weekly visits from National
Security Bureau saying,
"We know what your daughter-
Inside China?
In Beijing.
They would just come and sit down for a chat
in the living room and say,
"We know what your daughter is doing.
We don't like it.
Have her stop doing it or else everybody's
going to be in trouble."
We had an erhu soloist, so this is a person
who plays a two-string erhu,
like the Chinese violin, and her husband was
jailed while she was with Shen Yun.
And so this is some-
For her work in Shen Yun.
We don't really know exactly how,
but it was definitely for his beliefs.
They're both Falun Gong practitioners and-
So there's also that.
It's like a double-
There's also that, and we have-
A double crime, right?
Yeah.
And we have people,
members of the company,
who actually experience persecution.
They're not the vast majority,
but we have people who were tortured in China,
we have people who've lost family members,
we have a dancer whose dad was killed when
she was an infant and thrown in a ditch.
So this persecution story is very relevant
to people,
but I think what we try to portray on stage
is also just the sense of hope and belief.
And the same with Shen Yun.
These performers have been through this now
for 14 years and it's never stopped us.
We've grown from one company to now up to
seven companies,
a tour simultaneously, and we've put up with
a lot.
So for example, the first year when we were
touring,
they would send other performing arts companies
to try to compete with us.
So they send like 60 something companies around
the world,
and we perform in a theater,
and they'd be across the street or right next
to us at the same time.
And we'd go to a certain country and they
say,
"Yeah, we've already seen Shen Yun."
Say, "What do you mean?
We just got here."
Like, "No, no.
We saw it last week,"
and it turns out that they got tickets for
this other show.
Wait, so you're saying that there is
a Chinese Communist state-sanctioned knock-off?
I've never heard of that kind of thing.
They paid companies to go out just to compete
with us.
And in some cases actually we would move the
show date because of scheduling issues
and they would move their show day to correspond
to it.
And they did this in LA,
across the Dorothy Chandler Pavilion did it,
they sent out companies here to New York.
It was just done, the first couple years especially.
Then it didn't work because the theaters were
empty for them,
and people weren't buying tickets,
and there was no competition, and the Shen
Yun brand got established.
So then they started pressuring theaters to
not allow us to perform.
So they would write the theaters or even knock
on the door.
Who would write to the theaters?
The Chinese consulates and embassies.
We had this in LA, in New York, in Sydney,
and Munich.
Name us a big city where we've performed,
they've done it.
Is the Chinese consulate even allowed to operate
like that on U.S. soil?
Well, that's a diplomatic question.
I think what's worse is sometimes they will
have
other people do the bidding for them,
which is really illegal, because then you're
operating for another regime.
Right.
Like I read about them slashing tires in,
like the tour bus tires in Ottawa.
Yeah.
So what happened was our driver would do a
pre-trip inspection
and he discovers a big cut on the front tire.
So he takes it to the shop, they say,
"Oh, this cut is really interesting."
So what's interesting about it?
Well, it was cut in such a way that the tire
would not deflate right away.
It was just several layers of the rubber had
been cut
so that on the highway at high-speed when
it expands,
then the tire would explode and maybe you
lose control of the vehicle.
At the very least you're going to be stalled
for a long time.
So and that happened.
The very next day we got news of this,
I was actually in Memphis,
and we were going to travel to Little Rock.
So we inspected our truck and we discovered
a very similar cut in our truck.
Of course, we just had the tire replaced.
And then that night our bus,
in a rain storm driving late at night from
Memphis to Little Rock,
had a flat tire and we were stopped on the
side of the road for a while.
So this went on for some time and then they
started trying to-
Did you know that the Chinese consulate was
behind this?
We can't prove it, of course.
They're not going to have the ambassador himself
with a badge saying,
"Here, I'm going to cut your tire now."
It could just be a coincidence, like all these
tire questions.
It could be a coincidence that we had three
tire slashes in 48 hours.
I mean especially in Canada, I mean it's full
of criminals there.
They're very nice though, very polite.
Yeah.
And then they start trying to tamper with
our gas tanks.
One case, it was in Texas, like 3:00 AM,
this other pickup truck shows up next to our
bus,
and then starts trying to do something with
the gas tank,
and then we have security now watching 24
hours a day.
So then he drives off, and eventually it's
a chase,
and they're calling the police, they're chasing
him.
These are volunteers, mind you.
And the police is coming over,
and the guy abandons his pickup truck and
runs away.
So whatever he was trying to do was so important
that he was willing
to give up his pickup truck and just give
run.
And this happened Atlanta.
We had people put corrosive material on a
promotions car in Chicago.
These are actually life-threatening type of
things.
Or would cut the cable so that you can actually
have an accident.
But then we have people spying on us,
waiting for us in hotel lobbies, people trying
to take pictures,
people trying to use universal remote controls
to shut off our projection in the middle of
a show,
protests outside.
The funny thing with the protests is they'll
show up and it's like clockwork.
Like the people who are doing this are clearly
not very motivated.
They show up at 9:00 o'clock and they leave
at 5:00 PM.
The audience members are coming in, but they're
gone.
They took their banners and left.
And this just happened just now in South Korea.
We were performing there and it was the same
group.
They would travel from city to city.
Who actually is that motivated to protest
a performing arts company?
They would take two, three weeks off from
work
and travel with professionally-made banners
from city to city,
just to follow us around.
But then they leave at 5:00 PM.
Leave at 5:00 PM, yeah, yeah.
I mean you got to take a break.
Protesting is tough work.
It's tough work standing there.
It's pretty cold sometimes too.
So this is not just a one-off thing.
This is like a constant...
They're sort of like state-coordinated type
effort it sounds like.
Yeah.
One thing that they did for example was they
would send emails to the theaters.
So all these various tactics before are not
working.
They would send these letters to theaters
saying,
"Don't allow Shen to perform."
And here in the States people are like,
"What are you talking about?
This is America.
We perform whatever we want."
And some [inaudible] would report this to
the FBI.
In some places like Eastern Europe, like Romania,
Moldova, Ukraine,
this has a bit of traction because they're
very susceptible to corruption.
As-
So those theaters have canceled the performances.
We've had performances cancel.
We showed up in a theater in Moldova after
a three day bus trip from Turkey,
and we showed up at the theater, and we get
to the hotel late at night,
we show up at the theater next morning for
setup, and they say,
"You can't perform.
Your show has been canceled."
And then all the media shows up,
and they do all these interviews,
and we find out what's going on.
Later on, somebody from town hall actually
found me at a coffee shop,
me and a couple of dancers, and told me,
"Here's the backstory of what happened.
We actually got visits from the Chinese embassy
on a regular basis.
They asked us at town hall to pressure them
to cancel the performance."
Then we met with the theater manager
and they brought in the foreign minister.
So they basically used a foreign ministry
connection between the PRC and Moldova.
Moldova is a very, very small and poor country
in Eastern Europe, mind you.
Very beautiful, don't get me wrong.
But what is the diplomatic incentive here
for China to be that close to Moldova?
They get the foreign minister to do the bidding
for them.
They sit in the theater, you got your foreign
minister,
your Chinese ambassador, your mayor,
and this other executive and the theater manager
saying,
"Cancel the performance."
And this executive from town hall was saying,
"Do not cancel it.
You have a contract.
You have no legal backup if you do this."
And they said, "Well, we have to do it."
What they often uses the carrot and stick.
If you cancel Shen Yun we will bring some
companies from China to perform instead.
If you don't cancel Shen Yun you'll never
get a performance from China,
you're not going to get a visa.
So we had a case in Berlin where the guy who
was working there,
the theater manager, received a similar visit
from the Chinese embassy,
this was a couple of years ago, and they did
the same thing.
"You will not be allowed to visit China personally
and we will not bring any Chinese company
to perform in your theater."
This is the Chinese consulate telling them
this.
Chinese embassy in Berlin, yeah, yeah.
And-
So how did he react?
Well, he was from Eastern Europe,
so he kind of knew the deal with communism,
and he actually experienced persecution himself,
and he said, "Goodbye."
And that's what happens most of the time,
especially in strong democracies.
Like the theaters just say,
"We're not going to be intimidated by this.
We're going to run the show."
No, no.
In fact, yeah, they have an opposite effect
on them.
So for example, in Australia,
we were performing in Canberra our first year
on tour,
and after the show we walk outside the theater
and we see two parliament members standing
there.
And they say, "Actually, we got a letter from
the Chinese embassy saying,
'Do not come see the show.'"
And were like, "We hadn't heard of Shen Yun.
What is this?
This isn't interesting.
Let's go check it out."
And all parliament members got the letter
and a bunch of them were there.
Just could have had their meetings there and
everything.
Czech Republic, one time a TV station got
a letter saying,
"Do not interview Shen Yun, do not promote
them."
Like, Shen Yun, what's that?
It's coming to town.
Okay, we weren't planning on interviewing
them.
It's like, okay, well now we're going to call
So then they got our dancer and our concert
master
wanting to do this interview in the Czech
Republic,
and they said, "This is Czech Republic.
Maybe this is how you do things in China.
Here we decide who will and who will not be
in our show,
who and who will not be on stage,
and we're very glad to have you,
and good luck with your performance."
And this is really the phenomena worldwide.
It's kind of like free advertising.
But the thing is they do some things that
are very tricky.
So for example, they have the China Daily,
is the mouthpiece of the Communist Party in
English.
It's for general consumption.
You can buy it here on the street in New York
City.
They actually had a paid insert that they
put in the Washington Post
and other newspapers in the U.S. and around
the world
pretending to be an article by the Washington
Post criticizing Shen Yun.
It's the China Watch section.
I've seen that in the papers.
Yeah.
So you think, "Oh, the Washington Post has
a cool China section."
Right.
And it's like little font.
It's like paid advertisement,
like at the very bottom [crosstalk].
Yeah, it's a very little font.
But it's formatted like an article.
It's like a 3D or something, yeah.
It looks like a regular article.
So unless you're aware of this dynamic
and you're aware of all the forces behind
the scenes trying to do this,
you're not going to pick up on that.
And they're using this sort of state-sanctioned
China watch section to criticize Shen Yun.
Yeah.
And the title was something like Shen Yun
is a Blasphemy to the Arts
or something very over the top communist sounding.
And then this was Washington Post, it was
the Wall Street Journal,
it was in Melbourne, it was in Nashville,
it was in London Telegraph, all over the place.
And so you think, "Oh, all these newspapers
really don't like Shen Yun,"
and then they would send emails to theaters-
But it's not like that they don't like Shen
Yun.
They're just happy to take lots and lots of
money in exchange for pretending it's,
oh, it's not my problem if it criticizes Shen
Yun, right?
Yes, money turns out to be the currency.
Funny that.
Yeah, but what we've really seen is that it
doesn't really affect us that much.
The recent thing that they're doing is they're
trying to kind of tweak,
and I can't prove this,
but it seems like there's an attempt to mess
with Google's rankings of Shen Yun articles.
So if you go to Google and Google Shen Yun,
it will come up with...
You know how they have suggested fields for
things to ask,
you have to search for?
They'll be like, what's the deal with Shen
Yun?
Is Shen Yun a cult?
These kinds of really bizarre things that,
you know,
where's your Shen Yun reviews?
Where is Shen Yun performing arts?
These are very basic things.
So it's not like the Shen Yun website.
It's like the [crosstalk].
Shen Yun website is still there.
Maybe there's a paid ad for [inaudible] website
still at the top.
Then Wikipedia has a bunch of stuff.
Wikipedia is this whole other battlefield.
There's constant people trying to put negative
stuff about Shen Yun at the top,
and an editor's going in, and they fight over
it,
and it goes back and forth.
You can see it on a daily basis.
Wikipedia fights, you can never win those.
Yeah, I guess it's a war of attrition.
And then there's these few articles
that had negative reviews about Shen Yun.
We did perform in front of a million people
last year.
I'm on stage, I see the audience reaction.
I know how positive it is.
I walk through the lobby, I talk to people,
I've seen interviews with people.
But yeah, there's some negative articles out
there.
Not that many, but then somehow they're always
at the top of Google.
If you go to the Yahoo, you go to Bing, nowhere
to be found.
Yeah, there's just a bunch of these-
It's just funny because there's been so much
news recently of Google
using people to actually control what goes
in the search results
instead of using the algorithm.
So here's what I don't know;
I mean I use Google like everybody else to
find things.
Maybe use a different search engine, but-
Just try Baidu.
Sure.
Yeah, just go to the Chinese embassy, you
know, .gov,
and see what their perspective on everything
is.
But I don't know if it's Google doing this.
If there is somebody on the inside in Google
or is somebody in China
who's figured out some sort of algorithm
to mess with the search engine optimization
rankings.
They're doing inbound linking.
You know how they post comments linking different
things?
They have the whole 50 Cent army doing things,
which we know they've used for many years
to attack whoever they happen to not like
at a time.
And they've hacked our website.
They hacked our website one year at the very
beginning of ticket sale season.
Oh, good.
So the Chinese hackers are also in it.
It's like everything from the slashing tires,
to the writing letters to the theaters,
to the getting overseas Chinese students to
protest, to the hacking.
It's just like every aspect of this type of...
I guess in other contexts we often call it
subversion, right?
Yeah, yeah, basically.
And then if you take a step back, it's like,
why?
I mean, you do not have bigger issues to deal
with?
This is what's concerning the performing arts
company outside of China?
You're clearly a huge threat.
I mean, that's a lot of resources.
Yeah, apparently.
And it's not even-
I mean, they haven't done that to China Uncensored,
so obviously we're not nearly as much of a
threat.
Well, maybe you'll join the party one day,
and certainly if we're communicating over
email
they now know about you as well.
Oh, that's nice.
I think they probably discovered you before,
but the thing is it is a threat to them,
but the reality is that our performers, me
personally,
I've been to China,
I spent time studying and working throughout
Asia,
I would love to bring a show to China.
And I'm the white guy in the show.
I mean, most of the performers are I think
Chinese,
from China, from around the world.
What their dream is to bring the show back
to China,
because it's about celebrating traditional
Chinese culture,
a culture that had almost been entirely lost
because of the cultural revolution,
the anti-five, and anti-three, and anti-rights,
and all this stuff that they did there.
And now many generations of people
who have been brought up under the regime
not really knowing what traditional Chinese
culture is about,
and people that are heroes are portrayed as
villains.
And here we have a show that's bringing out
these stories,
and actually, this is what this person was
actually about,
and here's the virtue that this person represents
in Chinese history,
and want to share it with them.
So you're subverting 70 years of communist
cultural destruction.
At the very least 70 years.
But do you really think they're going to let
you into China?
So people who are in China and can afford
to,
they will fly out to Taiwan especially, but
to Japan,
Vancouver, LA, wherever they can go.
And we even had people from the communist
parties bureaucracy
come to us after a show.
Like they'll tell somebody through in the
lobby.
Really?
They'll secretly come to Shen Yun?
They go “jia you,” which means we support
you, good luck.
After a show, you know, we were sent here
to spy,
but we really like your show, so good luck.
We had dancers from China who just admired
the standards of Shen Yun,
especially now that we're really established,
they'll come and try to learn and try to mimic
stuff,
is of course the highest form of flattery,
but also some people try to defect,
and so they're really on the guard for that.
They try to block performance from leaving
China to join us.
So it's just a matter of time.
And on the website we get constant emails
from China saying,
"Hey, will you please come perform in China?
We can't wait.
Can we buy a DVD?
We really are rooting for you guys."
And our performers can't wait to go there
to perform,
but this is the reality right now,
that if you really want to see a performance
of traditional Chinese culture,
you have to go to Lincoln Center,
or you have to go to Taiwan.
You can't go see it this way in Beijing.
You guys have like a,
I saw something like 150 cities in the next
six months.
Yeah.
So we have seven groups that tour around the
world at the same time.
Each company will do 25, 30 cities.
Usually we're somewhere for two, three days,
sometimes two or three weeks, depending.
But yeah, it's a 150 cities or so.
Which is to say, the Chinese Communist Party
is not very good at stopping you.
No, they're not.
And like I said, it's free advertising,
and then they got more and more work.
The first year we were just one group with
30 cities.
That's 30 letters with multiple copies to
send out.
I mean, that's a lot of work.
I mean, you're really just creating so much
work
for those poor communist officials in China.
Well, it's providing employment for all those
people
posting the comments I guess.
That's true.
You're a job creator.
Yeah.
There you go.
Well, good luck on your upcoming tour-
Thank you.
...and make sure to check those bus tires.
Absolutely.
There's a new tactic every year, but it doesn't
stop us.
We really want to just go perform and we really
hope that
we can perform in China someday,
but in the meantime,
we'll just put up with this stuff.
All right, well thanks for joining me.
Thank you.