On this episode of China Uncensored,
Another North Korean assassination plot?
L.O.L.!
Shanghai becomes a ghost town!
The ghosts are just there for the shopping.
And finally, does trade trump human rights?
I know just the guy to ask.This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
In our top story,
Chinese authorities apparently broke up
a North Korean assassination plot.
According to South Korean media sources,
several North Korean agents were apprehended
by Chinese police in Beijing.
They were allegedly part of a plot to assassinate
Kim Jong-un’s 22-year-old nephew,
Kim Han-sol.
North Korean leader Kim Jong-un
had apparently ordered his bounty hunters
to bring him Han-sol...
and a cookie.
Sadly, they weren’t able to bring him back
that cookie, either.
Kim Han-sol is the son of Kim Jong-un’s
half-brother,
Kim Jong-nam,
who was assassinated in Malaysia
earlier this year by two women.
One of whom was wearing a shirt that said
L.O.L.
Beijing authorities were tipped off this time
because one of the North Korean agents
was wearing a similar shirt.
The Chinese regime has been sheltering
Kim Jong-un’s half-brother’s family—
including Han-sol—for years.
Some people believe it’s because
they wanted them to replace Kim Jong-un someday.
You see,
Kim Jong-nam was a market reform type communist.
Whereas Kim Jong-un is more of a
destabilize-all-of-Asia type communist.
But not everyone in China
is completely opposed to Kim’s North Korean
regime.
Apparently one of China’s biggest
state-owned investment groups
may have links to a cargo ship
that was doing illegal trading
between China and North Korea.
On the bright side though,
it seems like the Chinese regime
is repairing relations with the other member
of the Korean peninsula:
South Korea.
Earlier this year,
South Korea installed THAAD,
a US-made missile defense system.
The Chinese regime flipped out.
What’s the problem with a missile defense
system
protecting South Korea
from a North Korean nuclear strike?
Well, it could also theoretically be used
someday
against China.
The Chinese regime encouraged people t
o boycott South Korean products.
They even shut down some Korean businesses
operating inside China,
like this Lotte store in Jiangsu Province
that suddenly had “fire safety issues.”
But that still didn’t stop South Korea
from installing the missile defense system.
So eventually the Chinese regime
kind of backed down.
and now they’re agreeing to normalize relations
anyway.
It’s for the greater good
of denuclearizing North Korea, of course!
Not that China, or any other country,
might need to do much to achieve that.
North Korea might be accidentally denuclearizing
itself.
An estimated 200 North Koreans were killed
at a nuclear testing site in September
when a tunnel collapsed.
That’s according to a Japanese news broadcaster
with North Korean sources.
It’s still unconfirmed,
but experts say it’s possible the most recent
nuclear test
weakened the ground around the site.
In fact, according to this Washington Post
article,
after so many nuclear tests,
the mountain may just be exhausted.
Of course it’s exhausted.
I felt the same way after taking six standardized
tests
in a row in school.
They also accomplished practically nothing
and just left everybody frustrated.
So is this the end of North Korea’s nuclear
testing?
No, probably not.
But “Chinese scientists already have warned
that further nuclear tests could cause the
mountain
to collapse and release the radiation from
the blast.”
And that mountain is only 50 miles
from the Chinese border.
So a radiation leak is not the kind of North
Korean export
China is looking for.
In other news,
after the CCP’s 19th Party Congress last
week,
Chinese leader Xi Jinping rose to
even greater heights of power.
So what did he decide to do?
Why, make a trip to his arch rival Jiang Zemin’s
powerbase,
Shanghai.
There’s something called being a sore winner,
Xi.
Shanghai is a big city.
And yet it was turned into a ghost town for
Xi’s trip.
The streets were practically empty.
Unless you count all the police.
Visiting Shanghai is symbolic for Xi Jinping.
Just being able to visit and dominate the
city like this
shows he’s killin’ it.
And by “it”
I mean the careers of all who oppose him.
Here he is with his crew visiting
the site of the first Party Congress.
I assume they’re doing the universal gesture
for “I just won.”
Trump had called Xi Jinping last week
to congratulate him—
and teach him about the raised fist thing.
Speaking of “trump”:
Over in Hong Kong,
imprisoned student activist and friend of
the show
Joshua Wong is out on bail.
And he’s warning the world:
Trade trumps human rights.
In an interview with the Associated Press,
Joshua Wong said,
"Business interests override human rights...
It unfortunately seems to be a common trend
in the world."
Well, trade may trump rights,
but you know what?
Trump trumps trade.
President Donald Trump will be making
his first state visit to China next week.
Trade will be a major topic of discussion,
especially as the White House beings a probe
into China’s unfair trade practices,
including stealing US intellectual property.
And finally,
the Chinese regime is pushing somehow
even more Internet censorship.
Apparently, people aren’t paying enough
attention
to heavily censored state-run media,
turning to the Internet instead.
And who knows where that information
is coming from!
On the Internet,
any random guy can just produce some videos
that slander the Chinese regime.
Now, new Chinese regulations
“will force news and information platforms
to conduct regular assessments
to prevent the spread of ‘illegal information.’”
What counts as illegal information?
Don’t worry,
it’s left intentionally vague.
Speaking of Chinese censorship,
it may even be extending to America.
Facebook has removed the account
of Chinese billionaire dissident Guo Wengui.
“Facebook said Oct. 1
it had taken down a page associated with Guo
and stopped him from posting to his own account.”
It comes after Guo posted negative things
about China’s Anti-Corruption Czar
and Eeyore impersonator Wang Qishan.
Now I’m no particular fan of Guo Wengui.
But having Facebook arbitrarily remove his
page after
“[receiving] a report from a representative
of the Chinese government
about that account”
is maybe not a good sign of things to come
here in America.
I wonder if it had anything to do with Facebook
trying to get into China?
On a totally unrelated note,
here’s Facebook’s Mark Zuckerberg
at a meeting on Monday with Xi Jinping.
He even put on adult clothes!
So what do you think?
And is the China Uncensored Facebook page
at risk?
I hope not,
because I post cool content there that
you don’t see here on the YouTube channel.
Thanks for watching.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
I hope you’ve been watching these videos
at the end of my YouTube episodes.
Otherwise you won’t know about ChinaUncensored.tv.
Its our very own website.
And every Friday,
we upload full half hour episodes of the show
for free.
Check it out now!