Stalled progress on a US-China trade deal.
The threat of new tariffs coming Friday.
Trump is playing hardball.
But what’s really at stake?
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Friday’s coming and you know what that means
here at China Uncensored—
It’s Friday, Friday gotta get down on Friday!
If you’d like to feel old,
that song came out eight years ago.
Anyway, this Friday,
you know who might not be partyin’, partyin’
yeah?
See, for five months,
US and Chinese negotiators have been trying
to work out a big trade deal.
Back in December,
President Trump had said he would raise tariffs
on $200 billion worth of Chinese goods on
March 1.
He extended that deadline,
and then kept extending it,
so a trade deal could be made.
But on Sunday,
President Trump said enough is enough.
Well, he Tweeted enough is enough.
“For 10 months,
China has been paying Tariffs to the USA
of 25% on 50 Billion Dollars of High Tech,
and 10% on 200 Billion Dollars of other goods.
The 10% will go up to 25% on Friday."
Thank goodness Twitter allows
up to 240 characters now.
So this Friday—
two days from now—
is the deadline.
And maybe he means it this time.
“The Trade Deal with China continues,
but too slowly,
as they attempt to renegotiate. No!"
This is a change of tone from early April,
when Trump met with Vice Premier Liu He in
the Oval Office.
At that time, it seemed like things were going
well.
"We are rounding the turn,
we'll see what happens.
We have a ways to go but not very far.
We've made a lot of progress."
The Chinese Vice Premier agreed there was
progress,
and tried to butter up the president a little
by praising his direct involvement the negotiations.
“Because of your direct involvement,
we do have great progress.
Although we still have some remainings,
hopefully we get a good result.”
Oh Liu He, flattery will get you everywhere.
Except maybe to a trade agreement.
So why have the trade negotiations
hit a speed bump since then?
On Monday,
US Trade Representative Robert Lighthizer
and Treasury Secretary Steve Mnuchin,
who have been leading the trade talks,
said that Chinese officials had been reneging
on previous commitments.
And they confirmed that US tariffs
would be raised on Friday.
According to Lighthizer,
Chinese officials were trying to make
substantial last-minute changes to the agreement.
What?! Who could have seen this coming?
Well...a lot of people, actually.
Bloomberg columnist and finance professor
Noah Smith
says that for China to make good on its promise
to reduce its 400 billion dollar a year trade
surplus with the US,
it would have to make big sacrifices.
“It seems improbable that China will follow
through on
this big trade-war concession,” Smith argues.
“Chances are high that it turns out to be
a red herring.”
That’s because following through on
any kind of structural reform
would hurt China’s economic growth too much.
But of course, not signing a trade deal
would also hurt China’s economic growth.
That could be why, last Friday,
Trump suggested that the US would be just
fine without a deal.
"We'll see what happens over the next couple
of weeks,
but we're getting close to a very historic
monumental deal
and if it doesn't happen we'll be fine too,
maybe even better."
One reason the US could be better off holding
out for now,
is that these negotiations are a unique chance
to reset America's relationship with China.
That’s what hedge fund manager Kyle Bass
recently told CNBC.
And there’s good reason to listen to Bass.
He's one of the few people who correctly predicted
the sub-prime meltdown that sparked the 2008
financial crisis.
He says reducing America's 400 billion trade
deficit with China
is small potatoes compared to the big play:
forcing China to stop stealing American technology.
"With China, our real issue is forced technology
transfer,
it's intellectual property theft,
it's subversive industrial policies
that circumvent WTO rules,
it's basically the way the Chinese lie,
cheat and steal their way through our economy."
Bass says that for the trade deal to be meaningful
it's gotta have teeth.
Like sanctions on China
if their promises turn up empty.
"It's really important for this new agreement,
whatever it is,
to be measurable and punishable."
And that’s one of the sticking points with
the current deal,
which the Chinese officials tried to renege
on.
But if you ask former White House chief strategist
Steve Bannon,
the US has to demand that the Chinese regime
make structural reforms that will transform
China
into the kind of free market system
that China promised to be so many years ago.
And if we can’t get that from the trade
deal,
we shouldn’t sign it at all.
"I think we should walk away from this right
now.
We ought to start playing hardball,
we ought to start playing smash-mouth."
Yeah, we ought to start playing Smash Mouth!
“Hey now, you’re an all star.
Get your game on, go play.”
If you’d like to feel really, really old,
that song came out 20 years ago.
What’s that, Shelley?
I see.
Steve Bannon is not a fan of late nineties
rock music.
He just meant aggressive and confrontational.
That makes more sense, I guess.
Anyway, Trump *is* getting more aggressive
and confrontational.
His Tweets on Sunday...
were a warning that things are moving too
slowly,
and that Chinese negotiators had better not
get overconfident or drag things out.
It’s time to make a deal.
Or no deal,
if they want to play it like that.
And he’s gotten support from some unexpected
sources.
Like Democratic Senator Chuck Schumer,
who tweeted that Trump should “hang tough
on China.”
Meanwhile, Chinese officials have agreed to
resume trade talks Thursday and Friday,
so there’s a possibility that tariffs
might not go into effect on Friday, after
all.
So what do you think about Trump's threat
to slap China with more tariffs?
Leave your comments below.
And while you’re still here,
it’s time for me to answer another question
from a fan who supports China Uncensored
with a dollar or more per episode—
through the crowdfunding website Patreon.
J R Harrison asks:
“Who are you interviewing this year
for the anniversary of the T.S. Massacre?
Is it going to be Fang Zheng again?”
Thanks for your question.
Last year during the Oslo Freedom Forum,
I interviewed Fang Zheng—
a Tiananmen Square student protester
who was run over by a tank.
This year, I have a new guest lined up:
Zhou Fengsuo.
After participating in the 1989 Tiananmen
Square protests,
and surviving the massacre,
Chinese authorities labeled him as number
on their “most wanted” list.
They arrested him,
and threw him in a re-education camp.
Now, he’s in the US and fighting to make
sure
Tiananmen Square gets remembered.
I think you’re going to love this interview.
It’ll come out June 3.
And thank you to everyone
who supports China Uncensored on Patreon.
I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.