Hong Kong’s Iron Lady
Knows How to Fight for Freedom
For decades, Emily Lau
Has been on the frontlines of the battle for
Hong Kong
Welcome to China Uncensored,
I'm Chris Chappell.
Joining me now is a woman who was
a household name in Hong Kong, Emily Lau.
She's been a journalist, a politician,
and a major thorn in Beijing side.
Perfect for China and Censored.
Emily, thank you for joining me.
Hi.
So in 1996, you and other legislators laid
down
in a major road to protest how Hong Kong's
chief executive would be selected.
So you're basically the first umbrella movement
protestor.
I guess you're right!
And if you tell those kids out there they
would say,
“Oh, what?
Really?”, because that was before they were
born.
And that's true.
And then of course I get a very bad nickname
for that,
but that's true.
What was the nickname?
Well, in Chinese it's [foreign language],
that means 'someone lying in the street'.
And actually, I ran into
a high court judge a few months later,
and he said, “Emily.
Haven't you got a bed to lie on?”.
So, what do you think of the tactics and strategies
protestors have been using in the umbrella
movement,
and the current extradition bills?
Well, the umbrella movement started out as
the occupation movement,
and we have the Occupy trio;
Benny Tai, Chan Kin-man, and Reverend Chu.
And my party, the democratic party,
was the first to come out to support them.
Because they say, where we have been fighting
for democracy
for so long and get nowhere,
maybe we should use civil disobedience to
fight.
Occupy central with peace and love.
No violence.
No disorder.
So my party said, "OK, well, let's have a
go."
So we supported it,
but then when it did happen two years,
which of course got everybody very impatient.
And then we have the students rushing into
the government complex,
they were arrested, and the people got very
excited.
They want to come and save the students.
So, the whole movement changed from a peace
and loving occupation,
to something that we want to rescue the students.
Are you talking about now or during the Umbrella
Movement?
The Umbrella Movement.
Yeah.
It was initiated like that.
Because of the students climbing into government
complex
and were arrested, it changed.
And then the occupied trio were in a bind
because they wanted to do it on October 1st,
outside the Mandarin hotel.
Actually they wanted to do it for two days.
And they had already briefed the police!
They say we'll have hundreds,
maybe a thousand people lying down in the
street,
and we'll be arrested,
and it should be over in one or two days.
But because of the students and all that,
many people rushed into [inaudible]
outside the legislative council complex,
and the government offices there.
And the trio were forced to say,
“Oh, don't wait for October 1st!
Forget about your plan, let's do it now!”.
The students just took the reigns.
Well, not the students.
And they felt quite difficult
because some people said, “Go ahead!”,
and then say, “Don't go ahead!
Don't you hijack our movement!”.
So there was already some argument then.
And in the end they decided to call it there,
instead of coming to the Mandarin hotel.
And then many people came.
It was very peaceful.
And it was amazing.
And many people who came,
foreign journalists,
where did they come from?
They come from Syria.
They come from Yemen.
Venezuela, Iraq,
where there is carnage and slaughter every
day.
But here, we have hundreds of thousands of
people
occupying the main thoroughfare,
but doing homework,
doing waste separation.
So peaceful!
That's why it's news.
Otherwise, if there's carnage,
you can not be more violent than Syria.
So it was very good.
But, of course, the government would not relent.
We were asking for democratic elections, and
Beijing said no.
So the government here, of course, said no.
And in the end, it dragged on for seventy-nine
days.
In fact the occupied trio pull out earlier,
because they said, “Well, that's it.
They're not going to clear us out.
And the people do not want us to continue.
Let's go home.”
But the young people did not want to go.
So, it dragged on for seventy-nine days
and finally they came to Admiralty to arrest
us one by one.
And, still, I have not yet been charged.
But they still can charge me
with taking part in illegal assembly.
Public nuisance.
Or whatever, yeah.
And if they charge me with that I'll say,
“Yes, guilty.”
That's about civil disobedience,
but they haven't charged me.
Just like back in 1996, they did not charge
me.
You do seem like public nuisance,
like a very dangerous figure.
Is that right?
That's right.
So maybe you should've, in your '96 protest,
stayed on the streets for seventy-nine days.
How long were you out there for?
Well, we were there for maybe one hour.
You gave up too soon.
Well, no!
Actually, what happened was the police people...
The road was closed, and they were calling
up Chris Pattern,
who was the last governor,
"Hey gov!
Emily Lau here is lying on the street."
Actually we were not blocking anything
because they were having the fast inside,
co-election.
And we were just lying there,
so they picked us up one by one,
and took us back to the Wan Chai police station.
Sitting in there, I got a call from the BBC.
So the police allowed me to go out
and I dial a collect call to the BBC.
I say, "Emily Lau calling you.",
"Oh, Emily!
Good.
We are about to go on air, hang on.
Let's put you on!
Top of the news.
Today in Hong Kong they elected the first
Chief Executive
of the future Hong Kong special administrative
region.
Outside the convention center,
there were demonstrations,
and the demonstrators were arrested.
One of them is legislator Emily Lau.
Emily, where are you?".
I said, "I'm in the Wan Chai police station.",
"Oh!
Have they beaten up?", I said, "Not yet!".
Was that a risk?
No risk.
No, that's the thing about Hong Kong,
even from then up to now,
Hong Kong is one of the safest and most peaceful
city in the world.
Definitely in China, but in the world.
So, they say, "We have to pass this extradition
bill,
if not, we will become a haven of fugitives."
I said, "We've been negotiating with China
for twenty years about an arrangement, and
we can't do it."
And no one called us a haven of fugitives.
Everybody said, "We are a booming city",
they should come and invest.
What's going on?
Well I think, because of that, what you mentioned,
when the police cracked down so hard on the
extradition protest
on Wednesday June 12th,
I think that really shocked a lot of people
in Hong Kong
and help contribute to the 2 million strong
protest,
the march that happened that Sunday.
Yes, exactly.
And the police, their behavior was really
terrible.
And the thing is, they did not wear their
badge and no number,
and also they were wearing all the gear
that you could not recognize them.
Some people were saying,
“Oh, they actually don't look like Hong
Kong policeman!
They might be China national security.”
Well, who knows?
But people are very, very suspicious,
and they are very, very angry.
So they just suspect all kinds of things.
And it was terrible, because in the past,
maybe during the Umbrella occupation,
relations between the police and especially
young people, was tense.
But, by and large it's OK the relations.
Now, having seen them beating people up like
that
and then going to hospitals to arrest patients,
and all these things make people very angry.
That's why we are demanding an independent
inquiry
and to make sure it is a fair and just investigation,
we hope that it would be chaired by a very
eminent judge.
But the government still refuse.
Why do you think the extradition bill protests
have been so intense?
Many people have said the administration,
particularly Carrie Lam,
have underestimated the Hong Kong's people's
fear of the communist party.
Because this thing goes through the heart,
and they fear that if the bills pass, one
day,
they themselves, or their friends or relatives,
could be sent to China.
And why is it so terrible to be sent to China?
Because over there, it's complete lawlessness.
Here, under the British tradition, we have
the rule of law.
We have an independent traditionary.
People are presumed innocent until they are
found guilty.
Defendants would not be tortured.
All these things are non-existent over there.
So the people are very fearful.
But Carrie Lam obviously did not sense that.
But why?
If you look at the time when she become Chief
Executive,
two years ago, she went through several difficult
things.
Very difficult.
Like disqualifying legislators,
disqualifying candidates for election, from
the pro-democracy camp.
And then the Beijing National People's Congress
standing committee,
issued an interpretation of the basic law
to justify those things.
And then she passed,
[inaudible] passed a bill on co-location,
that is co-locating the immigration and customs
authorities,
both of China and Hong Kong, just over there,
next to the Star Ferry,
which we think is in bridge of the joined
declaration.
But all these things went past,
and it seems not too many people bat an eyelid.
When I travel overseas, people say,
“Hey!
How come all these things happen.
Hong Kong people seem to just take it.”
And so, I guess in the words of a bible,
she thinks she could walk on water.
So this time round she said, “Jesus!
Nothing.
Look at all the things I have conquered!”
And she thought this would be the same.
But this time, she got it terribly wrong.
Well let me challenge you on how you said
China is lawless.
Their courts have a 99.9% conviction rate.
I mean, that's law right there.
That is law, but it's not the legal system
as we know it.
I mean, I speak with a bit of authority, although
I'm not a lawyer.
But I am sitting on the board of directors
of the China Human Rights Lawyers Concern
Group.
We set up the group here eleven years ago,
to offer support to the human rights lawyers
in mainland China,
who are very brave.
Some of them are in jail, being tortured,
and some have disappeared, but they still
carry on.
If they have a chance, sometimes they don't,
if they have a chance to come here to meet
with us,
they would tell us how terrible it is.
Some of them cannot practice.
It's been taken away, the license,
and they cannot argue for their client in
court.
And so, it's really terrible.
And they may say, I think the Chinese judicial
system
looks excellent on paper.
But in practice, it's something else.
And that's why even ordinary Chinese people
know,
because they have relatives and friends over
there, and they know.
And who are the people who are most fearful?
It's the business people.
And some have said it publicly.
They say, “If you do business in China,
you have to pay bribes.”
So, under this bill, they're all guilty,
and you don't know which day they will be
nominated
as targets for extradition.
So they are very fearful.
Well I can see why the people of Hong Kong
would be very concerned about this extradition
bill,
but do you think meaningful reform can happen
in Hong Kong,
as long as the Chinese communist party is
the ultimate power broker?
Since 1997, because we were handed over to
Chinese rule in 1997,
I think for the initial ten years things seemed
OK,
although we have no democracy, we still don't
have it,
but we have the rule of law.
We enjoy freedoms, civil liberties, and personal
safety.
These are things which are very close
to the Hong Kong's people's hearts, not democracy.
We don't even know what a democratic Hong
Kong is like.
But these freedoms, personal safety, are very
close to our hearts.
So, our institutions, they may not be perfect,
but they ensure that we enjoy these things
which are our core values.
And I am sure they are core values of people
in many countries.
And ironically, the level of freedoms and
personal safety,
and the rule of law we enjoy here,
is much higher than that of many democratic
countries.
If you look around Asia or elsewhere,
you can count till your face turns blue.
There are many countries which have periodic
elections,
but their people certainly do not enjoy
the level of personal safety and freedoms,
and the rule of law,
independence of the judiciary that we enjoy.
So, we cherish what we've got, we want to
reform it,
make it better.
And we know China can come down on us like
a ton of bricks,
but as I've told many people in the last two
weeks,
Hong Kong is not Tiananmen Square.
Just on June 4th this year,
we had a commemoration of the massacre thirty
years ago.
And we had about one hundred and fifty thousand
people
turning up to the candlelight vigil, at Victoria
Park,
which is the starting point for the big marches.
So, I think China can do it.
The People's Liberation army is just there.
Yep.
That used to be their British barracks.
So, the tanks, the machine guns, everything
are there.
But will they deploy them on us?
And if they did, it would be at a very high
price.
And not just for us,
you should also remember many Chinese rich
people
and their children have invested a lot here.
That's why some people say to me,
“Actually, this fight over the bill is a
fight
between former President Jiang Zemin
and current President Xi Jinping.”
Because, Jiang Zemin has a lot of business
interest.
His friends, and relatives.
And this bill, of course,
goes to the heart of those people.
And the Chinese government have also said
publicly,
that we need this bill because there are close
to
three hundred fugitives from the mainland
who have come here, who are hiding here,
and I can tell you most of them are staying
at the Four Seasons hotel over there.
They abducted one business man from there
a few months ago,
that guy did not file a report with the police.
So they have people here,
but if the two communist leaders are at loggerhead,
they are fighting it out,
it's very sad that we are just caught in the
middle.
But Hong Kong as it is,
we will always be like that.
But, I say, if they try to destroy us,
the price is very high.
Not just for us, but for them too.
And now we are caught in-between the war
between President Trump and President Xi.
And again, because America has a lot of interest
here,
they have many people living here, working
many companies are here.
So they have a stake.
And of course they should speak out.
Well I know we've certainly covered on our
show
the battle between Xi Jinping and Jiang Zemin,
so I hope people will check out those episodes.
What do you think others countries like the
US
can do about this situation at Hong Kong?
Because Hong Kong is very much dependent on
the US
because many of our business people,
they trade with the US,
they think the US is a very important market
for Hong Kong,
and it's no secret.
And of course, there is the United States–Hong
Kong Policy Act,
which was enacted before 1997 to give Hong
Kong special treatment,
especially the bid on us being an independent
custom's territory.
And some people say,
“Oh well, if Hong Kong loses one country,
two systems,
then maybe the bill should be amended!"
We take away that independent custom territory.
The leader of the liberal here Felix Chung
said,
“If that should happen,
the game is over.”
He said the game is over,
not just for the business community,
but for the whole of Hong Kong.
And we certainly don't want that sort of
catastrophic thing to happen to us.
But some Americans and others are suggesting
maybe we should have a law,
targeting those people who try to undermine
human rights and the rule of law in Hong Kong.
Particularly senior government officials
who perpetrate such acts so that they would
be banned
from entering the United States and their
assets.
The United States would be frozen.
And I say, that is tremendous!
I think that's great.
Sort of like the Magnitsky Act?
Yeah, maybe something like that.
So you only target the guilty individuals
and not harm all the other Hong Kong people,
because we are friends with the Americans.
They don't want to harm us.
But there are certain individuals who have
done such evil acts,
so they should be targeted.
What about the upcoming G20?
Well, we certainly hope that not just President
Trump,
but the other leaders attending the summit
would also use the occasion to voice their
concern,
and voice their support for Hong Kong.
I've noticed many have already spoken out.
A few days ago, over there in Western,
in the central government liaison office,
which is the representative of Beijing here.
And they summoned many of the probation politicians
there to give them a lecture and to tell them
to support Carrie Lam,
and say Beijing supports Carrie.
And afterwards one of them came out, Mr Tam,
and he told the media,
“They told us to support Carrie,
and they say the bill was OK.
Except then, there was foreign interference.
And they said in the last few days,
there were sixty-seven statements issued by
foreign governments.”
I said, “What?
Big deal!
If you don't care about them,
even if it's six hundred and seventy statements,
what the hell?
It's not sixty-seven bombs!”
Now the fact they counted it so closely, shows
they care.
And that's what the human rights lawyers told
us, when we met.
They said, “Don't believe it.
If someone tells you China
doesn't care about international public opinion.
It's not true.”
I said, “Really?”
They said, “Yes.
China does care.
Why?
Because China cares about face.”
So sixty-seven statements.
To me, that's not enough.
I want a lot more!
I hope they will be issued before the G-summit,
or during the summit in Osaka, and of course,
when they meet President Xi Jinping,
I hope they will raise it too.
Tell President Xi that Hong Kong people
don't want the extradition bill,
they don't want erosion of civil liberties
and the rule of law,
and we want to have democratic government.
We want to have the ability to elect our government.
We're not fighting for independence.
We're not fighting for self-determination,
we know we are part of the People's Republic
of China,
but China has made a promise of one country,
two systems.
China's now negating on it, and we are very,
very angry.
Well in 1994, I know you ask Margaret Thatcher
if it was morally defensible to hand a city
of over five million people,
to a communist dictatorship.
Do you think the UK has upheld its side of
the Sino-British Joint Declaration?
The UK is terrible, really.
The UK is always looking after its own interests,
like the question I ask Mrs Thatcher.
They want money, they want trade and all that.
And it's very sad when they pulled out of
Hong Kong,
Hong Kong had no democratic institutions.
They left nothing behind.
And when they pulled out,
there were over three million British citizens,
but citizens who have no right to live in
the UK.
They created a form of citizenship called
British National Overseas,
the BNO, which they cannot pass on to their
children,
but they can use it during their lifetime
as some form of travel document.
So whenever I meet British officials, I said,
“Do you know what BNO stands for?”
This Britain's says, “No?”
But, whether you like it or not,
there are still several million British citizens
here.
And many of them are very angry and very frightened.
So Britain has a responsibility towards these
people,
and the rest of us too.
Because you ran this colony for one and a
half centuries.
And now the people here are very, very fearful.
So what the least Britain can do is to speak
up.
I know Brexit is a big problem, but still,
not only them but Parliament,
the British people should look at Hong Kong
and say,
“Hey, can we not do something for Hong Kong
people?
Speak out, tell the Chinese to stop cracking
down on them.
Respect one country, two systems.”
And Britain should talk to its allies,
if it still has some.
I hope it does!
Tell the allies to speak out too,
because international public opinion does
matter.
I can see why some people call you Hong Kong's
Iron Lady.
So what's next for the future of Hong Kong?
No.
I think we will just keep on fighting.
Although I stepped down from the legislative
council
after serving for twenty-five years,
but I've said I will never step down from
the fight
for human rights, democracy, and the rule
of law.
And we will continue to have marches,
but we will do it in a peaceful and orderly
way,
and the next one is on the 1st of July,
I hope you'll be around to see it.
We will.
And I tell you, like a bad penny, we will
keep turning up.
Thank you so much for joining us today.
It's a pleasure.
Thank you.