On this episode of China Uncensored,
China’s propaganda targets the heart of
America:
Iowa.
Wait, Iowa??
Hi, welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
When I heard about the 4-page spread called
China Watch
run in Iowa’s biggest newspaper,
the Des Moines Register...
I thought, well look at that adorable little
kid
with that adorable robot!
Surely there’s nothing sinister about this!
China Watch is a paid supplement—
that is, an advertisement—
designed to look like news articles.
And they’ve got great content!
Like about the book that tells of Xi Jinping’s
fun days in Iowa in the 1980s.
And the part about “Women’s Liberation:
How...feminine face of China changed”...?
Who writes this stuff?
Oh, wait.
China Daily,
an official publication of the People’s
Republic of China.
And there’s also this helpful front page
article
“Duel Undermines Benefits of Trade.”
Yes, Trump’s trade war is bad for you,
the good people of Iowa.
That’s why we paid tons of money for this
benevolent public service announcement,
coincidentally right before US midterm elections.
I mean, imagine if the US governmentpaid
to put anti-Xi Jinping propaganda
in a provincial newspaper in China
right before China’s midterm elections?
For those of you who are new here,
China does not have national elections.
And the price for putting articles
critical of China’s leader in a local newspaper
would be...going to prison.
Anyway, placing propaganda in Iowa’s biggest
newspaper
is one small piece of the Chinese Communist
Party’s plan
to undermine farm-country support for the
Trump administration—
and its tough trade policies with respect
to China.
It also takes advantage of America’s
democratic process and free press.
Now granted, the Chinese regime wanted people
in Iowa to read it.
But they probably didn’t expect President
Trump would.
“China is actually placing propaganda ads
in the Des Moines Register and other papers,
made to look like news,” Trump tweeted.
Iowa is a crucial state in presidential elections.
It went big for Trump in 2016.
But now the trade war between the world’s
two largest economies is heating up,
and Iowa exports corn, soy, and pork to China.
The US just announced tariffs on
200 billion dollars worth of Chinese imports.
And that’s on top of the 50 billion dollars
in goods the US
already hit with earlier tariffs.
The tariffs are meant to be a response
to years of unfair trade practices by China,
that include allegations of state-sponsored
intellectual property theft.
Like Chinese spies stealing corn seeds from...Iowa.
Hmmm... no articles about that in China Watch.
The US ambassador to China is Terry Branstad,
who also happens to be Iowa’s former governor.
He criticized the China Watch advertorial
in a letter,
saying that China is “doubling down on [their]
bullying
by running propaganda ads in our own free
press.”
But not to worry, says Trump.
“We are beating them on Trade, opening markets,
and the farmers will make a fortune when this
is over!”
The trouble is, until the trade war is settled,
China’s $50 billion of retaliatory tariffs—
soon to increase to $110 billion—
could mean pain for Iowa’s exporters.
“The tariffs and counter-tariffs we are
enduring
in this trade war with China and the U.S.
is having a real impact on Iowa farmers."
According to an Iowa State University study,
Iowa farmers are projected to lose up to $2.2
billion dollars
from Chinese counter-tariffs.
"Is that a lot?
Yeah, that is a big number.”
That’s John Crespi, an economics professor
at Iowa State
and and co-author of the study.
He said the trade war could cost Iowa’s
soybean industry
up to $891 million,
and Iowa’s corn industry could lose as much
as $579 million.
Because the Chinese regime isn’t just targeting
the good people of Iowa with badly written
newspaper advertorials.
They also created tariffs on corn, soy, pork,
and other agricultural products that hurt
midwestern farmers—
conveniently also the people who tend to
vote for Trump and the Republicans.
Former US National Security Council spokesperson
Tommy Vietor
called it a “Pretty savvy political play
being run by China.”
That article “Duel undermines benefits of
trade”
warns that Chinese importers may have to to
turn to South America
as their go-to soybean source.
So basically, the Chinese regime imposes tariffs
that hurt farmers in pro-Trump states.
Then they say it’s Trump’s fault.
And then maybe those farmers will think twice
about
voting for Trump in the next election.
It’s like you put a banana peel on the ground,
so someone slips on it.
And then you tell them,
“Hey, it’s Chiquita’s fault
for making products with slippery peels.”
That’s why, you, the good people of Iowa,
should remember that “as long as Trump is
president...
it will cost both countries in terms of innovation
and economic performance.”
Yes, for you Iowa farmers,
this trade war will definitely not be fun.
You know what would be fun, though?
Another visit to Iowa by Chinese leading Xi
Jinping,
whose last visit to Iowa was very fun!
Joking aside, Iowa is actually kind of famous
in China,
because of Xi’s visits there.
Arguably more famous than Iowa is in the US,
where people often confuse it with Idaho.
And it didn’t just start with Xi.
Iowa has been establishing ties with China
since the 1970s.
Last year, the Des Moines Register
did a series of stories on Iowa’s ties to
China.
Including one on the “Iowa mafia,”
a close group of Iowans doing business in
Beijing.
You don’t want to double cross them.
They’ll break your kneecaps with corn cobs.
10 percent of students at the University of
Iowa are from China,
and they contribute about 170 million dollars
to the local economy.
China’s even building a “friendship farm”
outside Beijing
that will include a “Disney-style version
of a small town in Iowa.”
A Disney-style small town in Iowa?
I hope they have singing pigs.
Speaking of small towns in Iowa,
Muscatine is the town where Xi Jinping visited
in 1985,
and which has seen a lot of Chinese investment
in the last few years.
Last month, Chinese officials visited Muscatine
and commiserated about the trade war.
Iowa is a place with a decades-long relationship
with China.
It’s gotten a lot of positive attention
from Chinese officials,
and it has an economy that’s increasingly
tied
to doing business with China.
Sounds like the perfect place for the Chinese
Communist Party
to start changing how Americans feel about
the US-China trade war.
But it might not be as easy as Chinese officials
are hoping.
When the Washington Post talked to farmers
in Muscatine,
they found farmers were concerned about
things like intellectual property theft,
and supported the US taking a stronger stand.
And take the China Watch advertorial.
Even the Des Moines Register,
which ran the China Watch advertorial,
pulled no punches in exposing
the true intent of their big advertiser.
It quotes an expert saying that readers
“may not appreciate trying to be manipulated
by a foreign government.”
But China’s information war against the
US
goes way beyond running ads in corn-country
newspapers.
For years, they’ve run China Watch sections
in major national papers like the New York
Times
and the Wall Street Journal to influence public
opinion.
I mean really, it’s the original “fake
news.”
And a US official told Reuters that China
is guilty
of perpetrating a “broad malign influence
campaign”
in the United States.
“‘They employ a whole of government approach
using political, economic, commercial, military
and informational tools’
to influence U.S. public opinion.”
Now there does seem to be a bright side in
all this for Iowa farmers.
To offset the impact of China’s tariffs
the Trump administration announced in July
that U.S. farmers will be helped with a $12
billion bailout.
And Iowa growers could see about $550 million
in the first round of federal aid.
And at least some of that money’s going
to come from—
that’s right—
tariffs on Chinese goods.
So what do you think of China’s propaganda
advertorial?
Will it affect US elections?
Leave your comments below.
And before we go, it’s time when I answer
a question
from a viewer who supports China Uncensored
on the crowdfunding website Patreon.
Rabbit L. Benkei asks:
“Hey Chris, some big drivers of the tariffs
are the demands
that China stop stealing American intellectual
property
and stop requiring joint ventures with Chinese
firms,
but did American entrepreneurs ever even lobby
or ask the US government to do something about
it?”
Good question, Rabbit.
American business have actually complained
about
China stealing intellectual property for years.
This article from 2005 talks about how China
was creating cheap knock-offs of Viagra,
which is a blood pressure medication.
They wanted the Bush administration to act.
But ultimately, their response proved to be
a bit impotent.
Meanwhile, Chinese theft of US intellectual
property escalated.
Some US companies continued to complain.
Others kept quiet because they wanted the
opportunity
to do more business in China.
But it seemed neither the Bush nor Obama administrations
were able to do much to change the situation.
By 2015, it had gotten so bad that President
Obama and Xi Jinping
made a very public agreement to stop stealing
commercial secrets.
And this sort of worked, but not as well as
people hoped.
Because when US companies get hacked,
the Chinese government would issue public
statements
like “It totally wasn’t us.
It was rogue hackers.
And how do you even know they were from China,
huh?”
Now President Trump has a different philosophy,
which is:
Put direct economic pressure on China until
the Chinese leadership
feels enough pain to rein in the problem themselves.
So far, there has been pain on both sides
from the trade war.
But it’s not clear yet what the ultimate
outcome will be.
Thanks for your question, Rabbit.
And thank all of you for watching.
Be like Rabbit, and support China Uncensored
with a dollar or more per episode
on the crowdfunding website Patreon.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Want your question answered?
Of course you do!
Click this orange button
and sign up to support China Uncensored
by pledging a dollar or more per episode
on Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
There’s a lot of cool perks,
and one of them is having me potentially
answer your questions at the end of my episodes.
Click here to support the show.