On this episode of China Uncensored,
the only thing blacker than heavy metal?
Politics.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
This is Freddy Lim,
the Godfather of Taiwanese death metal.
It’s a look that just screams “politician”.
Ok, maybe just screams.
But he’s also a politician.
Seriously.
Here he is campaigning for office.
Here he is getting food
from a local street vendor,
because you have do do that in Taiwan, too.
And here he is looking like
a serious politician
because serious people
wear suits.
But unlike most politicians in suits,
Freddy Lim is inspiring young people
to get passionate about politics.
He expanded from death metal
to politics after the 2014 Sunflower Movement.
Students and civil groups were protesting
a trade pact they felt would make
Taiwan economically dependent
on the Chinese Communist Party.
So Freddy Lim co-founded
the New Power Party,
and ran for office himself.
He was elected to parliament in 2016.
His party is now Taiwan’s
most important third party contender.
I sat down with Freddy Lim
to talk about how Taiwan
needs to resist threats from
the Chinese Communist Party,
and promote a future as the only Chinese democracy.
Thank you for joining me today.
My pleasure.
So, you've said you got into
heavy metal music because you wanted
to shout, you needed to roar.
Do you think it's time for Taiwan
to shout and roar?
Yeah, but not just Taiwan,
not only Taiwan because there are
many countries who are
under oppression in the world.
There are many countries
that are suffering
under worse conditions.
So I think it's never too late
to let the voices be heard.
And I know in your music,
you're very inspired by the stories
and culture of Taiwan.
Do you see Taiwanese culture as something
distinct from Chinese culture?
Definitely.
Yeah,
Taiwan is a country with fruitful cultures,
and we have cultures from different regions,
like we have our local aboriginal cultures…
We have some cultures originally from
outside Taiwan,
even those cultures from outside
are quite localized now.
So yeah definitely.
And so you're a heavy metal music performer,
which is one of the blackest things there
is.
But, you decided to get into
the blackest field of all,
politics.
What inspired you to found
and co-found the New Power Party
and enter political life?
I think I have always been quite involved
in politics and social issues,
social movements.
But in 2013,
there were more and more
young activists and young opinion leaders
who joined the social movements.
They led the social movements.
So I felt it's quite important
for Taiwan if we want to
make bigger change,
we need all those young forces
being introduced from the movements
to the political arena.
So, I and some other activists,
we worked together,
tried to build up a new platform for them.
So I think, yeah
this is a new party for the young people.
How do young people in Taiwan
feel about the political life
of the country,
and the relationship with China?
I think most of the young Taiwanese
are just like the young people in other countries.
They are a bit frustrated with politics,
so most of the time they
aren't concerned with politics.
But if there's an opportunity for them
to make a bigger change,
they could be very enthusiastic too.
So, I think quite similar to the young
in other countries.
And regarding China,
I think most of the Taiwanese people,
most of the young Taiwanese,
they try to stay calm towards China,
they try to treat China just like
other countries in the world.
But at the same time,
they try to stay cautious
... especially when it comes to
issues regarding freedom
and human rights
and especially at international events.
Yeah, the young Taiwanese
could also be very ...
To stay high cautious against China too.
Well the Chinese Communist Party
has threatened to seize
Taiwan by force.
How does that affect what you do?
I think China's military threat
has always led all the neighboring countries
to stay very cautious
and also try to move forward
in their direction
very carefully.
So yeah of course it affects us,
but not just Taiwan I think,
all the neighboring countries
can feel the same threat from China.
Well because of the growing influence
of the Chinese Communist Party,
Taiwan has been losing allies around the world.
Where does that leave Taiwan?
I think Taiwan's diplomatic strategy
has been reformed,
has been changed a lot in the recent years.
We used to care, I think,
too much about the number of
official diplomatic relations,
and tried to buy relations from those countries.
But in recent years,
I think, it’s become not just about
the number of them,
but also about trying to work with those
non-diplomatic relationship countries,
and I think that's more important
in Taiwan in the current situation.
Especially when in the recent years,
there have been more and
more non-diplomatic relationship countries
supporting us in international meetings
and international organizations,
they spoke for us, they supported us
in joining those organizations.
So I think this is the right direction,
and we should work hard for this direction.
Now, Taiwan may have found
an unlikely ally in the Trump administration.
How would you like to see
the US and Taiwan work together?
I think, no matter who is in power in the
US,
I believe that it's in the interest of both
sides
to strengthen Taiwan/US relations.
And so, if we want to strengthen these relationships,
I do believe that eventually
we should establish
official diplomatic relations
between Taiwan and the US.
I think that can consolidate our relationship
more.
So ultimately, are you optimistic
about the future of Taiwan?
Yes, I'm quite optimistic,
and of course I think
we have to be optimistic.
Because like what I had said,
that although we have been oppressed
by China in the international arena,
but there are so many more nations
in the world under worse oppression.
And in Taiwan, at least
We’ve kept our independent sovereignty,
and also we maintain our economic strength.
So we should stay optimistic,
and then I think,
and we are like a hope for those nations
that are under worse conditions.
And also, on the other hand I think
the current international situation
is undergoing a big change now,
and the world can treat Taiwan fairly.
And they used to compare Taiwan to China,
and it makes Taiwan too small.
But actually Taiwan is a country
like what I just said, that
we have a rich landscape,
we have a rich culture,
and also we have a population of 23 million,
that's quite equal to the population of
now five northern European countries.
So we are small,
but not that small,
no country would consider
Scandinavian countries as nothing.
Yeah.
So, at the same time
I think we are a mid-sized country,
we deserve fair treatment,
and we are always an option
for those businessmen or tourists
or the people want to do culture exchange,
we are an option that can be fairly treated,
and I do believe that it's time,
there is a optimistic future ahead.
Well, I was going to ask,
what do you think Taiwan's role
or responsibility is as one of
Asia's few democracies?
Just like what I have said.
That we have to stay optimistic,
and we have to be an inspiration
for those people in Asia who are still
under worse conditions,
no matter whether in human rights
or other conditions ...
I know that there have been so many people
from Hong Kong, from China,
or from other Southeast Asian countries
who come to Taiwan to observe
our elections or to join some protests,
to join in some activities,
and I know that they try to learn
a lot from the experiences in Taiwan.
And so, I think we should stay optimistic,
a
nd we should keep moving forward,
and we should let the world know
that even in the frontline against China,
there is a small country still trying
to move forward, to our goal,
in our direction,
carefully but eventually we will be
in a position to never go back.
So I hope that we can cheer more people on
under worse conditions,
So they can believe in themselves,
and we will try our best to support you as
well.
So I have two very important questions for
you.
Number one,
can I get tickets to your next concert?
Sure!
All right.
It's a free entrance concert
that we will play at this Sunday.
Perfect.
So yeah, come at five o'clock this Sunday.
All right.
And then the other big question is,
can you teach me to roar like you?
Okay,
I'll try.
Yeah.
[Freddy Lim roars]
[Chris roars]
Yeah, now you are a metal singer..
All right.
Yes.
I'm glad I have a fallback career.
Okay, yeah.
All right.
Well thank you so much for joining us today.
Thank you.
My pleasure.
Good luck.
Thank you.