On this episode of China Uncensored,
It’s a baby!
Or possibly a super baby.
Or, really, no one knows.
Hi,
welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
In our top story,
a Chinese scientist may have created
the world’s first genetically engineered
babies.
“A Chinese researcher claims to have helped
make
the world's first gene edited babies.
Twin girls whose DNA he says he altered
with a powerful new tool that lets scientists
edit the genetic code.
I feel a strong responsibility that it's not
just to make a first,
but also make it an example.”
Well, China is great at using people to make
an example.
He Jiankui says he edited the DNA of the twin
girls
to make them immune to HIV.
“He says he edited embryos for 7 couples
in IBF fertility treatment.
So far there's been one pregnancy.
The gene editing was done using a tool called
CRISPR-Cas9.
It works by making a cut in the DNA to disable
a specific gene.”
Now his claim has not been independently verified,
so we don’t know for a fact Dr. He did what
he says he did.
But even so, it’s created a huge controversy.
Gene editing is banned in many countries.
Guess what?
Not in China.
The reasons most countries ban it are:
One,
this is a totally new frontier
so no one knows if other genes might be accidentally
affected.
And two,
if the girls survive to adulthood and have
kids,
it will have changed the human genepool,
affecting future generations.
But Chinese authorities have always been
a little less strict about the rules.
At least about safety rules.
Political rules are very strict.
But the Chinese Communist Party has managed
to draw scientists from around the world
with promises of big state-backed dollars,
and none of those pesky ethical restrictions.
Which is how you have scientists in China
experimenting with things like...
head transplants!
It’s a no brainer, really.
But in this case of editing the genes of human
embryos,
the international backlash has been intense.
“More than 100 scientists said in an open
letter
the use of CRISPR-Cas9 technology
to edit the genes of human embryos was
risky, unjustified and harmed the reputation
and development
of the biomedical community in China.”
The backlash has been so intense,
that even official Chinese state agencies
are getting involved.
“China’s National Health Commission late
on Monday
ordered officials to ‘seriously investigate
and verify’ He’s claims.
Shenzhen’s Health and Family Planning commission
said it was investigating the ethics committee
and review process of He’s work.”
Also, we don’t even know for sure if the
girls are immune to HIV.
This is what happens when science is conducted
in a black box.
No one knows what's real.
Even the school where He worked
Southern University of Science and Technology
is trying to create some distance from him.
“This research work was carried out by Professor
He Jiankui
outside of the school,” the school said,
calling it a “serious violation of academic
ethics and norms”.
But when has unconstrained scientific experimentation
ever led to anything bad happening?
Though what the Chinese Communist Party giveth,
it can also taketh away.
So what do you think about the possibility
that
China is genetically engineering human babies?
Leave your comments below.
And before you go, now is the time when
I answer a question from a fan
who supports China Uncensored with a dollar
or more per episode
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
Joseph Bergeron asks,
“Why doesn't the P.R.C. put pressure on
Mongolia to reunify with China,
as historically both Taiwan and Mongolia (and
other lands)
were a part of the Qing Dynasty's unified
territory?
Is it because they aren't culturally Chinese,
because they want a buffer state with Russia,
or some other reason?”
Interesting question.
It has to do with the Soviet Union.
Near the tail end of World War II in 1945,
at what was called the Yalta Conference,
the US wanted the Soviet Union to join the
war against the Japanese.
One of the conditions was
that the area we now know as Outer Mongolia
would be independent.
Well, not so much independent as a Soviet
satellite state.
Now remember, at the time,
China was ruled by the Republic of China government,
which was also a US ally.
And since they were too weak at the time to
challenge the Soviets,
they agreed to it if the Soviet Union agreed
not to support
the Communists inside China.
A few years later, the Communists took over
China anyway,
and formed the People’s Republic of China.
They weren’t able to challenge the Soviets
either.
“As late as 1989 then-Chinese leader Deng
Xiaoping
was still complaining to the Americans that
Stalin had
‘severed’ Mongolia from China.”
And when the Soviet Union fell,
Outer Mongolia truly became independent.
But maybe someday,
the Chinese Communist Party will try to give
Mongolia
a taste of some of that win-win cooperation.
Thanks for your question, Joseph.
And remember,
if you want to have your question answered
on the show,
sign up to support China Uncensored on Patreon.
Go to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored to learn
more.
We’ll give you some cool perks as well.
Once again, I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.