China has a knife violence problem
And the Chinese Communist Party doesn’t
like to talk about it
Welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
As we’ve all been told, everything is harmonious
in China.
But that might not quite be the case.
And the content we’re going to talk about
in this video may be disturbing.
Which means, I can bet you YouTube will demonetize,
and maybe age restrict this video.
That means YouTube is going to prevent people
from seeing this, even though this is a really
important story and we’re choosing not to
show any gratuitous violence.
You can help us fight back against the censorship
by sharing this video, and if you can, contributing
a dollar or more on the crowd funding website
Patreon.That lets us stand up to YouTube’s
demonetization, and we’ll give you some
cool perks as a way of saying thank you.
Visit Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored to learn
more.
So, here we are in Guangxi province in southern
China—
where in April, Xi Jinping did an inspection
tour.
Yep, the mountains look good.
Yep, your tiny kitchen looks good.
Yep, the giant red star looks imposing.
But the day after Xi Jinping’s visit, there
was a brutal knife stabbing in the same region
that killed 2 people and injured 16.
Including children.
“The suspect’s wife worked as a teacher
in the kindergarten.
The two couples divorced because of a quarrel.
The man then climbed the fence and broke into
the kindergarten and knifed people.
‘Even his own son was hacked to death.’”
Now there’s no evidence suggesting that
this knifing was related to Xi Jinping’s
inspection tour the day before.
But for the Chinese Communist Party, the timing
was very inconvenient.
Social media platforms like Weibo quickly
blocked users from discussing the incident.
But perhaps this knifing was just an isolated
event.
At least that’s how state-run media report
on it every time it happens: as if it’s
a very rare event with absolutely no larger
context.
But unfortunately, knife attacks happen a
lot in China.
Back in 2010, the Chinese government publicly
promised to prevent these incidents—even
though they, um, almost never happen.
They’ve given the death penalty to a number
of the perpetrators, and they’ve also tightened
public surveillance measures.
But that clearly hasn’t solved the problem.
In 2018 in Chongqing, a 39-year-old woman
assaulted a group of kindergarteners with
a kitchen knife.
In 2020, in Guanxi, a 50-year-old security
guard attacked 39 students and teachers at
a kindergarten.
According to Ding Xueliang, a sociology professor
in Hong Kong: ‘The Chinese society has generated
enormous pressure on individuals and some
of those individuals have perhaps had emotional
and psychological problems.
They want to cause general attention from
the population and attacking kids perhaps
is the best way from their perspective of
achieving this objective.’
Chinese society appears harmonious if you
look at state run media reports.
But there’s a huge amount of pent up anger.
And people aren’t even allowed to talk about
it!
There’s no outlet.A video that circulated
online this May shows a man in Nanjing running
over his ex-wife with a car in public.
The man later ran out of his car swinging
a knife, and injured 7 nearby pedestrians.
In May this year, a woman brought a fruit
knife into the Shanghai Business Center and
attacked 5 people.
Earlier in June, a man in Anhui in Eastern
China attacked people in the street with a
knife.
These acts of violence seem to be getting
worse.
And they’re not just knife attacks.
In May, a man drove a car through a red light
on purpose—plowing right through dozens
of pedestrians in a crosswalk.
“The suspect, a hairdresser surnamed Liu,
had decided to take revenge against society
after losing money in a failed investment
scheme.”
“The police said Liu had not been drinking
or on drugs... nor did he have a history of
mental illness: He was clear-minded when he
committed his crime.”
These “revenge against society” attacks
are some of the darkest social issues facing
China.
So much for everything being harmonious.
If you haven’t heard about it, it may be
that Chinese state-run media are too busy
to cover it.
Instead they spend their energy on more productive
things, like criticizing America’s gun violence.
You see, according to state-run media, China
can offer lessons to the US in protecting
human rights.
“The US should learn from China and genuinely
protect human rights.
If the US does not control its guns, problems
caused by firearms in the foreseeable future
will continue plaguing US society.”
Now, they’re right—the US does have a
problem with mass shootings.
But in China, no one is allowed to have guns.
And there are still essentially the same problems.
But with knives.
And cars.
And yet, according to Chinese state media,
rampant gun violence makes the U.S. a proven
hypocrite on human rights.
Gun ownership and deaths are out of control
in the US.
And how can the US police the world when it
can’t even protect its own people?
Surely if the US adopts China’s model of
authoritarian harmony, that will solve everything.
As long as you censor what gets reported.
And now to do what Chinese state-run media
would never do: Answer a question from a supporter!
Oh, especially a Freedom Fighter: “I think
the best way to handle the CCP is to boycott
all Chinese goods.
Can you think of any other way to hurt the
CCP?”
You make a good point, Freedom Fighter.
The way to hurt the CCP is to go after the
money.
But it should be about more than just boycotting
goods.
That’s a great way you, as an individual,
can help.
But what can have a larger impact is if Western
governments—I’m looking at you, America
—stop their companies from investing in
China.
The CCP is running out of cash.
Especially American dollars.
It needs dollars to sustain its own currency.
So one thing China’s doing is opening domestic
bond markets.
They’re trying to get foreigners to invest
their American dollars into China, with the
promise of big returns.
They want you to think: Wow, they’re giving
me an opportunity to make money!
They’re not giving you an opportunity to
make money.
They’re giving themselves an opportunity
to make money.
But American investment companies are pitching
it.
And American investors are snapping it up.
You’re giving the CCP the money it needs
to sustain its authoritarian regime!
And also, it’s a trap!!!
You’re not going to get your money back,
stupid.
Don’t do it!
The US government has already restricted investments
in certain Chinese companies with military
ties.
But Wall Street needs to know that investing
in China is bad for their bottom line.
If the world stopped pumping money into China,
that would hurt the CCP.
Badly.
In fact, it would eventually bring down the
CCP.
But it’s a long road ahead.
Thanks for your question, Freedom Fighter.
Be like Freedom Fighter and join our China
Uncensored 50-Cent Army—fans who support
us through the crowdfunding website Patreon.
It especially helps when YouTube is constantly
demonetizing or restricting our videos.
Visit Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored to learn
more.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.