On this episode of China Uncensored,
China’s great and glorious Photoshop fails.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
China has been photoshopping since before
it was cool.
Before there was even photoshop actually.
For example, why let a perfectly good historical
photo of Mao be ruined
just because this one guy later got purged
from the Party?
Delete!
This happened a lot, actually.
Back then they used airbrushing to, uh...
edit the historical record.
Unfortunately, advances in technology
don’t necessarily make people better at
what they do.
So here are 5 shocking examples of Chinese
photoshop fails.
Number 5 Floating Officials
You know, Chinese officials are busy.
They don’t have time to, you know,
visit places and do their jobs.
That’s where Photoshop comes in.
Here are some such hard-working officials
inspecting a new highway in Sichuan.
Yeah, no one was fooled by that.
Netizens mocked the bad photoshop job
by showing that they have better skills than
the government.
The Guardian called it
“one of the worst-doctored photographs in
internet history.”
But I’m guessing no one at the Guardian
saw these next four.
Number 4 Doctoring the elderly
The story is, these officials were supposed
to be visiting
the oldest woman in Ningguo city.
Then the local government actually tried to
pass off this photo as real.
But like this official’s legs,
the government’s attempts to doctor the
photo are pretty transparent.
Why is this old woman so tiny?
How does anyone decide that this looks ok
to publish?
Eventually officials admitted the image was
doctored.
Shocking!
That they admitted it, that is.
In an official statement,
they said the image was fake,
but they did really visit the old woman.
And other photos emerged showing that,
at least at some point,
they did.
So why the fake?
Well according to the statement,
the photographer wasn’t able to take a picture
that could
fit all the officials and the elderly woman.
I mean you know how hard it is
to take a photo of five people at the same
time?
So they had to fake it.
But that doesn’t explain why they had to
fake it so poorly…
Number 3 Copy and Paste Africans
A state-owned enterprise in Shandong province
wanted to commemorate the beginning of their
Angola Infrastructure Transformation Project.
But rather than hold some kind of actual ceremony
and take a picture of it,
they instead opted for the,
“Photoshop random Africans in front of their
company banner.”
Number 2 Parks and Re-creation
So you may have noticed that a major part
of being a local government official,
is going out an inspecting things!
And these guys may just be the perfect local government employees,
at least according to Ron Swanson,
He shows zero initiative.
He's not a team player.
He's never wanted to go that extra mile.
Tom is exactly what I'm looking for in a government
employee."
And this photoshop job is just as incompetent
as the government ought to be,
according to Ron.
I guess no one in the government noticed
that this guy’s whole body is as big as this
guy’s torso.
Which is also as big as a tree.
It’s about as good as my annual inspection
of
Hollywood,
New York,
Birthday Town,
and Space.
And finally number 1
Well hey, that’s not too bad actually.
It more or less looks like these officials
are actually there!
Oh.
These six officials in Shanxi are overseeing
the destruction of fake alcohol.
And it’s true!
That is definitely fake alcohol.
So what do you think of the Chinese government’s
Photoshop fails?
Do you think you could do better?
Prove it!
Download the photo in the Description below
and show me your Photoshop skills.
I’ll post the best ones on my Facebook page.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell. See you
next time!