On this episode of China Uncensored,
Chinese New Year is a time of feasting.
And purging.
At least for Chinese leader Xi Jinping.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Well, it’s that time of year again:
Chinese New Year!
The largest annual mass migration,
where millions of Chinese people
travel back home to the countryside
for the holidays.
And to celebrate the New Year,
a city in Northern China has made this statue
of US President Donald Trump.
Trust me, it’s a compliment.
No seriously.
2018 is the Year of the Dog.
Last year, another mall did one
for the Year of the Rooster.
Are they going to do this every year?
Because it gets a lot less flattering.
2019 is the Year of the Pig.
And 2020 is the Year of the Rat.
I guess it depends how the bromance is going
by then.
Speaking of Chinese leader Xi Jinping,
Xi has his own way of celebrating the New
Year—
besides of course watching the very entertaining
state-run CCTV spring gala.
CCTV gala
or bad acid trip?
We report, you decide.
Now I know what you’re thinking.
Could Xi Jinping possibly have a better way
of celebrating the new year
than watching a girl in a dog costume jump
rope
with an actual dog?
Yes.
Xi Jinping is starting the new year off right,
by purging his political enemies.
First up, this shameless,
two-faced king of the internet has finally
gotten
what he deserves.
No, not Mark Zuckerberg,
this other guy, Lu Wei.
Zuckerberg still hasn’t gotten what he deserves.
Which of course is the entry of Facebook
into the Chinese market
followed immediately by the
wholesale destruction of Facebook.
Lu Wei was once the powerful head
of China’s Cyberspace Administration.
Basically he was the king of China’s Internet.
But his kingdom was not a very free kingdom.
Lu Wei is the guy responsible
for China’s heavy handed internet censorship.
He’s also the guy who drafted cyber security
laws
that put foreign companies’ intellectual
property at risk
by forcing them to store their data inside
of China.
But, he won’t be getting on a train back
home
with millions of ordinary Chinese citizens
this year.
Unless it’s a one-way train to prison.
We reported back in November that Lu Wei
had been put under investigation,
which meant, sooner or later
he’d get purged.
Well, “sooner or later” is now.
The Internet King—or czar—
has been expelled from the Communist Party,
and charged with bribery
and sexual misconduct.
I know I know, you don’t usually hear “Internet,”
and “sexual misconduct,” in the same sentence.
But if you’re a powerful official in China,
you’ve probably done something illegal
at least two or three...hundred times.
So it’s easy for Xi Jinping’s crew to
find
something to charge you with.
But in a lot of cases,
the people being purged are not necessarily
more corrupt than everyone else;
they’re just one of Xi Jinping’s political
enemies.
They’re often part of the faction
of former Chinese leader Jiang Zemin.
Sorry, wrong Internet toad.
There we go.
But what makes Internet King Lu Wei’s story
a little unusual is not just how
high ranking he was before the purge,
but the vitriol being used against him now.
China’s anti-corruption watchdog—
in an official statement—
called Lu Wei “shameless,”
“tyrannical,” and “two-faced.”
Nooooo, the guy who said there’s
no internet censorship in China, “two-faced”?!
And as for shameless,
well, he is the guy who hired a famous songwriter
to write that jazzy, Soviet style anthem,
“Cyberspace Spirit.”
“Powerful Internet country!
The Web is where glorious dreams are!”
Throw the book at him.
But Internet King Lu Wei isn’t the only
one
to take a fall this Chinese New Year.
Former CCP “Rising Star” Sun Zhengcai
has also been indicted.
Okay, unless you have a scorecard next to
you
with all the names of your favorite purged
officials,
you probably don’t know who Sun Zhengcai
is.
Well, according to a well-connected Beijing
Source,
“Sun Zhengcai was basically Jiang Zemin’s
designated, cross-generational successor...
Sun Zhengcai’s fall cuts the Jiang faction
off
from their escape route.”
I believe we have footage of that.
So what do you think of the holiday purging?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Wait, before you go,
I have something important to tell you.
You know, not many companies are brave enough
to advertise on China Uncensored.
But there is one I want you to know about.
They sell amazing food:
Thrive Life.
And unlike a lot of other meal delivery food,
they’ve got GMO Free,
Gluten Free,
and organic options.
And unlike Blue Apron,
Thrive Life meal packs won’t go rotten
in you fridge after a couple days.
Thrive food is freeze dried,
so it lasts several months,
even years.
I know what you’re thinking.
Freeze dried food?
Are you sure about this?
I was skeptical too...
until they sent me a box of samples.
And I can honestly tell you,
it’s delicious.
They sent me this whole box.
There’s a ton of amazing food in here.
Everything from snacks to meals.
My personal favorite,
South Pacific-Style Stir Fry with Pulled Pork.
Now I know,
it comes in a box,
but this is what it looks like cooked
and it only took me a few minutes to make.
And they sell hundreds of other foods.
Uncensoring China takes a lot of energy.
And I don’t always have time to plan meals.
I can’t tell you how many times food in
my fridge
has gone bad because I couldn’t cook for
a few days.
Thrive Life basically solved this for me.
It’s super convenient,
tastes great,
and I don’t have to worry about it going
bad.
It’s also more affordable the Blue Apron.
I’ve provided a link below to order.
Just try one or two meals.
You’re gonna love it.
And China Uncensored gets a commission
on any purchase you make.
So this is a great way to help the show,
and get some tasty food out of it.
Plus, if Kim Jong-un ever does launch a nuke,
you’ll have all the food you need
in the post-apocalyptic future.
So help out the show,
and buy yourselves some treats from Thrive
Life.
Click the link below.