On this episode of China Uncensored,
forget the stock market bubble,
this is China’s incredible bike-share bubble.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
The good old bicycle.
That trusty two-wheeled iron steed.
So whether you’re out for some fresh air
and exercise
taking your kid to school
or grabbing some fast food at “WickDonald’s”,
bikes and China, like marriage,
go together like a horse and carriage.
Unfortunately, thanks to a bubble in dock-free
bike-sharing,
that relationship has turned toxic.
So on today’s episode of China Uncensored,
let’s look at how China’s bike-sharing
program
has become a complete disaster.
One giant difference between China’s bike-sharing
and what you’re used to in the US is docking.
For bike-sharing in, say, San Francisco…
or New York—
you have to pick them up from a dock,
and return them to a dock.
And you can unlock a bike with a physical
key,
or a mobile app.
The benefits are that it’s easy for the
city governments
to keep them tidy in designated places.
It’s easy for the bike-share companies to
track them,
and use vans to move bikes around to where
they’re needed most.
But there’s a “last mile problem”.
That is, there are only so many docks,
and if there’s no dock within about a mile
of where a person wants to start or end their
trip,
they’re simply not going to use the bike-share.
Sorry, everyone who lives in the Bronx!
But in China, cities have a cure for this
last mile problem:
dockless bikes!
Thanks to GPS chips in every bike,
you can just unlock one using your mobile
app.
And when you’re done, leave it wherever
you want!
And I mean: Wherever you want!
Sometimes the cure can be worse than the disease.
This is a photo of the entrance
to a park in the city of Shenzhen.
Where, as you can see, people ride shared
bikes
right up to the entrance, and then just throw
them
on top of the ginormous pile of other bikes
before going inside to enjoy the scenery.
China’s dockless bike-sharing industry
grew like mad in recent years,
thanks to the brilliant combination of cutthroat
competition
and no government regulation.
There’s now about 500 or so competing dockless
bike-sharing companies in China,
each desperate to win market share
by filling cities with their bikes…
…with the idea being that if their bike
is on top of the pile,
people will choose their brand over their
competitors’.
With no limits to the number of companies
that could operate in a given region,
or to the number of bikes,
this led to unsightly clutter…
and crippling choice anxiety.
I think she realized she’s better off
just walking that last mile.
Two of the biggest bike-sharing startups in
China are Ofo
and Mobike…
Between them they’ve got more than 120 million
registered users
and more than 13 million bikes piling up in
Chinese cities.
And what made it all possible
is billions of dollars in venture capital.
Ofo, with its trademark canary yellow bikes…
…has raised at least 1.3 billion dollars
in investment
across five rounds of funding.
And Mobike,
recently got 600 million in its latest funding
round,
bringing its market cap to about $1 billion
dollars.
And these companies with 10-figure market
valuations
are locked in a cash-burning race to dominate
market share
by pumping out bikes as fast as possible,
keeping the prices as low as possible,
and stacking them in the streets as high as
possible.
To deal with this, some cities have starting
sending
crews out to impound shared bikes.
Which make sense.
This cyclist has to ride in the street with
cars,
because the bike lane has turned into a bike
pile.
Here’s a series of photos
from a Shanghai bicycle impound lot,
which thousands…
upon thousands
of bikes now call home.
Fortunately, there’s still space in Shanghai
to plant huge fields of colorful flowers…
Haha, no it’s more bikes.
And more bikes.
And...more...bikes!
But at least there’s been some pushback
lately.
For example, after Shanghai realized
it had 1.5 million shared bikes—
that’s one for every 16 residents—
it started to say enough is enough.
On August 18, the Shanghai Transportation
Bureau
ordered bikeshare companies to stop
adding more bikes to the streets.
There’s also a proposal in China to punish
people
who park badly and misuse shared bikes.
And if anyone is good a monitoring and punishing
its citizens,
it’s the Chinese government.
According to the National Interest…
…their surveillance technology can scan
the entire population “in one second.”
I know it might feel like 1984
meets Terminator
meets Premium Rush...
but if it’ll prevent people from leaving
heaps of shared bikes all over the place,
it’ll be totally worth it.
Or—and I know this sounds crazy, but hear
me out—
instead of punishing individual citizens,
the government could step in to design
and implement thoughtful policies to make
sure
the bike-sharing companies act responsibly.
Haha, just kidding.
It’s way easier to just punish people.
So what do you think about China’s bike-sharing
disaster?
Leave your comments below.
And now it’s time when I answer a question
from one of you—
my 50-Cent Army supporters who contribute
to China Uncensored on Patreon.
Primo asks,
“One thing I've been wondering is have you
ever thought of going to being more serious,
or do you think the satirical way of the show
is the way it should be?”
Good question.
So I started China Uncensored back in 2012.
Before that I was covering China
but in a straight news kind of way.
And I’m sorry to say, I found nobody really
cared.
Which bothered me because I knew China is
a really important country and was having
a big impact
on our lives in the United States.
This was also around the time the Communist
Party
started building those artificial islands
in the South China Sea
and claiming that proved it was their territory.
I found I couldn’t keep a straight face
saying,
“the Chinese government has started to build
fake islands
and are claiming it as ancient Chinese territory.”
No, that’s absolutely redonkulous.
So I created China Uncensored with the tone
it has
because that’s the only way I felt like
I could really say
what I wanted to say about the Chinese Communist
Party.
And over the years,
I’ve found using satire has actually helped
bring
a larger audience to China news and politics.
And be honest:
If all I did was straight news reporting,
would you still be watching?
Thanks for your question, Primo.
And if you’d me to answer your question,
join up in the China Uncensored 50-army.
We have a very low mortality rate.
And for only a dollar or more per episode,
we’ll give you some cool perks
and you’ll have the chance to send me questions
that I could answer right here on the show.
So head over to Pateron.com/chinauncensored
to learn more.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.