bjbj,(,( On this episode of China Uncensored,
I don t think Chinese feminists understand
what feminism means Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I'm Chris Chappell. Does the perfect man exist?
Maybe he does, but why on earth would he want
to marry you? That s the advice China s Women
s Federation is offering to what they call
the leftover women, women who have spent too
much time getting an education, not enough
time finding a hubby, and have now reached
the unmarriageable age of 27. Now before you
get offended, keep in mind, the way they calculate
age is a little different in China so really,
by US calculation, they mean 26. Again, this
comes from China s state feminist agency,
the All-China Women s Federation, which was
founded in 1949 to protect women s rights
and interests. Aww, look at them. They coined
the term leftover women in 2007 with articles
like Overcoming the Big Four Emotional Blocks:
Leftover Women Can Break out of Being Single,
and, Eight Simple Moves to Escape the Leftover
Women Trap. China s Ministry of Education
has even added the term to its official lexicon
Here s a taste. I have to thank Times Contributor
LETA HONG FINCHER for finding this gem from
2011. Pretty girls don t need a lot of education
to marry into a rich and powerful family,
but girls with an average or ugly appearance
will find it difficult. These kinds of girls
hope to further their education in order to
increase their competitiveness. The tragedy
is, they don t realize that as women age,
they are worth less and less, so by the time
they get their M.A. or Ph.D., they are already
old, like yellowed pearls. And these are the
feminists! I mean this stuff sounds like some
nightmare version of Cosmo or some of the
more painful writing on Mad Men. Now, I know
what you re probably thinking, boy, do I hate
leftover women. Well according to the Women
s Federation, you should. They just spend
their nights going to clubs for one-night
stands, becoming mistresses to rich officials.
It is only when they have lost their youth
and are kicked out by the man, that they decide
to look for a life partner. Therefore, most
leftover women do not deserve our sympathy.
But to all my lady viewers, which according
to Youtube analytics I have none, even if
you get married, your job s not done. Say
one day you find out your husband s having
an affair. Don t get mad at him. It s your
fault. You should probably get a new haircut
or something. No man is capable of spending
a lifetime being loyal to an outmoded wife
who never changes. At this point I would just
like to say I m totally capable of spending
a lifetime being loyal to an outmoded wife
and I think 27 is a beautiful age. (wink)
hOVu hOVu gdF< :pF< [Content_Types].xml #!MB
;c=1 _rels/.rels theme/theme/themeManager.xml
sQ\}# theme/theme/theme1.xml G$$DA : BR \{i5@R
V*[_X ,l\Y Ssd+r] 5\|E Vky- V4Ej 6NGU s?^V
* 7;wP EBU` 5VD
GGHPXNT, /M,W m2iU [[v _Xtl theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.rels
6?$Q K(M&$R(.1 [Content_Types].xmlPK _rels/.relsPK
theme/theme/themeManager.xmlPK theme/theme/theme1.xmlPK
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.relsPK
<a:clrMap xmlns:a="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/main"
bg1="lt1" tx1="dk1" bg2="lt2" tx2="dk2" accent1="accent1"
accent2="accent2" accent3="accent3" accent4="accent4"
accent5="accent5" accent6="accent6" hlink="hlink"
folHlink="folHlink"/> On this episode of China
Uncensored, I don t think Chinese feminists
understand what feminism means Chris Chappell
Normal.dotm Chris Microsoft Macintosh Word
PICT! Ag9V kZg9Z o\{kZg9Z g9kZZ o\{g9w g9g9kZg9o\
Ag9^ kZg9s kZkZ^ kZo\{kZo\{kZw o\{kZkZg9s g9kZkZw
kZkZ\{ g9g9o\{o\{c kZkZs o\{kZkZc g9kZo\{s o\{kZg9kZo\{
kZo\{kZkZs kZo\{w o\{kZkZw o\{kZg9s o\{kZ\{ o\{o\{s
kZo\{kZ\{ o\{o\{kZkZw o\{kZo\{ kZkZw o\{g9 o\{g9w
o\{g9 Ag9g9^ kZg9c o\{g9^ kZg9c o\{kZw g9g9c
kZo\{kZ^ g9g9c g9o\{kZg9c g9o\{kZ^ o\{o\{w o\{g9g9^
kZg9^ g9JRc kZg9s @g9kZkZo\{kZkZc o\{kZs o\{kZw
o\{o\{s kZkZc kZkZo\{s kZg9s kZkZo\{kZs o\{kZ\{
kZo\{w o\{g9kZkZw kZo\{w g9g9w kZkZ\{ g9o\{s o\{kZo\{kZg9kZkZw
kZo\{c kZo\{w o\{g9\{ kZg9kZw g9kZ\{ kZo\{o\{w g9kZo\{kZo\{kZw
o\{kZs o\{g9\{ kZo\{o\{c kZkZ^ g9o\{ *g9w Nso\{V
o\{g9R kZg9^ o\{g9c kZg9o\{ g9kZc g9g9^ kZo\{c
o\{kZs o\{kZkZs kZg9o\{kZ o\{o\
g9o\{c o\{g9s g9kZg9g9V g9g9s o\{o\
g9g9Nsg9^ o\{g9g9^ o\{kZs AkZkZc kZg9^ kZg9^
o\{kZg9c g9kZo\{^ g9g9c ;g9^ g9o\{g9^ g9kZ g9g9^
kZkZ kZo\{g9g9o\{s o\{o\{c kZkZw o\{kZs kZo\
kZo\{o\{ o\{o\{w o\{kZs kZo\{s g9kZs g9o\{ kZo\{ kZg9o\{o\
g9g9o\{c o\{g9c kZg9 kZkZs o\{o\{ kZNsV Nsg9^
(o\{R kZkZ^ g9kZc kZkZg9o\{Z kZkZg9g9o\{^ kZo\{g9g9o\{c
o\{g9s kZg9o\{g9o\{^ g9g9 o\{o\{kZg9o\{s g9g9kZo\
o\{o\{kZ kZkZo\{s kZkZs kZo\{w o\{o\
this episode of China Uncensored, I don t
think Chinese feminists understand what feminism
means Title Microsoft Word 97-2004 Document
NB6W Word.Document.8