The Coronavirus
A PR Disaster for China?
Or a Propaganda Victory?
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
You know, I criticize the Chinese Communist
Party.
A lot.
But as many commenters have reminded me,
it’s also important to praise the Party
when they do things well.
So I will.
The Chinese Communist Party is really, really
good...
at turning their terrible mistakes into propaganda
wins—
and convincing the rest of the world to agree.
They’re doing it right now with the coronavirus.
And they’ve done it before, too.
For example, after Mao Zedong took over in
and enforced collective farming,
the Chinese Communist Party plunged the nation
into poverty and starvation.
Then, Deng Xiaoping made free market reforms,
and Chinese people were able to make a living
again.
But the Chinese Communist Party spun it
as if *they* lifted people out of poverty—
even though it was actually Chinese people
themselves
who worked their way out of poverty once the
Party
backed off a bit on those communist economic
policies.
Here’s how Chinese Chinese state-run media
covers it:
China lifts millions of people out of poverty.
The Communist Party has gotten respected
global institutions like the World Bank
to carry that same line.
Then Chinese state-run media repeat their
propaganda,
this time citing the World Bank to make it
sound legit.
Then Western media pick up the story because
the World Bank said it.
So all the credit for “lifting people out
of poverty” goes to “China”—
i.e.
The Chinese Communist Party.
And nowhere does that article mention how
the Chinese Communist Party
put all those people in poverty in the first
place!
It’s like you throw someone overboard,
watch them struggle to swim, and then eventually
you throw them a rope and watch them claw
their way back to the boat.
And now you’re the hero for saving them.
The Chinese Communist Party has repeated the
same playbook over and over—
like with faking GDP growth,
or covering up their shady organ transplant
business,
or hiding how they’re putting Uighurs in
concentration camps.
And now, we’re seeing that same propaganda
machine at work
with the deadly coronavirus disease.
It’s only been a few months,
and the virus is spreading globally.
And we’re seeing headlines like this in
Western media:
“The First Signs Are Emerging That China's
Coronavirus Containment
Could Be Working”.
And “Can China’s COVID-19 strategy work
elsewhere?”
Yes, says the Wall Street Journal!
“Drastic measures—similar to those deployed
by China
and imposed in parts of Italy—
to contain the epidemic are now overdue elsewhere.”
So let’s back up, and look at how the Communist
Party
went from massively screwing up the initial
response to the outbreak,
to convincing the world that they did everything
right all along.
Starting with...
Step 1: A Massive Coverup
As of now, the first case of the coronavirus
disease,
Covid-19, can be traced back to November 17,
2019.
“By the final day of 2019, the number of
confirmed cases had risen to 266.”
But the Chinese Communist Party responded,
not by implementing health measures,
but by covering up what was happening.
They detained people who talked about it online.
They arrested the first doctors who reported
on it.
As an important political meeting took place
in Wuhan,
officials spent two weeks saying there were
“no new cases of infection,
no firm evidence of human transmission and
no infection of medical workers.”
Those were all lies.
In fact, the coronavirus was already spreading
outside China.
By mid-January, there were so many cases that
the Chinese Communist Party
realized they couldn’t continue to cover
it up.
It was time for...
Step 2: A Declaration of War
Haha, what cover up?!
We’re fighting a war against the coronavirus!
Communist Party leader Xi Jinping came out
and said
China will “resolutely curb” the outbreak
of the virus.
That’s right about when the number of reported
coronavirus cases tripled.
The coronavirus wasn’t actually spreading
faster.
It just got politically riskier for local
officials to cover it up.
Especially after central authorities announced
that
“lower-ranking officials who covered up
the spread of the virus would
‘be nailed on the pillar of shame for eternity.’”
Then the Communist Party pivoted to...
Step 3: Ruthless Authoritarianism
By the end of January,
China was reporting almost 12,000 cases of
infection and 259 deaths.
And those were just the official statistics,
so the real numbers were probably much higher.
Authorities put an entire province of 58 million
people under lockdown...
and restricted the movements of more than
half the country
in one way or another.
On the ground, local authorities rounded up
infected people
and put them into mass quarantine centers.
Even though the conditions were not the most
sanitary.
When people were caught outside without face
masks,
police savagely beat them...again and again.
Or in some cases, authorities even welded
sick people into their apartments.
And they made sure to censor “negative”
news about the coronavirus outbreak.
Including disappearing citizen journalists
into indefinite quarantines.
Did it work?
Well, I’ll tell you what didn’t work:
The people of China.
They were told not to go back to work.
And China’s manufacturing hit a record low.
But soon, the Chinese Communist Party saw
this as a huge problem—
because their political legitimacy is based
on
delivering continuous economic growth.
Clearly, it was time for...
Step 4: Announcing They’ve Won
The Communist Party has no choice politically
but to get people to go back to work and revive
the economy.
So that’s what they’ve told people to
do now.
First, state-run media started pushing the
narrative
that the number of coronavirus infections
was on the decline.
They started doing this back in mid-February.
Even though at the time they were
(a) only talking about areas outside the main
epicenter of Hubei province,
and (b) being misleading.
The total number of infections was not actually
declining.
There were still new infections every day,
but the number of *new* infections per day
was declining.
They’re saying it had gone from this, to
this.
So it’s still going up!
But forget about that.
The Chinese Communist Party leaders
wanted you to believe the coronavirus was
on the decline in China.
And that they controlled it in only three
weeks!
But here’s the rub:
Communist Party leaders didn’t actually
believe it themselves.
If they did, they wouldn’t have canceled
their own hugely important political meeting
in March.
So yes, Chinese leaders were...putting a good
face on things.
And that’s why, while they were implementing
ruthless authoritarianism,
and announcing they’d won, they were also...
Step 5: Co-Opting Respected Global Institutions
...institutions like the World Health Organization,
or W.H.O.
This report on the coronavirus comes from
a joint mission
between the W.H.O and the Chinese government.
It says, “China has rolled out perhaps the
most ambitious,
agile and aggressive disease containment effort
in history.”
In fact, the leader of the Joint Mission said,
“Hundreds of thousands of people in China
did not get COVID-19
because of this aggressive response.”
Don’t worry, he’s basing that on data
given to the W.H.O. by Chinese scientists.
And here’s what the head of the W.H.O. had
to say.
“Almost all member states are praising China
for what they did.
China took action massively at the epicenter,
at the source of the outbreak.”
Here’s another W.H.O. official.
“If I had COVID-19,
I’d want to be treated in China.”
If you’re wondering how on earth the W.H.O.
would be willing to lavish such praise on
the Chinese Communist Party,
even though *this* is happening on the ground...
...I suggest you go back and watch my episode
from February 22
called “Coronavirus: How WHO Corruption
Helped It Spread”.
Suffice it to say, when respected global institutions
take Chinese money,
sometimes it colors their vision.
And impaires their hearing.
And after co-opting the W.H.O.,
the Chinese Communist Party has been...
Step 6: Repeating the Praise in State-Run
Media
Oh, look!
The W.H.O. head praises China’s efforts
to curb the coronavirus!
Even the head of the United Nations has praised
China’s efforts!
Here’s a video released by state-run CGTN
showing
how the Communist Party has done such\h a
good job fighting the coronavirus,
that they’re now sending a team of Chinese
experts to help Italy.
“China has sent a special medical team to
Italy
to assist with control efforts there.
It comes after China's foreign minister told
his Italian counterpart
that Beijing stood ready to help.
And after pushing that message through English-language
state-run media,
the stage is set for...
Step 7: Getting Western Media to Praise China
Now that the Chinese Communist Party has claimed
it’s won against the coronavirus,
and co-opted global institutions to agree,
and pushed that message aggressively in its
own state-run media,
it seems Western media are willing to pick
up the narrative.
Here’s a video from South China Morning
Post.
“A 7-member team was sent to Italy,
the worst-hit country after China.”
Hmmm... that footage looks familiar.
Here’s an article from the Associated Press:
“W.H.O. chief praises China’s virus fight,
urges more from world”
That article does not mention the Chinese
Communist Party’s coverup,
or its ruthless authoritarianism.
And the Associated Press is a *newswire* service,
so that article got picked up by potentially
hundreds of other Western media.
And here’s a report from Reuters—
another newswire service.
“It’s a sign Chinese efforts to contain
coronavirus are working.
President Xi Jinping visited its epicenter,
Wuhan, on Tuesday,
for the first time since the outbreak began.
His arrival in the city where coronavirus
is understood
o have taken hold late last year
could suggest China is about to declare victory
in the battle.
Xi visiting those who were on the frontline:
health workers, soldiers, police, and volunteers.”
Wow, thanks Reuters—
for creating a story entirely based on Chinese
state-media footage,
and then pushing that pre-packaged video out
to
the thousands of Western TV channels
that subscribe to your newsfeed!
And also, thanks for not questioning any of
it.
Including how, when the video cuts to show
Xi Jinping
talking to the guy in the hospital,
he’s actually not talking directly to the
guy.
It’s through a TV screen nine feet away.
As if the coronavirus could get through the
TV screen.
And here’s a reporter from the New York
Times interviewed on MSNBC.
“China has had enormous success in beating
down its epidemic.”
He goes on for a full 5 minutes about how
great China’s approach is.
He makes the Chinese medical system look really
competent,
when that’s just not the reality most people
on the ground have been facing.
Although, in a way he’s right...
“China has had enormous success in beating
down its epidemic.”
Clearly, a lot of Western media organizations
are not as skeptical as they should be
when it comes to Chinese government propaganda.
Which means now, we’re going to see...
Step 8: China Saves Us All
The natural extension of this is that, since
the Chinese Communist Party
has done such a great job beating the coronavirus—
Oh, sorry, wrong clip.
“If I had COVID-19, I’d want to be treated
in China.”
Thank you.
—now it’s time to learn from China!
If only we could implement
the same great system here in the West!
Western media: Take it away!
“Can China's COVID-19 strategy work elsewhere?”
“Drastic measures—similar to those deployed
by China...
to contain the epidemic are now overdue elsewhere.”
Yes, but could you put it even more clearly?
“China saves its people as democracies slaughter
theirs”.
And it’s not just the idea that
China’s repressive authoritarian communist
system
has done a great job at containing the coronavirus
inside China.
I
t’s also the idea that China’s repressive
authoritarian communist system
has saved the rest of the world.
Back in February,
Chinese state-run media started rolling out
the idea t
hat China was buying the world time by controlling
the epidemic.
In fact, they made claims about how the fact
that China
had 99% of the world’s coronavirus cases
proved that they were helping the world.
You have the most coronavirus,
which means you’re the best?
Got it.
Of course, as the coronavirus continued to
spread around the world,
the Chinese Communist Party couldn’t claim
that
they had successfully contained it in China
anymore.
But the idea that their massive lockdown bought
the rest of the world time,
well, that took hold.
Like in this New York Times headline.
And that’s how the Chinese Communist Party
has taken
what should have been a devastating PR disaster,
and turned it into a propaganda win.
I really gotta tip my hat to them.
They’re truly the best.
And now that we’re busy trying to drag *ourselves*
out of the water,
we’ve totally forgotten who threw us overboard
in the first place.
But there are still some pesky Western media
that haven’t forgotten.
And they’re blaming China.
Which is why the Communist Party’s propaganda
machine
has created a new spin,
by tapping into a hot-button issue Western
media organizations
love to report on:
Racism!
That’s something I’ll be talking about
in our next episode.
For now, be sure to share this episode,
so your friends and family know the truth.
Don’t let the Chinese Communist Party’s
propaganda win the day.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.