Hong Kongers Celebrate V for Vendetta Day!
As violence takes a turn for the worse.
And Carrie Lam is here to stay
This is China Uncensored,
I’m Chris Chappell.
Before I begin, I just need to remind you
that YouTube is demonetizing
nearly all of our Hong Kong episodes.
We’ve only been able to keep making them
because of an amazing outpouring of support
from fans who contribute through
the crowdfunding website Patreon.
So a big thanks to them,
and if you can,
please consider supporting the show.
So hey, did you remember, remember
the 5th of November?
Hong Kongers did.
It’s Guy Fawkes Day.
Or, let’s be real,
more commonly known as V for Vendetta Day.
Hundreds of protesters took to the streets
in Hong Kong
wearing Guy Fawkes masks from the movie.
The Hong Kong government outlawed masks a
few weeks ago
and as you can see that’s really working
well.
But that’s not all.
Remember your college graduation?
Parading through campus with your friends.
Wearing Guy Fawkes masks to protect your identity
while protesting your authoritarian government.
Ah, youth.
The protests in Hong Kong have now entered
their 22nd week.
And this week, things got bad.
“What started as a peaceful protest quickly
turned chaotic
when riot police stormed the place
and a man with a knife went on a stabbing
spree outside.
District Councilor Andew Chiu tried to intervene
and the attacker turned on him.
The man was finally subdued -
and beaten - by protesters.”
Wow, props to Andrew Chiu.
But “the attacker turned on him”
doesn’t quite do justice.
The attacker bit his ear off.
Then a few days later, a Pro-Beijing lawmaker
was approached by a man bearing flowers...
who then stabbed him.
Don’t worry folks, he’s going to be ok.
It’s really almost a miracle that no one
has been killed yet
in direct relation to these protests,
or else things might really fly off the rail.
Oh.
Police were using tear gas
to clear protesters out of a parking garage.
You’re not really supposed to use tear gas
in an enclosed space like that,
but I guess at this point,
the police are well beyond “supposed to.”
It’s unclear exactly what happened,
but a student protester fell from the parking
garage.
He was hospitalized for his injuries on Monday,
and he died on Friday.
Protesters say police directly contributed
to Chow’s death,
not only by tactics to roust protesters,
but also by delaying first responders,
who they say had to proceed to the scene on
foot
after police cars reportedly blocked the ambulance.”
Protesters held an impromptu memorial for
Chow.
And guess who showed up?
Police.
“‘Do you know you can’t wear masks at
a rally?’
a police commander said…
‘This is a funeral, are you crazy?’
another man was heard yelling back.”
So people in Hong Kong are on edge.
It doesn’t help that millions of people
there
have been exposed to tear gas
at some point over the past few months.
In that time,
police have shot around 6,000 canisters of
tear gas.
And I can tell you from personal experience,
it doesn’t feel very nice.
But don’t worry, those days are done.
Now, Hong Kong police have switched to
a new version of tear gas made in China.
It’s explosive,
and it can burn your skin off.
Not as much of a burn though,
as when the police call you a cockroach.
Apparently not just protesters.
Anybody.
Even bystanders and journalists.
It’s nice to know the police think of the
citizens
as bugs to be squashed.
And if you’re wondering,
how is Hong Kong’s Chief Executive Carrie
Lam
still in power after all this?
Well, Chinese Communist Party leader Xi Jinping,
the guy who has real power in Hong Kong,
says Lam isn’t going anywhere.
The two of them are close.
I mean, not physically close.
At all.
But they do dress to match.
But it’s not just Carrie Lam
who’s receiving messages of support.
A group of Cuban Americans turned up at a
Miami Heat game
wearing shirts supporting the Hong Kong protesters.
Something about escaping communism
must make you sympathize with other people
trying to escape Communism.
And people inside Mainland China
also are sending their messages of support
for Hong Kong protesters.
You know how I know?
Because the Party has launched a massive effort
to scrub all those messages from the Chinese
Internet.
But there’s two sides to every issue.
A UK baking competition decide to show its
*support*
for tyranny and oppression.
They disqualified a Hong Kong protest themed
cake.
Cake International said
“the content and message behind the cake
has been viewed as offensive
and led to complaints from attendees.”
As you can see,
the cake was very offensive.
It even had fake tear gas.
I hope its fake,
because typically you don’t want your cake
to make people cry.
And finally, Hong Kong is banning political
satire...
at its annual Lunar New Year fairs.
Because of safety issues.
People have in the past sold items
that make fun of the government.
Which is very unsafe.
Gotta get rid of those pro-democracy tote
bags.
And with that,
I think I’ll answer a question from a Patreon
supporter.
Remember, this show wouldn’t exist
without the support of fans on Patreon,
so be sure to give them a big thanks in the
comments below.
Benja Sophon Sariwatta asks,
“What would you say to someone who is brainwashed
by the CCP propaganda?”
Well that’s a good question
and unfortunately I don’t have a great answer
to it.
It kind of depends on how well you know the
person.
A buddy of mine tried to convince me that
Huawei
was a totally independent company
and I was crazy to think otherwise.
When I told him that by Chinese law,
Huawei would have to turn over data to the
government,
his response was,
“Oh, but it’s okay that the US bombed
Serbia?”
I honestly didn’t know what to say to that.
If it’s a friend or family member,
keep gently trying telling them all the news
that’s coming out.
Better yet, show them videos.
Of course, if it’s some random person on
the internet,
well, there probably isn’t much you can
say or do to reach them,
so I’d recommend just going outside
and smelling some flowers instead.
Thanks for your question, Benja.
And if you have a question for me
you want to hear answered on the show,
sign up to join the China Uncensored 50 cent
army,
by supporting the show with a dollar or more
per episode.
Again, YouTube is demonetizing us so much
we would have to shut down the show
if it weren’t for your support.
And to everyone, thanks for watching!
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.