On this episode of China Uncensored,
Donald Trump and the One China Policy…
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Did you hear what President Trump did?
Uhhh, okay let me narrow that down a bit.
Did you hear what President Trump did specifically
with regards to China’s One China Policy?
He called the entire policy into question!
Oh no no.
Sorry.
That was from two months ago.
I meant to talk about the latest development.
He agreed to uphold the One China Policy!
How dare he do the same thing every US president
has done
since the 1970s!
So what does that mean?
Well according to the “analysts”
in this The New York Times article,
this proves that Trump is a weak leader.
Look, I know how it goes.
You're supposed to write an article
about what "experts" think about Trump's decision.
You're in Beijing, on deadline,
and no one's answering your calls,
so you end up with an article with eight paragraphs
of quotes
from two Chinese professors who are more than willing
to talk about how the US is weak.
Unfortunately,
that plays right into the Communist Party's
hands.
You see,
according to this Pentagon study on “China:
Three Warfares,”
the Party specifically uses “Media Warfare,”
to shape international public opinion on China
and "Psychological Warfare" to “foment anti-leadership
sentiments.”
But that's a whole ’nother episode.
Anyway, what actually happened
with Trump and the One China Policy?
First, a brief recap of the One China Policy.
Basically,
after the Communist Party seized control of
China
in 1949,
the previous Chinese government fled to Taiwan—
a government in exile.
Both sides claimed they were the true captain.
I'm your captain, Spock - can't you tell?!
Shoot!
And by captain,
I mean the legitimate government of China.
But rather than shooting,
the two Chinas came to a collective agreement
called the One China policy.
“Yeah, there’s only one China,
but we’re not going to say whether it’s
the one in Taiwan
or the one in the mainland.”
Vague diplomatic ambiguity is the key
to successful international relations.
But it is kind of awkward—
because it’s forced the US and most other
countries
to have official diplomatic relations
with only one of the two Chinas.
Kind of like when your two best friends in
elementary school
made you pick which one was your real best
friend.
No, Bobby, you can't have two best friends!
Pick me or pick him!
Most countries, including the US,
eventually picked mainland China, and not
Taiwan.
Even though the US stills sells weapons to
Taiwan every year.
But that’s a whole ’nother, ’nother
episode.
Anyway,
Trump tossed the One China Policy into the
air in December
when he spoke with Taiwanese president Tsai
Ing-wen
over the phone.
The first time a US president has done so
since the 70’s.
Then, he further shook the beehive by saying
this.
I fully understand the One China Policy,
but I don’t know why we have to be bound
by a One China Policy
unless we make a deal with China having to
do with other things,
including trade…
To which Chinese state run media responded
with,
he’s “playing with fire.”
Western media jumped on Trump for using Taiwan,
America’s ally,
as a bargaining chip with Beijing.
Fun fact:
Hillary Clinton had also considered using
Taiwan
as a bargaining chip.
So Trump wasn't that different from Clinton
here,
he was just more confrontational about it.
Because if you’re the US president,
you bargain with Taiwan's future.
It’s what you do.
But last week,
President Trump and Chinese leader Xi Jinping
had a phone call.
And it was,
according to the White House,
“extremely cordial”—
and since it was over the phone,
presumably less awkward than this moment
with Japan’s prime minister.
Please, look at me.
Anyway, on the call Trump agreed
“to honor our ‘one China policy.’”
So Trump dropped his hardline stance.
Does that mean Trump is backing down?
Is he caving in?
Or is he giving China the upper hand?
Or maybe none of those.
As J Michael Cole,
editor in chief of Taiwan Sentinel, points out,
the White House statement says the US will
“honor our one China Policy.”
As I've pointed out in previous episodes,
America's One China Policy
is a bit different from China's One China
policy.
America’s is that
“the U.S. acknowledges Beijing’s position
that there is only one China.”
Yeah,
the US acknowledges that Beijing
has that position.
It’s like me telling these guys,
“Yes, I acknowledge that you believe
that you’re a superhero.”
Once again,
vague diplomatic ambiguity saves the day.
This is a huge win for Chinese leader Xi Jinping, though.
This means that instead of fighting with Trump
over the One China issue,
he has more time to kick back, relax,
and continue his life-or-death struggle
to purge his political rivals.
In fact, Ming Chu-cheng,
a professor of political science
at National Taiwan University,
believes that the United States
has been quietly supportive of Xi Jinping
over the years,
and that “Donald Trump may, in honoring
the ‘one China’ policy,
be reverting to the status quo.”
Trump?
Reverting to the status quo?
What’s going on in this crazy mixed-up world?
Well, lately the Trump family
has been trying to strengthen its China ties.
No, not those ties.
Before Trump was elected,
his son-in-law met with a major Chinese business
tycoon
to discuss property development.
For the Chinese New Year,
Ivanka Trump and her 5-year-old daughter
paid a visit to the Chinese embassy.
Aww, she’s scared of the Chinese ambassador.
Then Trump’s national security advisor
hand delivers a letter from Trump to China’s
ambassador
with new year’s wishes.
It said “he looks forward to working with
President Xi
to develop a constructive relationship that
benefits
both the United States and China.”
So maybe that US-China war isn’t “a practical
reality” just yet.
So what do you think of Trump’s so-called
“caving in to the Chinese”?
Is that what’s happening?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.