On this episode of China Uncensored,
The Chinese military wants a pay raise.
A tragic medical affliction
may be plaguing Chinese dissidents.
And finally,
with new Chinese tariffs,
we’ll see a rise in the price of tinfoil
hats.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
China is gearing up for another meeting
of the National People’s Congress.
It’s a time when everyone in the Chinese
government
vies for power.
Including Chinese leader Xi Jinping.
More on that later,
but this is also the time when the budget
for 2018 gets set.
And everyone wants a piece of the pie.
Especially the military.
“China may have the world’s largest military,
but for some it’s not enough.
As Beijing gets ready to release
its defense budget for the year,
sources told Reuters that top brass
are pushing for a big bump in spending,
to combat modern threats.”
I mean, can you blame them?
It’s not cheap to build
your capture the flag courses
out of LEGOs!
China is second to only the United States
on military spending.
Of course, “China’s defense spending
is only about one-quarter that of the United
States,
if official figures are accurate.”
Which is a big if.
But still,
they barely have enough to make
a proper propaganda video.
Look at what they rolled out
ahead of the Chinese New Year.
Behold the power of China’s single tank.
The...navy?
They’re even trying to reuse tanks as boats!
You get the point, they need more money.
Official figures from the past two years
show the smallest increase in the military
budget
in a decade.
But “Experts say the true figure
is likely much higher than what is officially
reported,
with money for some military projects
included in ostensibly non-military spending.”
What?
These missile launchers are totally for civilian
use.
Now off to Xinjiang in Western China.
It’s home of the much maligned
ethnic Uighur population.
They’ve had to deal with
a massive security crackdown,
surveillance using face recognition technology,
and Minority Report style precog criminal
justice.
But somehow,
these Western news reports keep getting out!
Those meddling journalists…
Well now, the Chinese regime
is going after the journalists, too.
Authorities have detained the relatives
of four US-based reporters
with Radio Free Asia
who have been covering Xinjiang.
First, Chinese authorities just asked the
relatives
to call those reporters and ask them
to stop reporting on Xinjiang.
But when threatening nicely didn’t work,
the abductions started.
One reporter learned that Chinese police
had arrested 20 of the her relatives
because of her reporting.
Another one had relatives taken
to a political reeducation center
called the Loving Kindness School.
Don’t worry.
It’s one of China’s top political reeducation
centers—
along with the the Government Loves Everyone
Academy,
and the CCP Besties 4-Ever Institute.
Of course, since we’re hearing about
how journalists’ relatives are being detained,
clearly the strategy of intimidating journalists
is not working.
A Chinese man was admitted
to a hospital earlier this week
for a minor stomach ache.
Even though previously he had
a clean bill of health,
this turned out to be a much deadlier condition.
He had contracted a case
of what Chinese military doctors call,
“being a rights lawyer.”
A few hours after entering the hospital,
the condition dramatically worsened
until tragically, he bled to death.
Because of a liver problem.
Yeah...
Some are calling rights lawyer Li Baiguang’s
death
at the No. 81 Military Hospital
a mysterious death.
But Bob Fu,
head of the Chinese Christian rights group,
ChinaAid, calls it murder.
Li Baiguang defended underground Christians
in China.
They’re the ones who refuse to worship
in state-approved churches
run by the atheist Communist Party.
A Twitter programer who was visiting his family
in China
was invited to tea by the Chinese Public Security
Bureau.
How friendly.
First, they asked him if he did anything
to “harm national interest.”
And then they asked for Twitter code technology
so they could monitor twitter content.
For national interest.
Now this may surprise you,
but Radio Free Asia suspects the Chinese regime
may be pressuring his family.
But even if the Public Security Bureau
didn’t get the Twitter code they wanted,
at least they have Apple’s Chinese users
data.
Apple has officially put
all their Chinese users’ iCloud data
on servers belonging to the state-run company,
Cloud Big Data.
Apple will also store
Chinese iCloud encryption keys there.
Just to make sure the Chinese regime
has easy access.
“Because of the move,
the Chinese government will be able use
its own legal system to ask Apple
for its users’ iCloud data,
whereas before the government had to
go through the U.S. legal system.”
Now Apple has said
they weren’t happy about it.
But in the end,
what choice did they have
other than to cave in?
I mean, it would be practically unethical
not to seek a share of that sweet,
sweet China market.
And finally,
President Trump has said he will implement
new tariffs on imports of aluminum and steel.
He’s complained frequently about
how US manufacturing gets hurt,
because Chinese companies
get government subsidies
and export their goods
at below market prices.
“So, we’re bringing it back
and we’re going to bring it back relatively
rapidly.
And we’re going to be instituting tariffs.
Next week we’ll be signing.”
From the initial announcement,
it looks like these tariffs will apply
to all aluminum and steel imports,
not just those from China.
Meanwhile, the Chinese government already
has plans to retaliate.
“Its commerce ministry investigating
imports of US sorghum,
which is used to feed livestock.
And officials say China
could further target soybeans.”
So is this the start of a trade war with China?
Well, what China doesn’t realize is that
the US can actually survive just fine
without selling soybeans to China.
They really should put a tariff on iPhones.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China Uncensored.
Once again, I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Well the Chinese Communist Party
is certainly rotten.
But you know what never goes bad?
Food from Thrive Life.
Thrive Life sells freeze dried meals
that stay fresh.
And if you order through the link
in the description below,
China Uncensored gets a cut.
I wouldn’t ask you to eat their food
if I didn’t also personally love it.
So support your belly and China Uncensored
by buying some delicious food from Thrive
Life.
The link is below.