On this episode of China Uncensored,
China tells South Korea to stop dancing.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I'm your host Chris Chappell.
Did you ever see The Sound of Music?
More like The Sound of Propaganda!
Here I think I'm watching a nice musical celebrating
Austrian culture...
when suddenly it turns into a story about
Nazi oppression.
Now clearly, the Third Reich is not one of
their favorite things.
But I mean, how dare they use art to make
people think?
Now speaking of artistic performances that
make people think: Shen Yun.
It's a classical Chinese dance show run by
a nonprofit Chinese-American company.
Apparently, the Chinese Communist Party considers
Shen Yun a major threat
including in South Korea.
Why is that? Well let's see.
According to the Shen Yun website,
It's "reviving 5,000 years of civilization."
It "features the world's foremost classically
trained dancers";
and it was "established by Falun Dafa practitioners
in 2006."
I feel like it's probably one of those three.
And if you want some background
on why the Communist Party is so intent on
stopping Falun Dafa, a.k.a. Falun Gong,
watch this video here.
Now Shen Yun tours around the world
in hundreds of cities.
I've watched it a few times at Lincoln Center
in New York.
Each show has about twenty dance and music
numbers.
Some of them depict historical things,
like the founding of a dynasty.
And a couple of them usually depict contemporary
issues,
like Falun Dafa meditators standing up the
to Communist Party's suppression.
Well apparently, in South Korea,
the use of the arts to make people think
about certain contemporary issues is a huge
threat
to the stability of the Chinese Communist
Party.
You see, KBS Hall in Seoul had signed a contract
with promotion company New Cosmos Media
to host Shen Yun performances here in May
2016.
But then on January 26, just a few weeks ago,
KBS suddenly canceled the contract.
Organizers suspect the Chinese Embassy was
behind it.
Now, I know that sounds like wild speculation.
But there are numerous, well-documented cases
of Chinese Embassies around the world trying
to stop Shen Yun.
Let's call it "diplomacy with Chinese characteristics."
They often tell theaters that hosting Shen
Yun
"may compromise relations" between China and
their country.
For example, according to Spain's biggest
newspaper,
in 2014 a Chinese diplomat tried to pressure
a theater in Barcelona
to cancel its contract with Shen Yun.
When the theater refused,
the Chinese official tried to pressure Spain's
Foreign Ministry instead.
Shen Yun performed anyway,
and it got rave reviews from Spanish media.
And when Shen Yun was scheduled to perform
in Berlin that same year,
the German Chinese Embassy's cultural attaché
met with the theater’s marketing and sales
manager, Jörg Seefeld,
telling him he had better cancel Shen Yun.
This German Newspaper reported on the incident,
saying,
“It sounds like something out of the Cold
War.”
Fortunately for Shen Yun,
Mr. Seefeld had been a prisoner during the
Cold War in communist East Germany.
He told the Chinese attaché to go pound sand.
And those are just two of literally dozens
of examples,
around the world, of Chinese diplomats
"diplomatically" trying to force theaters
to cancel Shen Yun.
And most of the time, their efforts have failed
because theater managers stand up to them.
So when getting theaters to cancel on Shen
Yun doesn't work,
they sometimes try a different approach.
Like trying to stop people from attending.
"Last week, Seattle City Council members received
a letter from the Chinese Consul in San Francisco
urging them not to promote or attend the show."
Or the year before:
"The Chinese government's been told to butt
out of local politics
after apparently asking city council members
to stay away from a dance show."
"Cathy Casey says the Consul-General's letter
is a breach of human rights."
"'China has its own laws. This is New Zealand.
We are a democracy. We have freedom of expression
and freedom of association.
And this breaks every rule in the book.'"
You know, I feel like there are more important
things the Chinese Embassies could be doing.
But anyway, back to Korea.
Shen Yun has tried to perform here every year
since 2008.
And almost every time, whether in Seoul, Busan,
or another city,
the theaters have told organizers they received
pressure from Chinese officials not to hold
the show.
In some cases, theater owners have withstood
the pressure and let Shen Yun perform.
But in many cases,
the Korean theaters folded under pressure
like it's their first time at the poker table
claiming "Hey, it's not our fault! The Chinese
Embassy pressured us!"
But let’s not completely blame the victim.
I should point out that Chinese pressure on
Korea has been unusually severe.
You see, South Korea has a very tight relationship
with China.
China is South Korea's largest trading partner
a relationship worth more than 200 billion
dollars a year.
And Chinese money is critical to Korea's economic
development.
And that may be why KBS Hall broke Shen Yun's
contract and canceled this year's show.
Also, KBS Hall is owned by state-run Korean
TV broadcaster KBS.
And KBS has lots of reporters in China.
Reporters who need Chinese media visas.
And speaking of media,
guess who shares a building with KBS in Seoul?
Why, the local bureau of China Central Television!
But, you know, I don't want to make wild accusations
about what's behind KBS Hall's cancellation
of Shen Yun.
So I attempted to contact KBS for their side
of the story.
I sent a letter to their official email account,
but it was returned because of "an error in
the mail server."
I called several numbers for the relevant
departments,
but they all said something like this.
“The number you have dialed is temporarily
not in service."
Then we called their main phone number,
and asked to be transferred,
but the representative refused;
she insisted we send an email instead.
I did speak about the issue with Changsik
Lee,
who's promoting Shen Yun in South Korea.
”Shen Yun has been performing in Korea for
the last nine years
and 10,000 people every year have watched Shen Yun
and the response has been fantastic,
they like the show very much."
"Have you talked to anyone at KBS since they
canceled the contract?"
"Yes, yes we met with some people,
and they all know that the show has no problem
and the show is very famous worldwide."
"So why cancel the show?"
"They have no choice.
They just got ordered from the higher level."
"Did they say who the higher level is or why?"
"They cannot tell."
Mr. Lee also gave me a copy of KBS's official
termination notice for Shen Yun.
KBS wrote that, "there is concern that it
may damage our public corporation's image."
Hmmm.. Well that same concern didn't seem
to apply for this show,
which I saw rehearing at KBS Hall:
The "Korean Overseas Chinese Friendship Association
Lantern Festival Gala."
And it's sponsored by, you guessed it, the
Chinese government!
It's performing this week.
Oh, according to the program,
it features such traditional Chinese classics
as,
"I'm so sexy."
Which is apparently fine for KBS’s public
image.
It's just that, when you compare it to Shen
Yun...
Wait a second! I know what's going on!
It's like those off-brand LEGOs I kept seeing
in South Korea.
I guess KBS Hall only wants the cheap, Chinese
knockoff.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below,
and subscribe to this channel for more episodes.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell. See you next time