O say can you see...
by the Chinese flag?!
In San Francisco?!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Today is October 10th—
National Day,
where people come together to celebrate the founding
of the Republic of China.
Which,
despite its sometimes rocky history,
is now a free and democratic society,
with elected leaders and rule of law.
And that's because the Republic of China
is the one that governs Taiwan.
The big China
is the People’s Republic of China.
The one founded by Mao Zedong,
the dictator who killed more people than Hitler
and Stalin combined.
People celebrated that Chinese National Day
on October 1st,
the anniversary of the Communist Party’s,
um,
“liberation” of China.
Anyway,
the mainland Chinese National Day
wasn’t just celebrated inside mainland China
this year.
It was also celebrated
in Taiwan.
A China Uncensored viewer sent us these photos
he took in downtown Taipei
during the October 1st celebrations.
He says mainland Chinese were raising the
flag
of the People’s Republic of China,
and blaring communist propaganda songs from
loudspeakers.
Taiwan locals on the street could hardly believe
what they were seeing.
But on the other hand,
it’s not so hard to believe.
The Chinese Communist Party considers Taiwan
to be just another province of China.
Maybe if they say it enough,
it will become true!
Well, if they say it enough
and also keep sixteen hundred missiles pointed
at Taiwan.
As you may know,
the Communist Party has threatened
to take Taiwan by military force
if it ever officially declares independence.
So it’s little wonder Taiwan people were
upset
by having all those mainland Chinese flags
waving around.
But you know who welcomed the Chinese Communist
Party’s
National Day celebrations?
Officials from Vancouver, Canada.
According to another China Uncensored viewer
there
who works near City Hall,
there were dozens of Chinese flags being flown
outside,
and security guards blocked off a whole area
for a Chinese National Day event.
This photo from the local Richmond News shows
the ceremony.
The guy in the center wearing a red scarf
is Vancouver’s acting mayor,
Kerry Jang,
a third-generation Chinese-Canadian.
A huge backlash erupted over the flag-raising
ceremony,
and especially over the fact that Canadian
officials in the photo
were wearing those red scarves.
Mayor Jang dismissed the backlash as racist,
and he also defended wearing the scarves because,
"Red is the Chinese colour for luck and good
fortune."
Okay,
what Jang said about the color red is true.
And some of the backlash against the flag
raising
might be prejudiced.
There is growing resentment in Vancouver
over hordes of rich mainland Chinese coming
over
and buying up real estate with cash,
driving average housing prices into the millions.
But that's not why people are upset about
the red scarves.
You see,
those red scarves have a specific meaning.
And it isn’t from traditional Chinese culture.
Those scarves represent the blood
of communist revolutionary martyrs.
They’re generally worn by schoolchildren
who are members of the Young Pioneers.
The Young Pioneers official slogan is:
"Be prepared, to struggle for the cause of
Communism!
Always be prepared!"
They’re just like the Boy Scouts!
Except their theme song is called
“We are the Heirs of Communism,”
which talks about cleanly annihilating their
enemies.
I have never been so afraid of a six-year-old
before.
The point is,
the red scarf is a widely used symbol in different
communist countries.
Here is it on a Soviet postage stamp.
And being worn by Vietnamese Young Pioneers.
But some of us don't read Wikipedia.
Like that awkward-looking guy on the left,
also wearing a red scarf.
That’s Canadian Member of Parliament Joe
Peschisolido.
In his defense, though,
he regretted it more than the girl who wore
this to her wedding.
Afterwards,
Peschisolido told the Richmond News
that when the Chinese organizers told him
to wear the scarf, he
“didn’t realize it had the [connotations
of] the Cultural Revolution
and persecution that it did.”
What persecution?
Let's ask former Vancouver mayoral candidate
Meena Wong,
who wrote on Facebook:
“During the infamous Chinese Cultural Revolution,
the red guards wearing red scarves came to
our home
and took everything valuable.
They abused my aging grandmother
and threatened my parents.”
So that's why there's now a Change.org petition
asking acting mayor Kerry Jang to apologize,
and then resign.
And it wasn’t just some patriotic Chinese
Canadians
who organized the Vancouver event.
It was the Canadian Alliance of Chinese Associations—
the same group that helped organize a
“Praising Mao” event in 2013,
celebrating the birthday of the most successful
mass murder
in human history.
Successful not only because Mao killed like
100 million people
without getting punished,
but because hipsters still wear him on their
t-shirts.
But while we’d all love to blame Canada—
and we do—
it’s not just Canada.
In San Francisco,
Chinese American Mayor Ed Lee
also enthusiastically threw his support behind
Chinese National Day.
In this footage from China Daily’s Twitter
account,
we can see Mayor Lee during the Chinese national
anthem,
and then speaking,
at the National Day Event organized by—
wait for it—
the Chinese consul-general.
Here he is being praised by Chinese state-run
media for it.
But strangely,
Mayor Lee forgot to mention it on his official
webpage.
As if perhaps the people he represents in
San Francisco
might be upset by him cozying up to a regime
that’s killed more people in the last decade
than...
the entire population of San Francisco.
This is not the first time, either.
In fact,
Lee was criticized two years ago for raising
the Chinese flag
while pro-democracy protests were happening
in Hong Kong.
Look,
I'm not trying to pick on ethnically Chinese
government officials.
I mean,
last year,
California governor Jerry Brown also joined
the CCP’s National Day Ceremony.
And I know that both Vancouver and San Francisco
routinely raise flags for different countries'
national day holidays,
as a way of celebrating the diversity of their
cities.
I think that's a good thing.
But the People’s Republic of China is different.
It's worth noting that the loudest protests
against these national day celebrations
come from Chinese people.
The Communist Party,
besides being responsible for atrocities like
the Cultural Revolution
and the Tiananmen Square Massacre
still kills its own citizens on a regular basis.
The Party uses events like these national
day ceremonies
to make itself seem like a totally legit,
normal government,
hiding what it’s done,
not only from its own people,
but also the from rest of the world.
And it really helps when foreign officials
raise the flag for them.
So what do you think of foreign countries
celebrating Chinese National Day?
Leave your comments below.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.