On this episode of China Uncensored,
the Communist Party is putting pressure on
US airlines.
But it’s not going to fly with the White
House.
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
China’s sacred territory is very important
to the Chinese Communist Party,
especially when the Party only has
questionable claims to that sacred territory.
Take the South China Sea for example.
Indisputable territory of China since ancient
times.
Made even more indisputable by the man-made
islands
armed with missile launchers.
But the Chinese Communist Party
can’t build missile launchers on everything.
Probably.
That’s why the Party has other ways to give
everyone
a friendly reminder about what is and isn’t
Chinese territory.
In April, China’s Civil Aviation Administration
sent a letter to 36 foreign airlines.
It demanded that they stop referring to Taiwan,
Hong Kong and Macau as countries or regions
separate from China.
Here’s a copy of the actual letter,
obtained by the Washington Post.
Yes, they’re not separate countries!
Taiwan, of course,
has its own democratically elected government,
its own military, currency, passports,
pop stars, and border control—
but as the Communist Party will tell you,
Taiwan is just a renegade province of China,
not a separate country!
Hong Kong and Macau also have separate governments,
although legally,
they are under the authority
of the People’s Republic of China.
So no dispute there.
Although since they have their own laws and
border control,
some people think of them as separate regions.
But not for long!
Because that letter from China’s Civil Aviation
Administration
warned some airlines that if they failed to
comply
with the friendly request to stop listing
these...places
as separate regions and/or countries,
there would be friendly consequences.
This is hardly the first time the Chinese
Communist Party
has pulled this tactic.
In January, fashion brand Zara and Delta Air
Lines
had to apologize for listing Taiwan
as a country on their websites.
Later that month,
hotel chain Marriott suffered the same fate.
But this time, it’s different.
The Trump Administration won’t let
the Chinese Communist Party get away with
bullying US airlines.
Because if the Trump Administration understands
anything,
it’s bullying.
White House press secretary released this
statement...
...saying President Trump will “will stand
up for Americans
resisting efforts by the Chinese Communist
Party
to impose Chinese political correctness
on American companies and citizens.”
And the statement called the Communist Party’s
demands
“Orwellian nonsense.”
Because if the Trump Administration understands
anything,
it’s references to classic 20th century
literature.
And so the Communist Party responded in a
way
they know will get President Trump’s attention:
a Twitter war.
This actual tweet
from China’s State Council Information Office
asked, “how would you like it
if we listed one of your states as a country?
Huh?
Huh???”
I gather that China’s State Council Information
Office
has never been to Texas.
Or California.
Or New Hampshire.
Frankly, we’ll give away Florida.
But seriously, the State Council Information
Office
makes a great point.
It’s exactly like a Chinese airline
listing Texas as a separate country...
if Texas had its own military, passports,
currency, and border patrol.
And no,
Walker, Texas Ranger does not count.
The US Embassy in China reposted
the White House’s statement about this
“Orwellian nonsense”
on their Weibo account.
Weibo is China’s version of Twitter.
But the post was censored by Chinese authorities.
Well, censored-ish.
They can’t take it down
without causing a diplomatic incident,
but they can stop other people from reposting
it.
And some Chinese netizens were enjoying the
show.
Before their own comments got censored.
But according to my favorite state-run media,
the Global Times,
other Chinese netizens were furious
that the White House called these tactics
“Orwellian Nonsense.”
Although some were also confused about
what Orwellian means.
By the way,
George Orwell’s books are not
completely censored in China.
You can buy Chinese translations
of Animal Farm and 1984.
So not understanding references
to classic 20th century literature—
that’s on you, kids.
Trump would be so disappointed.
Anyway, China’s Foreign Ministry went the
route of,
“this is just the price of doing business
in China.”
So what’s the big fuss?
Many airlines have already tried to adapt.
Like British Airways.
They used to list Taiwan, Macau, and Hong
Kong
under a drop down menu labeled “countries.”
But earlier this year,
they changed their menu to just say “From.”
Now like I said earlier,
Hong Kong and Macau are officially part of
China,
even though they have their own passports
and governments.
But Taiwan is a trickier matter.
The Communist Party calls Taiwan a province,
but Taiwan operates like a completely independent
country
in every way.
Because of this, the Communist Party
has vowed to take over Taiwan,
by force if necessary.
In fact, according to this book...
...the Communist Party has laid out a comprehensive
plan
to do just that by the year 2020.
So it’s really awkward when airlines
list Taiwan as a country.
I think the most accurate solution
would be to simply list Taiwan as
“The province of China that China is going
to invade
even though it’s definitely already a province
of China.”
In the past, some airlines got around this
sticky situation
by listing Hong Kong, Macau, and Taiwan
under a “country/region” menu,
instead of just “country.”
But according to the letter
sent out by China’s Civil Aviation Administration,
that no longer flies.
Nope.
Even if it’s under a country/region menu,
it has to say “Taiwan, China”
or “Taiwan region, China”.
Not “Taiwan” by itself.
What are you thinking?!
So it’s getting harder and harder
to please Chinese authorities.
And with China expected to be
the world’s largest air travel market by
2022,
a lot of airlines are feeling the pressure.
But the good news is,
it’s not just the US government
that’s noticed this Orwellian nonsense.
Australia is speaking out as well.
So what do you think about this “Orwellian
Nonsense”?
And would you wear a T-shirt that says “Orwellian
Nonsense?”
Because, we’ve made T-shirts that say “Orwellian
Nonsense”.
Seriously.
Click the link below to buy one of these T-shirts.
The US Embassy and the Global Times
translated Orwellian Nonsense two different
ways in Chinese.
We, of course, went with the Global Times
version.
And no, the shirts are not made in China.
Which is why they’re more expensive.
So buy an obscurely hilarious t-shirt,
and leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Don’t go anywhere!
Because I’m answering questions from fans
of the show.
This question comes from a member
of our 50-Cent Army on Patreon.
Largezo asks:
“Is the PRC aware of your existence?”
Great question.
Of course they do!
I’m kind of a big deal.
On two occasions,
I sent faxes to the Chinese consulate in New
York
trying to arrange an interview with Chinese
leader Xi Jinping.
Why fax?
A
pparently Marx’s relentless march of history
is a little slow when it comes to
the Communist Party’s communication systems.
Oddly enough, the consulate never got back
to me.
But I’m sure I’ll get that interview someday.
I do know people are watching
China Uncensored in China.
And for reasons I can’t explain,
the chinauncensored.tv website
is not blocked inside China.
So Xi Jinping, if you’re watching,
which I know you are,
I’m ready for that interview.
Want your question answered next time?
At the end of each episode on YouTube,
I’ll answer questions from Patreon supporters.
That is, fans who contribute a dollar or more
per episode.
China Uncensored relies on support from our
viewers,
so this is my thank you to the amazing supporters
who make this show possible.
Click the orange button to join!