Protests erupt across Hong Kong.
Chief executive Carrie Lam
called them "organized riots."
So I'm braving the danger,
and heading into the chaos.
It was the night of Sunday, June 16th,
right after two million people
took to the streets of Hong Kong.
They were protesting a controversial extradition
bill
that could see Hong Kong authorities
send people to mainland China for trial.
Hong Kong's chief excutive, Carrie Lam,
called last week's protests "organized riots."
That's after Hong Kong police launched
150 tear gas canisters into the crowd.
I mean, Sunday's protest seemed pretty peaceful,
at least during the day.
It was Father's Day, after all.
But as night fell,
a fringe group of extremists
occupied this eight-lane highway
near the Hong Kong government offices.
And I could smell trouble in the air.
Shelley, what are you doing?
Why aren't you in your safety gear?
What?
What are you doing?
Why aren't you in your safety gear?
Don't you know this is where the protest
turned violent last week?
Have you looked around?
I really think it's fine.
But I wasn't convinced.
The place looked like a warzone.
Is that a tank?!
That's definitely a bus...
with pandas.
She may have a point.
This doesn't exactly sound like a warcry.
Sing Hallelujah to the Lord!
And the police didn't exactly seem on-edge.
In fact, it didn't eveen seem like
they needed to be there.
Though clearly, someone should've called the
grammar police.
Are you sure it's safe?
Why don't we walk around and talk to some
people?
Okay...
But I'm at least wearing the helmet and the
googles.
Were these a bunch of mastermind rioters
waiting around for a chance to strike?
Or just a bunch of kids standing around,
looking at their cellphones?
Or sitting around, looking at their cellphones?
Or lying around, looking at their cellphones?
Kids these days...
So are you one of these violent protesters
I keep hearing about?
No.
Where are those people?
Sorry?
Where are they?
Where are those violent protesters?
I'm freaked out.
I'm not sure.
Are you one of those violent protestors I've
heard about?
No, no!
Definitely not!
I am a peaceful protester.
That's what a violent protester would say!
Are you one of those violent protestors?
No, I am not, well, I'm scared too.
I don't support being violent.
So you're one of those violent protestors
I've heard about?
Nope.
This doesn't make sense.
Carrie Lam said these were rioters.
Does that mean this wasn't an appropriate
use of force?
Well so then who got violent last week?
Police do the violence first.
The police fired first?
Yeah.
We are peaceful.
We don't want to hurt anyone.
We don't want to hurt police.
We are all Hong Kongers.
So you're putting on the goggles and the helmet
to protect yourself from the police?
Yeah, we have the goggles and the vests already
in case the police put the tear gas
or anything else onto us.
We will do our protection.
So it's some of the police I need to watch
out for?
Yeah, it's the police you should watch out
for -
not the protesters.
I was beginning to think that Carrie Lam
may have been wrong to decribe this -
thank you -
as an organized riot.
I mean, there's been absolutely zero looting
in a place with a lot of high-end stores and
malls.
Crowds even moved out of the way for an ambulance.
Okay, I found the water guy.
There's also a couple of water guys, too.
And also a lot of water stations.
Someone also offered Shelley a sandwich.
Oh really, oh that's lovely.
It was.
It was very lovely, actually.
It actually makes me want to cook up a bunch
of sandwiches
and bring them here, and be like, hey,
anyone want some?
Anyone hungry?
I'll wait here for those sandwiches.
I'm beginning to think I may have overracted.
Slightly.
Hey.
What's wrong?
Oh you know, I just witnessed
a once in a lifetime historic moment
of a group of nonviolent protesters with no leader
changing the world.
Isn't that a good thing?
Yeah, I guess,
but I was hoping to become the leader of the revolution myself.
But I guess they don't need me.
Don't worry, you'll always have China Uncensored.
Thanks, Shelley.
I think this is the continuation of a beautiful
friendship.