On this episode of China Uncensored:
Looking for the perfect man?
You’ve found him!
No, not me, but thank you.
It’s the latest Chinese dating simulator.
And it’s got Chinese women swiping right.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
China has a gender problem.
And not just because there are too many men.
There’s also too much competition...
from virtual boyfriends.
It’s dating simulator Love and Producer.
Which is a name that totally makes sense.
You play as a female TV producer
struggling to save your
late father’s production company,
while falling in love with these
four heartthrobs.
Zhou Qiluo, the carefree pop icon.
Bai Qi, the police officer
that makes you feel safe.
Xu Mo, the genius scientist,
as smart as he is sensitive,
and Li Zeyan, the successful CEO.
Oh Li Zeyan, you can be the lord of my world
any day.
Wait, why is he pulling a gun on me?
Wow, dating simulators are intense.
Which I’m obviously just discovering
because I’ve never played one before.
This game, Love and Producer,
“has accumulated more than 2 million
daily active users
since its launch in December,
with the overwhelming majority
being females in their early 20s.”
Of course winning in love isn’t easy.
You see, in the game,
men are attracted to purple diamonds.
Just like in real life.
So if you want to go on a date with
one of these eligible bachelors,
you need to give them
one of your purple diamonds.
You can get them either by completing
in-game missions,
which is hard—
or, the much easier way,
using real money to buy them.
And Chinese women have spent
around 32 million dollars on it.
It’s hard to underscore
just how successful this game has been
with Chinese women.
But perhaps this will give you an idea.
Fans of my favorite character,
Li Zeyan,
who has the superpower to freeze time,
in case you were wondering—
well, his fans spent almost 40 thousand dollars
to have this happy birthday message
written on the side of a skyscraper in Shenzhen.
That’s a wonderful gift.
For the people who created the dating simulator.
So what do you think of the obsession
with Love and Producer?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Let me guess,
you think that app should have the option
to give a purple diamond
to a fun-loving TV host from New York, right?
Well if you want more of me,
head over to ChinaUncensored.tv,
where you can see all our episodes,
including ones you won’t see on YouTube.
Once again that’s ChinaUncensored.tv.