China is using the New Zealand Massacre
to justify mass surveillance of Muslims in
China
Are you really surprised?
This is China Uncensored,
I’m Chris Chappell.
The March 15 massacre
at a mosque in Christchurch, New Zealand
shocked the world.
A lone gunman killed 50 Muslims.
This is and will be one of New Zealand’s
darkest days.
Now we can all agree it was a dark day for
New Zealand.
But no country was hurt more by this senseless
massacre, than China.
That’s because the Chinese Communist Party
deeply loves all Muslims.
You can tell by how they treat
some of the Muslims under their own rule—
the ethnic Uighurs in the Xinjiang Uyghur
Autonomous region.
The Chinese regime has installed a mass surveillance
system
unlike anything the world has ever seen.
“The security here is incredibly tight.
There are armored cars on the street.
Police stations on every corner.
And tons of surveillance cameras.
In the past year,
police have stepped up security.
The region is now under probably
the most intense government surveillance in
the world.”
Wow.
The Communist Party is really sparing
no effort to keep the Uighurs safe.
And the New Zealand Massacre
is an important reminder as to why.
At least according to the Xinjiang government.
Why, they’ve event sent a fax to the Wall
Street Journal
saying just that.
The fax said,
“The recent mass shooting in New Zealand
that harmed so many innocent lives is a strong
warning.
The goal of improving security at mosques
is to protect the ability of the Muslim community
to hold normal, orderly religious activities.”
Yes, the Chinese regime
is using the New Zealand massacre
to justify its mass surveillance of Muslims.
And don’t forget,
according to my favorite Chinese state-run
media,
the Global Times,
it’s a model worth copying.
The Xinjiang government felt they needed to
straighten things out with the Wall Street
Journal
in their fax.
Yes, the country with the world’s
most advanced surveillance system
wants you to know,
it still relies on the world’s
least advanced communication system.
A few weeks ago, the Wall Street Journal published
this article.
And they showed this satellite footage of
a Uighur neighborhood being razed to the ground.
But the Chinese fax clarified,
“This argument that ‘shantytown redevelopment
is intended to force some Uighur migrants
to leave the city and place others in residential
buildings
that are easier to monitor’
is a slanderous fabrication.”
Again, the surveillance is for their safety!
Why is it so hard for people in the West
to understand that to keep you safe,
it’s necessary for the government
to monitor you at all times?
Otherwise how will they know if
you’re being threatened by dangerous beliefs?
Like a belief in a higher power.
Other than the Communist Party, of course.
And safety is also why Chinese authorities
are working hard to bring that kind of surveillance
to the rest of China.
It will make for a more trusting society.
Don’t agree?
Well, “Denouncing the Chinese system
from a Western point of view
is tantamount to a neo-imperialistic attitude.”
The fax to the Wall Street Journal
also criticized the paper for lying about
so-called internment camps in Xinjiang.
“According to the UN,
authorities are detaining as many as a million
Uighurs
in facilities like the one we saw in Urumqi.
Satellite images show how China’s government
has built these facilities at a frenetic pace.”
Gah, those no good satellites.
Don’t worry,
I don’t think they’ll be a problem for
long.
Also, those so-called internment camps
are actually just job training centers...
that also combat extremist thinking.
With job training.
And that’s why the people in those training
centers are so happy.
“If you’re happy and you know it clap
your hands.”
So what do you think of China
using the New Zealand Massacre
to justify mass surveillance of Muslims in
Xinjiang?
Tell me what you think in the comments below.
And now it’s time for me to answer a question
from one of you—
a fan who support China Uncensored
with a dollar or more per episode,
by contributing through Patreon.
Rabbit L. Benkei asks,
“Chris, what country would you say
China is most effectively influencing?”
That’s a hard question to answer.
There is barely a country on Earth
that the Chinese Communist Party isn’t influencing.
That was something I really realized
after I went to the Oslo Freedom Forum in
2018.
It’s a big human rights conference
where activists around the world talk about
their struggles with authoritarian regimes.
And it seemed like no matter which country
they come from,
the Chinese Communist Party was somehow
working there behind the scenes.
It’s not just authoritarian countries, either.
Western liberal democracies like the United
States
are also being heavily influenced.
China has tremendous sway over Hollywood.
American politicians have been influenced
and bought off.
Got a 401K?
Or mutual funds?
Odds are some of your money is invested in
China.
And with China setting its sights on the moon
And Mars,
It may even be trying to influence other planets.
But which country is the Chinese regime influencing
most?
I’d say Taiwan.
They’ve tried to interfere with Taiwan’s
elections.
They pump money into Taiwan
to influence politicians and business leaders.
And they’ve forced the government
to spend enormous resources
preparing for a Chinese military invasion
of their island.
On the other hand,
maybe Taiwan isn’t the country most influenced—
since according to the Chinese regime,
Taiwan’s not a country;
it’s been a province of China since ancient
times.
Thanks for your question, Rabbit.
And thanks to all my 50-Cent Army soldiers
who support China Uncensored.
It’s only because of your support
that we’ve been able to cover topics like
this,
that most other media don’t want to.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.