On this episode of China Uncensored,
how the Chinese Communist Party is influencing
Australian politics.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I'm Chris Chappell.
Chinese money has been pouring into Australia
over the past few years.
Some of it is connected to the Chinese Communist
Party--
and it's being used to influence
the Australian government and its policies.
So I sat down with Craig Kelly--
who's a representative in Australia's
House of Representatives--
to talk about why this is such a big deal.
Thank you for joining us, Mr. Kelly.
So, the Chinese communist party is
buying influence with Australian members of
Parliament.
What's the going rate these days?
Very funny question.
We saw our ex-Labor senator, Senator Dastyari,
accept a couple of thousand dollars that we
know about
from influential Chinese businessmen and actually
being forced to resign from the Senate.
So, the price seems to coming at the moment.
It seems like to sell out your country,
a thousand dollars,
a couple thousand isn't that much.
Well, look. What the real issue with Mr. Dastyari
was that the Australian government,
both the coalition, which is in government
now and the Labor party who are the opposition
had a bipartisan position on China's influence
in the South China Sea.
What Senator Dastyari actually did ...
he went to our Parliamentary offices in Sydney,
special Parliamentary office of Federal
Parliamentarians where special interviews
are held
with heads of state, went into the commandeered
the
main interview room, and took two left turns
with the
Australian crests in front to give all the
official,
stood on one, looked to himself,
had his Chinese business friend on the other
lead turn, and basically went and said views
that were completely contrary to both his
own party,
the Australian government, the Parliament
of
Australia's position on the South China Sea.
So, he made it look very official.
He made it look very official that he was
actually taking,
if you want to call it,
the Chinese communist party's position.
Contrary to all other international positions
in Australia
and almost every other nation in the world
on the South China Sea,
and then we find out later that he'd been
accepting money from this Chinese businessman
to help pay some of his legal bills.
And it isn't just Sam Dastyari.
How else have you seen Chinese communist party
infiltration affect Australian politics?
Look, I'll give you one example.
I was at function last year,
and there was a lot of Chinese businessmen,
and I just went along as my position
of member or Parliament.
We have invitation.
At the time, Shen Yun, the ballet,
in the play, in the opera,
the play or ballet, opera play.
I'm not sure.
Chinese classical dance.
Classical dance, which has been
shown in Sydney was on.
Now, I've been in the Shen Yun before.
They're invited. I liked it.
I must admit I'm a more sort of football
and sporting type of guy
that would rather go to a sporting event
than something at the ballet,
so although I enjoyed it,
I'd prefer to go the football
if I had my choice.
That's right. Yes.
So, now this very high-ranking
Chinese government official said to me
at the time,
"You shouldn't go to these things.
This is not China's official custom.
Therefore, you shouldn't go."
I didn't really have any great intention of
going,
but I said to him ... I said,
"Look. We also have a custom in Australia.
And when people tell us not to do something,
it makes us want to go and do it."
I said, "So I was actually ... "
So, I said, "Well, I was actually going to
watch the football that day,
but now I just might go and see it."
That actually sounds a lot like how
Americans respond to that sort of thing.
That certainly is.
And actually, how has this Chinese communist
party
infiltration affected U.S. Australia relationship?
Well, look we have very close relationship
with the U.S.A.
So, Australia's relationship,
our trade relationship,
our belief in freedom of speech,
democracy, all those freedoms
that we hold so dearly are equally held
by Australians and Americans.
Do you think the communist party
is trying to drive a wedge between
our two countries?
I don't know if I ...
I don't think they'll be able to achieve that.
I did just want to say the communist party
is trying to buy influence in Australia,
but partnering with the U.S.,
there can be a lot of benefits to us as well.
Very good, I guess. Absolutely.
That looks very good.
I'll put that on my desk in
Parliament House proudly, very proudly.
Oh, see it's yours. No, it's yours.
Thank you. Thank you.
So, what can Australian politicians
and officials do in the face of
communist party infiltration?
One issue is also that we have
very big economic ties with China,
and that's the commercial reality of the world.
China is our biggest export market,
so of course, we need good relations with
China.
That's just the bottom line economics,
but we have to tread those lines carefully.
I think one thing that from my business dealings
with China before I came into politics
is they respect if you are firm.
If you show signs of weakness, if you show
signs of appeasement, they just take advantage
of that.
Do you support the foreign interference laws?
Yeah. Absolutely.
They're important laws.
We need to make sure that the outcome of the
elections
in Australia are determined by the Australian
people.
That's what we need to do at the moment.
There's evidence of influence of foreign money
coming in to influence those elections,
and that's what we need to stamp out.
And do you think there's any risk
that the laws are written in a vague way
that could have negatively affected Chinese
Australians?
I don't think so, not at all.
I think the ... Look,
we have many people from China
that have settled in Australia.
One of the reasons that they've settled
is because of our democratic systems
and democratic beliefs,
and the right that they get to go
to their polling booth and vote
for whoever they want to.
If they don't like the way the government
is going,
they can stand up, and they protest
as loudly as they like without knowing
there's any going to be sort of come back
or sanctions against the person.
I know you've actually spoken up on behalf
of Chinese Australian groups
that are often victimized by the Chinese communist
party.
Have you faced any consequences for that?
I haven't personally, no.
But, it is ... we have ...
This is an area that all of us in politics
know that we have to tread carefully
because we don't want to be doing things
that actually upset our trading relationship
with China because that's very important to
us.
So, how do you balance keeping
a good relationship with China?
Well, I think most ...
most important thing that I've seen
that Chinese respect strength.
If you show them you have a solid position
on a certain issue,
and you are not going to bend
or weaken on that,
I think that's what they respect.
Well, thank you very much for joining me today.
And let's have a little cheers
to the future.
We'll celebrate. Absolutely. Thank you.
Just wanted to give a big thank you to all of our supporters on Patreon.
Because of you, we're able to come to Australia to cover these great topics.
So if you're interested in supporting us on Patreon, click the button below.