On this episode of China Uncensored,
you’re princess isn’t in another castle.
She’s been kidnapped by...
Chinese censors.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
Video games makers are no strangers to censorship.
The very first controversial video game came in 1976.
The arcade game Death Race,
where you run over “gremlins” in your
car.
Barbaric.
And of course, it only got worse from there.
I think I’m going to be sick.
Now there are a lot of different opinions
about the degree to which video games should
or shouldn’t be censored
mainly over the level of violence.
But now China has taken video game censorship to a
whole new level.
For years, the Chinese regime had banned video
game consoles.
Although that ban has now been lifted—restrictions
apply.
But it’s left a void that allowed a flourishing
mobile game market.
The biggest in the world, in fact.
In 2015, that market was worth 7 billion dollars,
with 400 million gamers consuming
10,000 games released that year alone.
That’s about 27 new games a day.
But this is about to be a thing of the past.
As of this month,
Chinese censors will need to approve every
mobile game before it’s released.
Games that are already released
will have to retroactively get approval before
an October deadline.
The government organ in charge of this is
the State Administration of Press, Publication,
Radio, Film and Television.
And now apparently games?
SAPPRFTG?
They really need to work on those acronyms.
Anyway, the guidelines allow the Chinese authorities
to ban pretty much any game they want.
For example, some developers in China
have reported their games got canned
because they contained English words.
Not politically charged words.
Pointless video game words
like “mission start” and “warning.”
Others have reported similar problems
with games containing traditional Chinese
characters
that’s what they use in Hong Kong and Taiwan,
but not the Mainland.
Doesn’t stop there.
The Cyberspace Administration of China
is the agency responsible for censorship and
control over China’s Internet.
Starting August 1st,
mobile app developers will be required
to give users’ personal information to the
agency.
That’s crazy!
I much prefer to voluntarily give all my information
up.
But this isn’t just about censorship.
It’s also about business.
And this is going to kill the indie game scene
in China.
The mobile game market in China is super competitive.
According to one developer interviewed by
Sixth Tone,
“If you’re lucky a game will make you
1,500 yuan.”
That’s about 200 bucks.
But getting your new game approved can cost
over 2,000.
Why so much?
Well, for one, don’t expect the censors
to download your game.
They don’t have time!
You, the developer, have to send them a phone
with an active sim card and data plan,
and your game pre-installed.
Two phones if you’re publishing on iOS and
Android.
It’s a pretty sweet gig, being a Chinese
censor.
It also can take up to 3 months to get your
game approved.
If you’re an indie developer, working alone,
investing your own money into a project,
that’s a long wait for a return on investment.
That is, if everything works smoothly.
This basically means most indie game makers
won’t be able to survive.
Instead, they’ll get stomped on
—like proverbial goombas—
by big corporations like Tencent and Netease,
companies with close ties to the government.
Now these new restrictions don’t apply to
foreign game makers.
They were taken care of back in February.
Foreign companies are required to work with
domestic content providers.
And they now need to get approval from...
SAPPRFT...
for online publication of any “creative
works.”
Wait, so does that mean
they don’t need approval if their games
aren’t very creative?
There might be a future for Great Giana Sisters
after all!
So what do you think about the future of gaming
in China?
Is there room for a sequel?
Or will it be game over?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell. See you
next time.