On this episode of China Uncensored,
get your nuclear submarine ready,
because we’re diving down,
into China’s deep state.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
China has long been seen
as the final go between for North Korea
and the rest of the world—
the only country that could do what sanctions
and international condemnation couldn’t—
get North Korea to back down
from its ballistic missile and nuclear program.
Kind of like North Korea's more responsible,
slightly less outwardly totalitarian big brother.
How's that going, by the way?
Yeah, ok, seems to be going really well.
Unfortunately for China, the United States,
and the rest of the world,
North Korea is hitting its difficult teenage
years
and going full-on Rebel Without a Cause.
But instead of this:
You’re tearing me apart!
It's coming off more like this:
You’re tearing me apart, Lisa!
So has the Chinese regime really lost all
sway
over its Communist little brother?
If North Korea carries out its 6th nuclear
test,
would it, as my favorite state-run media
the Global Times says,
take relations beyond the point of no return?
And let me just say,
if the hawkish Global Times,
the ones who’ve said that
“China's nuclear capability should be so
strong
that no country would dare launch
a military showdown with China
under any circumstance,”
is arguing restraint,
you know things are bad.
But you may have noticed that in the past,
China treated North Korea less like
the responsible big brother
who gets you to quit smoking,
and more like the irresponsible big brother
who teaches you how to smoke
in your room with the windows open
so you're mom can't smell it.
China did things like supply 80%
of North Korea's imports.
And the Chinese Communist Party
turned a blind eye to Chinese companies
that violated UN sanctions
by supplying North Korea with,
for example,
nuclear bomb materials.
So what's different now?
Has North Korea just gotten so extreme
with all their nuclear talk
that they're even freaking out the Chinese
regime?
"Bro, I told you you could smoke a couple
of cigarettes
with the windows open,
not light the house on fire!"
Well, it's complicated.
And it all ties back
to China's very own deep state.
Loyal viewers of the show will remember me
talking once or twice about the life-or-death
fight
between former leader and toad-in-the-hole,
Jiang Zemin
and current leader, Xi Jinping.
But North Korea used to be much friendlier
when China was controlled by Xi’s political
rivals,
a faction tied to former Chinese leader, Jiang
Zemin.
Jiang Zemin and former North Korean god emperor,
Kim Jong-il were close.
Really close.
Uncomfortably close.
I guess they really took Mao’s quote
about being as close as lips and teeth
to heart.
By the way,
I fully expect this photo to inspire
some totalitarian leader relationship fanfiction,
because the internet.
North Korea was the first foreign country
Jiang visited after assuming power
in the wake of the Tiananmen Square Massacre.
Primarily because North Korea was the only
country
cool with that sort of thing.
According to this Radio Free Asia article,
Jiang may have even given North Korea
the enriched uranium they needed
to start the nuclear weapons program
in retaliation for all the bad vibes he was
getting
from the rest of the world.
Jiang, you're such a troll.
Now Jiang Zemin is 90,
so he’s not all that active anymore.
Mostly.
But this toad literally dug a hole a
nd planted his own deep state
within the Chinese Communist Party-
loyal followers who carried out his plans
even when he was out of power.
And by the way,
if you've ever wondered why
I don't talk much about Hu Jintao,
the Chinese leader that came between
Jiang and Xi,
it's because Jiang put so many of his people
in positions of power
that they basically crippled Hu
for almost his entire time in office.
In fact, this photo pretty much expresses
how Hu and Xi feel about Jiang.
Anyway, Jiang's faction continued to have
very close ties with North Korea.
And as one China analyst told the Epoch Times,
Jiang’s people, “may have even influenced
the timing of North Korea’s five nuclear tests”
as a distraction whenever their faction
came under attack.
For example,
North Korea conducted its first nuclear test
shortly after one of Jiang's proteges,
and a potential future Party leader,
was sacked for corruption.
And it goes beyond just influencing
North Korea's nuclear tests.
Here's another Jiang guy,
Wang Jiarui.
For 12 years he was the head
of the International Liaison Department.
Here he is with Kim Jong-il.
And Kim Jong-un.
He's the guy who allowed all that trade
between China and North Korea.
Including those nuclear bomb materials.
Then there’s Zhou Yongkang,
known to his friends as "Sunshine"
and one of the highest ranking members
of Jiang’s clique, brought down in Xi Jinping’s
anti corruption campaign.
Before he got purged like the aftermath
of a Fourth of July hot dog eating contest,
he was the head of the Communist Party’s
internal security apparatus,
and one of the biggest supporters
of the Kim dynasty.
Why, he was even there
when Kim Jong-il led his son, Kim Jong-un,
out as the heir apparent.
"Hi kid,
say hello to your Uncle Zhou!"
And speaking of uncles,
Zhou also may have been responsible
for Kim Jong-un's execution of his own.
Kim’s uncle visited China in 2012
to meet with Hu Jintao.
Apparently to discuss stopping North Korea’s
nuclear program
in exchange for economic development,
and replacing Kim Jong-un with his step-brother,
Kim Jong-Nam.
You know,
the one who was just assassinated.
By poison.
But according to this China analyst,
Zhou told Kim about Jang's conversation,
and Kim had his uncle purged.
And executed.
And it continues to this day.
Xi Jinping is opposed by three members
of the Jiang faction
in the Politburo Standing Committee,
the most powerful old dudes in China.
The two Zhangs,
no relation,
both studied in Pyongyang
and have made several state visits.
Here’s Zhang Dejiang with the two Kims.
And here’s Liu Yunshan
having a grand time with Kim Jong-un.
It was under Jiang Zemin and his cronies
that North Korea was able to develop into
the potential nuclear threat it is today.
So it’s not too surprising that Xi Jinping,
the political enemy of North Korea’s Chinese
allies,
has had such a hard time reigning in
the rogue regime.
So can China stop North Korea
from developing a nuclear bomb?
It may depend on how much trouble
Jiang's people can still cause.
Because even though Xi is doing a pretty good
job
of digging out Jiang's faction so far,
the roots go pretty deep.
What do you think about China's ability
to stop North Korea?
Leave your comments below.
And if you’d like to finance
the China Uncensored humor program,
consider making a contribution
on the website Patreon.
Viewer support like yours
is what keeps the show going,
despite Youtube sanctions.
Link is below.
Once again I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.