On this episode of China Uncensored,
what, is this the Roman Empire or something?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored. I'm your
host, Chris Chappell.
Karl Marx, the creator of communism,
said religion is the "opiate of the masses."
And so the Chinese Communist Party set out
to prove
how much more rational and broadminded they
were than
people who partook in silly superstition
by going Hulk smash on it.
Especially during China’s Cultural Revolution
a systematic campaign in the 60s and 70s
where they wiped out religion and traditional
culture.
They destroyed China’s priceless cultural
and spiritual heritage
and even tortured Buddhist monks.
Yeah! That'll…teach people…something.
Probably that when the Chinese Constitution
guarantees freedom of religion,
it's guaranteed in the same way as freedom
of the press.
“This is our own David McKenzie and his
team roughed up by police in Beijing.”
But!
"There’s been an awakening."
That's right, religion in China is on the
rise.
Not for Communist Party members, obviously.
They’re required to be atheist.
But Christianity in particular has seen a
massive resurgence.
There are estimates at this very moment,
there could be 100 million Christians in China
that’s more than there are Communist Party
members!
Hmm, when was the last time I heard about
a 100 million-strong spiritual movement in China
Oh right! Falun Gong.
So you can guess how this is going to go for
Christians.
Actually, you don't have to guess!
There's been a 150% rise in the Chinese government’s
persecution of Christians in just one year
according to last year's annual report by
ChinaAid.
It's particularly bad in Zhejiang Province,
sometimes called the Chinese Jerusalem because
of how many Christians live there.
Pastors have been arrested
and congregations have been assaulted for
defending their churches from being demolished.
Over a thousand crosses have been torn down
there since 2014.
Though to be fair,
the Party did give them the option of destroying
their own crosses first.
The persecution is most severe,
unsurprisingly, for "house" churches.
Those are illegal, unregistered Churches.
Because if you want to have a church,
it’s supposed to be registered with the
government,
so the atheist Communist Party can appoint
the priests and pastors.
That could be why a developer in Henan Province,
who was hired by authorities to demolish one
of these unregistered house churches,
felt he might have been authorized
to bury two people alive who tried to stop
it!
The house church leader, Li Jiangong, and
his wife, Ding Cuimei,
stepped in front of bulldozers to stop the
demolition.
According to ChinaAid, one of the crew said,
"Bury them alive for me. I will be responsible
for their lives."
So the bulldozer knocked them in and buried
them.
Li was able to dig himself out but Ding didn't
survive.
There’s video of this, but it’s pretty
disturbing.
You can watch it here if you want to feel
terrible and angry.
But look: If you think authorities
would tolerate this kind of outrageous behavior,
you’d be wrong.
Authorities have already stepped in…
to pressure Li not to give details to the
media.
Because come on,
there's no need to make people feel bad about
the Communist Party as a whole!
Really, this is only the problem of one single
developer.
What’s that, Shelley?
It’s happened before?
Wow, I would’ve thought killing people with
bulldozers
would have been a one-off thing.
But more importantly,
the Communist Party doesn’t want the media
to know
how widespread and common their persecution
of Christians has become.
Anyway, two perpetrators from the demolition
crew
that killed Ding Cuimei last week are already
being criminally detained.
So come on, justice has been done right? Time
to move on.
Surely, that’ll be the last time Christians
are persecuted in China.
Oh.
So what do you think? What will the future
hold for Christians in China?
Leave your comments below.
And if you like China Uncensored, please consider
supporting us on Patreon.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell. See you
next time.