A Chinese soldier gets lost
And India finds him
Plus China’s hostage diplomacy
And what can the CCP do to find love?
That and more on this week’s China news headlines
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.\h
This week’s China news headlines.
India captured a Chinese\h
soldier along a disputed border.
The Chinese corporal apparently got lost.\h
I believe we have footage of the capture.
Yeah okay, that works.
This disputed border between India and\h
China has been causing a lot of grief.\h\h
Earlier this year, Chinese\h
soldiers killed 20 Indian soldiers.
So at last, a chance for revenge!\h
“The Indian troops fed the\h
captured Chinese soldier a meal.\h\h
They gave him oxygen and some warm clothes.”
And then, they returned him.
I guess the Indian army is going with the\h
“kill them with kindness” form of revenge.\h
According to the PLA, the soldier got lost “while\h
helping local herdsmen search for missing yaks.”
Wow, this is a rare story where everyone comes\h
out looking good. Congratulations everyone.\h
I hope China will treat the Americans it's\h
threatening to kidnap as nicely as the Indian\h\h
soldiers treated the PLA soldier. Because China\h
is now actually threatening to detain Americans.
That’s because the US has recently arrested\h
at least 5 Chinese scholars—scholars\h\h
who broke the law by not disclosing their\h
military affiliations on their visa applications.\h\h
And they may have been spying\h
on US research centers.
The US State Department would just like to remind\h
Americans about its travel advisory on China.\h\h
Which they updated back in September to Level 3:\h\h
Reconsider Travel, “due to COVID-19 and\h
arbitrary enforcement of local laws”.
And they specifically call out the risk of\h
arbitrary and wrongful detentions in China and the\h\h
use of exit bans. Exit bans are when you’re not\h
actually imprisoned, but you can’t leave China.\h
Meanwhile China obviously denies that report. And\h
says the US is mistreating the Chinese scholars.
So if you’re an American in China,\h\h
should you be worried? We’ll have more on\h
that in a future episode, so stay tuned.\h
But China’s “hostage diplomacy” is nothing new.\h
At the end of 2018, China detained two Canadians,\h\h
Michael Kovrig and Michael Spavor.\h
That was in retaliation for Canada\h\h
arresting the CFO of Huawei, Meng Wanzhou. She\h
was accused of violating US sanctions on Iran.\h
Canada still has not been able to\h
get China to release their citizens.\h\h
At a high level UN Security\h
Council Meeting this week,\h\h
colleagues of the two detained men appealed\h
directly to China for their release.
That happened just a few days after\h
Canadian Prime Minister Justin Trudeau\h\h
said Canada won’t stop calling\h
for human rights in China.
He said that because the Chinese ambassador\h
to Canada warned Canada not to accept Hong\h\h
Kong refugees. “He said that could have\h
consequences for the ‘health and security’\h\h
for the 300,000 Canadians living in the\h
theoretically autonomous Chinese territory.”
So...he’s threatening that if Canada\h
tries to make Hong Kong people safe,\h\h
China will make Canadians in Hong Kong less safe.\h
Yeah, it sounds like appealing\h
directly to China to release\h\h
the two Canadian Michaels is\h
probably not going to work.\h
Meanwhile, US diplomats in China are\h
being monitored by the Communist Party.\h\h
According to leaked documents\h
obtained by the Epoch Times,\h\h
“Chinese authorities see U.S. Consulates as\h
‘hostile forces’ that conduct ‘infiltration\h\h
and sabotage’ activities on Chinese soil and have\h
ordered officials to monitor key U.S. diplomats.”
Although, I’m going to go out on a\h
limb and say that US diplomats in China\h\h
probably already know they’re being monitored.\h
According to one leaked document, which is\h
from 2018, the Chinese Communist Party was\h\h
especially concerned with “blocking [the\h
consulates] from establishing connections\h\h
with key [Chinese] political\h
figures, prominent lawyers,\h\h
‘public intellectuals,’ ‘rights\h
defenders,’ and special interest groups”
How did Party officials plan to stop that from\h
happening? The document advised officials to\h\h
“‘Use all efforts’—including ‘reminders,\h
warnings, and a mild degree of force’”\h\h
to stop those people from being able to\h
attend events held by the US consulates.
Hey, what’s wrong with using a mild\h
degree of force on your own citizens?\h\h
It’s for their own good!\h
And we’ll be back with more news after the break.
Welcome back.
China has passed an export control law after\h
the US did the same to China last month.
“[The] controlled items include\h
military and nuclear products,\h\h
as well as other goods, technologies\h
and services and relevant data.”
You know, all the things the US so\h
desperately relies on China for.\h
Meanwhile, China is also forcing Chinese\h
textiles to stop using Australian cotton.
That follows similar action on\h
Australian beef and coal. Now some might\h\h
call this a trade war, which\h
would be totally unoriginal.\h\h
And I wouldn’t want to accuse the Chinese regime\h
of just copying things that other countries do.
As my favorite Chinese state-run media,\h
the Global Times says “Such groundless\h\h
speculation by Western media outlets is a clear\h
reflection of [the Australian government’s]\h\h
hostility toward China and its attempt to\h
push China to import more Australia cotton.”
I mean sure China’s ban on Australian imports\h
will hurt Australian farmers in the short run.\h\h
But that’s not China’s fault.\h
According to the Global Times,\h\h
this is simply the result of market competition.
And the Chinese Communist Party\h
is all about the free market.
And not to worry, because China can get\h
all the cotton it needs from Xinjiang—where\h\h
forced labor is just part of\h
China’s incredibly free market.
Hey, it’s just a mild degree of\h
forced labor. It’s for their own good!
Sweden has banned Chinese telecom companies Huawei\h\h
and ZTE because they’re\h
controlled by the Chinese state.
But that’s just the beginning of what\h
happened in the past week around the world.
In a virtual summit with Brazil,\h
US Secretary of State Mike Pompeo\h\h
said the two countries need to reduce\h
their dependence on imports from China.
And now Brazil is saying it won’t buy\h
a Chinese made coronavirus vaccine.
The US also blacklisted two Chinese men and six\h
Chinese entities for violating sanctions on Iran.
And that comes on top of a US\h
warning to international banks\h\h
about violating US sanctions on Hong Kong.
I don’t get it. It’s like the world is for some\h
reason afraid of the Chinese Communist Party.\h\h
What more can the Communist\h
Party do to make people love it?
Wait, I know, you catch more flies\h
with honey than vinegar right?\h\h
China can just sell us some\h
sweeteners! It's the perfect plan.
Except the US had to go and seize\h
imports of a Chinese sweetener,\h\h
just because China used a little\h
bit of free market slave labor.
The US government found that a\h
Chinese company in Inner Mongolia\h\h
was producing the sweetener\h
stevia using prison labor.\h
This was the first forced labor finding issued\h
by US Customs and Border Control since 1996.
The US agency said that the finding “tells U.S.\h
importers who fail to eliminate forced labor from\h\h
their supply chains that their shipments\h
may be subject to seizure and forfeiture.”
But what if it was just a\h
mild degree of forced labor?\h
Given what we know about Chinese supply chains,\h
I have a feeling that the US government is\h\h
going to be doing a lot more of\h
these seizures in the future.\h
And now it’s time for me to\h
answer a question from one of you,\h\h
who supports China Uncensored through\h
the crowdfunding website Patreon.
James Wallberg asks,\h\h
“Chris what will you and the China Uncensored\h
crew do after the CCP is overthrown?\h
Well, that will be a glorious day\h
when the CCP finally bites the dust.\h\h
At one point I would have said that as soon\h
as that happens, Matt, Shelley and I would fly\h\h
over to China and celebrate and see the sights.\h
I’d say we more than earned a little vacation.\h
But then we started our\h
other show America Uncovered.\h\h
And judging by how things are in the\h
US, I don’t think we’ll ever get a\h\h
chance to retire. If you haven’t yet, please\h
subscribe to America Uncovered on YouTube.
Thanks for your question James.
And if you’d like to have me respond to\h
your question or comment on the show for\h\h
hundreds of thousands of people to hear, join\h
what I call the China Uncensored 50 Army...
and support us in the battle against the Chinese\h
Communist Party. You can join for as little as a\h\h
dollar per episode on the crowd funding website\h
Patreon. You’ll also get some other cool perks\h\h
as well. Head over to Patreon.com/China\h
Uncensored to learn more. Link is below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell. See you next time.