On this episode of China Uncensored,
just when you thought it couldn't get any
more complicated
than a territorial dispute between China,
Taiwan, Vietnam, Malaysia, Brunei,
and the Philippines, well...
Indonesia had to show up
like a...seventh wheel.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I'm your
maritime mariner, Chris Chappell.
The South China Sea is becoming a powder keg!
And who is to blame?!
"It is exactly one country and let me not
avoid mentioning the name:
that is, the Philippines…"
Well, umm, I don't think that's really…
"We are on high alert for Japan's moves in
the South China Sea."
Ok, no, it's not Japan this time either.
"I suggest to the media that in your reports
you not selectively pump up or ignore things."
Okay, fine! Everyone's stirring up trouble
in the South China Sea!
In fact, there is only one country not stirring
up trouble:
Indonesia.
"And lastly I reiterate that Indonesia is
not a claimant state in South China Sea issue."
Finally! A country actually not involved in
the South China Sea dispute!
It's almost too good to be true!
"On March 19, the Chinese fishing boat was
attacked by an Indonesian armed boat."
Oh. It was too good to be true.
You see, on Saturday, Indonesian authorities
"attacked" a Chinese fishing vessel in "traditional
Chinese fishing grounds."
Of course, by "attack,"
the Chinese Foreign Ministry means Indonesia
fired warning shots into the air
while approaching the Chinese vessel that
was fishing there illegally.
And by "traditional Chinese fishing grounds,"
they mean Indonesia's Exclusive Economic Zone,
located within 200 miles around the Natuna
Islands.
Don't worry, I didn't know what the Natuna
Islands were either.
Apparently, they're here, outside the giant
area of the South China Sea covered by China's
ridiculously large
I mean, historically accurate
Nine-dash line.
But a small part of the 200-mile Exclusive
Economic Zone around the Natuna islands does
overlap with the Nine-dash line.
Fortunately, Saturday's incident is nothing
like what happened back in 2013,
when Indonesian authorities caught other another
Chinese fishing vessel.
That time, a Chinese patrol ship came,
armed with mounted machine guns and demanded
they release the boat and crew.
This time the Chinese coast guard was much
better behaved.
They merely followed Indonesian authorities
through their Economic Zone,
into Indonesian territorial waters,
then began literally ramming the Chinese fishing
boat until they released it.
The eight-person Chinese crew is still in
Indonesian custody,
but China has called for their release.
Now Indonesia has typically stayed out of
South China Sea territorial disputes
partly because Indonesia's waters are so far
away from China, it's kind of ridiculous.
But now, that may have changed.
"With the events which unfolded yesterday
we feel that we were interrupted and sabotaged
in our efforts and our years of works to promote
peace in the South China Sea."
Wait a minute, Indonesia.
Your efforts to promote peace?
Didn't you know that China is the one doing
all the peace promotion?
"And, we don't hope to see anymore close-up
military reconnaissance or the dispatch of
missile destroyers or strategic bombers to
the South China Sea.
This is something we have a responsibility
for under our non-militarization commitment."
See? Non-militarization commitment.
Except last month, when this was reported.
"The Chinese military has deployed an advanced surface to air missile system on one of the disputed
islands in the south China Sea."
Or shortly after that.
"China deploys war planes to disputed South
China Sea Islands."
But compared to previous times Indonesia has
dealt with illegal Chinese fishing vessels,
their response this time has been much stronger.
"Indonesia will summon China's ambassador
over an incident involving a Chinese fishing
vessel in the Natuna Sea."
Summoning the Ambassador?
That’s a pretty bold move for a country
that relies on China as its largest trading partner.
But here's the thing:
China doesn't even dispute Indonesia's territorial
claims.
"The sovereignty of the Natuna Islands belongs
to Indonesia.
China has no objections to this."
Yet China insists that their fishermen were
still in traditional Chinese fishing grounds?
I guess there is something to be said for
tradition.
If everyone just respects each other's traditional
fishing grounds, then we should be fine.
What's that, Shelley?
Ok, nevermind then.
But anyway, the biggest problem for China
is that by alienating Indonesia,
they may have lost the closest thing to a
neutral ally in the South China Sea disputes
disputes that have put China at odds with
pretty much everyone else.
So how do you think this incident will affect
Indonesia's involvement in South China Sea?
Leave your comments below.
And remember to subscribe for more episodes
of China Uncensored.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell, see you next
time.