On this episode of China Uncensored,
oh there’s nothing comic about this.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored; I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
You know, my mama always said
you should never talk about religion or politics
over the dinner table.
Well, I would add to that one more highly
sensitive topic—comic books.
More specifically, movie adaptations of comic
books.
Nothing is more certain to generate a hellstorm
on Internet forums
than minor changes made to beloved characters.
Or the occasional flaming train wreck.
But the most recent atrocity to befall comic
bookdom
was the decision to change the Ancient One,
a Tibetan male sorcerer in Doctor Strange,
to a white woman in the upcoming movie.
The movie’s creators have been lambasted
for what’s being called another example
of Hollywood “whitewashing.”
But earlier this month, actress Tilda Swinton,
who has been cast as the Ancient One,
said there were “very great reasons” for
the changes.
The greatest reason of all, it turns out,
may have been money.
On the Double Toasted podcast,
Doctor Strange movie writer C. Robert Cargill
explained why Tilda Swinton was cast as the
Ancient One.
And the answer is
to make sure the Chinese Communist Party doesn’t
ban their movie.
The Thing with the Ancient Once is it is Marvel’s
Kobayashi Maru.
Hey, now, I don’t believe in no-win scenarios!
But please, carry on.
“He originates from Tibet,
so if you acknowledge that Tibet is a place
and that he’s Tibetan,
you...risk the Chinese government going,
‘Hey, you know one of the biggest film-watching
countries in the world?
We’re not going to show your movie because
you decided to get political.’”
OK, I’m pretty sure the CCP is not arguing
that Tibet doesn’t exist.
In fact, according to state-run media,
“Tibetans now live a free, prosperous and
civilized life,
and with the loving care and efforts of the
Central Government.”
Just look at how happy she is!
And besides, Cargill later hit Control-Z on
that interview,
saying he wasn’t representing Marvel when
he said that.
But the problem is that Tibet is still a very
politically sensitive issue.
And if you mention it in your very expensive
movie,
you run the risk of being denied access
to one of the world’s most lucrative movie
markets.
Brad Pitt still has trouble getting his movies
shown in China
because he was in 7 Years in Tibet almost
20 years ago.
The Communist Party only allows 34 foreign
films a year
and they have to get approval from censors.
Specifically, the State Administration of
Press, Publication, Radio, Film and Television,
or SAPPRFT.
I'm starting to see a pattern here.
So it makes sense Marvel would alter their
movie
about a hero standing up to evil...
by appeasing a tyrannical government.
And if this is Marvel kowtowing to the Chinese
government,
it wouldn’t be the first time.
For example, do you remember this scene from
Iron Man 3?
No, of course you don’t.
It was only in the Chinese version.
See, Iron Man 3 was a co-production with a
Chinese studio,
which means it didn't have to compete with
other foreign films
for one of those coveted 34 film slots a year.
And you can make more money this way.
A foreign film studio can only get 25% of
box office profits from China,
but in a co-production,
the foreign studio can keep almost 50%.
But that also means you have to shoot part
of your film in China,
cast Chinese actors, have Chinese investors,
or show "positive Chinese images."
And that's why Marvel added several totally
unnecessary scenes to the Chinese version
of Iron Man 3,
featuring famous Chinese actors,
and famous Chinese product placement.
And to appease Chinese censors,
Marvel allowed censors to vet the script for
the entire film.
And it worked! Iron Man 3 got into China
and made an extra 95 million dollars there!
Other movies have done it, too.
In the film Looper,
they changed the idealistic future from Paris
to Shanghai.
Because what could be more ideal
than another 60-plus years of Communist Party
rule?
And in the 2012 Red Dawn remake,
the enemy that attacked America was China....
when they shot it.
But after being criticized by a Chinese newspaper,
they reportedly spent a million dollars to
digitally change the baddie in post-production
to North Korea.
So for Doctor Strange,
Marvel had a real conundrum.
And they solved it by casting the spiritual
teacher as a white woman.
Who’s Celtic.
A group known for their love of Asian temples
and martial arts.
I mean, they could have cast a famous Chinese
actor...as...a...Tibetan.
Ok, that’s also pretty racist
that whole all-Asians-look-the-same thing.
Hmm...ok.
Hey, I got it! If you’re going to change
it to a Celtic woman,
why not just change the character from Tibetan
to Han Chinese.
Knows kung fu, qigong, mystic powers
hey the CCP would probably actually love that!
Oh, but then Dr. Strange is still the white
hero goes to Asia for enlightenment
and then becomes the best trope.
Which is still a bad stereotype.
And I guess the mystic powers might be a little
much,
since censors don't want to promote "superstition"
either.
Actually, in that case...
Doctor Strange may have a hard time getting
into China
even without Tibetan monks.
Wow, I guess this really is a no-win scenario.
Especially when you have filmmakers unabashedly
kowtowing to China.
Of course, Marvel did sort of solve this issue
in Iron Man 3.
The villain The Mandarin was played by Sir
Ben Kingsley,
who is...not Mandarin.
Marvel walked the edge of the whitewashing/racist
Fu Manchu villain issue
by writing the Mandarin as an unemployed actor
who was just a front for the real villain.
So I suppose there's a chance that Marvel
could pull something off
that adequately explains why a Celtic mystic
is living in the Himalayas.
So what do you think of Marvel’s decision
to change the Ancient One from a Tibetan dude
to a Celtic woman?
Leave your comments below. Once again I’m
Chris Chappell, see you next time.