On this episode of China Uncensored,
move over pizza rat,
there’s a new rodent in town!
On the Internet.
And by the way,
this episode has some graphic photos.
So hide your children.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Ahh, childhood in China.
It’s come a long way since the days of Mao’s
cultural revolution.
Kids are no longer encouraged to
purge rightist elements in society
with stolen military weapons.
Now they mainly just have to take exams.
But that doesn’t mean childhood
is without its joys!
In China,
the land of knockoffs,
there’s always fun-filled slightly imperfect
versions
of beloved Disney Classics.
From toys,
to movies
To...oh my gosh!
I don’t remember that scene in Ratatouille…
This image has become the biggest thing on the Chinese internet
over the past several days.
Yes, even bigger than using fake Donald Trump tweets
to wish your family a happy new year.
Now I don’t know who ratted him out,
but apparently this little guy was caught
stealing rice.
And rather than a simple extermination,
it was given the Cultural Revolution treatment.
This sign says
“I won’t dare do it again.”
Get it?!
Cause he’s dead...
or I guess he will be soon.
Honestly, people just don’t have a sense
of humor anymore.
Apparently, of the almost 6,000 comments this
image got
on Weibo, China’s version of Twitter,
many “weren’t finding it funny.”
What’s wrong with a little unnecessary cruelty
against a helpless creature
that also conjures up memories of a time of
constant inhuman torture
and suffering the Chinese Communist Party
forced upon its citizens?!
That’s the problem with kids these days.
They weren’t brought up committing
or being victimized by atrocities that will
haunt them
for the rest of their lives.
This is a sign of changing social mores in
China.
In the early days of the Communist Revolution,
life was, how shall we say...
cheap?
Like when Chairman Mao said this in 1957,
when talking about why he wasn't afraid of
nuclear war:
There are 2.7 billion people in the world;
it doesn’t matter if some are killed.
China has a population of 600 million;
even if half of them are killed,
there are still 300 million people left.
Demonstrating a strong grasp of math and population
control,
both of which would continue to guide the
Party for decades.
People back then were encouraged to kill pests,
whether they be sparrows
or landowners.
Seriously,
that was a landowner about to be shot.
But don’t start hating on Chinese people.
You should actually be hating on
the Chinese Communist Party.
It was the Party that wiped out China’s
traditional values
as a way to establish its own ideology.
It was the Party that told people
it was fine to kill landowners for the crime
of...
owning land—
and then forced or brainwashed its citizens
into taking part.
So after one or two generations of this,
well, you can see why even today,
you’ll find cases of people doing things
like,
oh I don’t know,
adopting dogs, plural,
and feeding them to their pet snake.
He posted a video of it online.
And no, I’m not going to show it to you.
But on the other hand,
there’s a growing movement of Chinese people
going the other way.
Remember the story I ran
about the world’s saddest polar bear?
Thousands of Chinese citizens petitioned
and got him removed from his horrible display
case
at the mall.
And even Chinese celebrities
are speaking out for animal rights.
You don’t have to play ball to be a great
shot blocker.
Never buy illegal wildlife products.
I know what you’re thinking.
Who releases an elephant and Yao Ming into
a basketball court
and then starts shooting?
But the mind of a poacher is a hard thing
to understand.
By the way,
Yao Ming was part of a selective breeding
program by the state
to create a basketball superstar.
Just a fun little aside.
But there is a growing animal rights movement
in China.
And they’re trying to change the fact
that China is the only major industrialized
nation
with no serious legislation against animal
cruelty.
And that could affect things like the
Yulin Dog Meat Eating Festival,
where 10,000 dogs are served as food every
year.
That’s not how you wok the dog.
Or the practice of making tiger wine.
Or whatever’s going on here.
Oh my gosh.
Poor Yogi.
And Boo-Boo.
So from now on,
if you’re going to reference the cultural
revolution in a photo,
at least leave it for your graduation photo.
So what do you think about the picture?
Does the rat’s punishment fit its crime?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.