Once a British Colony
Hong Kong may have developed...
But now it’s ruled by A Communist Dictatorship!
See how people in Hong Kong celebrate
their Un-Independence Day
Welcome to China Uncensored I'm your host
Chris Chappell.
Coming to you from Hong Kong.
This episode is sponsored by Surfshark...
because if you’re going to be protesting
an authoritarian government,
you’re going to want a reliable VPN to hide
your identity.
I’m here at the beautiful Victoria park
on this lovely summer day.
July 1 is a special time for Hong Long.
It's the city’s unindependence day,
when people celebrate the 1997 transition
from British colonial rule to communist dictatorship.
There were marching bands,
Crowds cheering
And of course, delicious barbequed...
whatever that is.
I probably don’t want to know.
The celebrations began before dawn,
when all these happy people gathered for
the annual flag raising ceremony.
That’s when the Hong Kong government,
including the unelected Chief Executive,
raises both the Hong Kong flag,
and the People’s Republic of China flag.
To show how happy everyone is,
to have been handed over from the UK...
and reunited with the motherland.
I’m sure they’re all smiling under those
masks.
Of course with so many people ready to demonstrate
their love for the motherland,
the Hong Kong government decided to deploy
5,000 riot police.
And layer after layer of barricades.
Barricades taller than a man.
Which meant that Hong Kong Chief Executive
Carrie Lam
had to travel to the ceremony...
in a boat.
But because of the really bad weather,
and definitely not for any other reason,
the ceremony had to be held inside.
Fortunately, the people had their own flag
raising ceremony
outside government offices.
Only this was the flag they raised.
And the real Hong Kong flag was raised at
half mast.
People were so moved, they were in tears.
At least this one guy was.
Ok that might be because of the pepper spray.
But that didn’t stop the afternoon
Un-Independence Day celebrations!
Half a million people marched through the
streets.
Happy to show their true feelings about Hong
Kong’s leadership.
“When you think of your chief executive,
Carrie Lam,
what’s the first word that comes to mind?”
“Selfish.”
“Arrogant.”
“Out of touch.”
“B-----.”
“I would say f--- her. Hahahaha.”
Yes, the people of Hong Kong can’t get enough
of
their post-colonial government.
So much so,
that they broke into government headquarters.
And showed both Hong Kong and Beijing what
they really thought.
But they still remembered to pay for their
drinks.
These celebrating Hongkongers
left the legislature around midnight.
But police decided the party had gone on long
enough.
And after a long night, finally,
people were able to go home and get some sleep.
And then Chief Executive Carrie Lam
held a press conference.
In the police headquarters.
At 4 am.
Yes, 4 am.
Proving again why she’s so beloved.
And so the people of Hong Kong have a message
for Carrie Lam and the Chinese communist party.
We will not go quietly into the night,
we will not vanish without a fight
we're going to live on
we're going to survive!
Today we protest our unindependence day!
And this episode has been sponsored by Surfshark.
People in Hong Kong know it’s important
to protect your identity.
That’s why so many people here use VPNs
like Surfshark
when they go online.
You should be using a VPN, too—
whether you’re protesting communist China,
or simply going online in a public place
anywhere in the world.
With Surfshark, you can protect your private
information
while surfing the web.
Like your banking info,
or the websites you visit.
And if you’re in a country that doesn’t
allow you
to access the entire Internet...
...you can use Surfshark’s NoBorders™
mode to get around it.
But Surfshark also makes sure that all of
your favorite apps
and websites will still work no matter where
you go—
when you add them to their Whitelister™
feature.
Plus you can connect as many devices as you
want.
Try it out with a 30-day money back guarantee.
And Surfshark has an amazing discount for
China Uncensored fans.
Go to Surfshark.com/uncensored and use the
code UNCENSORED
to get 83% off a 2-year plan.
PLUS get one extra month free.
Protect yourself online.
Click the link below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.