On this episode of China Uncensored,
Tweet-le Dee and Tweet-le Dumb.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
And you thought Twitter was dead.
Far from it!
Twitter is having a resurgence.
It’s all anyone can talk about.
And it’s all thanks to soon-to-be president,
Donald Trump.
On the campaign trail,
Trump promised to be tough on China.
And now, before even assuming office,
he’s set his sights on the Chinese regime.
In 140 characters or less.
In two Tweets he tweeted Sunday,
Trump attacked China for being a currency
manipulator,
and then for militarizing the South China
Sea.
Now these are both things
the US has criticized China for in the past.
Just not via Twitter.
It follows on the heels of a phone call between
Trump
and the President of Taiwan, Tsai Ying-wen.
That’s the first time in 40 years a US president
or president-elect
had a phone call with Taiwan’s leader.
Taiwan is considered a province by the Chinese
regime.
I believe this was the Chinese Foreign Minister’s
response to Trump's tweets:
My favorite state-run media, Global Times
slammed Donald Trump, saying
“Trump's reckless remarks against a major
power
show his lack of experience in diplomacy.”
This one warns that Trump will learn not to
cross China.
That’s ridiculous!
How does an eagle throw a rock?!
Eagles don’t have opposable thumbs, people!
Now in the West,
Trump has also been slammed for his “Twitter
diplomacy.”
Because the proper way for a president to
deal with China
is to let the Chinese regime walk all over
you!
And for all those who criticize Trump as lacking
experience,
well, at least he has experience on Twitter,
where his verbal war with China goes all the
way back to 2012,
when he said that China invented global warming
to hurt US manufacturing.
Sorry, Al Gore.
2012 also saw Trump weigh in on other important
matters,
such as the relationship between Twilight
stars Robert Pattinson
and Kristen Stewart.
He was right then and he’s right now!
So is it appropriate for the future president
of the United States
to use his Twitter account to discuss
high level diplomatic issues?
Well, it certainly is a new medium.
Perhaps what’s strange and unusual now
might be common practice in the future.
The real problem is his snapchat account.
So what do you think?
Is Trump standing up to China?
Or will his Twitter diplomacy result
in a Myspace-level catastrophe?
Leave your comments below.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Internet censorship is a disease,
a cancer of this planet.
It’s a plague.
And ExpressVPN is the cure.
ExpressVPN helps users in China and around
the world
access blocked websites the censors don’t
want them to see.
They have fast servers in 87 countries,
24/7 customer support,
and VPN apps to secure all of your devices.
ExpressVPN will show you a world without rules
and controls,
without Internet firewalls and boundaries.
A world kind of like…
America.
That’s right,
ExpressVPN lets you browse the Internet like
an American,
even if you’re in China.
After all, what good is the Internet
if you’re unable to speak?
Click the link below to learn more about ExpressVPN!