Hello and welcome to this special episode
of China Uncensored.
I'm your host, Chris Chappell.
And I'm your producer, Matt Gnaizda.
Chris, Have you ever wondered what the future
will be like?
We live in the future, Matt.
No, I mean the future. With hoverboards.
“He’s on a hoverboard!”
Actually, hoverboards have already been invented.
This is a real video from last year of Tony
Hawk riding a hoverboard made by the company
Hendo. But the downside is that it only works
on a special copper-plated surface.
And not, say, on water.
Not unless you've got power! But if you've
watched the 1989 movie Back to the Future
Part II—and surely you have—you know what
the real future looks like.
"We're descending toward Hill Valley, California
at 4:29pm on Wednesday, October 21st, 2015."
"2015? You mean we're in the future!?"
Wow. We are living in the future.
Yep. And that's why today we're going to look
at the top 10 things Back to the Future Part
II got right.
Number 10: TV screens everywhere
Given that this is what a brand new Magnavox
TV looked like in 1985, it's amazing that
Back to the Future was so on the spot with
this.
“Channels 18, 24, 63…”
Giant flat-panel TVs. Hundreds of channels.
Even a wide-screen aspect ratio. Wow.
Number 9: 80s Nostalgia
So Marty McFly goes into the Cafe 80s. And
in 2015, the 80s are back. People love the
80s.
Well, the 80s did produce some of the greatest
hosts on YouTube.
Yeah, anyway, once again we have jeans jackets.
Puffy vests. Goofy sweaters. Thanks, Katy
Perry.
“Last Friday night”
Number 8: Restaurants without waiters
Did you notice that there are no waiters in
the Cafe 80s?
Yea, McFly orders a Pepsi from a TV screen.
And today we actually have that in a lot of
restaurants. Like Chili’s—they have those
table-top tablets.
It would be more fun to make President Reagan
bring you a drinkm though.
Yeah, but then you have to interact with other
humans. Which kind of defeats the whole purpose.
Number 7: Hands-free video games
You know that part where the kids say:
"You mean you have to use your hands?"
"That's like a baby's toy!"
Well, now we actually have things like the
Xbox Kinect and the Wii.
Yeah, only babies use their hands for stuff.
Number 6: Machines you talk to
“Hydrate level four, please.”
"Hey Siri, do you like to talk with me?"
"I'd rather not say, Matt."
Number 5: Wearable technology
Wow, that looks surprisingly like Oculus Rift.
But you know what makes this really accurate?
People paying more attention to their technology
than their loved ones around the table.
Wait, what? Did you say something?
Number 4
“Wait a minute. Cubs win World Series—against
Miami?”
Amazingly, it is actually possible for the
Cubs to win the World Series this year.
For the first time in a century.
But...the movie got the dates wrong. So as
of this recording, we still don't know whether
the Cubs will win.
But you know what they did get right? There's
a team from Miami.
Yeah, Florida didn't even have a baseball
team until two years after this movie was
made. And they weren't called the "Miami"
Marlins until 2011.
Number 3: Surf Vietnam
You might have missed it the first time, but
Doc and McFly are actually standing in front
of an advertisement that says "Surf Vietnam."
In 1989, Vietnam was not exactly a place where
you'd want to go on vacation.
But now, well...Surf City.
Number 2: Drone Reporters
Chris, remember when you used to be a reporter?
Yes, I was replaced by a drone.
Well in 2015, a lot of people are using flying
drones like this to take pictures and footage.
And even though it's technically against FAA
regulations for media companies do it, it's
being done anyway.
Well the most accurate part here is that human
reporters are being replaced by machines.
And Number 1
Hey, what’s Doc Brown looking through?
Why, it sure looks like an iPhone to me.
Boom.
Considering this movie was made almost 30
years ago, they actually got a lot of things
right.
But you know, they didn't get everything right.
And that's why you should check out our other
video, "10 Things Back to the Future Part
II Got Wrong."
Back to the Future predicted the future traveling
30 years ahead from 1985. So your prediction
for 2045?
Everyone in the world will be able to speak Chinese.
Totally.