On this episode of China Uncensored,
what happens when a beauty pageant gets ugly.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
You know,
when I started a comedy show that exposes
the things
that the Chinese Communist Party wants to
keep under wraps,
I never imagined I would spend so much time
talking about beauty queens.
Specifically, Miss World Canada Anastasia
Lin.
We know her,
we love her.
And she...
at least knows who I am.
I mean,
she’s been on my show.
What’s awesome is that she’s been
using her Miss World platform
to expose human rights atrocities in China.
Now you’d think Miss World
would be proud of someone like Anastasia Lin.
The UK-based Miss World beauty pageant
isn’t just about looks.
After all,
their motto is "Beauty with a Purpose."
They even got rid of the swimsuit competition.
As Miss World’s chairman Julia Morley said
in an interview
with Elle Magazine,
"I don't care if someone has a bottom two
inches bigger
than someone else's.
We are really not looking at her bottom.
We are really listening to her speak."
That’s a nice sentiment—
if it were true.
Because when the bottom in question
is Miss World’s bottom line,
speaking suddenly gets more complicated.
You see,
all of the Miss World organization’s sponsors
appear to be Chinese companies.
I know it’s a little hard to see there
because it’s really tiny and they put it
all the way at the bottom of their site.
You know,
the way you do when you're really,
really proud of your sponsors.
Since 2003,
the Miss World finals
have been held in China 7 times,
mostly in the city of Sanya.
And Sanya has put a lot of money into Miss
World,
including a $31 million dollar investment
into infrastructure for the pageant.
Last year, Sanya paid Miss World 4.8 million
dollars
to host the finals in their city,
and let them keep 100 percent of the broadcasting
fees
paid by TV networks outside China.
So what happens when one of your contests
is,
I don’t know,
“misguided by her values,”
according to Chinese state-run media?
She gets barred from entering China.
That’s right.
In 2015,
China refused to grant Anastasia a visa,
calling her "persona non grata."
And Chinese public security officers harassed
her father,
who still lives in China,
and eventually bankrupted his company.
What did the Miss World organization do?
I mean, what could they do, am I right?
Their hands were tied.
It's not their fault if a contestant somehow
violated
the host country's regulations!
What were they going to do, speak up for her?
It wasn't all bad though.
The media firestorm gave Anastasia a new platform
to speak about human rights,
and she did:
at places like Oxford University,
the National Press Club, and the Oslo Freedom
Forum.
She spoke to the British Parliament,
testified in front of Congress,
and met the Dalai Lama.
And she's also starring in a movie that was
just released,
called the Bleeding Edge--
a thriller about Western companies
taking huge sums of money to help China
censor its citizens,
and the cover up of forced organ harvesting
from prisoners of conscience.
I bet that movie’s banned in China.
Download it on iTunes while you still can.
Plus Miss World Canada,
the quasi-independent Canadian division of
the organization,
which stood up for Anastasia Lin in the first
place,
decided to extend her title an extra year.
That way, she can compete in this year’s
finals—
which fortunately are being held in Washington,
DC—
not China.
Anyway, Miss Lin goes to Washington,
and everything goes smoothly after that.
Well if that were true,
you wouldn't be watching this episode right
now.
You see, the Miss World organization
is now itself actively silencing Anastasia
Lin.
According to the New York Times,
“Pageant employees warned her that she would
be ejected
from the competition if she spoke to reporters.”
When a Boston Globe reporter took some initiative
and intercepted her in her hotel lobby,
Miss World officials hustled her away
while accusing her of causing trouble.
Which is funny,
because Chinese media have been given full
access
to interview the contestants.
The Miss World organization even tried to
block
a U.S. State Department official who wanted
to meet
with Anastasia Lin.
They finally agreed,
but only on the condition,
that they got to play chaperone during the
meeting.
And they forbid the State Department
from tweeting about the meeting.
Can they even do that?
Plus, Miss World denied Anastasia permission
to go to the premiere of the Bleeding Edge
in Washington DC.
So a British-owned beauty pageant
is preventing a Canadian beauty queen
from talking about Chinese human rights abuses
on American soil.
It really is Miss World.
It's not clear if the Miss World organization
is censoring Anastasia because they've been
pressured
by the Chinese government or their Chinese
sponsors,
or if they're just worried about possibly
being pressured
or losing money.
But it is clear that the organization itself
is doing the censoring.
They can't blame it on the hosting country's
visa requirements
this time.
Wait, what's that Shelley?
Well, well.
It looks like things have changed.
Just one day after everyone from the New York
Times to Cosmo
reported on Anastasia being silenced,
she's suddenly allowed to speak to the media
again.
And even attend her movie premiere.
I guess bad PR can really turn things around.
You know,
many companies are craven enough to self-censor
or censor others to appease the Chinese Communist
Party
for Chinese money.
And sometimes the only thing we can do
is to call them out on it.
Good old fashioned public shaming.
I don't often say this,
but bravo, media, for covering this.
But you know what,
I think Anastasia could use an even bigger
megaphone.
Who could we get to talk about this?
Let's see...
it would have to be someone who has experience
with beauty pageants,
who likes using social media,
who enjoys shaming people,
and who angers Chinese officials with big
symbolic gestures...
hmmmm....
Ok, I know what you're thinking.
Donald Trump doesn't have the best track record
when it comes to beauty queens.
But I still think he should meet with Anastasia.
Not in a dressing room,
and possibly with a chaperone.
But he is about the be the leader of the free
world.
He likes to do things that are out-of-the-box.
He does read Twitter.
And that meeting might just make Chinese officials
explode.
So seriously.
Whether you love him or hate him,
tweet at Donald Trump right now.
Tell him,
“Meet with Beauty Queen #AnastasiaLin
to talk about China.”
Be sure to copy @ChinaUncensored
so I can see your tweets.
And after you’ve done that,
leave your comments below
and tell me what you think of this whole thing.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Now get on Twitter and send a message to Trump.
You can copy the text below.
Do it now.
This is gonna be huge!