South Korea was one of America’s closest allies
But now the country is\h
falling to Communist influence
From China…
And North Korea
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m\h
Chris Chappell. Before we start,\h\h
I want you to smash that like button because\h
that’s a big help with YouTube’s algorithms and\h\h
we need all the help we can get fighting it.\h
And if you like the show, please subscribe.\h
So, ever since taking office in 2017, the\h
president of South Korea, Moon Jae-in,\h\h
has been pushing for closer ties to\h
China, and unbelievably—North Korea.\h
That...kind of didn’t sit well with\h
a lot of South Koreans. You know,\h\h
what with that whole North Korea threatens to turn\h
South Korea’s capital into a sea of flames thing.
But this April, Moon Jae-in’s party won a\h
landslide victory in the legislative election.
That means President Moon has been able to\h
push through legislation like this—banning\h\h
people from sending leaflets into North\h
Korea with uncensored information.
Kim Jong-Un really didn’t like North\h
Koreans reading those leaflets.\h\h
So Moon’s party did him a solid.\h
But that’s what the people of South Korea wanted,\h
right? After all, Moon’s party won in a landslide,\h\h
right? Well, as we talked about on this\h
episode of the China Unscripted podcast,\h\h
there have been widespread allegations of voter\h
fraud. And China may have had a hand in it.
Joining me now is North Korean\h
defector and author Yeonmi Park.\h
Yeonmi, thanks for joining me again.\h
It's always a pleasure to have you on.
Thank you so much for having me. It's an honor.
Well, so new legislation has been passed in South\h
Korea that makes it illegal for South Koreans to\h\h
send leaflets into North Korea. First, what did\h
those leaflets mean to the people in North Korea?
It just means a lot of things.\h
When I was in North Korea,\h\h
I actually didn't get to personally pick up a\h
leaflet, because I wasn’t living in the border\h\h
town. However, there are so many of the regime\h
warnings to us that if you ever see a leaflet,\h\h
the South Koreans put a poison in it, do\h
not pick it up. And we hear about stories\h\h
how people get to know the outside the\h
world through picking up these leaflets.
So one, what this leaflet does is that\h
it providing truth, information to North\h\h
Korean people that they do not get from\h
the state government of media. The second\h\h
one is also a symbolic thing, that it reminding\h
North Koreans that they are not alone in this,\h\h
that people outside really care about them and\h
cheering for them. So it is so heartbreaking\h\h
how this most important thing that is being\h
banned in South Korean, in free democracy.
So, what impact do you think\h
banning these leaflets will have?
It will have a lot of things. The first thing,\h
the South Korean now, I don't want to even\h\h
call it government, the Moon administration, they\h
confirm that how they are treating North Korean\h\h
defectors in South Korea, which is treating us\h
like second citizens. When people talk about\h\h
systemic racism in the Western civilization,\h
but that is happening in South Korea.
Actually the South Korean government systemically\h
discriminate North Korean defectors living there.\h\h
Even though we are South Korean citizens, we can\h
not hold certain positions in the government,\h\h
because they think we can be\h
a spy, we can be a terrorist,\h\h
and also this. We have freedom of speech. It\h
is under the constitution that is protected,\h\h
but because we are North Koreans, we do not\h
have a right to practice our freedom of speech,\h\h
which is sending leaflets to North Korea,\h
through balloon launches in the border towns.
Well, why do you think Moon Jae-in's\h
government banned the leaflets?
Well, he's very known lover of communism\h
and Kim Jong-un for all his life. So the\h\h
reason why he chose to not do the right thing\h
and silencing defectors who are risking their\h\h
life to free their people. He chose to please\h
Kim Jong-un, which means that Kim Jong-un gets\h\h
really bothered by this information inflow.\h
This is how impactful this informations are.
Kim Jong-un doesn't want to start the war over\h
a lot of things, but whenever these balloons\h\h
going into North Korea, Kim Jong-un gets really\h
offended and demands South Korea to stop it,\h\h
and Moon Jae-in, of course, the puppet of Kim\h
Jong-un, so he's going to do that for Kim Jong-un.
You really think that situation is that\h
bad? That Moon Jae-in is just a puppet of\h\h
North Korea and possibly China?
Oh yes. Even before he became the\h
president, his whole career was\h\h
dedicated to help the dictator in North Korea.\h
He was serving the normal hand, the previous\h\h
Democrat laborer president before him was Kim\h
Dae-jung and Moon Jae-in whole dedicating his\h\h
life to bring socialism and communism to South\h
Korea and also, let the dictator to survive and\h\h
maintain his power in the North. That is\h
his whole entire career mission has been.
So how did it get to be that the president of\h
South Korea has such pro-North Korean feelings?
It is a mystery, kind of be for me too, how\h
this is possible the flourishing democracy.\h\h
It was the beacon of hope for a lot of\h
Asian countries in that region. Suddenly,\h\h
this guy who is so procommunism\h
and socialism and dictatorship.\h\h
I think that is the thing freedom is fragile.\h
The thing is that it's not even in South Korea,\h\h
a lot of developed economies in the world.\h
Once you are rich and comfortable for a while,\h\h
you can afford to be a dreamer and thinking\h
about socialism. This has been a global trend\h\h
in South Korea, in America, anywhere, I think.\h
Literally right now, it's a huge trend where\h\h
people are wanting something like socialism,\h
because they've been too comfortable, I think.
So how is the current government in South Korea\h
getting more friendly with China and North Korea?
But though now as Moon Jae-in is very looking\h
forward to having Biden in the office in America.\h\h
They did not really have a good relationship with\h
Trump before. Moon Jae-un is very pro Xi Jinping\h\h
and therefore pro Kim Jong-un as well. They didn't\h
like that much with Trump, but they're really\h\h
happy for Biden to be in the office and looking\h
forward to having a good relationship again.
So you mentioned North Koreans aren't\h
treated very well in South Korea.\h\h
Has it gotten worse over the\h
years or what's been going on?
It definitely got really, really worse by\h
Moon Jae-in. Before then, there was some\h\h
effort in South Korean government to try to\h
avoid that, so at some point they were even\h\h
letting North Korean men to go to military. Before\h
that it was illegal for us to go military in South\h\h
Korea. But Moon Jae-in now, criminalizing\h
so many things that defectors cannot do.
For instance, Moon did, during the peace talks\h
with North Korea in the last couple of years,\h\h
and with America, there was one North\h
defector who was journalists from the major\h\h
newspaper. They were banning him because\h
just simply, he was North Korean defector,\h\h
so he couldn't go report about that piece\h
for something that he had with Kim Jong-un.
Yeah, he's talking about systemic racism,\h
this is what systemic racism looks like.\h\h
Even though with the same citizenship\h
we have, we can not hold the same jobs,\h\h
we're sent to prison for the same things\h
that South Koreans wouldn't go to jail for.
I guess I just really don't understand\h
it. What could possibly be the appeal\h\h
of being closer with a horrible\h
regime like North Korea?
I think it is why would some people were not like\h
socialism or communism have to do to get their\h\h
heads. I think initially in\h
the past that North Korea did\h\h
plant a lot of spies and feeding\h
this ideology and brainwashing them,\h\h
that North Korea is very, very good corrupt. Even\h
in today's world, like YouTube, you can see this\h\h
North Korea propaganda channels, like Echoes\h
of Truth and other places, that North Korea\h\h
has been doing this so much in South Korea\h
and they're planting their allies there.
I think in college campuses, they studied\h
to the ideology that North Korea holds\h\h
as a more senior philosophy. So, I think Moon\h
was influenced by the ideology when he was young,\h\h
when he was in college and he was in this a\h
lot of the peaceful ... North, South Korea is\h\h
now for the much respect than he was looking\h
for some democracy, but I think he meant too\h\h
far with it. So, he became a communist. I didn't\h
know what's going on in his as actually really.
So, how do people in South Korea\h
in general feel about communism?
Young people really definitely like it. The\h
young people actually singing songs like the\h\h
true leader in North Korean peninsula like Kim\h
Jong-un and they are dreaming of becoming like\h\h
North Korea someday. They think America\h
is their enemy, sworn enemy, exactly what\h\h
North Korea preaches to North Koreans. They\h
demonize America, they demonize Japans, and\h\h
free democracy, then worship is ideological,\h
worshiping kings and Juche and socialism.
So, I wouldn't really say even like my ...\h
a lot of nation defectors after experiencing\h\h
this authoritarian dictatorship, they\h
still just fall into this promise of\h\h
the government. "We're going to take\h
care of your future, your happiness,\h\h
your college education, your healthcare." So,\h
even defectors falling into this first promise,\h\h
that government is god and can do everything\h
for you. So, I don't know, I feel so helpless\h\h
even after experiencing that much\h
oppression, they still fall for it.
I know it must be difficult, you\h
fled North Korea and risked your life\h\h
to get to South Korea at one\h
point. So this must be shocking.
Yeah. I think also the thing that is\h
very lucky to me that I came to America,\h\h
so I have no much threat going to jail\h
for what I'm doing right now. I'm speaking\h\h
out against North Korean dictatorship and also\h
talking about South Korean government critically,\h\h
is going to get a lot of people in trouble now.\h
And I wouldn't dare to now go to South Korea. We\h\h
just South Korean citizenship, I'm waiting\h
to go back once I become American citizen,\h\h
because I might get arrested\h
there too in South Korea actually.
Well, speaking of that, I know there have\h
been accusations that in South Korea,\h\h
this year's legislative election was rigged. South\h
Korea also has some pretty insane liable laws that\h\h
make it almost impossible to talk\h
about that. But what are your thoughts?
I mean, the fact that Moon Jae-in as\h
soon as he got into office, he sent\h\h
to a previous president, who were not liberal,\h
who were in a more conservative party,\h\h
sent to prison. There were sentences\h
more than like 20 something years.\h\h
It's not like they were rapists or murders,\h
right? Is something is so awful about it,\h\h
she changed entire people in the intelligence\h
everywhere. And just switching up or entire people\h\h
is like, in North Korea, I saw a lot of purges\h
whenever a new king comes up, but, you know,\h\h
thankfully there was not much ... I will not say\h
thankfully, but you know, there were not too many\h\h
kings. When each one comes in, they hold power for\h
some time, but in South Korea every five years.
But whenever this labor's coming\h
in South Korea, they do this like\h\h
similar thing called a great purge. We remove\h
everybody that disagrees with them and has like\h\h
more free market views. And they went\h
to extreme to the part where they're\h\h
sentencing and sending their ex president into\h
jail and sentencing more than like 10, 20 years.\h\h
I think the words that they say the bad\h
idea like of [inaudible 00:11:49] and\h\h
freedom in South Korea, but definitely South\h
Korea is not free right now, we don't know.
Wow. Well, I'd like to at least end\h
on some good news. You've started\h\h
an amazing new channel about your experiences in\h
North Korea and the channel really is blowing up.\h\h
Why do you think people are\h
so fascinated by North Korea?
I think even though the governments,\h
even U.S. administration, the EU, UN,\h\h
what they are actually caring about just nukes,\h
right? They try to remove this security threat\h\h
parties to the U.S., Japan, South Korea. But\h
when it comes to individuals, I think people\h\h
have way more warmer heart\h
and care about human rights.
So, I think when governments, just their approach\h
to talk about North Korea has always been\h\h
talking about the nuclear threat and dictatorship.\h
And I think when I talk about the people's story\h\h
of North Korea, that's when I get the most\h
response from people. Think ultimately,\h\h
you know, we get touched by people's story, and I\h
think people really care about what is happening\h\h
to the 25 millions of North Korean people\h
now just need a new story maker Kim Jong-un.
Well, thank you for joining me. It's\h
always a pleasure talking to you and\h\h
I'll be sure to put a link to your\h
channel below. I highly recommend it.
Thank you so much everyone and thank you Chris.
Be sure to check out Yeomi’s YouTube\h
Channel, Voice of North Korea.\h\h
I’ll put a link below and in the endscreen.\h
She has a million super interesting stories\h\h
about everything from daily life in North\h
Korea to Kim Jong-Un’s pleasure squad.
And if you want more of this interview,\h
watch our hour-long podcast with Yeonmi,\h\h
on our other channel, China\h
Unscripted. The link is below.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored. Once\h
again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next time.\h