The US-Taiwan relationship is a little awkward.
Because Beijing keeps causing drama
But should America even care about
hurting the feelings of the Chinese people?
No, these Chinese people.
Welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell here in Taipei, Taiwan.
You know, there are a lot of things the US
government
can’t say when it comes to Taiwan
because it would anger China’s communist
leaders.
And no one knows that better than William
Stanton,
the former director of the American Institute
in Taiwan.
That’s the de facto US embassy here.
So he’s a former ambassador
who can’t be called an ambassador in a US
Embassy
that can’t be called an embassy
in a country that can’t be called a country.
I sat down with him to talk about the future
of this country.
Thank you for joining me today.
Pleasure to be with you.
So if I call you the former US ambassador
to Taiwan,
will I start a war with China?
Well you could.
They're very, how should I say?
They're very orthodox about such questions-
Orthodox is an interesting word for it.
Yeah.
Well, there's a lot of orthodoxy
when you're talking about China,
and they've got a lot of stipulations and
rules
and unfortunately in many ways,
the rest of the world often abides by them.
You may have seen just yesterday I guess,
there was a news report that they had criticized
the 60 some odd countries that had congratulated
Tsai Ing-wen
on her election victory here in China,
and they said that was totally inappropriate.
So why is it that the president of the United
States
can meet with the leader of North Korea
but not the democratically elected president
of Taiwan?
Beats me.
I've never understood it.
I mean we've had, why is it that up till now
officials ...
military people can go on the Pentagon from
Taiwan,
but we've never allowed even low level officials,
although periodically I know that's been changed.
But I mean we've had Jerry Adams,
a terrorist was in the state department,
I think Yasser Arafat at one point visited
the state department.
We've had all kinds of people come to the
state department,
we've had Russian spies,
we know that somebody came in
and bugged the state department at one point.
So why is it that a fellow democracy, a friendly
country,
people we ought to have a close relationship,
why do these old fashioned rules still guide
so many of our policies,
although Congress now is at least twice passed
laws that say
we should have higher level visits from American
cabinet officers,
for example, come to Taiwan.
And why is it that the Taiwanese also,
we've invited them to come at a higher level,
but that never happens because we're not getting
White House approval.
Well, it seems like for years the US government
has operated with the idea that we can't anger
China.
Why not?
Well, absolutely.
I mean I've often said we may have hurt
the feelings of the Chinese people,
but the Chinese government has hurt
the feelings of the American people
because they do some...
That's how I feel.
In a way you're exactly right.
I mean they do all kinds of things in terms
of
their treatment of Muslims and Christians
and,
the Falun Gong and any religion that they
find dubious
or doesn't strictly adhere to the preset serve
now,
Xi Jinping thought Marxist theory with Chinese
characteristics.
They object to it.
It hurts their feelings.
Well I'm sure most of the people of China
don't know and don't care,
but if you want they can come up I guess with
2 million blog items
saying that their feelings are hurt,
but we shouldn't care.
But you know, this has become such
a tradition.
We should never value a relationship for its
own sake.
You have a relationship with a country
because if it's in your
mutual interests.
But we've also had over the years,
so many people who have retired from government
and then made money leading CEOs from America
to China
and getting paid for it.
And these people have maintained orthodoxy.
But a lot of that has changed now.
I've noticed, I began to notice it really
in 2014 thereabouts.
What it is clear is that people on both sides
of the aisle,
Democrats and Republicans increasingly believe
that
the US China relationship is out of whack,
and that it was serving one country's interest
more than the other.
So there's been a sea change.
I know you've argued that the US and Taiwan
should have a free trade agreement.
What would that be?
Absolutely.
Yeah.
Well, my argument is based on the fact
if you look at all of the 20 free trade agreements
that the United States has had
or just call it a trade agreement,
all of them,
I would say the principal motive for most
of them
was political and strategic and for a few
others
there was also particularly the case of NAFTA
because Mexico and Canada are our neighbors,
they're not hostile neighbors.
I'm not convinced about Canada.
Please carry on.
But the idea was that we could,
we had interests in strengthening these countries.
The very first free trade agreement was with
Israel
and that wasn't for economic reasons.
And then what followed were with moderate
Arab States,
which were basically more friendly toward
Israel, l
ike Morocco and Jordan and Oman.
And then we did Central American States,
not because they were economically important,
but because we hoped that would help stabilize
their economies
and would cut down illegal immigration.
And I suppose maybe drugs, I don't know about
that.
With Chile and Peru in large part
was because they were moving towards more
of capitalist systems
in their governments.
So what would a free trade agreement with
the US and Taiwan do?
The main importance of it would be strategic
as a sign of US endorsement
and support for Taiwan because Taiwan is kind
of lonely out here
and it would encourage other countries who
have been,
a relatively positive view toward Taiwan like
Japan
to think about trying harder to create free
trade agreements
because the ultimate goal would be,
and it's already happening as a result of
the trade war
between the United States and China,
is that increasingly Taiwan doesn't want to
be
so economically dependent on China, on PRC.
And so it would serve that purpose.
It would make Taiwan,
I think more attractive partner for other
countries
and it'd be a way of showing our support.
I mean, after all,
it's a country of 23 million people that's
a democracy
and friendly to us.
Now we don't give them any aid.
But let's remember that it's over $3 billion
last time I checked,
I thought it was $3.5 billion in aid we give
to Israel.
Why do we do that?
Well, there are historical reasons,
but basically also we consider it a democracy
that's friendly to the United States.
So if we're doing it for Israel,
why shouldn't we be more helpful to Taiwan?
And I'm not saying give them money necessarily,
but at least do a free trade agreement with
them
and lower the cost of their exports.
And we, they're already our 11th largest trading
partner.
So it's a significant country.
Well, I'm curious, besides a free trade agreement,
what more could the US do to support Taiwan?
Well, we've done some of it already.
Under the current administration,
we've been selling more arms that they've
asked for.
We should, I think there's a lot more interaction
between our militaries than is apparent,
but we should increase it if we're going to
invite the Chinese
who have been declared a strategic competitor,
which is a nice way of saying,
not very friendly or worse, why don't we invite
Taiwan?
Now possibly what would happen is other countries
would say,
well we can't participate
because it'll hurt the feelings of the Chinese
people.
But in that case we can have our own exercise
with Taiwan.
We should be doing that.
It'd be very useful in the event of some natural
disaster out here
that we participate in if we've got a record
of participating.
I think we should consider,
I hope we are more of the latest technology
are for weapons systems.
We should be, we already have joint training
in some areas.
I think that should be increased.
I would like to see some Pentagon officials
openly come here.
High level.
There are other things we could do.
I mean, we should speak out more strongly
about Taiwan.
Every time that the PRC objects to something
with regard to Taiwan for example,
are the fact that Pompeo congratulated Tsai
Ing-wen,
our Secretary of State congratulated Taiwan's
newly elected,
again elected president.
Chinese complained about it.
I would like to see the press person get out
there
and speak more strongly about that stuff.
When Wang Yi, the Foreign Minister of Hong
Kong
makes a statement that we have to sever the
black hands
who are interfering in Hong Kong affairs
and then takes a swipe at the US for what
it's been doing.
We should say this is nonsense,
and it's not the kind of language that civilized
countries use,
is particularly unfortunate at a time
when there's so much Chinese PRC espionage
going on in inside the United States.
We shouldn't let them get away with that kind
of rhetoric used against us
and we just supine and we take it.
We've been doing that for far too many years
and we should talk back.
Well, how do you think the Trump administration
has been handling Taiwan?
Well, clearly in a much better fashion in
many ways.
But, I'm troubled by what,
I don't know what Trump really thinks about
Taiwan.
I know he received the phone call initially,
which I gather his staff advised him to do
from Tsai Ing-wen.
It was a nice gesture.
But for example, we know he then later went
to Mar-a-Lago
and he met with Xi Jinping
and he talked about how Xi Jinping
had explained to him in just two minutes,
the whole history of Korea and how Korea had
always been part of China.
And I thought to myself, well that's interesting.
I'm sure the Koreans are going to be unhappy.
And they were.
But I thought to myself,
surely they didn't meet for all that length
of time in Mar-a-Lago
and he talked about Korean history as part
of China
and he didn't talk about Taiwan.
And subsequently we've heard on one occasion
there's,
I don't remember the exact phrase,
but they were suddenly implying that
perhaps Taiwan could be a bargaining chip,
everything was negotiable.
Something along those lines.
The people who've stood up most strongly
have been people like Randy Schriver,
Department of Defense has now left,
Peter Navarro who's on the trade negotiating
team,
Matt Pottinger in the NSC.
John Bolton, who's now left the government
who's always been very strongly supportive,
so that gave a certain complexion.
I think Secretary Pompeo,
I think his own views also are very supportive
of Taiwan.
But, it's been intermittent and I guess maybe
the president
said something after the election just now
of Tsai Ing-wen,
but he should do more.
But I guess he's so worried about getting
a trade deal.
But my own view has always been that I don't
think we're ever
going to get from the PRC the kind of trade
deal we want and need:
protection of intellectual property,
ending subsidies to state owned enterprises.
And so I don't think, frankly,
my own view is that trade is all that with
China,
PRC is all that important.
United States, if you look at the list of
countries
least dependent on exports of goods and services,
US is one of the least dependent countries,
or the least top, the lowest 10.
So I know that Chinese communist party
has threatened military action against Taiwan.
If it actually came to that, what would the
US do?
Well, I'm always asked that and, who knows.
I mean really, but my answer is we could no
longer be the United States
if we didn't step in and defend Taiwan.
I mean, God knows we've fought wars in the
name of democracy
and fighting off communism in Vietnam.
We went into Iraq because they had weapons
of mass destruction
and they didn't.
And by the way,
people in that I knew in the state department
who were following arms said that was the
case,
we went into, we stayed in Afghanistan to
this day.
And it's still a hodgepodge.
And that was one of the motives
was also against ISIS,
but we've been involved in Syria.
So if we can get involved in these kinds of
conflicts
we certainly ought to support Taiwan.
So otherwise we stop being the United States.
That means we don't stand for principle.
We just look after our own interests.
And, as I once said to an Australian scholar
who is brushing off on the importance of Taiwan,
I said, well I can think of another country
that it's a democracy with only about 23 million
people
that we could brush off too.
That would of course be Australia,
but we firmly consider them an ally.
So, but even more important perhaps for some
people if,
you don't care that much about principles
or the nature of the United States,
it's geo strategically important.
One of the reasons China wants it is because
then
they put military bases on Taiwan
and they extend their reach into the Western
Pacific
and they rupture the first island chain of
defense
that General MacArthur famously talked about.
So the other thing is, what are our allies?
What is Japan going to think?
What is Singapore going to think?
Recently Indonesia and Malaysia in various
ways
have always both expressed unhappiness with
the Nine-Dash Line
are we just going to turn it all over
once they control the South China Sea and,
or if they control it and if they control
Taiwan,
basically Japan and South Korea our allies
and friends
are isolated and China calls the shots or
PRC calls the shots.
So, is it possible then for the US to normalize
relations with Taiwan,
just treat it like any other country?
Like what would China actually do?
Well, I'd like to see that they come.
I think there were mistakes way back
during the time of Chiang Kai-shek
where Taiwan could have remained in the UN.
That might've been changed by PRC eventually,
but there could have also been,
there were discussions of dual recognition
that was a possibility,
so I think we've dropped the ball in the past.
Whether we could pick it up in the future
I don't know.
I'd like to see that they come because in
my view,
Taiwan is clearly a country.
It's a sovereign state, it's independent,
they have elections and it's a democracy.
But, I understand those who argue that
we don't want to necessarily do anything
that's going to provoke a conflict.
What I always say is anything we do with regard
to Taiwan
that might lead to threats to Taiwan there
were already enough threats.
We should always consult very closely with
Taiwan
because they're in the best position to judge
what is safe,
what is doable.
They have a better eye out in reading of what
might happen.
It sometimes worries me for example,
I have, some of my friends are big independence
advocates,
but that's all because they feel sure
that the US will come in and save the day.
But, one of the factors I think everybody
realistically
has to recognize is that PRC today is much
stronger militarily.
And, it could be a very risky confrontation,
not only for us but also for the PRC.
I mean, we're not pushovers for sure.
I know you've called Taiwan a modern miracle.
What does that mean?
All that it's accomplished in 40 years.
The miracle that in about less than four decades
really,
it went from poverty to prosperity
and it went from military dictatorship to
democracy.
And it's a model of democracy in Asia now
and from many other parts of the world and
it's done all of that.
The real miracle is it's everything
it's done it's done without really any natural
resources
except the skills, the hard work, the education
of its people.
It didn't start off like the United States
with the great river system,
the largest plots of fertile land in the world,
and, with immigrants who could make America
great
because we would bring in skills as we needed
them.
They basically got a little bit of help from
the United States
and from others, from missionaries, and people
came in the beginning.
But by and large,
it's been on its own and it's been politically
isolated since 1972
and yet they've accomplished all this.
That's a miracle, I think.
Wonderful.
Thank you so much for joining me.
My pleasure.