On this episode of China Uncensored,
some people are dying to get married.
Some people die to get married.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
Boy, first dates can be a killer.
Especially when you’re dead.
“Friend?”
But surely, that’s only the stuff of movies,
right?
Well, in China, they have a way of making
movies into reality.
Like a new program to predict crime before
it happens.
A surveillance network called Skynet.
And of course, the tradition of Ghost Weddings.
Now this is actually an ancient tradition,
but in recent years it’s been making a resurrection
in Shanxi province.
It’s considered bad luck if a young man
dies before getting married.
So earlier this year,
a family in Shanxi married their son,
three years deceased,
to the corpse of a woman from a local village.
And it was a bargain at only $27,000!
I am not making this up.
In fact, that was a discount price
because the bride’s family felt it was a
good social match.
Ghosts can be such snobs about social status.
So why are Ghost Weddings haunting the people
of Shanxi again?
Well, for one, there’s a lot of coal mines
in Shanxi.
Coal mines in China and survival,
don’t really go together.
Kind of like Vegemite
and anything else.
In other words, there’s a lot of eligible
dead bachelors
who need dead bachelorettes.
So many, that grave robbing is becoming a
thing.
“Ah.”
According to local police reports,
at least three dozen female bodies
have been stolen from their graves in the
past three years.
This man had his mother’s body stolen.
If this sounds extreme,
it’s just the beginning.
Because this is just one current manifestation
of a much larger crisis facing China.
Too many men.
You may have heard the term “leftover women.”
That’s what the Chinese government's supposedly
feminist All-China Women's Federation
calls unmarried women over the age of 27.
They wasted time getting an education and
now they’re too old to find a man.
Basically what they’re really saying is,
“FOR THE LOVE OF ALL THAT IS HOLY, MARRY!
MARRY NOW!”
Because China’s real problem isn’t leftover
women.
It’s leftover men.
Decades of the One Child Policy
plus sex-selective abortion and female infanticide
have led to this:
There are 22 million more men than women in
China.
And by 2040 that number could be 40 million.
And when state-run party mouthpiece China
Daily
tries to tell you that this isn’t a problem,
and uses a cute cartoon to illustrate its
point,
you just know IT’S A HUGE PROBLEM.
To illustrate.
This is the population of New York...
Los Angeles... and Chicago.
This is the number of single men in China
with no hope of getting married.
These men are referred to as “bare branches”
because they’re not adding to the family
tree,
and usually they’re poor, rural, and uneducated.
And they also contribute to China’s rising
problems
with prostitution, sex trafficking, violence,
and ethnic strife.
And apparently, when they die in horrific
accidents
caused by insanely bad safety conditions in
really terrible jobs,
they’ll still be competing for corpse brides.
So what do you think of Ghost Weddings?
And what do you think the gender imbalance
means for China’s future?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.