On this episode of China Uncensored, the China-UK
relationship has gone nuclear!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I'm your
host Chris Chappell.
Oh ho man!
Chinese leader Xi Jinping just got done with
an amazing tour of the United Kingdom.
And believe me, it was way better than hanging
out with that stick in the mud Barack Obama
Let's sample the delicate aroma of our fine
wine.
Pff, c'mon, put on your sunglasses, 'cause
it's time to party with the British entourage!
And then head to the pub to pound back a few
brews with the Prime Minister.
Yes, the old world knows how to throw an old
school party.
And like Chinese media said, it was a "redder
than red carpet welcome."
And to celebrate Great Britain's new so-called
"Golden Era of Relations" with China, what
better way than to ride with the queen in
her golden carriage?
The queen even gave Xi a tour of her personal
collection of Chinese treasures.
Halooo!
How do you enjoy all the beautiful things
we stole from your country?
Sorry about the Opium Wars.
Anyway, the message was clear.
Britain is now China's "best friend."
And the "most open country" to Chinese investment.
And also the least open to frank dialog about
human rights.
Judging by how British police kept all the
protesters behind metal barriers like cattle.
And how the government prevented reporters
from having any meaningful access to the Chinese
leader during his entire visit.
And probably all of Britain's..."self-restraint,"
shall we say...impressed Xi Jinping.
Because he signed an extra 16 billion dollars
in trade deals, compared to what was originally
planned.
Oh man, Li Ka-Ching!
The UK is raking in it!
This worked out way better than the time in
2012 when David Cameron met with the Dalai
Lama and China was all pissy.
I mean, what can the Dalai Lama do for you?!
Inner peace?!
Yeah, whatever.
And Cameron made a very good point: "The stronger
our economic, trading, business and other
partnerships, the stronger our relationship
and the more able we are to have the necessary
and frank discussions about other issues."
It's the same logic former US President Bill
Clinton used back in 2000 when he pushed to
open up permanent trade relations with China.
And look at how well that's worked out!
I mean, China's human rights situation is
the best it's been in...um, wow, ok that's
a pretty low bar.
But anyway, the biggest deal to come out of
this new golden era of relations is the announcement
that China will invest a 30 percent stake
in the construction of a nuclear reactor at
England's Hinkley Point power station.
Is letting China build a nuclear reactor in
the UK a good idea?
Some people don't think so.
For example Britain's own intelligence agents.
There seems to be a concern that allowing
a Chinese state-owned company to work on the
nuclear reactor could give them an opportunity
to insert backdoor traps into the technology.
That could allow the Chinese regime to shut
down the reactor in the event that the UK
decides to, you know, "hurt the feelings of
the Chinese people" by say, acknowledging
Taiwanese independence.
According to an anonymous security source
quoted by the Times, "There is a big division
between the money men and the security side...
The Treasury is in the lead and it isn't listening
to anyone--they see China as an opportunity,
but we see the threat."
There's also a general concern from economists
that while the UK is buying up everything
China has to offer, there's not much money
flowing the other way.
But perhaps most disconcerting is how this
affects the West's ability to deal with the
Chinese regime.
Up until now, the West has been able to collectively
bargain with China, albeit not with overwhelming
success.
They pressure China to, for example, follow
international law, improve human rights, et
cetera.
But now the UK has just sent the message that
we won't even raise those concerns if the
price is right.
So other countries may start to feel pressure
to do the same.
This also affects the US's ability to get
the UK's support in its dealings with China.
I mean, what happened to the good old days
when the UK would follow whatever hair brained
scheme America came up with?
Also, you know, it might not be wise for the
UK to lean too hard on a country that could
face a major economic crash or regime toppling
political instability--and both of those could
easily happen within the next decade.
And when that happens, all that glitters might
not be gold in the golden age of UK-China
relations.
So what do you think?
How many billions of dollars would you require
in exchange for letting China build a nuclear
reactor in your back yard?
Leave your comments below, and if you liked
this episode, please consider taking a moment
to contribute to the China Uncensored Patreon
campaign.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell, see you next
time.