On this episode of China Uncensored...
I’m back from vacation—
and just in time for China
to make a threatening military action
against Taiwan!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your relaxed and tan host Chris Chappell.
You know what I like about Taiwan?
Well, it’s like the parallel dimension China
that has democracy
and didn’t destroy their traditional culture.
And they have anthropomorphized food mascots
that serve you smaller versions of themselves.
Adorable and creepy at the same time.
The mascot, I mean.
Oh, and Taiwan's government officials know
how to play it cool.
I want to emphasize our government has sufficient
capability
to protect our national security.
It's not necessary to overly panic.
Not overly panic?
What’s there to not-overly panic about?
Military jets and navy ships
scrambled off the coast of Taiwan on Wednesday.
The latest sign of heightened tensions across
the water
as a group of Chinese warships
sailed too close for comfort.
Ah, Chinese warships sailing close to Taiwan.
That...might be cause for panic.
Especially since the Chinese military reportedly
has 1,600 missiles
pointed at Taiwan at all times.
Anyway, on Wednesday,
the Chinese military sailed its only aircraft
carrier, the Liaoning,
through Taiwan’s Air Defense Zone.
If only it had been a Sea Defense Zone as
well.
Even though the Liaoning did not enter Taiwan’s
actual territorial waters,
it was enough for the Taiwan military to scramble
F-16 fighter jets
and other aircraft,
in a move that absolutely was not panicking.
That makes the third time in just three days
China has caused another country to “not
panic.”
Earlier this week,
China sent eight warplanes over the waters
between Japan and South Korea.
And over the weekend,
China sent a nuclear-capable bomber plane
over disputed waters
in the South China Sea,
where some say World War III could start.
But hey, why is everyone getting so upset?
I mean, according to the Chinese Foreign Ministry,
this is totally normal.
It is normal for the Liaoning to go back and
forth
through the Taiwan Strait in the course of
training,
and it won't have any impact on cross-Strait
relations.
And he has a point.
Sending warships close to a country/region
you’ve repeatedly said you plan to conquer
is totally normal.
Which is why they tried it once before in
2013.
And it was totally normal back then too.
It's so incredibly reassuring
when you keep emphasizing how normal something
is.
Like when I used to wake up to find my roommate
Carl
standing over me with a knife.
Sure, it was scary at first.
But then Carl explained how it was a totally
normal
part of his sleepwalking.
Made me feel so much better.
Anyway, the Liaoning was normally passing
through
the Taiwan strait
on its way back from training drills
that it had started in the region on December
24,
Christmas Eve.
Of course it didn't have to sail through Taiwan’s
Air Defense Zone.
So was China trying to send a message to Taiwan?
Well, they may have actually been sending
it
to the Donald Trump administration.
Frankly,
I would suggest maybe using
diplomatic channels next time.
Like having state-run media send him a tweet.
At the end of last year,
Trump enraged the Chinese regime
by calling into question the One China Policy.
That’s where everyone agrees there’s one
China,
without having to specify whether it’s the
Communist Party-run
China in the mainland,
or the democratically-run one in Taiwan.
Chinese state-run media even vowed revenge.
And earlier this week, Taiwanese president
Tsai Ing-wen
visited the US and met with Texas Senator
Ted Cruz
and Texas Governor Greg Abbott.
Presumably,
they talked about all the things Taiwan and
Texas
have in common.
Like a deep-seated love of barbecue
and fried food on sticks.
And also how they both want to split off
and be their own countries.
All this is making the the Chinese regime
pretty angry,
since the US isn’t supposed to have official
diplomatic relations
with Taiwan.
Because Taiwan is part of China.
Even though America has vowed to protect this
part of China
from the other part of China.
Like by selling them weapons.
Well, the new year is off to a good start.
Happy year of the rooster, everyone!
So what do you think about China sending its
aircraft carrier
near Taiwan?
And how do you think the US should respond?
Leave your thoughtful policy analysis below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
And if you like this show,
please support me and the team on Patreon.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.