On this episode of China Uncensored,
Mars ain't the kind of place to raise your
kids.
Unless the Earth is destroyed by nuclear war.
Xi Jinping might be getting his name written
into
the Chinese constitution.
And an American University that crossed the
Chinese Communist Party
just got schooled.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
The Chinese Communist Party has had
a lot to freak out over this week.
Most of it revolved around this man.
Kim “Rocketman” Jong-un.
Yes, Kim’s been burning out his fuse up
here alone,
with his insistent push to turn North Korea
into a nuclear power.
Now, sure, all this science,
he don’t understand.
It’s just his job 5 days a week.
Cause he’s a rocket man.
That is of course what US President Trump
called him
at meeting of the UN Security Council.
“Rocket man is on a suicide mission for
himself…”
Now I know there were
mixed reactions to Trump’s speech,
and I understand.
On one hand,
President Trump quoted Elton John at the United
Nations.
That’s got to be worth something.
But on the other hand,
everyone knows that Space Oddity
is the far superior
“man lost wandering the far reaches of space”
song.
So that’s disappointing.
But calling Kim Jong Un rocket man
does make Trump’s threats to destroy North
Korea
sound more folksy.
And you know who definitely liked Trump’s
speech?
Japan.
“We also highly regard President Trump’s
stance
of announcing all options are on the table,
and we would like to continue our cooperation
in security matters between Japan and the
U.S.
as well as among Japan,
the U.S. and South Korea.”
Yes, Japan would absolutely love to continue
its cooperation in security matters.
And you know what would really help them do
that?
A strong military.
Last week,
North Korea launched a missile right over
Japan.
And that’s reignited a debate about
whether or not Japan should have
a more aggressive military.
Japan was banned from having a military
for any purpose besides self defense
after its defeat in World War II.
Or as it’s known in China,
the War to Resist Japanese Aggression.
And the Chinese regime absolutely does not
want
Japan becoming a military rival
in the Asia Pacific region again.
And as much as China would like to think
it’ll be a long long time before Japan can
do that,
Rocketman is giving them a pretty good reason
to do it.
That’s why, according to the White House,
just before his big Rocketman speech,
President Trump and Chinese leader Xi Jinping
“committed to maximizing pressure on North
Korea
through vigorous enforcement of United Nations
Security Council resolutions.”
That was the fourth phone call
between the leaders of the US and China.
And honestly,
Trump’s been in office for nine months now,
and only four phone calls?
Would it kill Xi Jinping to call a little
more often
and just let Trump know he’s okay?
He worries.
But while the Chinese regime is quick to say
threats won’t help the North Korean situation…
...just in case, China and Russia are holding
military drills
in the waters near the Russia-North Korea
border.
Unfortunately, Xi Jinping missed President
Trump’s UN debut.
That’s most likely because he’s preparing
for
the 19th Party Congress next month.
It’s a big event where
more than half of China’s Communist leadership
is getting a big shake up.
It’s also particularly important this year,
because according to state-run media,
they’re going to amend the constitution.
The Communist Party’s constitution, that
is.
While the article doesn’t say exactly
what it will be amended to say,
it will probably be related to something Xi
Jinping said.
His predecessors,
Woodie McWoodface and Toadie McToadface,
also had their policies written into the Party’s
constitution.
You know, the famous “scientific development”
and the “three represents.”
Yes, they all have catchy nicknames like that.
Can’t wait to see what Xi comes up with!
What’s that, Shelley?
T
he four comprehensives?
What does that even...nevermind.
In other news, the Chinese regime and India
are still repairing ties a month after wrapping
up
a tense border conflict.
But China may have found a way to solve
its troubles with India...permanently.
Let the country drown.
This is the Brahmaputra River.
It’s one of Asia’s major rivers.
It starts in Chinese Tibet and flows down
through India and Bangladesh before emptying
out
into the Ganges River.
It also often floods during the monsoon season.
That’s a major problem in Northern India
and Bangladesh.
That’s why these countries have an agreement
with China.
China, being upstream,
shares information with India and Bangladesh
so they can prepare if it looks like
a flood is going to happen.
But gosh, this year,
China didn’t share that information with
India.
“Beijing has said its hydrological stations
are being upgraded
which means it cannot share data.”
Shoot.
Except, the BBC found that somehow,
China did manage to share the data with Bangladesh.
Funny that.
But just in case flooding does happen in India,
the Chinese regime will be ready to help.
They’re building a highway in Tibet to Nepal,
that will give the Chinese military
easy access to South Asia,
in case they need to send troops into India.
You know,
to help with flood relief, of course.
Speaking of a disaster,
a Chinese-born New Zealand Member of Parliament
is under fire.
He’s accused of being trained by Chinese
spies.
A joint investigation between New Zealand’s
Newsroom
and the Financial Times found Jian Yong,
had “studied at an elite Chinese spy school,”
was likely, “an officer in Chinese military
intelligence,”
and of course,
“a member of the Communist Party.”
Now while that may sound bad,
Jian Yong has a pretty good defense.
No, he is not a Chinese spy;
he just taught English to Chinese spies.
Well, I guess case closed.
And over in Hong Kong,
it’s a hotbed of political unrest.
Many people there feel the Communist Party
is rapidly encroaching on the rights and freedoms
they’ve had for decades.
Pro-democracy activists have been imprisoned.
Mainland Chinese police plan to
patrol a Hong Kong train station.
And democratically elected leaders
have been kicked out of office.
But Beijing-backed Hong Kong Chief Executive
Carrie Lam
has a plan to soothe those worries.
By telling everyone to stop that independence
talk,
because it’s making Beijing mad.
Well if Beijing is getting mad, of course!
Keep quiet about all the problems you’re
facing,
and surely they will all magically go away.
But if you don’t do what Beijing wants,
there could be consequences.
And that’s what one US university is learning.
In June, the University of California San
Diego
disregarded the demands of the Chinese embassy,
and allowed their commencement speech
to be given by a known terrorist,
a wolf in monk’s robes,
the Dalai Lama.
Imagine that!
The Chinese international students
had begged the University to cancel
the Dalai Lama’s speech,
or stop him from talking about political topics,
like, Tibet.
Well, now the Chinese regime
is showing American Universities
that if they do something
the Communist Party doesn’t like,
there will be consequences.
The Chinese government has now
apparently barred Chinese scholars
from getting state funding to attend UCSD.
Although Chinese students make up around
10% of UCSD’s student body,
it's not clear how many receive scholarships
from the Chinese government.
Hopefully at least some Chinese students
will still be able to enjoy fish tacos
and Legoland.
What do you think?
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Like this episode?
You know you could have seen it earlier,
along with other great segments,
if you had visited our website ChinaUncensored.tv.
Check it out!