On this episode of China Uncensored,
Vietnam’s most famous pop singer
has something to say.
But some powerful people don’t want her
to say it.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
As I’m sure you can imagine,
life under the Communist regime of Vietnam
isn’t always easy.
Even if you’re a famous celebrity.
Like Mai Khoi.
In 2010 she won a prestigious songwriting
award
from state-run Vietnam Television.
Her style was conventional pop music.
But she never liked the heavy hand
of the authoritarian communist government,
and she started to speak out in favor of democracy.
“She was one of a small number of activists
who tried
but failed in 2016 to gain seats to Vietnam's
parliament,
which is dominated by the ruling Communist
Party.”
Her music began to reflect her transformation
into an outspoken political activist.
Here’s a more recent piece,
called Re-education Camp.
she...
doesn't need
to sit inside there
And let’s just say,
when you criticise a communist regime,
they don’t like it.
She’s been detained by authorities...
and effectively banned from performing in
her own country.
Obviously, I thought:
“Sounds like someone I’d like to meet.”
So I sat down with Mai Khoi
at the Oslo Freedom Forum in Taiwan.
Thank you for joining us today.
My pleasure.
Great.
So, you used to be like the Lady Gaga of Vietnam,
but now you're more like the Pussy Riot of
Vietnam.
Why did you put all that fame at risk for
activism?
Actually, I don't care what people call me,
because they can have their opinions but I
just care about what I am doing now.
Because the fact is,
I have to face the problems myself
and I have to spread the message myself
so what I have is my fame.
And because since I’m famous,
many people follow me
and they watch what I'm doing every day.
That is a good way to say something
if you want to change the society.
It gave you a platform.
Right.
And how has your activism
affected or changed your music?
My music has changed in style,
because I was performing in many styles of
music before:
pop, rock, jazz, folk,
but when I turned to protest kind of music,
I had to do something different from before.
So, I choose experimental ethnic jazz,
contemporary, kind of,
that kind of music to express my lyrics
because is very strong music.
It touches people’s emotions through
the very big range of in dynamics.
Yeah, so my music is now very abstract
but very strong.
And what's it like being
a performer under Communism?
I’ve never performed for the Communist Party.
I just ... because I was born there,
I've grew up there
and I have to worked under the censorship
system.
If I wanted to release the new album, release
new song,
if I wanted to get on the television,
the media, they control everything
so you ask for permission before you can do
anything.
And those kind of things I want to reject.
The censorship system for art and music
is really useless.
People don't need that.
So I know as a performer,
censorship is a big issue for you.
Do you think, when I post a clip of this interview
on Facebook, it will be viewable in Vietnam?
Facebook is under pressure now.
I mean, the government has a new cybersecurity
law,
and from that law they want to censor the
contents on Facebook,
and Google, and YouTube.
And the news that you're making about me
or about political issues may be censored,
yeah I don't know if people can see it or
not
but it depends on the content,
on how you write the article.
Why do you think communist dictatorships
rely on censorship?
The Communist Party, is very scared
to receive criticism from people every day.
So when people have internet and social media,
they write,
they can write their opinions on Facebook
every day
and the government receives so much criticism.
They fear this.
And they are scared they will lose their power.
Yes, because they realize
the power of freedom of expression.
So what can people living
under Communism do to get freedom?
As I said,
we have to step out of fear
and we have to learn,
we have to discover,
we have to know about our rights.
Yes.
It's lucky that we have internet,
if we didn’t have internet,
maybe to this day, we would still be living
in the dark.
Yes.
And I can see,
I can see people in my country
have made big improvements,
they can get information from internet
without censorship.
And that's a good way for people to show their
power.
And how do your fellow countrymen
feel about what you've done?
Many young people have been inspired
by me and they sent messages to me
every day on Facebook.
And they want to make a change.
They want to do something.
They want to be an activist.
Yes.
And I'm so happy when
what I've do encourages young people
to make a change for their country.
So what advice would you give
to young people living under an authoritarian
regime?
You know, to play by the rules,
within the law.
I still follow their law.
What I am doing now is not illegal.
I'm following their law so they have no reason
to stop me
or they have no reason to put me in jail.
And it’s lucky that I am famous
and many people already know me.
So I have a voice.
I have a bigger voice than other people.
What can people in western countries
do to help or change the situation?
I know, western countries can help a lot.
Especially, on freedom of expression
if everyone can raise awareness
about the internet issues
and put more pressure on
social media companies like
Facebook, Google, YouTube
to force them to protect freedom of expression.
That will be a good way to help
the people in my country.
I know, Vietnam is a small country
many countries have problems too
but we can,
together,
make the connection
and we can raise awareness of the problems in our country.
And I think,
if the western countries just
pay attention and spend a little bit
more time to think about the problems
of other countries like my country
and do something.
Everyone can show,
everyone can do something.
Thank you so much for joining us today.
I know our fans, in Vietnam in particular,
will be very happy to hear your words.
Yes.
They also very nervous.
They also very worry about me.
But many of them hope
that we can make a big change.