Abducted in China
Stranded and helpless
This is the fate of Americans,
Britons, Canadians, and Australians
Who became pawns for the Chinese Communist
Party.
Welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Canada is feeling the consequences
of crossing the Chinese Communist Party.
After Canada arrested a Chinese businesswoman
at the request of the United States,
for violating sanctions on Iran…
...China promised retaliation with severe
consequences.
And for starters, they detained two Canadians...
saying those Canadians had somehow
“endangered national security.”
The US State Department may even issue a travel
warning
to US citizens going to China now...
just to be safe.
Because this is a tactic
the Chinese Communist Party has used before.
And will use again.
Here are 5 other times Chinese authorities
detained foreign citizens for no good reason.
Number 5
In 2015, a group of 20 British, South African,
and Indian tourists was arrested
in China’s Inner Mongolia region.
They were there with a larger tour group
as part of a 47-day sightseeing adventure.
But little did they know,
one of the sites they would see,
would be terrorism!
According to state-run Xinhua,
the group was arrested for “watching video
clips
that advocate terrorism and religious extremism.”
They spent several days in detention,
and according to state-run media,
admitted their crimes \hand repented.
Then they were deported.
I know, you’re dying to see
which extremist video clip they’d watched
that got them into so much trouble.
It was...a BBC documentary.
“The only things watched by myself and the
group
was a short clip of the 10 best Western cowboy
films of all time
and a 40-minute BBC documentary on Genghis
Khan.”
Now, this looks like a case where the local
authorities in Ordos
made a Keystone Cops style mistake that
then turned into an international incident
because it’s impossible for the authorities
in China to back down.
The tourists said that no one admitted to
or repented anything,
and in the end no charges were brought against
the group.
After being deported back to the UK,
one of the tourists called for an apology
from the Chinese Communist Party.
I believe he’s still waiting.
Number 4
If you’re a Chinese citizen,
and you get on the bad side of the Chinese
Communist Party,
they’ll stop at nothing to get you,
even if that means holding your family hostage.
Even if your family members are American citizens.
Liu Changming is one of China’s most wanted.
He used to be the executive at a Chinese state
owned bank.
Until he was accused of playing a part
in a $1.4 billion dollar bank fraud case.
He fled China in 2007.
And so when his estranged wife and two children,
all American citizens, went to China to visit
a sick grandparent,
they were captured by Chinese authorities.
“[Chinese authorities] moved [the mother]
to a secret site,
commonly known as a black jail.
The children discovered at the airport
that they could not leave China.”
How could Chinese authorities hold American
citizens without cause?
Well, they shouldn’t be able to.
For one,
the Chinese government doesn’t recognize
dual citizenship.
So according to Chinese law,
Chinese citizens automatically lose their
citizenship
when they gain citizenship in another country.
And even more bizarrely,
one of Liu’s kids was born in America,
making him an American citizen from birth.
Which, according to Chinese law,
means he’s never been a Chinese citizen.
But once Liu Changming’s family were inside
China,
all that went out the window.
Because regardless of the law,
the Chinese Communist Party treats
ethnically Chinese people like pandas.
No matter where you were born in the world,
you belong to China.
Even if your passport says you’re an American.
Number 3
Here’s the story of another Canadian citizen,
who also happens to be a panda.
I mean ethnically Chinese.
Sun Qian.
She’s a successful businesswoman.
She and her husband co-founded
Beijing Leadman Biochemistry Co.
She became a Canadian citizen back in 2007.
She preferred to live in Canada, not China,
partly because she started practicing Falun
Gong in 2014.
That’s a spiritual practice that’s severely
persecuted in China.
Anyway, Sun found out that
her husband was having extramarital affairs,
and she was planning to divorce him.
So, according to Sun’s family,
when she was visiting China,
her husband called the public security bureau
and told them
his wife was practicing Falun Gong.
Chinese police came and arrested her.
Oh, and tortured her.
Sun’s sister said,
“[Sun’s] husband colluded with certain
individuals
in the public security bureau,
using the policy of suppressing Falun Gong
to bring about Sun’s illegal detention and
prosecution.
In the meantime,
Shen forged Sun’s signature and produced
a fake document,
thereby gaining 2 billion in assets.”
Wow, that’s cold.
Her husband reported on her to the police
for practicing Falun Gong,
knowing she’d be persecuted—
so he could take her money?
At least she’s probably not so mad about
his affairs anymore.
But look, Sun Qian is a Canadian citizen,
and didn’t actually commit any crimes.
So couldn’t her lawyer have at least gotten
her
deported back to Canada?
Well, she actually lost her lawyer, because,
“Partners in his law firm told him that
if he represents
Ms. Sun or any other Falun Gong case,
they ‘will cancel his contract to continue
working with the firm.’”
That was after the local Justice Bureau put
pressure
on both the law firm and the lawyer.
You know, the Justice Bureau.
Justice with Chinese Characteristics.
And then they did the same with
the next 10 lawyers Sun’s family tried to
hire.
The latest update on Sun’s case comes from
the Globe and Mail.
Sun has pled guilty,
but most likely under torture.
What’s really sad is how little the Canadian
government has done.
Sun has been held for almost two years.
Last year, when asked about Sun’s case,
all Canada’s ambassador to China
John McCallum had to say was,
“That doesn't always help, for the person
in detention,
If we broadcast their situation in public,
so I think for those cases,
almost all the time,
it is better to proceed in a low-profile way.”
You know, not high profile enough that it
would stop torture.
Number 2
What happens when you’re one of the world’s
biggest mining companies,
and you decide to renege on a deal with China?
Let’s just say,
you don’t want to have your people inside
China.
In 2009, Stern Hu,
an Australian citizen and General Manager
of Rio Tinto
was abducted by Chinese authorities
and charged with stealing state secrets.
The charge was later downgraded to bribery
and stealing commercial secrets.
I’m sure had nothing to do with Rio Tinto’s
decision
the month before “to scrap a planned $19.5
billion investment
in the mining company by Chinalco,
a state-owned Chinese company.”
A later Businessweek investigation
also exposed the fact that the Chinese regime
was hacking Rio Tinto at the time,
and that the arrest of Rio Tinto’s employees
may have been linked to the company’s attempts
to change their iron ore prices.
Stern Hu was another good target.
Because even though he held Australian citizenship,
he was born in China.
In the end,
Rio Tinto basically threw him under the bus,
and the Australian government also
didn’t really do anything to intervene.
But don’t worry,
Stern Hu was released only nine years later,
just this summer actually.
He was released two years early because of
good behavior.
Clearly this case was handled well.
And now,
Number 1
One thing you might be wondering about is
what is it like
for foreign citizens being detained by the
Chinese regime?
Well, here’s Peter Humphrey from the UK
to describe it in his own words.
From the very first moment you’re dropped
into a cell,
you’re there to be crushed,
you’re there to have your spirit broken.
During the 700 days I was in captivity,
I never slept with the lights off.
I sometimes think I never slept at all.
He, and his wife were abducted in 2013
and charged with “illegally acquiring personal
information”
about Chinese nationals.
Actually, he and his wife were fraud investigators.
“Humphrey, a former Reuters journalist,
and his wife were hired by pharmaceutical
giant GlaxoSmithKline
to conduct the company’s internal probe
in January 2013.”
The Chinese authorities liked to play
fun mind games with Humphrey and his wife
while they were in detention.
For instance, right before their trial,
police told him his wife’s brother had died.
So when Humphrey sees his wife for the first
time in ages,
at the start of the trial,
he offered his condolences.
“And I expressed my condolences to her,
believing that she knew.
And she didn’t.
They had lied to me.
So Ying broke down.”
Those police are such tricksters.
Humphrey was released in 2015.
And now he’s in a battle to get Chinese
state-run
CCTV’s license revoked in the UK.
That’s because they had broadcast
his forced television confession in the UK.
The one where he was forced to sit in a small
metal cage
and police read out his confession,
the one police had written for him.
Now this was just a small selection among
many,
many cases of the Chinese regime abducting
foreign citizens.
In most cases, their home countries could
do nothing.
In other cases, their home countries chose
to do nothing
for political reasons.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And now it’s the time you’ve all been
waiting for,
when I answer questions from a member of my
50-Cent Army,
fans who support China Uncensored
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
Rodney Lee Hall asks,
“Chris, do you think we will go to war with
China?
If so, any thoughts on when or the casus belli?
Ah, the million dollar question.
In a way, the US and China are already at
war.
In 1999, two Chinese army colonels published
a book
called “Unrestricted Warfare,”
on how a country like China,
that couldn’t challenge the US military,
could win an unconventional war with unconventional
tactics.
This 2014 report from the US Army Special
Operations Command
details just a few of those warfare tactics
they’re already using
But actual troop on troop action,
right now, and for many years to come,
would be an embarrassing loss for the Chinese
military.
Hopefully, by the time the Chinese military
is on par with the US,
the Chinese Communist Party will no longer
rule China.
But, only time will tell.
Thanks for your question.
And if you’d like your question answered
on the show,
join the China Uncensored 50-Cent Army on
Patreon.
Most of our revenue comes from you guys.
And as a way of saying thanks,
I’ll give you some cool perks,
as well as answering your questions on the
show.
Thanks for watching.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.