bjbj,(,( On this episode of China Uncensored,
China s Dino Juice! (aka oil) Hi, welcome
to China Uncensored. I m Chris Chappell. You
know, big oil is a wonderful thing. No one
s here to say otherwise. Well, except for
maybe these guys. These are residents in Ningbo
city, in China s Zhejiang Province. Last month,
they protested against the 8.8 billion dollar
expansion of already the largest oil refinery
in China, owned by state-run Sinopec. They
were concerned about environmental damage.
And there was also the chemical plant that
was making 500,000 tons of a toxic chemical
paraxylene that can damage the central nervous
system, liver and kidneys, and can cause cancer
and death. But only if you re exposed to a
lot of it. Liberal hippies. And so the police
hit them with tear gas. I mean come on, when
have toxic chemicals ever hurt anyone. If
there were any danger, why would companies
like BP manufacture so much of it?. They care
about the environment. China s state-run Xinhua
responded saying it was groundless to say
paraxylene can cause cancer, and they do have
a point. There aren t a whole lot of studies
about its effects. Which is kind of strange,
when you think about it. With all these extremely
wealthy oil companies like BP, Chevron, Sinopec,
making so much of it, you d think they d be
able to fund some studies on what the effects
are. But they aren t. Hmph. China is the second
largest oil consumer next to the United States
and oil is getting kind of tricky to find,
so besides potentially poisoning its own citizenry,
Beijing has had to sometimes really bend over
backwards to get oil. Take Syria as an example.
China is Syria s main importer, but just because
there s a little civil war going on, the Western
powers slap sanctions on it, despite China
s attempt to prevent any international intervention.
Fortunately, Iran helped China break the embargo
and provided a boat to ship an estimated $80
million dollars of oil to another of China
s state-owned oil companies. Actually it turns
out that several Chinese oil companies are
giving billions of dollars in assistance to
the Syrian regime to expand its crude operations.
As for the citizens of Ningbo, officials said
they d put the construction on hold, so they
re safe for now. At least until the 18th Party
Congress is over this week. That does it for
this episode. Once again, I m Chris Chappell
and this is China Uncensored. Thanks for watching.
hrIJ hrIJ hrIJ gdrIJ :prIJ [Content_Types].xml
#!MB ;c=1 _rels/.rels theme/theme/themeManager.xml
sQ\}# theme/theme/theme1.xml G$$DA : BR \{i5@R
V*[_X ,l\Y Ssd+r] 5\|E Vky- V4Ej 6NGU s?^V
* 7;wP EBU` 5VD
GGHPXNT, /M,W m2iU [[v _Xtl theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.rels
6?$Q K(M&$R(.1 [Content_Types].xmlPK _rels/.relsPK
theme/theme/themeManager.xmlPK theme/theme/theme1.xmlPK
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.relsPK
<a:clrMap xmlns:a="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/main"
bg1="lt1" tx1="dk1" bg2="lt2" tx2="dk2" accent1="accent1"
accent2="accent2" accent3="accent3" accent4="accent4"
accent5="accent5" accent6="accent6" hlink="hlink"
folHlink="folHlink"/> China Uncensored China
s Dino Juice (a Chris Chappell Normal.dotm
Chris Microsoft Macintosh Word PICT" 3g9V
kZg9Z kZg9V g9kZkZc kZo\
kZkZ\{ kZo\{kZc g9kZo\{kZ\{ g9g9kZg9kZw g9kZo\{kZo\{w
g9o\{o\{g9kZg9^ kZkZ\{ kZo\{s o\{o\{w o\{o\{ kZo\{^
o\{o\{s o\{kZo\{ kZg9o\{kZ^ o\{kZs kZkZo\{o\{w o\{kZkZ
kZo\{o\{s kZo\{w <g9c o\{kZkZc g9g9c o\{g9c kZg9s
g9kZkZc o\{kZo\{c )o\{kZs o\{o\
g9g9 o\{g9c g9o\{ kZkZ\{ o\{kZo\{kZw kZo\{kZc kZg9c
kZo\{o\{s o\{o\{kZ kZkZw g9g9w g9o\{s kZkZw kZkZs
o\{kZo\{s g9o\{ o\{o\{c kZg9o\{w kZkZ^ 2o\{^ g9kZc
kZg9g9o\{g9g9o\{g9s g9o\{g9c g9g9^ g9g9Z o\{g9\{
kZo\{o\{kZo\{ o\{o\{w o\{o\{kZs kZo\{o\{s o\{o\{g9g9\
g9kZ\{ kZo\{o\{s kZ's o\{o\{w g9o\{s kZkZg9g9s o\{kZc
g9g9kZo\{o\{kZg9o\{s o\{g9g9kZg9kZo\{g9o\{o\{ kZkZ
%kZc g9o\{^ &g9g9Z o\{kZZ kZg9Z Nsg9g9Z @o\{kZc
kZg9\{ g9kZg9g9kZw g9kZkZZ g9g9o\{^ kZo\{c kZg9w
o\{o\{w g9o\{g9w kZo\{kZs o\{o\{w o\{g9s o\{kZo\{kZkZo\{g9\
kZg9c kZg9kZkZg9s o\{o\{g9o\{g9g9w g9o\{c kZg9o\{g9kZg9kZs
kZo\{ o\{g9s g9g9Z kZo\{^ g9g9^ o\{o\{ kZo\{kZZ
g9kZR g9kZkZs g9kZkZc kZkZ o\{kZZ o\{g9c g9g9o\{g9s
kZg9g9w o\{kZkZ^ o\{o\
o\{%s o\{kZo\
o\{o\
o\{g9o\{kZ^ g9kZkZg9o\{g9w kZg9g9kZo\{c NskZkZ
kZkZo\{kZg9kZkZg9g9s g9kZkZo\{s o\{kZ o\{kZkZs
kZg9s o\{o\
g9o\{kZ g9 \{ o\{g9g9c kZg9s o\{g9g9Z g9o\{w g9g9^
o\{g9kZg9c o\{kZ kZkZZ kZNsV kZg9g9Z .g9s kZkZV
g9g9V kZg9c g9kZ^ kZg9g9V g9kZc g9g9c o\{g9c
g9kZc o\{g9^ g9kZkZg9kZkZg9 o\{o\{kZ kZkZZ kZkZR
o\{kZo\{ g9o\{V g9g9kZo\{g9o\{o\{s g9kZs kZ(o\{c
kZo\{g9kZ kZkZs o\{g9kZc o\{o\{kZc kZg9kZkZs kZkZo\{s
o\{o\{w kZkZs g9o\{g9kZg9w o\{kZkZw kZkZw kZo\{w
kZg9^ g9kZw kZg9w kZkZw o\{g9c g9o\{c China
Uncensored China s Dino Juice (a Title Microsoft
Word 97-2004 Document NB6W Word.Document.8