On this episode of China Uncensored,
when sharing high-level government intelligence,
keep your friends close,
but your enemies closer.
Wait, that’s a terrible idea.
Who came up with that?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
In our top story,
there could be major ongoing intelligence
leaks
among English-speaking countries.
And guess who’s to blame?
There’s something called the Five Eyes.
No, it’s not a group of exotic Batman villains
from the 1970s.
Or a terrible ’90s boy band.
It’s actually an intelligence network that
was set up
in 1955 between the United States, Canada,
the United Kingdom, Australia and New Zealand.
These five countries routinely share sensitive
intelligence—
on everything from [BLEEP] to [BLEEP]
What’d you expect?
It’s highly sensitive information!
But there could be a leak...
from within New Zealand.
And I’m not talking about it’s delicious
dairy.
The leak is what former CIA China expert Peter
Mattis
talked about when he testified last month
before the U.S.-China Economic and Security
Review Commission.
He suggest that maybe New Zealand
ought to be kicked out of the boy band
formerly known as the Five Eyes.
Then terrorists and evil regimes would be
left to tremble
before the might...of the Four Eyes intelligence
network.
Just try and take our lunch money.
So what’s the possible leak within New Zealand
intelligence?
Well, this is China Uncensored, so you guessed
it:
It’s Russia.
Haha, no, it’s the Chinese Communist Party.
They’ve gotten very close to
or inside New Zealand’s political core.
One example is Jian Yang,
a New Zealand Member of Parliament.
He’s a New Zealand citizen now,
but when he lived in China,
he just so happened to train Chinese spies
at a top military university.
Don’t worry, he’s totally not a spy himself.
Now when that story broke last year...
well, the New Zealand government did nothing.
Jian Yang remained a member of parliament.
And China expert Peter Mattis is concerned
New Zealand’s former prime minister Bill
English
routinely briefed Jian Yang
on sensitive China-related intelligence—
intel that may have ended up on the desks
of Chinese Communist Party officials.
As for current Prime Minister,
her party has accepted donations that may
be
linked to the Communist Party.
Mattis points out the level of Communist Party
infiltration in Australia is also similar
to New Zealand.
But he did not recommend Australia be kicked
out.
That’s because Australia has been responding
to the problem,
while New Zealand has denied there’s any
problem at all.
Don’t worry,
we might not be stuck with four-eyed intelligence.
Mattis suggests that New Zealand could be
replaced by Japan.
And they’d bring to the table giant robots.
And tentacles.
Hmmm...maybe let’s skip the tentacles.
Speaking of giving sensitive information
to the Chinese Communist Party—
Facebook.
At this point it should come as no surprise
that
Facebook sells an incredible amount of user
data.
But it may surprise you that Facebook even
went so far
as sharing that data with at least four Chinese
companies.
One of them is Huawei, the Chinese telecommunications
firm
owned by a former engineer in the People’s
Liberation Army,
and that gets billions of dollars from the
Chinese Communist Party.
US Intelligence agencies have been very concerned
about Huawei and the security risk they pose.
Since at least 2012 in fact.
Facebook, though: Not very concerned.
Their data sharing agreements with Chinese
companies
have been in place since at least 2010.
And apparently, are still in place.
“The four partnerships remain in effect,
but Facebook officials said in an interview
that the company would wind down the Huawei
deal
by the end of the week.”
Well that’s good.
You got to commend Facebook
for doing what’s right...after getting caught.
And it’s time for another fan question!
Jordan Laramore asks:
“I have a question in regard to the South
China Sea.
We know that the dispute has soured the view
of China
in some countries but how about relations
with Taiwan,
seeing as they claim the same area
and occupy an island in the sea?”
Great question, Jordan.
You’re right.
This is one of those weird things that both
the People’s Republic of China and Taiwan
agree on:
that everything within the Nine-Dash Line
belongs to China.
Though obviously they don’t agree on which
China that is.
As you pointed out,
Taiwan has had its own small island
in the South China Sea for decades.
It’s called Itu Aba.
But Taiwan’s Coast Guard uses it mainly
for search and rescue in the area—
like to help a fishing boat that capsizes,
no matter what country it’s from.
See, when you build hospitals instead of missile
silos,
your neighbors react a little differently.
Basically, the problem other countries have
isn’t China’s historical claims to the
South China Sea.
It’s the Chinese Communist Party being extremely
aggressive
about building up islands for military use.
Also, of course, we trust Taiwan because it’s
everyone’s ally.
Whereas the PRC is, at best, a frenemy.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Thanks for watching.
it's hard for a controversial show like China Uncensored to get advertisers.
And a lot of our YouTube videos get demonetized.
That's why we rely mainly on your support.
So click this orange button to visit our Patreon website,
and help us make China Uncensored even better.