Hey Shelley,
is there any particular movie character
I remind you of?
Yeah, Agent Smith.
Hey Allen,
do I remind you of a famous actor?
Agent Smith.
Hey Matt, do I…
This is ridiculous!
I look like lots of different actors.
I do!
Uhhh, Eddie Rodney Fleming in the Interview.
Johann Schmidt in Captain America.
Oh!
Elrond in Lord of the Rings!
Uhh, Chris.
You know what those parts
all have in common?
Yeah!
They all look like me.
No, that’s not…
You know what?
Forget it.
I'm out of here.
I should have taken an Uber.
This is the greatest day of my life.
Really?
Shelley?!
What are you doing here?
And why are you dressed like that?
I look like Rose Tico.
Who?
From Star Wars.
But this is Lord of the Rings!
It has nothing to do with Star Wars!
Oh, you mean the story set in a faraway past
where a lovable bunch of misfits
leads a resistance against a dark lord?
Wow, I never thought of it like that.
Allen?
Why are you dressed like Wonder Woman?
Because I look like Wonder Woman.
No you don’t.
I can see it.
It’s the beard.
Thanks, Shelley.
Nice Agent Smith costume.
I’m not Agent Smith!
I’m Elrond!
No, I’m pretty sure you’re Agent Smith.
I agree.
It’s like looking into a mirror.
No!
I don’t look like you!
I don’t!
Agent Smith!
Noooooooo!
Oh, it was just a dream.
Hey Chris, have you seen my stilettos?
Noooooo!
Oh, it was just another dream.
Hey Chris, it's time to go.
Hey, Chris,
you know who else you look like?
Who?
Tick, from Priscilla, Queen of the Desert.