On this episode of China Uncensored:
Apple: the company known for giving users
loads of choices and freedom
to use their products however they want—
just broke my irony meter.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Boy folks,
what a month it’s been!
China Uncensored launched a brand new website,
thanks in part to the Youtube adpocalypse…
...and we launched on Roku, Amazon Fire TV,
and last but definitely least,
Apple TV.
It was a shock when we received
a notice from Apple saying they removed
the China Uncensored App from Hong Kong
and Taiwan.
Apparently because the show is illegal there?
Strange that I don't remember
narrowly escaping prison
when we went to Hong Kong and Taiwan last
year
and met with multiple government officials.
I wrote to Apple CEO Tim Cook
at the beginning of the month
asking for an explanation,
and a demand to put the China Uncensored app
on the app stores there.
And we started a petition!
Which I'm sure everyone watching this
has signed.
Because you're all good people.
Tim Cook has not yet responded to my letter.
And I couldn’t figure out why.
But now I think I’ve got my answer!
He’s been too busy
winning the Free Speech Award
from the Newseum in Washington DC.
The Newseum,
besides being the all-time winner
of the punniest museum name,
also "promotes, explains and defends free
expression
and the five freedoms of the First Amendment."
Which sounds great.
And they have some pretty cool exhibits.
Like an entire section of the Berlin Wall
with an East German guard tower.
And a memorial dedicated to journalists
who have died reporting the news.
And a permanent exhibit on...
the First Dogs?
Okay...
Uh, back to the Free Expression awards.
The awards honor people who
“have taken personal or professional risks
in sharing critical information with the public,
have been censored or punished by authorities
or other groups for their work,
or have pushed boundaries in artistic
and media expression.”
That's why Playboy founder Hugh Hefner
also won a Free Expression award.
I'm sure he got it just for the articles.
Tim Cook gave the longest
victory speech of the night.
According to Apple Insider,
he spoke of the importance
of freedom of speech,
“Not just the forms of speech
that entertain us,
but the ones that challenge us.
The ones that unnerve
and even displease us."
Wise words, Mr. Cook.
I totally agree.
In praise of Tim Cook,
Newseum made this video.
“We believe that a company that has values
can really change the world.
I think it's really important that
corporate leaders like Tim
care about principles like freedom of expression
and the advancement of human rights.
He takes risk at both a personal and a professional level
to engage in new ideas.
It’s not just about making money,
it’s also about making a difference
in the world.”
Yes, Apple:
making a difference in the world.
By doing things like being the Platinum Sponsor
of the 2017 Free Expression Awards.
I'm sure Tim Cook winning one of those very
awards
was a complete coincidence.
It's just like the time I won
the Best Host of a China-focused Comedy News
Show
Not Based in China award.
Right after I gave the hosting organization
two million dollars.
But let's talk about what Apple is doing in
China.
You see,
while Tim Cook was being honored
for his commitment to free speech,
Apple has been doing everything it can to
help
the Chinese Communist Party censor.
For example,
when the Chinese government asked Apple
to remove the New York Times
from the app store in China...
...along with a bunch of other
independent Chinese media...
...and an app that lets Chinese internet users
break through the Chinese Communist Party’s
Draconian Internet censorship firewall...
...plus of course China Uncensored...
they did it.
Because as Apple said,
“the content was ‘illegal’ in China.”
Sure, last year Apple told the FBI
they wouldn’t help in a terrorism investigation
for privacy and security reasons,
but that was the FBI!
The worst Apple could have faced
was probably a big fine.
But the Chinese Communist Party
could literally bring down
all of Apple’s operations in China
tomorrow, for any reason at all.
Even when they bend over backwards
to kowtow to the Party.
Which just shows that they don't know
anything about kowtowing.
It’s just like how one day,
the Chinese government offices
decided to ban Windows 8
and replace it with a Chinese knockoff—
and there was nothing Microsoft
could do about it.
The Chinese Communist Party’s
arbitrary, highly politicized control of the
government
and the judicial system
strikes fear into the hearts of
every company operating in China.
So I understand why Apple is concerned.
They don’t just make iPhones in China.
China is also the world’s biggest consumer
of iPhones.
I mean, the Communist Party
could just ban the sales of iPhones tomorrow
in the entire country.
I know it sounds crazy,
but it briefly happened in Beijing last year.
So Apple is facing a real threat
to its bottom line in China.
But at least by being so morally flexible,
and doing what the Chinese government tells
them,
Apple has had smooth sailing in China.
Just kidding!
At every step of the way,
the Chinese regime has still made things
as difficult as possible.
In 2012,
Apple had to pay 60 million to a Chinese company
to get the rights to the name iPad in China,
because Chinese courts
wouldn’t grant Apple the trademark.
And in 2013,
CEO Tim Cook was forced to issue a humiliating
public apology
to Chinese consumers
after Chinese state-media
launched a largely false campaign
to smear Apple’s customer service reputation.
Then in 2016,
Chinese authorities shut down the iBooks store
and iTunes movies just a few months
after Apple launched them in China.
Plus the whole iPhone6 ban
I mentioned earlier.
And just this month,
Chinese authorities summoned Apple to court
over its app store.
So, I guess Apple has learned a lesson
from being the victim of arbitrary,
unfair actions by the Communist Party.
And that lesson is:
That’s how Apple ought to treat everyone
else!
So I’m not super surprised that Apple TV
banned China Uncensored in China.
Though I am surprised they banned our app
in Hong Kong and Taiwan.
Unless that's just some more of that
backwards kowtowing on the One-China policy.
But you know what?
I say, if Tim Cook is willing to accept the
Newseum’s Free Speech Award,
he should accept the responsibility it implies.
Mr. Cook:
Put your money where your mouth is
and make Apple stop removing media apps
from your app stores in Hong Kong and Taiwan,
as well as in mainland China.
Because remember,
“It’s not just about making money,
it’s also about making a difference in the world.”
So what do you think Apple should do
to make a difference in the world?
Leave your comments below.
And to further encourage Tim Cook and Apple
to make the right decision,
click the link below to sign our petition
to get the China Uncensored app back in the
Hong Kong
and Taiwan app stores.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.