On this episode of China Uncensored,
it’s a credibility fire sale!
We’re selling off all our reputation!
Everything must go!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
The most prestigious publications in the world,
the Cambridge University Press,
totally caved to Chinese censorship.
“Late last week, the publisher
said it had removed around 300 papers
from its website in China,
covering topics like the Tiananmen Square
protests,
the Cultural Revolution,
and Tibet,
after the Chinese government threatened to
ban it
from publishing other material in the country.”
More than 300 articles written by
some of the most prominent China analysts
today.
Mind you, Chinese censors
weren’t actually reading their dry scholarly
articles.
It was based on a rough keyword search
that singled out the 300 peer-reviewed articles.
Mention of the Cultural Revolution was a big
one.
Taiwan, Tiananmen, and of course Falun Gong
keywords
were also targeted.
In an official statement,
Cambridge University Press wanted to let everyone
know
they are totally all about freedom of thought.
But they still were giving into the Chinese
regime’s
censorship demands,
because it’s better that some articles
get into China than none,
blah blah blah,
you’ve heard it all before.
It’s like when Apple CEO Tim Cook
blocked VPNs in the Chinese App Store,
saying, “We’re all for freedom of speech...
but we’re also all for compromising those
values
if we can get access to that sweet,
sweet China market.”
Not an exact quote,
but I’m pretty sure that’s what he meant.
Anyway, the Cambridge University Press’s
statement
ended with their mission of
“disseminating knowledge
in the pursuit of education,
learning and research at the highest
international levels of excellence.”
Right.
My favorite state-run media the Global Times
totally agreed with their decision...
while at the same time belittling them
for how few people read their crummy rag,
saying, “As the readership of the China
Quarterly is limited,
there will be little impact over the Cambridge
University Press
withdrawing some articles.”
But you know what is
going to be a hot seller?
A book about Xi Jinping!
The good news, though,
is that even though the Cambridge University
Press
is one of the world’s oldest
and most respected publishing houses,
this absolutely won’t set some kind of precedent
that will go into effect merely days later…
Oh.
The US Association for Asian Studies
also was asked to remove 100 articles
from its Journal of Asian Studies.
There goes the neighborhood.
But unlike the Cambridge University Press,
they said no right away.
But, wait!
This story has a happy ending after all.
Cambridge University Press did finally repost
everything they had taken down.
After a huge media backlash
and lots of public criticism.
“That sparked an international outcry,
with hundreds signing an online petition
and threatening to boycott CUP publications.”
You see?
All it takes to stand up to tyranny
is a little global condemnation.
I think this random Chinese gif
best sums up their response to the whole incident.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Well gang,
it looks like things worked out this time.
But what about next time?!
Better stay informed by going to ChinaUncensored.tv
to watch full half hour episodes of China
Uncensored
that we give you for free every week.
And unlike Cambridge University Press,
we’ll never pull our content off our Chinese
website...
mainly because we don’t have a Chinese website,
since, well you know...