On this episode of China Uncensored
From Russia with love
China’s richest man is retiring, and headed
to the beach.
And, how to adjust your watch...to terrorism
time.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
President Trump’s trade war with China
has the Communist Party worried.
China’s Shanghai stock exchange has hit
a 31-month low.
Trump is asking big American companies
to move production back to the United States.
And he wants to put even more tariffs on China.
And you know what that means:
A stronger alliance between America’s two
biggest rivals:
China and Russia!
Xi Jinping and Vladimir “No relation to
Dracula” Putin
met on the sidelines of the Eastern Economic
Forum.
What could these two masterminds of evil
possibly come together to do?!
Why, shopping!
And making pancakes!!!
Wow, Xi Jinping is so much better at it than
Putin
Be sure to load up on the caviar!
Two kinds!
You boys deserve a treat!
That’s the happiest I’ve ever seen Xi
Jinping...
Since that one time he got to hold
that really big cucumber.
Now while making pancakes together
may not seem sinister or evil,
may I just point out to you,
metal utensils on nonstick pans.
Noooooo!
This is what we’re up against, people.
Anyway, in between the shopping and cooking,
Xi Jinping did suggest, “both countries
should continue
investing in energy, agricultural projects,
tourism,
infrastructure and education.”
While also emphasizing, that, you know,
“China is open for international cooperation”
and is “willing to study” opportunities
with other countries.
Speaking of international cooperation,
Putin also gave Xi Jinping a ticket to the
gun show.
No, not that gun show.
This gun show.
Russia just hosted its biggest war games
since the fall of the Soviet Union.
And Putin invited his pancake buddy to join
in.
It was massive exercise near the Russia-China
border.
Russia and China have hosted joint war games
before,
but this was by far the biggest.
They mobilized 300,000 troops.
China’s Defense Ministry said don’t worry,
the games were only focused on “defenses,
firepower strikes and counterattack”—
and were “not directed against any third
party”.
You hear that, President Trump?
Not directed at any third party.
But while the war games were going on
along one Russia-China border,
the US has expressed its concern with
another area near China’s border—Xinjiang.
The US State Department expressed concern
over
the worsening crackdown on Uighur Muslims
there.
That’s right.
The Trump administration is expressing concern
about the treatment of Muslims.
Apparently they’re even considering putting
sanctions
on Chinese officials who’ve been persecuting
them.
But the Chinese Communist Party hit back,
saying “whoa whoa whoa,
there’s no religious persecution in China!”
“The Chinese government guarantees freedom
of religion
for its citizens in accordance with the law.
All peoples of China fully enjoy freedom of
religion
in accordance with the law."
My gosh, he didn’t even bat an eyelash.
I think Shelley has some competition
for the ultimate straight man.
Meanwhile, China is drafting a law
to crack down on “chaotic online religious
info.”
My favorite Chinese state run media the Global
Times
says the draft law is very timely,
because “religious information on the Chinese
internet
is chaotic due to the illegal promotion
of some extreme forces and cults.”
Basically if you want to talk about religion
online,
you need a license.
And no more live streaming.
But remember…
“All peoples of China fully enjoy freedom
of religion
in accordance with the law."
Speaking of saying one thing and doing another,
the Chinese regime has approached the World
Trade Organization
for permission to sanction the US.
You know, the same World Trade Organization
whose rules
China has violated dozens of times.
China’s push for sanctions is based on a
2013 complaint it made
about the anti-dumping duties the US had put
on China.
They were designed to offset the artificially
low cost
of Chinese imports that were undercutting
US manufacturing.
But how the US calculated those dumping duties
was found to have been illegal in a string
of trade disputes
brought to the WTO.
But don’t worry, those sanctions on the
US
won’t be happening any time soon.
“It is likely to lead to years of legal
wrangling.”
Man, I can see why everyone just ignores the
WTO.
And why President Trump thinks it’s the
worst deal ever.
No, seriously.
“I would say the WTO is the single worst
trade deal ever made,
and if they don’t shape up,
I would withdraw from the WTO.”
The world of Chinese business is incredibly
murky,
especially because of the close working relationship
private businesses have to have with the Chinese
government.
So it definitely raised some eyebrows when
Alibaba CEO
and richest man in China Jack Ma said he was
retiring.
Even Vladimir Putin was surprised!
I mean, Putin didn’t retire even when the
law required him to!
But considering the tendency for powerful
business leaders in China
to be purged and end up in detention,
Jack Ma’s retirement has people wondering
about
whether he or his company might be in trouble.
“In China, businessmen who fly too high
have a habit
of falling out of favor with the ruling Communist
Party.”
But Jack Ma says not to worry, there are no
charges against him,
and he’s not going to prison!
He just wants to hand over the company to
younger leadership—
so he can have a chance to live life.
As he put it, he’d rather die on the beach
than in his office.
Die on the beach?
In China?
Um...dying in the office doesn’t actually
sound so bad.
Anyway, speaking of having a chance to live
life,
three offices related to family planning have
closed down.
“Family Planning” in China is a euphemism
that refers to the Communist Party-run offices
that control how many children you’re allowed
to have.
And if you try to have too many,
they help make sure mom gets an abortion,
whether she likes it or not.
But China’s population is getting old
and there aren’t enough young people anymore.
That’s why the Communist Party is doing
away with
the Family Planning office that implemented
the famous
One Child Policy and then the Two Child Policy.
But while policies change,
the Communist Party isn’t planning to relax
control.
They’re just replacing the Family Planning
offices
with “a new office for ‘population monitoring
and family development’”.
That doesn’t sound creepy at all.
It will be responsible for, “improving birth
policy
and to organize implementation,
and to establish and improve the system
of extraordinary family assistance for family
planning.”
Okay, yeah, that’s sounding really creepy
now.
A man in China’s Western region of Xinjiang
has been detained on terrorism charges.
Is it because he’s Muslim?
No.
Was he plotting a terrorist attack?
Also no.
It was much more serious.
He had set his watch two hours behind Beijing
time.
You see, even though China covers
what normally would stretch across five time
zones,
The Chinese Communist Party decided long ago
that all official clocks must be set to Beijing
time.
So 9am in Xinjiang might not even have daylight
yet.
That’s why people in Xinjiang
also keep their own informal local time—
you know, so things make sense.
But insisting that things make sense
is also a subtle way to subvert the central
authorities.
But really, in a region where the paramilitary
is employing surveillance cameras
and even drones to watch your every move,
it’s probably worth setting your watch to
the official time.
And now it’s that time when we answer questions
from fans
who support the show on the crowd funding
website Patreon.
With YouTube demonetization,
we basically rely entirely on viewer support,
so this is our way of saying thank you.
David Michael White asks, Matt,
what is your Chinese zodiak sign?
Dog.
Thanks for your question, David.
And remember, when you support this show—
like with a dollar per episode,
which is less than a cup of coffee by the
way—
you’ll be making a huge difference.
Head over to patreon.com/chinauncensored to
learn more,
and check out all the other perks we’ll
give you.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Oh hi...you’re still here?
I guess you must really want more!
In that case I’d say check out our new podcast,
China Unscripted.
The whole team talks China with some of the
leading experts.
You’ll love it.
Subscribe on iTunes, Stitcher,
Spotify, and even YouTube.
Once again that’s China Unscripted.