On this episode of China Uncensored,
nothing says Christmas
like a war on drugs.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
’Tis the season to be jolly, I say!
A time of brotherhood, a season of giving.
Just ask my friend Philippine President Rodrigo
Duterte.
He knows the true meaning of Christmas.
I mean, check out this video he made for Christmas
last year!
“I’m only human, so I’ll still say Merry
Christmas
to drug traffickers, thieves, corrupt criminals,
and those who’ve made life hard for Filipinos.
But if you don’t stop and the violence continues...
this will be your last Merry Christmas.”
Yikes.
He’s more like Krampus than Santa Claus.
Santa Claus, apparently, is being played by
China this year.
And it’s given Duterte a major yule log.
He’s been seeking weapons from China since
the beginning of his presidency.
Details of the deal aren’t public yet.
But Duterte has done a pretty good job of
making
last year’s Christmas threat a promise.
As of December 1,
his police have killed more than 2,000 people
in his war on drugs.
The international community has condemned
his drug war.
And Duterte has condemned the international
community.
“I would like to just give an advice to
all the human rights
(groups) who are shouting now, local or international.
I said you can all go to hell.”
Since Duterte became president,
he’s moved for closer ties with China
at the expense of ties with the U.S.
Duterte even agreed to take a “back seat”
on the hotly contested territorial dispute
between The Philippines and China.
So much so that Filipino fishing boats can
visit the Scarborough Shoal again.
Trust me, I know.
But here’s the thing:
Duterte wants help from China fighting his
war on drugs.
Yet, according to a reliable source,
a lot of the drugs, drug dealers, and materials
come from China.
And that reliable source is Duterte himself.
In fact, in July this year, shortly after
becoming president,
Duterte met with Chinese businessman Peter
Lim who is, um,
totally not a drug lord,
and instead of killing him,
gave him chance to clear his name with the
National Bureau of Investigation.
It probably had nothing do with them knowing each other from before.
Then in September,
Duterte spoke about how the machinery
that makes synthetic drugs like methamphetamine
comes from China.
“All of the materials come from China...
If you consider us your friend,
you want to help us,
but most of the materials,
and the machines and the boilers are from
China.
What does that mean?”
What does that mean?
It means this year,
“Santa Claus China” wears a pork pie hat.
You see, they supply the best drugs,
and the machines to make the drugs.
But amazingly, the drug enforcers ask for
their help.
Then, in the end,
they’re the ones to bring the big guns and
kill the drug dealers.
And millions of people think they’re the
heroes.
Now that’s smart business, China!
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And if you like this show, please support
China Uncensored on Patreon.
The link is below.
Thanks for watching this episode.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Hey. While I was in Taiwan,
I teamed up with Allen from Off the Great Wall
for a night market adventure.
Click here to check it out.
So yeah. It’s great to be in
basically the parallel timeline version of a democratic China,
where they didn’t destroy the culture.