On this episode of China Uncensored,
pollution solutions that will blow your mind.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
China has some of the worst pollution in the
world.
According to independent research group,
Berkeley Earth,
4,000 people a day die in China because of
air pollution.
That’s about 17% of all deaths.
Not including having your organs harvested.
“It’s as if every man, woman and child
smoked 1.5 cigarettes
each hour."
Doesn’t help that China has a smoking problem
either.
But the worst kind of pollution is this:
PM 2.5 particles.
Tiny little particles,
smaller than even individual particles of
pollen.
And you thought allergies were bad.
These PM 2.5 particles are mainly coming from
coal.
China burns almost as much coal
as the rest of the world combined.
Yeah, even more than
Uncle Nicky’s Coal emporium and Fun House.
So what’s being done to solve the problem?
Well, there are a lot of...um, brilliant...ideas.
And here are 10 of my favorites.
Number 10
Banning Stuff
Sure, the deadly air pollution caused by unregulated
factories
and unrestrained coal burning is bad.
But factories and coal plants make money!
So the government banned outdoor barbecuing instead.
That was back in 2013.
And obviously it didn’t work.
But if at first you don’t succeed,
try, try again!
Number 9
Vacuum it up!
A Dutch artist has worked with China to design
this:
The Smog Free Tower.
It’s essentially a giant vacuum that sucks
in pollution
and turns it into jewelry!
Here, honey, I got you this ring made of smog
to symbolize how I feel about you.
Number 8
A drone will work, right?
I know what I want
in one of the most repressive societies on
the planet—
drones everywhere!
Circling in the air,
spraying chemicals that will freeze pollution
and allow it to fall gently to the ground.
And onto the faces of an unsuspecting populace.
Brilliant.
Number 7
Let’s try shutting down more things.
Cars and factories are some of the biggest
sources of pollution.
But getting rid of them would be way too heavy-handed.
Except when you want to look good internationally!
Like during the 2008 Beijing Olympics!
Or the military parade in 2015.
Or this year’s G20 Summit.
But once the spotlight is off,
things can get back to normal.
It’s like how you really only clean the
house
before you have guests over.
Number 6
Cover it up!
Former CCTV anchor Chai Jing
was inspired to make a documentary about pollution
after her daughter was born with a tumor.
The documentary went viral.
A week later,
authorities solved the problem.
No, not by cleaning up the pollution.
By banning her documentary.
And the 200 million Chinese citizens
who had already watched it by then
surely forgot what they’d seen.
Problem solved!
Number 5
No, literally, cover it up.
When the world’s on your case for spewing
out so much pollution
that it even reaches the United States,
Whaddya gonna do?
Stuff cotton balls into your air monitoring
equipment.
Because then, how will anyone know there’s
pollution, mwhaha.
Oh yeah.
They have eyes.
Number 4
Turn on the sprinklers
No, not just any sprinklers.
Giant, giant ones!
Put them on top of skyscrapers.
It’s like how you’d spray water on a baseball
diamond
to keep the dust down.
This idea comes from Shaocai Yu,
a geoengineering researcher from Zhejiang
and North Carolina State universities.
Wow, his Photoshopping is even worse than
Chinese officials’!
Number 3
Conversion—it’s not just for infidels
anymore
If coal is the problem,
then converting it to natural gas
must be the solution!
Natural gas burns cleaner with less emissions.
Wow, do we have an actual idea here?
Well, before you get too excited,
there are a few problems.
One,
even though it won’t produce the same kind
of air pollution as coal,
natural gas can “release 36-108% more greenhouse
gases than coal.”
It also takes loads of water to convert.
So where should we build these?
Obviously in Xinjiang and Inner Mongolia,
where there’s almost no more water left.
But you know, that was almost a real idea.
Maybe the next one will be as well.
Number 2
Space Lasers.
To reduce its reliance on dirty coal power,
China has drawn up plans to build a gigantic
solar-powered spacecraft.
It would convert solar energy into microwave
energy
that would then be shot down to the Earth
like a giant laser beam,
and then converted to electricity.
What could go wrong with giant space lasers?
And Number 1
Change your thinking!
Why all this negative talk about pollution?
You can’t solve it.
So change your perspective!
Party mouthpiece CCTV did.
In an article that’s now been removed from
the Internet,
a CCTV editor argued that pollution has many
benefits.
Didn’t stop there.
My favorite state-run media Global Times pointed
out
that smog even has practical military applications.
I mean, your enemy can’t blow you up if
they can’t see you!
Well, those were all pretty crazy.
And that just scratches the surface.
I didn’t even have time to get to the giant
floating jellyfish.
That one will have to wait for next week,
when I release part 2,
yet another 10 insane pollution solutions.
So what do you think of these?
And what’s your guess about the jellyfish?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.