The Beijing 2022 Winter Olympics
Are just one year away.
And there will be no problems whatsoever.
Welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
It’s 2021, and the Olympic Games are almost
upon us!
No, I’m not talking about the 2020 summer
olympics in Tokyo that were postponed to 2021
because of Covid.
And which Japanese people are mostly opposed
to holding at all now—because of Covid.
No, I’m talking about the much anticipated
2022 Olympics in Beijing!
Yes, the Winter Olympics—the forgotten stepchild
of the good Olympics.
This month marks one year out from the Beijing
2022 Winter Olympics.
And according to Chinese state-run media,
it’s just received a vote of confidence!
Which is the only vote that’s allowed in
China.
Now, sure there have been some problems.
Like how the mountains near Beijing don’t...have...snow.
But that’s only a minor problem for Beijing—according
to this state-run media video.
"The National Alpine Skiing Center has been
built at an altitude of 2,198 meters with
great efforts."
Wait, go back.
See?
You can just cover your bare mountain slopes
in artificial snow, and no one will be the
wiser.
And that’s definitely not a metaphor for
anything else that happens in communist China.
It’s like how ahead of the 2008 Olympics,
they spray painted the grass green.
At least there was grass there in the first
place.\h
So I say, why bother to even make fake snow
for 2022—when you can just spray paint the
rocks white!
This way you can have the Winter Olympics
and the X Games all in one!
Of course, there’s one other pesky little
problem with the 2022 Winter Olympics: A lot
of human rights groups want to boycott it.
As Hong Kong Free Press put it last week,
“China will host the first genocide Olympics”.
Which, I don’t think is fair.
It’s actually the second Genocide Olympics.
The first one was when Beijing held the Olympics
in 2008.
But at least Beijing will be the first city
in the world to host both a Summer and Winter
Genocide Olympics.
Truly historic.\h
And for all those who are concerned, don’t
worry: There won’t be any genocide happening
*at* the Olympics.
It will be happening at the *same time* as
the Olympics, but in a totally different part
of China.
Where we can all ignore it while talking about
how impressive the opening ceremony is.
Nonetheless, the calls for a boycott are growing.\h
Last week, a group of UK Members of Parliament
from across the political spectrum called
for a boycott of the 2022 Beijing Winter Games.
As MP Ed Davey put it, “Our brightest and
best athletes should not be forced to be part
of a propaganda exercise for the Chinese Communist
party while it tries to wipe the Uighur people
off the face of the planet.”
They’re calling for British athletes to
simply not participate, unless the 2022 Olympics
is moved to another country that doesn’t
have these kinds of human rights abuses.
I know, it’s hard to move the Olympics only
one year out.
But there *are* other cities that already
have all the infrastructure for the Winter
Olympics...and totally different kinds of
human rights abuses.
See, the ones in Russia were the Gulag Games.
I hope you realize by now that no matter how
bad human right abuses get, the International
Olympics Committee really doesn’t give a
hoot.
Because as the former head of the IOC once
said, “we stand for human rights...but we
are only a sports organization.”
That’s from the same 2007 interview where
he said he believed the upcoming 2008 Beijing
Olympic Games would “be a force for good.”
How’d that turn out?
Anyway, there are still calls for a boycott
of the Beijing 2022 Olympics.
And the Chinese Communist Party wants you
to know, they don’t care.
As my favorite state-run media The Global
Times says, the forces inciting a boycott
of the Winter Olympics will never succeed.
Because their “extreme claims...will never
be widely echoed”.
And to prove how little China cares, they
will ‘seriously sanction’ any country
that boycotts the Winter Olympics.\h
This also shows that China opposes politicizing
the Beijing Winter Olympics.
To be clear, it’s other countries’ boycotts
that are politicizing things, not China’s
revenge sanctions.
Those are not political.
Now I’m not saying these threats haven’t
worked to stop the boycotts.
But they also haven’t not worked.
“The US has said it had no intention of
telling its athletes not to go.”
Yeah.
Sometimes you just gotta cooperate with China,
despite the genocide.
And Canada has taken it one step further.
The Canadian Olympic Committee is warning
its athletes not to even criticize China.
Which, sadly, might be good advice—if those
athletes want to be allowed to leave China.
Unlike all the Canadians that have been detained
there.
There were calls for boycotts of the 2008
Beijing Olympics, too.
But in the end, no countries boycotted.
But even without an Olympic boycott, people
around the world found ways to highlight China’s
human rights abuses.\h
Like when Beijing had the brilliant idea to
bring their Olympic torch relay around the
world.
And then people protested it.
At every...
Stop...
Along...
The...
Way.
It was pretty embarrassing for the Chinese
Communist Party, what with people around the
world airing their dirty laundry.
But despite, or perhaps because of, the global
embarrassment, the Chinese Communist Party
promised to allow protests during the Olympics.
They even set up special zones inside three
Beijing parks, where people would be allowed
to protest.
All protesters had to do first was “obtain
permits from the local police”.
And you can guess how that worked out: really
well!
For the police.
Who just arrested protesters ahead of time.
Pre-crime—I’m telling you—it works.
So now that we’ve learned from the 2008
Beijing Olympics, will anything change for
the 2022 Beijing Olympics?\h
Although there is more awareness globally
about the Chinese Communist Party’s human
right abuses, and their attempt to influence
the rest of the world, it’s still unlikely
there will be an Olympics boycott.\h
Historically, there have been two major boycotts
of Olympic games.
During the Cold War, the US, Canada, and more
than 60 countries boycotted the 1980 Moscow
Olympics.
The US boycotted because of the Soviet invasion
of Afghanistan.
In return, the Soviet Union and a group of
mostly communist countries boycotted the 1984
Los Angeles Olympics.
And since the US has said it has no plans
to boycott the Beijing Olympics, it’s unlikely
other countries will.
However, now some human rights groups are
calling for a different type of boycott—a
diplomatic boycott.
That means that countries would let their
athletes compete in the Olympics, but they
wouldn’t send a high-level official to attend.
That way, they take away some of the soft
power that the Chinese Communist Party gets
from hosting the event.
Will any countries do that?
It’s still too soon to say.\h
So despite all the protests ahead of the 2022
Olympics...
It looks like the 2022 Beijing Games are going
to go ahead as planned.
Snow or no snow.
And I think this is a terrible mistake.
Because what *should* happen, is the Chinese
Communist Party should *welcome* other countries
to boycott the Olympics.
Especially all the countries with the best
athletes.
Because then, China can win all the gold medals
for themselves.
And now it’s time for me to answer a question
from one of you, a viewer who directly supports
China Uncensored by contributing a dollar
or more per episode on the crowdfunding website
Patreon.
Casey asks:
“Are coin collectors unintentionally rewarding
the CCP by purchasing gold and silver panda
coins?’
I think the real question, Casey, is why would
anyone want to collect a panda-anything?
Pandas are the very symbol of Beijing’s
propaganda.
“Oh, we’re so cute, look at us.
The Communist Party is so soft and cuddly.
We could never forcibly harvest your organs.”
No!
It’s a lie!
Don’t fall for it!
Argh, stop!
So yes, don’t buy China’s stupid panda
coins.\h
Also, if you buy a gold coin from China, would
you really trust that it’s made entirely
of real gold?
Thanks for your question, Casey.
Be like Casey, and support China Uncensored.
Viewer support is the main way we fund China
Uncensored.
Go to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored to learn
more.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.