On this episode of China Uncensored,
the world’s biggest company
tries to bully the world’s most popular
comedy show...
about China...
based in New York...
starring Chris Chappell.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
I have a big announcement to make today.
The good news is that thanks largely
to the financial support of our viewers,
who contribute via Patreon...
...and thanks to YouTube
for constantly demonitizing our videos—
we’re taking China Uncensored to a new platform.
Television!
Digital television.
As of today,
you can download the free China Uncensored app
for Roku, Amazon Fire TV,
and Apple TV.
You do need the newest versions of each, though,
from mid-2016 or later—
because only the new ones let you download
apps.
You can search for China Uncensored,
or the technical name of the app, “China
Unsnsrd”
because you can only have up to 13 characters.
Anyway, this means you can sit on your couch
with a cup of tea,
and stream my face
directly through your television.
And even though that’s weird for me personally,
it’s good for the show.
The app is free for you,
and supported by ads that support us.
And since it’s not YouTube,
we’ll get better ads and our videos won’t
be demonitized
just because I talk about North Korea or whatever.
Don’t worry,
we’ll also keep putting videos on YouTube
too.
But I also have some bad news.
Remember how I said we’re on Apple TV?
Well, Apple did approve our app,
but then they sent us this notice:
It basically says, our app has been removed
from the China, Hong Kong, and Taiwan App
Stores.
I mean, I’m not really that surprised
Apple blocked us from mainland China.
After all, I do undermine China’s social
stability
every time I tell the truth.
And I’m sure Apple doesn’t want
to get in trouble in China,
since China is now the world’s largest market
for iPhones.
But blocking us from Hong Kong and Taiwan?
C’mon!
Is Apple so scared of the Chinese Communist
Party
that they’ve blocked us there too,
just in case?
Or did they somehow not realize
that Hong Kong and Taiwan
are independent regions?
I mean, Apple is the biggest company in the
world.
Don’t they have lawyers that could tell
them
that China Uncensored is legal in Hong Kong
and Taiwan?
I’ve definitely interviewed government officials
in both regions
and I distinctly recall not getting arrested
for it.
So I’ve retained my own public interest
lawyer.
And yesterday morning,
I express mailed a letter to Apple’s CEO
Tim Cook.
But I think Apple is going to need a bit more
of a push.
And they’re where you come in,
my 50-Cent Army!
Together, let’s put pressure Apple to stop
censoring
China Uncensored in Hong Kong and Taiwan.
Go to my website—
which I guess I’m also officially launching
today.
The link is below.
And sign this petition.
Every signature counts.
Be sure to share it with your friends, too.
And if you live in Hong Kong or Taiwan,
there’s one more thing you can do.
At the bottom of that petition website,
you can download and print out a paper petition,
and take it around in your city to collect
signatures.
And then email me a good-quality scan of each
page
to ChinaUncensored@gmail.com.
Don’t let the world’s biggest company
bully China Uncensored.
Click the link below and sign the petition.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell,
and you are the best viewers in the world.