Did China sink a ship in the South China Sea?
Trump bans investment in companies\h
linked to the Chinese military.
And Henry Kissinger is back—and he\h
wants us to “cooperate” with China.
That and more on this week’s China news headlines.
Welcome to China Uncensored. I’m Chris Chappell.
This episode is sponsored by Surfshark. You should\h\h
be using a VPN like Surfshark to protect\h
your identity whenever you go online.
The US military may be changing\h
its operational calculations if\h\h
new reports about Chinese missiles are true.
Back in August, China launched a barrage of\h
medium-range missiles into the South China Sea.
It was viewed as retaliation for a US spy plane\h\h
that flew over a Chinese\h
naval drill just days before.\h
Those missiles are what China\h
calls aircraft-carrier killers.
It’s all part of China’s peaceful\h
claims to the entire South China Sea.
According to US defense officials,\h
those missiles landed somewhere here,\h\h
between China’s Hainan Island,\h
and the disputed Paracel islands.
At first, it was believed those missiles just\h
hit water. But now, according to a PLA insider\h\h
speaking to the South China Morning Post, those\h
missiles may have actually hit a target ship.
If that’s true, it’s the first time China has\h\h
actually demonstrated its anti-ship\h
missiles can actually hit a ship.\h
Of course there’s still a lot of unknowns. We\h
don’t know how many missiles were fired, whether\h\h
the target ship was moving or how fast, and\h
whether we can believe the former PLA colonel who\h\h
said this happened. Because maybe he’s just trying\h
to scare the US military. Good luck with that.
But one thing is clear,\h\h
despite the Communist Party’s calls for US\h
China cooperation instead of decoupling...
their aim is to dominate the United\h
States by any means necessary.\h\h
And the US needs to adjust\h
its strategy accordingly.\h\h
Wait, I know how the US can fight against China’s\h
anti-ship missiles...with giant jaeger robots!
But economic decoupling is probably a\h
better route than military conflict.
Speaking of the US and China decoupling,\h
despite the Trump Administration having...a\h\h
lot on its plate right now,\h
experts say the administration\h\h
is still moving forward with plans to\h
decouple the US and China’s economy.\h
Trump recently issued an executive order\h\h
that will ban US investments in several\h
companies tied to the Chinese military.
Raising the question—why were US companies\h
investing in companies tied to China’s military?!
The Executive Order says China “is\h
increasingly exploiting United States capital\h\h
to resource and to enable the development\h
and modernization of its military,\h\h
intelligence, and other security apparatuses.”
That includes “weapons of mass\h
destruction, advanced conventional weapons,\h\h
and malicious cyber-enabled actions\h
against the United States and its people.”
According to White House trade adviser\h
Peter Navarro these 31 Chinese companies\h\h
represent at least half a trillion\h
dollars in market capitalization.
Wow, that’s a lot of money! Maybe I should\h
invest in companies tied to the Chinese military!
And if that sounds stupid, don’t worry,\h
there’s a lot of stupid going around.\h\h
Despite everything we know about\h
the Chinese Communist Party,\h\h
US companies just can’t seem\h
to quit the China market.
This is the actual first line to that article.\h
“For some American businesses,\h
having an office in China\h\h
may help them weather the impact\h
of the coronavirus pandemic.”
Think about that. They’re looking to the Communist\h\h
Party to help them deal with the economic\h
hit caused by the coronavirus pandemic,\h\h
which was caused by the Communist\h
Party’s lies and cover up.\h
At least that’s slightly better than this: German\h
companies saying we’re better off thanks to China.
In what world could that possibly be true?
But with the US presidential\h
election outcome still...in\h\h
progress, many US elites are hoping that\h
Biden wins...and that Biden would reset US\h\h
China relations to what they were\h
before the Trump Administration.\h
Which is why the specter of Henry Kissinger\h\h
has risen once again, calling on Biden\h
to restore relationships with China.
I mean, if the state-run People’s\h
Daily is praising Kissenger,\h\h
his ideas must be great! For\h
the Chinese Communist Party.
Kissinger made his remarks at\h
the Bloomberg New Economy Forum.\h
Fun fact, you can join the conversation\h
on the New Economy Forum using WeChat,\h\h
a Chinese mobile app that the US government\h
has called a national security threat!
Anyway, Henry Kissinger said,\h
unless China and the US can\h\h
cooperate, “The world will slide into a\h
catastrophe comparable to World War I.”
Which...is insane. America’s engagement with\h
and investment in China are precisely what have\h\h
enabled China to fund its militarization—which\h
at this point, could lead to World War III.
And who was it starting in the 1970s that kept\h
pushing for closer US-China engagement? Hmmm...
Hey, if there’s another World War, I\h
wonder which side Germany would be on.
This week was the one year anniversary of when\h\h
Hong Kong police laid siege to the\h
Hong Kong Polytechnic University.\h\h
Police were trying to arrest hundreds of\h
protesters who got trapped inside the University.
The police greeted unarmed\h
protesters with brutal force.
And they turned the school into a war-zone.
At one point, protesters had\h
to rappel out of the campus\h\h
to be picked up by volunteers on motorbikes.
Just one more reason why school can\h
be a dangerous place for young people.
The Chinese regime’s crackdown on Hong Kong is a\h
stern warning about what might happen in Taiwan\h\h
if the Chinese Communist Party seized power there.\h\h
And a growing US-Taiwan alliance is making\h
such a scenario less and less likely.
Secretary of State Mike Pompeo\h
made the unprecedented move\h\h
to come out and say Taiwan is not part of China.
China responded by warning of\h
action, whatever that means.
Only Henry Kissinger can save us!
But there is some good news for relations between\h
China and the UK at least. A British diplomat\h\h
saved a Chinese college student from drowning.\h
This is British consul-general in Chongqing\h\h
Stephen Ellison, jumping into the water to save\h
the woman. Someone throws in a floatation device,\h\h
and then Ellison swims her to that, and they’re\h
both safely pulled out of the water. The woman\h\h
later recovered. This video went viral in China,\h
and the 61 year old is being hailed a hero.
Unfortunately, all that goodwill between\h
China and the West has since been wiped out,\h\h
after Beyond Meat launched their\h
plant-based minced pork in China.
Not going to end well.
And this episode has been sponsored\h
by Surfshark. Whenever you go online,\h\h
you should be using a VPN like\h
Surfshark to protect your identity.
Because governments and your internet\h
service provider may be watching you.
And while protecting your identity online is\h
important, there’s also another advantage to\h\h
using a VPN: You can access websites that\h
are only available in other countries.
For example, let’s say you want to watch a\h
movie about giant jaegers. Like Pacfic Rim.
But you can’t access Pacific\h
Rim on Netflix in the US.\h\h
So, use Surfshark to switch your location\h
to Canada...log in again...and there it is.\h
Of course, these giant robots are\h
just futuristic science fiction.\h\h
Which is why Pacific Rim\h
was set in the year...2020?!
I’m not sure whether I’d\h
want that this year or not.\h\h
Probably not, if it comes with an attack on\h
all of humanity by inter-dimensional monsters.
Anyway, if for some reason you\h
don’t want to watch Pacific Rim,\h\h
there’s tons of other movies and\h
TV shows that you can only watch\h\h
if you’re logged into Netflix in another\h
country...by using a VPN like Surfshark.
And with one account, you can\h
connect as many devices as you want.\h\h
Try it out with a 30-day money back guarantee.
And Surfshark has a special discount for China\h
Uncensored fans. Go to surfshark.com/uncensored\h\h
and use the code UNCENSORED\h
to get our special Black\h\h
Friday deal that includes 4 extra months for FREE.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell. See you next time.