On this episode of China Uncensored,
North Korea got us a gift package!
I can’t wait to see what’s inside.
Welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Good news everyone!
So I took a little break from the news
over the Labor Day weekend.
I mean you need a little time off
every now and then.
And when I came back,
I was so happy to see that
the nuclear standoff with North Korea
had been peacefully resolved!
Apparently things have worked out so well,
that North Korea is sending the US gift packages,
isn’t that nice?
Wait, what’s that Shelley?
You want me to watch this Fox News clip?
Okay...
“Well, the US and it’s allies
contemplating the next move
after North Korea tests its 6th
and most powerful bomb to date.”
I’m not sure which is more disturbing.
The fact that North Korea considers
a nuclear bomb a gift package,
this Fox News graphic,
or the fact that Shelley
recommended I watch Fox News.
But before I freak out,
you know, again,
that was Fox News.
They exaggerate sometimes.
Let me see what the failing New York Times
has to say.
“The nuclear blast on Sunday
is roughly six times more powerful
than the North’s test of September 2016,
and eight times larger
than the bomb dropped on Hiroshima
in 1945.”
Everything’s fine.
No freaking out here.
The detonation caused multiple landslides…
and a 6.3 earthquake...
They said...it was a hydrogen bomb.
"The test of a hydrogen bomb
designed to be mounted on our
intercontinental ballistic missile
was a perfect success."
North Korea also released several pictures
of Kim Jong-un standing around
the alleged nuclear device.
Aww, look.
He’s doing a Napoleon impersonation.
Except Kim’s not a little man.
Well, the US is warning North Korea
not to try any more funny business,
or else it risks total annihilation.
Or, in language North Korea understands,
the US is going to give them
an unlimited Amazon gift card.
So what does this have to do with China?
Well, US President Donald Trump
is losing his patience with China
for not having stopped Kim Jong-Un already.
Even though Xi Jinping tried to explain to
him
his relationship status with North Korea
is complicated.
President Trump tweeted that the US
is considering stopping all trade
with any country doing business
with North Korea.
Yes, any country,
whichever one might be doing business with
North Korea.
Let’s see, who could that be?
It’s China, he’s talking about China.
Ok, and also Russia.
But this isn’t Russia Uncensored.
Sorry, guys.
Now the US has already put sanctions
on Chinese companies with ties to North Korea.
But that’s not enough.
Now Trump also wants an oil embargo
on North Korea.
Which is heartbreaking news
for the Chinese North Korea Friendship Pipeline
that runs under this river.
This year North Korea will receive
an estimated 850,000 tons of crude oil—
almost entirely from China.
Without oil,
North Korea’s military will be like
Popeye without spinach.
And that could make North Korea
unstable enough to collapse.
That’s why,
other than a 3-day embargo in 2003,
the Chinese regime has never cut
oil supplies to North Korea.
My favorite Chinese state-run media
the Global Times said back in April,
that if North Korea tests a 6th nuclear weapon,
“the Chinese society will be willing to
adopt severe restrictive measures
that have never been seen before,
such as restricting oil imports to the North.”
Well, North Korea did test
its 6th nuclear weapon on Sunday.
Global Times,
any thoughts?
“[China] should avoid resorting
to rash and extreme means
by imposing a full embargo on North Korea.”
I really can’t say I’m surprised
that the Global Times changed its mind.
The Chinese regime prefers to keep
the status quo,
even if the status quo is kind of scary.
Because you know what China
finds even scarier?
North Korea collapsing,
followed by millions of refugees
across its border.
But things may be reaching a tipping point.
The Chinese regime is facing pressure
from the Chinese people who are freaked out
about radioactive fallout from these tests,
let alone a nuclear war.
Under pressure from the public,
they’ve even set up a bunch of
new radiation monitoring sites
near the border.
And a few days after
this latest nuclear test,
the People’s Liberation Army began practicing
for a surprise North Korea attack.
Between pressure from the United States
and its own citizens,
Napoleon here might be facing his Waterloo.
In fact,
President Trump and Chinese leader Xi Jinping
spoke on the phone about North Korea,
and according to Trump,
it was a very frank
and very strong phone call,
and also Xi is with Trump 100%.
Well that makes me feel better.
And even if that doesn’t work,
there’s another man out there
who can fix this complicated mess.
A mature, experienced diplomat
who’s friends with both Kim Jong-Un
and Donald Trump.
Dennis Rodman has offered to step in
and “straighten things out.”
Yes, the fate of the world
could rest with this guy.
I’m sure it’s all going to turn out
just great.
No freaking out here.
What do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China Uncensored.
Once again, I'm your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Well it might not be
a North Korean mystery gift package,
but if you want a real treat,
head over to China uncensored.tv
to see full half hour episodes
of China Uncensored for free.
And even though there’s a chance
they may bomb,
they’ll never explode on you.
Radiation burns are possible.