On this episode of China Uncensored,
I’ve heard the expression
“Spare the rod, spoil the child.”
But I’m pretty sure this is not the kind
of rod they were talking about.
Hi, welcome back to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Well, it’s back to school time, kids,
and you know what that means—new backpacks,
freshly sharpened pencils, and mandatory military
drills!
Got to be ready to give your life
for the glorious Communist Party at any age.
But, at one kindergarten in Shenzhen,
the city where your iPhones are made,
thought they’d try something a little different
this year.
Pole dancing.
I think some kids kind of liked it.
American journalist Michael Standaert,
whose kids went to this kindergarten,
posted the pole dancing footage on Twitter.
It had been circulating on WeChat among angry
parents.
Apparently the principal of Xinshahui Kindergarten
in Shenzhen
thought pole dancing was the best way
to welcome students into a new school year.
According to Standaert, the principal even
personally
performed a pole dance using the school flagpole.
Which is...patriotic?
Then she brought in another dancer.
Because obviously, you can’t just have one
pole dance.
Kindergartens in China are part of preschool
education,
so the kids at the school were between 3 and
6 years old.
The principal, Lai Rong, defended her actions,
saying the pole dancing was to “liven up
the mood.”
And I can understand, kids that age are hard
to entertain!
I mean, the school already did
the military indoctrination thing over the
summer.
So there weren’t a lot of options left.
On the phone, the principal told Standaert’s
wife
that pole dancing was “international and
good exercise.”
She also told her that they were
“planning on having pole dancing classes
at the school.”
The parents of the kindergartners however,
were not thrilled.
Many called the police, the media,
and the local education bureau to complain.
So this story went viral.
Even the BBC had to cover it.
Very improper.
And once the story made Chinese and international
headlines,
the local education bureau
decided it should probably make a statement.
They said the pole dance was “inappropriate,”
and said the principal should be fired.
Well, she was.
After the public outcry, Principal Lai apologized,
saying
“It was a very terrible viewing experience
for the kids and the parents.”
I mean, c’mon, the dancing wasn’t that
bad.
Principal Lai also told the Washington Post,
“I just want the kids to know
the existence of this kind of dance.”
Perfectly reasonable!
3 to 6 year olds
should know about the existence of pole dancing.
Principal Lai calls herself a “pole dancing
enthusiast”
and said that she started pole dancing
to help her back and shoulder problems,
and even lost 20 pounds dancing.
I guess this is just a case where her personal
enthusiasm
overwhelmed her professional boundaries.
Like the time that Producer Matt tried to
build
an entire set for China Uncensored out of
Legos.
That was not ok, Matt!
I was stepping on Legos for weeks.
But unlike Matt, I think principal Lai can
be forgiven,
because pole dancing
is even being pushed in state-run media,
like my favorite, the Global Times.
Okay, I think that one got lost in translation.
That’s more like dancing with poles.
But here’s another Global Times article
that’s…
well it’s really not so much an article,
as it is just a series of pictures of women
pole dancing.
The headline is “Hot pole dancing staged
in the street”
but it doesn’t say which street.
Or even which country.
Wait, what’s that, Shelley?
You’re kidding.
Poland?
Pole-land?!
That’s too good.
Although that still doesn’t explain why
the Global Times
would publish those photos.
I guess it’s a mystery.
But the Global Times isn’t the only state-run
media
pushing the pole-dancing agenda.
Here’s a video from another state-run media,
the English version of Xinhua.
“The pole dance has become a way for people
to keep fit,
especially for girls and women.”
And can I just say, the guy teaching that
class is amazing.
Check out his t-shirt.
Yes, pole dancing is actually
something of a fitness craze in China right
now.
It started ten years ago,
according to this New York Times article from
2008.
I guess it’s like the yoga fitness craze
in America.
Only less spiritual and more...vertical.
According to CNN, “Hundreds of studios are
popping up across the country.”
One of the pole dancing experts they interviewed
said,
"At this point, in the whole country—everywhere,
every province, every corner—pole dancing
is popular...
Everyone has been exposed to this now."
Yep, everyone.
Including kindergarteners.
But get this:
“[Pole Dancing] is so hot that China
even has a national pole dance team,
and regularly hosts competitions in cities
like Beijing and Hong Kong.”
Yes, China has established its own national
pole dancing team!
And according to Principal Lai,
why shouldn’t she be able to introduce pole
dancing to the kids
when there’s even a pole dancing world championship?
Well, I there are plenty of things with world
championships
that I don’t think should be introduced
to young children.
Like Australian rules football.
Or air guitar.
But wait, if Principal Lai is saying that
pole dancing
is a prestigious international sport,
then this starts to make sense.
After all, the Chinese Communist Party
considers it a matter of national pride
to win international sports competitions.
That’s why for the Olympics,
they start the athletes out young,
and make them train brutally hard.
All for the glory of future Olympic gold.
Sure, Principal Lai has been fired from being
a principal.
But what if she’s playing the long game
here?
She could combine her love of children
with her love of pole dancing
and open her own pole dancing schools for
children!
And then one day,
when pole dancing becomes a recognized Olympic
sport,
she’ll have the last laugh.
After all, it’s not that much weirder than
racewalking.
You may see confused children,
but someone else clearly sees a future of
pole-dancing gold medals.
So what do you think about pole dancing at
a Chinese preschool?
Leave your comments below.
And before you go,
it’s that time when I answer questions
from fans who support China Uncensored
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
michiganpizza asks
“personally, china seemed less of a mess
under battle toad than under pooh.”
Ah, using the lingo like a pro.
For those of you who don’t know,
battle toad refers to this guy, Jiang Zemin,
former leader of China.
Winnie-the-Pooh is the current leader of China,
Xi Jinping.
I think it’s obvious why those are their
nicknames.
So Mr. Pizza, that’s a common misconception.
It’s not that things are worse under Pooh.
It’s that they’re more visibly bad.
Things were horrible under battle toad, too.
And in many ways they were worse.
For example, Jiang Zemin had the idea
to round up people for practicing Falun Gong,
even though Falun Gong had been recognized
by the government as being beneficial.
Then Jiang gave his security forces the order
to, quote,
“Ruin their reputations,
bankrupt them financially,
and destroy them physically.”
And destroy them he did.
Millions of people were put in labor camps,
detention centers, and prisons.
We don’t know exactly how many people were
killed under Jiang,
but it’s likely in the tens of thousands,
if not higher,
including through his whole scheme to harvest
their organs
and sell them for profit.
Plus he directed a huge anti-Falun Gong media
propaganda campaign.
But there was no social media in China
back in the 90s and early 2000s
when Jiang Zemin was officially in power.
And it was easier for the Communist Party
to manipulate how foreign journalists reported
on China.
Most of the issues we’re dealing with today—
intellectual property theft,
trade violations,
currency manipulation, well,
those were things Jiang Zemin helped kick
off.
It just took 20 years for the rest of the
world to catch on.
I’m not saying Xi Jinping is a great guy
and you should invite him to parties.
Under Xi Jinping, we’ve definitely seen
more news stories
about arrests of lawyers, dissidents, and
religious believers,
like in Xinjiang.
But I think partly that’s because there’s
just so much more reporting now.
There’s information now passed through social
media
that could not have been possible 20 years
ago,
and state-run propaganda is not as effective
anymore.
So both leaders have done bad things.
But it’s also not just these two leaders.
The Communist Party itself is the problem.
The Party is what creates the system
where persecution of groups is easy,
as well as practically necessary to maintain
power.
So it doesn’t matter which man is in charge.
There will always be serious abuses
while the Communist Party controls China.
But I suppose, at least when it comes to mass
murder,
Jiang Zemin is probably the worst leader since
Mao.
Or I guess better,
if you’re going for a gold medal for mass
murder.
Thanks for your question!
In case you don’t know,
China Uncensored episodes are often getting
demonetized
by YouTube because the content is too “controversial.”
So we started crowdfunding the show on the
website Patreon.
If you sign up to support the show,
you get some cool gifts,
plus you can ask me questions that I may answer
on the show!
So head over to pateron.com/chinauncensored
to learn more.
There’s a link below.
And don’t forget to give a big thank you
to all the patrons who have make this show
possible.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Did you know YouTube has been suppressing
China Uncensored?
Help the show by sharing this episode with
your friends!
And don’t forget to like and subscribe,
and turn on that notification bell so you’ll
get notifications
whenever we have a new episode out!