On this episode of China Uncensored,
Google is building an artificial intelligence
center in China.
If only they could make software to warn them
when things are a bad idea.
The Chinese regime starts collecting
the DNA of ethnic minorities.
Ancestry.com says you’re 97% in trouble.
And finally,
China has a new Youth Ambassador.
And he’s not a “he.”
Or a “she.”
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Forget about the looming specter
of nuclear war with North Korea.
The real threat to China is its own nuclear
power plants.
A key component of a Chinese nuclear power
plant
cracked during a safety test.
And it’s located pretty close to Hong Kong.
The plant is actually a joint venture
started in 2009 between China’s state-owned
China General Nuclear Power Corporation
and French utility,
Électricité de France.
After the component cracked,
the French scientists threw their hands in
the air and said,
“We give up!
We surrender!”
The completion of the plant
had been repeatedly delayed.
It was supposed to go operational
at the end of this year,
but now, maybe not.
Possibly, other countries might want to
reconsider nuclear joint ventures with China.
But Western companies seem to never learn
the right lessons about working with China.
Which is why Google has decided to build
its new artificial intelligence research center
in Beijing.
It’s been up and down for Google
and China over the years.
Google set up a presence in China
starting in 2005,
but pulled out in 2010
after getting hacked by Chinese authorities—
allegedly—
and being forced to self-censor,
which they didn’t like...
…slash-got criticised for.
But it’s been 7 years!
That’s plenty of time to forget
all the lessons you learned!
I mean I have zero recollection
of anything I learned in college.
Like that book I read, 1984.
What was that about again?
Anyway, Google doing AI research
in China is a big deal.
China is trying to become the world leader
in artificial intelligence,
and has invested 161 billion dollars into
the field.
And the Chinese regime has done such a good
job,
the Council on Foreign Relations
warns China could surpass the US.
And whoever leads in AI
will be the ruler of the world—
at least according to Vladimir Putin,
who knows a thing or two about staying in
power.
Moving on, you may remember last week
we reported on the mass evictions
and demolition of migrant homes in Beijing.
Well, a painter in Beijing, Hua Yong,
is afraid you might not believe the scale
of it.
So selfie time!
I’m actually more amazed
those police didn’t immediately grab him.
Don’t worry though,
they did try to grab him eventually.
In his home.
Fortunately, it was a swing and a miss, because
“He fled the city after the police came
to arrest him
for publicizing the evictions.”
This isn’t Hua’s first time getting in
trouble with authorities.
He was sentenced to a labor camp back in 2012
for,
I kid you not,
filming himself in Tiananmen Square,
punching himself in the face until his nose
bled,
and then using the blood to write “6-4”,
which is a reference
to the June 4th 1989 Tiananmen Massacre.
Hua Yong is now my favorite artist.
But Hua’s not alone in being targeted by
police.
Remember how, in pretty much
the only heartwarming thing about this story,
ordinary Beijingers were banding together
to help the migrants?
Well, they got in trouble with the police
too.
Yes, businesspeople who offered migrants jobs,
and charity workers who tried to find them
shelter,
have been interrogated by the police
and told to stop helping people.
I mean, what were they thinking?
Communism isn’t about helping people!
In fact, since the CCP
has decided to evict the migrant workers,
helping them is seen as “an act of defiance”
against the state.
And in the far West of China is Xinjiang,
a region home to about 11 million ethnic Uyghurs.
China’s central authorities have noted
that Uyghurs sometimes look slightly different
from other Chinese,
and are therefore extremely dangerous.
Which may be why
“Chinese authorities in Xinjiang
are collecting DNA samples,
fingerprints, iris scans,
and blood types of all residents”—
according to Human Rights Watch.
Now, sure, the mass collection of biodata
might sound scary.
But it’s being done as part of a free government
annual health checkup program
called “Physicals for All.”
Participation is totally optional...
unless you refuse.
But I’m sure it’s all for a good cause.
Such as checking on people’s organ health.
Although considering there is some evidence
that Chinese authorities are killing Uyghurs
to use their organs in transplant operations...
...maybe, “Physicals for All”
is just a handy way to identify potential
donors.
Again, totally optional—
unless they refuse.
And speaking of treating people like dirt,
it’s the 80-year anniversary of the Rape
of Nanking.
According to Chinese estimates,
300,000 Chinese civilians were raped,
tortured and killed in a six-week orgy of
violence
when Japanese troops invaded the Chinese city
during World War II.
Xi Jinping was there at a commemoration.
But he didn’t give a speech.
And considering the guy is known
for making three-hour long speeches,
that is a miracle.
Moving on to more horrible things
happening to women in China—
and this time, the Japanese aren’t to blame.
Chinese smugglers are buying North Korean
women.
Decades of the CCP’s One Child Policy
resulted in the killing of so many baby girls
that China now has a severe shortage of women.
In fact,
there are about 33 million fewer women than
men.
The obvious solution is trafficking women
from North Korea—where they’re sold
into a life of sex slavery.
On the plus side,
they’re rescued from a life of extreme poverty
under Kim Jong-un’s regime.
Those are both terrible choices.
And the Chinese Communist Party is worried
about the youth of China.
That’s why the Communist Party Youth League
just hired a new youth ambassador
to show them the way.
She’s a singer,
she’s only 15,
and according to her biography,
she’s an actual angel sent to Earth
to bring the happiness of music.
Here she is, Luo Tianyi.
No, she’s not a drawing.
She’s a vocaloid.
Kind of like that Japanese one,
only totally different because she’s Chinese.
As Global Times puts it,
Luo Tianyi will help instill correct thinking
into millennials.
And she’s so much better than an actual
human.
As her creators told the Global Times,
“[Virtual idols] are easier to manage,
different from real-life stars who make their
own decisions
and do things the way they like, which is
hard to control.”
A perfect role model for young people!
Don’t make your own decisions,
don’t do things the way you like,
and don’t be hard to control.
Be like Luo Tianyi.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored,
once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Hey, quit looking up fan art about Luo Tianyi.
There’s so many better things
you could be doing on the Internet.
Like checking out ChinaUncensored.tv.
That’s our website,
where you can see more great content from
us,
including half hour episodes you won’t see
on YouTube.
That’s ChinaUncensored.tv.
Okay, you can go look at some more fan art.