As former US officials travel to Taiwan
China performs combat training over the island
Plus, Jack Ma gets reined in
That and more on this week’s China news
headlines
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
This episode is sponsored by Daily Pnut.
The news can be a tough pill to swallow.
That's why Daily Pnut gives you a daily dose
of news in equal parts humor and substance.
That’s something I can appreciate.
This week, President Biden sent an unofficial
delegation to Taiwan.
The delegation included former Senator Chris
Dodd and former Deputy Secretaries of State
Richard Armitage and James Steinberg, who
served under the George W Bush and Obama administrations.
It’s an unofficial delegation in that none
of them are currently US officials—not unofficial
like these guys just randomly decided to go
to Taiwan on their own.
You know, visit Sun Moon Lake.
Eat fried squid at the night market.
Meet with Taiwan’s president Tsai Ing-Wen.
Just normal tourist stuff.
Biden’s move isn’t especially provocative
or unusual.
In fact, the White House emphasized that they
were following “a long-standing bipartisan
tradition of U.S. administrations sending
high-level, unofficial delegations to Taiwan.”
But of course that didn’t stop the delegation
from, say it with me folks, angering China.
Why did Biden send this delegation now?
“The dispatch of the ‘unofficial’ delegation
comes as the United States and Taiwan mark
the 42nd anniversary of the Taiwan Relations
Act.”
Plus, the Biden Administration sent this delegation
to Taiwan at the same time they also sent
John Kerry to China to talk about climate.
Which got totally overshadowed by the Taiwan
thing.
Because the Communist Party is really starting
to freak out.
It warned the US: don’t play with fire.
Really?
Playing with fire is Wall Street encouraging
Americans to invest in China.
Defending a democratic country from a hostile
communist takeover is the right thing to do.
It’s defending against fire.
Speaking of defending against fire, Taiwan’s
going to need some help with that.
Because the Chinese Communist Party knows
that you don’t just use your words in a
conflict.
You also take action!
That’s why the People’s Liberation Army
is holding live-fire drills near Taiwan during
the US delegation’s visit.
But as I’ve mentioned before, the Communist
Party has been escalating its actions against
Taiwan for months.
Earlier this week, before the US delegation
arrived, China sent a record number of warplanes
around Taiwan.
“The planes flown Monday included 18 fighter
jets, four bombers, two anti-submarine planes
and a surveillance aircraft.”
And the Chinese regime is no longer calling
these incursions routine military exercises.
As Biden’s emissaries go to Taiwan, China
is now calling them combat drills.
Hu Xijin the editor in chief of my favorite
Chinese state run media the Global Times,
warned, “If the U.S. and Taiwan take further
prominent actions, PLA fighter jets will fly
over Taiwan island to declare sovereignty.”
That’s not how it works.If it were, then
I would really be the owner of the Scarborough
Shoal in the South China Sea.
Hu Xijin also said, “If Taiwan forces open
fire, that will be the moment of all-out war
across the Taiwan Strait.”
Yes.
Instead, Taiwan should just let the Chinese
military invade Taiwan without defending itself.
That’s the best way to avoid war.
Unfortunately it seems like Taiwan just won’t
learn.
Besides meeting with US delegations, Taiwan
insists on unveiling new weapons it can use
for defense.
Doesn’t Taiwan understand the best defense,
is a quick unconditional surrender?
Obviously things are very tense right now
between the US and China.
That’s why the Chinese premier is calling
for more communication.
How’s this for more communication?
“We have a serious commitment to Taiwan
being able to defend itself, we have a serious
commitment to peace and security in the Western
Pacific and in that context it would be a
serious mistake for anyone to try to change
that status quo by force.”
Hmmm I wonder who would try to change the
status quo by force.
And more on the threat of communist China,
after the break.
Welcome back.
Once again, the annual threat assessment from
the US Director of National Intelligence,
says China poses the biggest threat to the
US.
“China increasingly is a near-peer competitor,
challenging the United States in multiple
arenas—especially economically, militarily
and technologically—and is pushing to change
global norms.”
Near peer competitor?
Not according to China.
Their message is the US and China are equal
now.
I mean, not in terms of military power, economic
advantage, or international respect, but other
than that, totally equal.
And the Communist Party knows a thing or two
about equality.
Speaking of equality, the Chinese regime is
also equally threatening Australia.
That’s according to this new report by the
Australian Strategic Policy Institute, a leading
Australian think tank.
Basically, China’s navy is targeting Australian
ports.
But not with weapons.
With investments.
The Australian government is under pressure
to take back a major Australian port that
was leased to a Chinese company.
Why?
Because, as the Darwin Port website says,
it’s a strategic location.
Just look at all the places you can get to
from it.
Taipei.
Very convenient.
And now, let’s hear from a man who really
doesn’t want to keep his job, Gau Fu, the
director of the Chinese Center for Disease
Control and Prevention.
He...may have admitted Chinese Covid vaccines
aren’t very effective.
But then he clarified: When he mentioned Chinese
vaccines aren’t very effective, he didn’t
mean Chinese vaccines aren’t very effective.
“In a message to The Associated Press, Gao
said...he was speaking about the effectiveness
rates for ‘vaccines in the world, not particularly
for China.’”
Yes, he was definitely not talking about China’s
Sinovac vaccine, which has an efficacy rate
of barely 50%.
He meant all Covid vaccines are ineffective,
including the American ones.
Coincidentally, the Communist Party has just
announced that Gao will be “volunteering”
for the next phase of human vaccine experiments.
And leaked documents from the Chinese government
show that the Communist Party is doing everything
it can to prevent the spread of Covid...from
getting in the way of persecuting Falun Gong
practitioners.
“The official document, from a district
in eastern China, listed a campaign to suppress
Falun Gong practitioners among the key achievements
in that area in 2020, alongside other tasks
such as controlling the pandemic and ‘maintaining
social stability.’”
Ok, so just imagine working for the Chinese
Communist Party.
Here’s your list of employee performance
goals for 2020:
Let’s see: attend leadership training, improve
time management, ah there it is.
Torture people for meditating.
Check that one off the list.
And it’s not just Falun Gong practitioners
being persecuted.
Elite Communist Party members are, too.
That includes billionaires.
More after the break.
Welcome back.
Jack Ma is a Communist Party member, and one
of China’s richest men.
But that hasn’t stopped the Chinese regime
from hitting him with a double-whammy.
Ma’s company, Ant Group, was hit with a
record 2.8 billion dollars in fines, and is
being forced to completely restructure.
This is clearly a warning to other Chinese
tech companies.
No matter how successful of a businessman
you might be , it's the Chinese Communist
Party that’s in charge.
Elon Musk must be taking that message to heart,
as it’s come out that Tesla is collecting
data on Chinese citizens and storing it in
China.
Where by law, the Chinese Communist Party
can freely access it.
Good news for the youth of China!
Your beloved Party is preparing you for the
meat grinder!
High School students are getting more military
training to strengthen national defense.
Might Chinese high school students be getting
nervous?
Well there’s no way to know, since China
has begun censoring speech about military
affairs.
Some of the most popular forums on WeChat,
China’s biggest social media app, have been
shut down.
It was “implied that agencies from other
countries use the discussion on military affairs
or weapons to analyze the regime’s military
developments, imposing a threat to national
security.”
It’s definitely not because Chinese youth
might express concern about the war with Taiwan
and the US they’re being pushed into.
Because Chinese youth are all patriots.
They have to be or else.
But just in case any of China’s youth might
be misled, the CCP has launched a hotline
to report on people distorting or denying
the Communist Party’s excellent history
and culture.
The notice from China’s top internet regulator
said, “For a while now, some people with
ulterior motives…have spread historically
nihilistic false statements online, maliciously
distorting, slandering and denying Party,
national and military history in an attempt
to confuse people’s thinking.”
And the punishment?
Totally unclear.
Though “Last week, authorities in Jiangsu
province detained a 19-year-old for his ‘insulting’
online comments about Japan’s 1937 invasion
of Nanjing during the Second Sino-Japanese
War.”
But don't forget, the internet surveillance
isn’t limited to just patriotic Han Chinese
kids.
The Communist Party hasn’t forgotten the
Uyghurs.
The CCP is forcing them to download a surveillance
app that will let authorities know if anything
on their phone might be dangerous.
The app is called web cleansing.
Such a nice name.
Not sinister at all.
“If a ‘dangerous’ file is identified,
the app sends a message to the person using
the phone telling them to delete it.”
And according to a research team with the
Open Technology Fund , “Any user with this
app installed will have every file stored
on their device sent to an unknown entity
for monitoring.”
Oh, did I mention when the app sends files
to the outside server, it’s not encrypted
either?
But speaking of the patriotic youth of China,
here’s a small group of young men attacking
a Hong Kong newspaper printing press.
This is the Hong Kong branch of the Epoch
Times—a newspaper known for supporting human
rights and democracy in China.
The Communist Party is not a fan.
Neither are the guys with sledge hammers.
Or as the Party calls them, equality sticks.
The attack has been condemned by US lawmakers.
The State Department.
And sledge hammer manufacturers worldwide.
They would like to remind everyone of their
motto—please use as intended.
Which I assume is for sledges.
Whatever those are.
And this episode is sponsored by Daily Pnut.
If you want more daily news—and not just
in a single 13-minute video—check out Daily
Pnut.
It’s a bunch of fast, timely news stories,
selected for you and available to read on
your phone, tablet, or computer.
Ok, you’re going to read it on your phone.
It’s why Alexander Graham Bell invented
phones.
Reading Daily Pnut is an easy way to filter
out the noise and learn more about the world
news that matters.
Join more than 250,000 other readers.
Education and entertainment—delivered right
to your inbox, every morning.
And the best part is, it’s free.
So sign up for Daily Pnut now.
Use the link in the Description below.
I’m Chris Chappell, thanks for watching.