China is holding Brazil hostage
After President Bolsonaro criticized the CCP.
China’s “Vaccine Diplomacy”
is calculated terror.
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
The coronavirus has become the greatest weapon\h\h
of the Chinese Communist Party. That’s one\h
reason I’ve been calling it the CCP Virus.\h
As I mentioned in the episode that came out a\h
few days ago, there’s growing evidence the global\h\h
pandemic that killed millions worldwide\h
accidentally leaked from a Chinese lab.
The Communist Party spent the crucial first\h
6 weeks of the outbreak covering it up.\h\h
They used that time to hoard medical supplies.
And now, the Chinese Communist Party is using\h
vaccine diplomacy to further strongarm the\h\h
world, particularly in Latin America.
The efficacy of Chinese vaccines is not high.\h\h
Especially compared to the other\h
first-generation coronavirus vaccines.
But there aren’t yet enough high-quality\h
American and European vaccines for every\h\h
country, so a lot of countries have no choice\h
right now but to rely on Chinese vaccines.
According to Jason Marczak, director of the\h
Latin American Center at the Atlantic Council\h\h
think tank, “From a public relations standpoint,\h
China has sought to shift the narrative from\h\h
China being at the center of the Covid problem to\h
China being at the center of the Covid solution.”
Which could very well be the greatest\h
turnaround in history. After Superbowl\h\h
51—when the Patriots were down 28-3 going into the\h
second half, and ended up winning it in overtime.
In other words, China’s\h
strategy is to be Tom Brady.
Or more like Evil Tom Brady. Because\h
China’s plan for a turnaround\h\h
involves *selectively* giving out vaccines—only\h
to countries that do what Beijing wants.
Brazil is a great example.
Brazil has been wary of giving\h
Chinese telecom company Huawei\h\h
access to the Brazilian market. You know,\h
because of serious security concerns.
US Officials have said using Huawei technology\h
opens the door to Chinese spying and censorship.
But with the Brazilian people\h
suffering from the CCP Virus,\h\h
President Jair Bolsonaro felt he had no\h
choice but to make a deal with China.
Back in January, in exchange for China speeding up\h
the procedures that would give Brazil the vaccine,\h\h
Bolsonaro’s government signaled\h
it would allow Huawei to bid\h\h
in the 5G auction later this year. The\h
contract is worth around 30 billion US dollars.
So Bolsonaro had to accept a\h
potential Chinese security threat\h\h
later, to stop a deadly Chinese virus now.
But it turns out, the deal\h
also comes with censorship.
In May, President Bolsonaro seemingly criticized\h\h
China for taking advantage of the coronavirus\h
for its own gain. He said, “It is a new virus,\h\h
nobody knows if it was born in a laboratory or by\h
some human being that ate an inadequate animal.\h\h
But it is there. The military knows what\h
chemical, bacteriological and radiologic war is.\h\h
Aren’t we facing a new war? Which country\h
grew its GDP the most? I won’t tell you.”
He’s talking about China. Obviously. But come on,\h
a new war? Isn’t that a bit of an exaggeration?\h\h
No. Because China does see it as war.
Not long after Bolsonaro’s comments, China\h
stopped sending vaccine ingredients to Brazil.
Brazil uses those vaccine\h
ingredients to make the final\h\h
vaccine that it distributes to its population.
But with China cutting these ingredients off,\h\h
it puts Brazil in a dangerous situation.\h
Especially as Brazil’s Covid death toll spirals.
Only about 7% of Brazilians have been fully\h
vaccinated. More than 420,000 Brazilians have\h\h
died. Again, from a disease the Chinese\h
Communist Party is responsible for.\h\h
Possibly for a lab leak, and certainly for their\h
6-week coverup that allowed it to spread globally.
So the Communist Party is taking advantage of\h
Brazil’s desperation for the vaccine. A rival\h\h
to Bolsonaro, São Paulo’s Governor João Doria,\h
criticized Bolsonaro’s government saying, “How can\h\h
they attack those who supply us with raw materials\h
and vaccines to save Brazil’s population?”
I bet China likes this guy. Maybe he could be\h
the next president! Doria also said he spoke\h\h
with Brazil’s Chinese Ambassador who said, “[The\h
Sinovac] raw material is ready and available\h\h
in refrigerated containers, just waiting for\h
the authorization of the Chinese government.”
In other words, there is no shortage\h
of ingredients for the Chinese vaccine.\h\h
The Chinese government is just\h
sitting on it until Brazil begs.
And Governor Doria begged.
So after Doria met with Chinese officials,\h
China released a new batch of vaccine supplies.
And this is how the Chinese government is forcing\h
Brazil to play its game. With moves like that,\h\h
no wonder it can pull an Evil Tom\h
Brady and win every Superbowl.
And this isn’t just happening in Brazil.
It’s happening all over Latin America.
“Latin American officials say China\h
has pushed their countries to cut\h\h
ties with Taiwan in return for\h
badly needed Covid-19 vaccines.”
Only a handful of countries in the world still\h
recognize Taiwan as a country. China is trying\h\h
very hard to change that. Since 2017, three\h
Latin American countries—Panama, Dominica,\h\h
and El Salvador—have broken ties with Taiwan\h
in favor of China. That’s because “China has\h\h
invested in ports, roads, dams and railways, often\h
offering loans to Latin American governments,\h\h
and made big purchases of minerals\h
and agricultural commodities.”
But countries like Honduras and Paraguay, which\h
still recognize Taiwan, don’t get all that nice\h\h
economic development. And guess which countries\h
aren’t getting Chinese coronavirus vaccines now?\h\h
Unless of course, they cut ties with Taiwan.
Now keep in mind, China is not donating\h
these vaccines. They’re selling them. Yeah,\h\h
when you get the world sick and then sell\h
them a cure, you can make a lot of money.
And this is what’s at stake\h
if the Chinese Communist Party\h\h
dominates global supply chains. It can hold\h
the world hostage to its political demands.
And now is the time when I answer\h
a question from one of our fans.\h\h
Normally, I take a question\h
from our supporters on Patreon.
But today, I want to give a special\h
thank you to the folks who watch our new\h\h
Portuguese channel. Yes, we have a\h
Portuguese channel. The link is below.
And so today I’ll answer a question\h
from one of our Portuguese-speaking\h\h
YouTube subscribers in Brazil.
Daniel H P Carvalho asks:
“Hello Chris. In what ways do you think\h\h
Brazil can help in the fight against China? I know\h
that China depends a lot on exports from Brazil\h\h
to feed its population. Could this dependency\h
be useful for Brazil as a negotiation tool?”
Good question, Daniel.
China does depend on Brazil,\h\h
especially on soybeans. About three quarters\h
of China’s soybean imports are from Brazil.
But that’s not good enough leverage\h
for Brazil. The Chinese Communist\h\h
Party is always willing to endure\h
short-term losses to punish others.
For example, a few years ago, after\h
the trade dispute with President Trump,\h\h
China tried to punish American farmers\h
by cutting off American soybean imports.
And then China increased imports from Brazil.\h
In other words, Brazil is just a pawn to them.
The key to not being China’s pawn\h
is to not play their game at all.
Brazil is a great country, and it was great\h
before it started working with the Chinese\h\h
Communist Party. The key for Brazil is to build\h
up its own manufacturing economy, and to work with\h\h
trusted allies—and gradually reduce dependence on\h
China in all respects. If the Brazilian government\h\h
continues to deepen its relationship with China,\h
Brazilians will become less and less free. You’re\h\h
already losing your freedom to Chinese-imposed\h
censorship. And that’s just the beginning.
So the best way Brazilians can help\h\h
is to vote for politicians who will\h
stand up to the Chinese Communist Party.
Thanks for your question, Daniel.
And thank you for watching. And please, tell\h
everyone you know who speaks Portuguese to\h\h
check out our new Portuguese channel, run by\h
my colleagues in Brazil. The link is below.
I’m Chris Chappell. Thanks\h
for watching China Uncensored.