Chinese telecom company Huawei
has been charged with racketeering
and stealing U.S. trade secrets.
But how serious is Huawei’s threat to America?
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Huawei.
The Chinese telecom company that brings us
together.
Because both Trump and Obama
agreed that it was a threat to the US.
The Justice Department has just charged Huawei
with racketeering and stealing trade secrets.
But despite warnings from US intelligence
agencies,
some of America’s allies still want to make
deals with Huawei.
Is the Huawei threat really that serious?
I sat down to talk about Huawei with economic
expert
and Policy Director with America First Policies
Curtis Ellis.
He was also a Senior Policy Advisor
to Trump’s presidential campaign in 2016.
Thank you for joining me today.
Yeah, it's great to be here.
Thanks for having me.
Sure.
So I know you've called Huawei,
essentially “the espionage arm of the Chinese
Communist Party
masquerading as a telecom company.”
What are you basing that on?
Well, they have back doors built into all
of their equipment
so that the Chinese government, the Chinese
military,
the Chinese Communist Party, can basically
tap into all of the data
and information that flows over Huawei networks.
So if you have an internet or a telecom network
using Huawei equipment,
you can be sure that the Chinese government
can tap into it at will.
That's espionage, that cyber espionage.
So it's that simple and there is no other
way to put it
to look at it any other way is just delusional.
We know that the Chinese government has a
law,
the civil military fusion law that requires
any Chinese company
to cooperate with the Chinese military.
This is a communist dictatorship, they call
it socialist if you want,
socialists with Chinese characteristics,
they want complete control over everything.
There is no such thing as an independent business
entity in China.
No such thing.
Well, so I know the NSA has been accused of
asking US telecom companies to build back
doors.
How is what China is doing with Huawei different
from that?
Well, one big difference is the United States
government
is not the Chinese Communist Party.
The Chinese Communist Party has a far different
agenda
than the US government.
The US government still at its best,
adheres to the ideals of Western values,
individual liberty, privacy, freedom of speech,
freedom of religion.
At its worst, the US government aspires to
those ideals.
The Chinese Communist Party has no desire
and no illusion
about even recognizing those ideals.
So you're looking in an organization,
the Chinese Communist Party that is intent
on staying in power,
accruing, acquiring and holding on to
as much power in its own hands as it can
and it aspires to ideals of the collective
above the individual.
No such thing as private property,
no such thing as individual liberty or individual
aspiration.
Those are the people who are going to be having
access
to all the information that flows over Huawei
networks.
Is what Huawei is doing, is that typical for
other Chinese companies?
Well, as I said, the Chinese law says that
all Chinese companies
must accede to the demands of the Chinese
government.
So if the Chinese government asks,
let's say a Chinese bank to turn over
the financial records of its customers,
it must do so.
It can't say no.
I got to get out of that Chinese bank.
Yeah, there you go.
And let's look at it further.
Every Chinese, we're told that the Chinese
government
or its industrial espionage outfits are stealing
hundreds of millions of dollars
of American intellectual property every year.
So how many of these companies are essentially
selling stolen goods?
These Chinese companies are selling stolen
goods.
And now the US justice department has just
charged Huawei
with racketeering and stealing trade secrets.
Practically speaking, what does that mean?
Well, it means that if your Cisco and you're
building internet routers,
Huawei is stealing your designs,
copying your designs,
building its own routers using your research,
using the fruits of your intellectual exploration,
making copies of it and selling it probably
for less money.
Because it didn't have to go through all the
expense,
blood sweat, and toil of designing it
and coming up with these designs on its own.
So, plus it's receiving government subsidies
so it can underbid legitimate companies like
Cisco
and it can sell that router for less and obtain
contracts.
So will this charge affect US policy towards
Huawei?
Well, it certainly has already begun affecting
US policy towards Huawei.
We are asking our allies not to use Huawei
equipment
as they build out their 5G networks.
We are looking at limiting sales of component
parts to Huawei.
We don't want to enable this company to carry
out its malicious activities.
So while everybody's focused on the trade
deals
and selling soybeans to China,
there's a vast spectrum of activities that
the US government
is looking at, a vast spectrum of interrelations
with China
that we're re-examining.
A lot of the premises that underlie our current
relationships with China
are now really, I'd say called into question
to put it euphemistically.
There is always this premise that the more
we engage with China,
the more they would become like us.
They would become more like us,
they would respect liberty,
they would respect private property,
they would open up their system,
they would become more peaceful.
What we've seen instead is they become more
prosperous
and acquire more Western technology.
They're moving in the opposite direction,
they're becoming a techno totalitarian state,
they're militarizing, they're stealing everything
that they can't buy or that we don't give
them.
So under the phase one deal,
they're supposed to address some of these
intellectual property theft issues
and they're supposed to purchase
more American goods and services,
but there's a whole lot of other stuff
going on outside the realm of trade,
which we're looking at.
For example, Huawei, for example,
the FBI says it has 1000 investigations
open across the country
of Chinese espionage.
Every field agency of the FBI in America has
investigations
into Chinese espionage activities.
So that's not going to be covered by any trade
agreement.
And the administration has made it very clear
that they're not linking the two.
We can do business with China,
they can buy our soybeans,
we can sell them certain goods of a non-military
sensitive nature,
but we're not going to say, well,
now we're going to play nice and make believe
that
you're not doing something wrong over here.
We did business with the Soviet Union throughout
the Cold War.
They had nuclear missiles pointed at us, we
knew they had spies
trying to infiltrate and influence
and plant moles and all kinds of things.
We still would sell them wheat and we'd still
do
all kinds of other business with them.
Occidental Petroleum, Armand Hammer,
was a famous industrialist who famously did
business with Russia.
The fact that we knew they were spying on
us and wanted to,
as Nikita Khrushchev said, we will bury you.
We knew they wanted to bury us, but we said,
okay,
well, we'll still take their money.
So the US both the Trump administration
and the Obama administration have warned about
Huawei.
Do you think that's been taken seriously?
It's being taken more seriously now than ever.
I really had questions about the Obama administration
taking this stuff seriously.
Look, so many of the apparatchiks in Washington
in both parties
have been compromised one way or another-
100%.
By the Chinese influence operations.
I'm not saying that they signed up for the
Chinese Communist Party,
they don't even know how they'd been compromised.
They're buying off Americans on both sides
of the aisle,
Albright Associates, Madeline Albright,
former secretary of state,
her company's made just tens of millions of
dollars advising companies
on how to move to China and how to do business
in China.
Dianne Feinstein's driver was a Chinese spy.
Her husband has made money investing in China.
You just go down the line, Henry Kissinger,
you've got all these Wall Street guys that
have made fortunes
investing in China, directing investment into
China,
and now it's, you've heard the stories,
it's gone down the line of it's infiltrated
so far
that now pension funds, the California state
pension funds.
And so you think this has held back
even though the Obama administration and the
Trump administration
have been pushing warnings about Huawei,
that attitude has blocked.
There's bureaucratic inertia.
Look, there's basic human nature
nobody wants to admit they're wrong, right?
Oh man, I was so wrong about that.
But the basic human nature of not wanting
to admit they're wrong,
close their eyes, well,
let's keep doing things the way we were doing
because I don't want to admit
that I believe the Chinese Communist Party.
They were lying to me for all these years
and I was a fool to believe it,
nobody wants to say that.
In addition, you have bureaucratic inertia.
There's huge bureaucracies in the Pentagon
and elsewhere,
other agencies of the US government,
that are still proceeding along those old
premises that,
as we get closer to China, as they develop
and become more prosperous,
they will become more American,
they will become more Western.
Absolutely.
If we give money to a totalitarian communist
regime,
they'll become a democracy.
Right.
I mean you hear the truncated version of this
is,
countries that trade with each other don't
go to war with each other.
Well, tell that to the Ukraines, Ukrainia,
Ukraine and Russia were the two largest trading
partners
before World War 1 France and Germany
were the two largest trading partners.
They went to war,
and this is like this economic reductionism,
this economism that human nature
can be reduced to dollars and cents on a spreadsheet.
It's a lot more complicated than that.
A lot of people say, we are trading,
the US is trading with China.
But still many of their actions
can only be described as a type of warfare.
Well, in the Chinese military strategy,
warfare goes beyond the battlefield.
The doctrine is the best general defeats the
enemy
without taking the battlefield.
They see the economic crippling of America
and acquiring the productive assets,
the technology and the factories of America,
acquiring them, moving them to China,
that is a form of warfare.
And Huawei is a part of this?
And Huawei is definitely a part of this.
Look, if a Chinese army invaded America, went
to Silicon Valley
and took all the factories,
took all the research labs and took the people
and moved them to Mongolia or moved them to
Manchuria
and set those factories up,
we would recognize that as an act of war and
the looting of America.
If you get, if Chinese capital
and Chinese influence gets Wall Street
to counsel Silicon Valley to move its research
operations into China
and to handover its innovation research and
technology to Chinese partners.
The goal, the end result is the same.
And we just make some money off of it.
And Wall Streets' made some money, they'd
been bought off,
China gets the capital
and you've got Think Tanks like the Cato Institute
saying,
oh, this is wonderful, it's free trade, it's
free market operations,
so therefore it's good.
Because you see, again, you have this ideology
that says all that matters is the money,
there are no such thing as nation States,
there's no such thing as culture,
there's no such thing as values, cultural
values.
It just all comes down to how many widgets
can we make?
How many widgets can we consume?
How many widgets can we acquire?
And that's all that matters.
And it's a very reductionist way of looking
at life,
it's devoid of humanity and the things that
I would hold say,
make living worthwhile.
So what does it mean for the US if its allies
like the UK
or other European countries use Huawei
to build parts of its telecom or 5G networks?
Well, unfortunately too many people in positions
in government
don't understand how technology works.
And that if Huawei equipment is in any part
of the network,
it will have access to all parts of the network.
So if Huawei equipment, if our allies use
Huawei equipment,
they're basically all of the information that
flows
over those networks and in the 5G network,
that's basically everything will be,
could be spied on, monitored, influenced by
someone in Beijing.
Now look, 5G networks are going to link devices,
power plants, electrical grids, ATM machines,
not just telephones, everything.
So what if you shut down the power grid?
What if, let's say China moves in, the Beijing
sends,
decides to move on Taiwan, right?
And simultaneously somebody gets a message
in Washington,
you can let this happen or you will lose power
in East Los Angeles,
North Philadelphia, Atlanta and Dade County.
And it'll happen on the first of the month
when the food stamp benefits are electronically
delivered.
The SNAP, the supplemental nutrition,
no longer stamps anymore,
it's an electronic card that automatically
are replenished.
They won't be replenished so there will be
no power,
there will be no food and what do you think
is going to happen
in your inner cities on that day?
Right?
Or there will be no power to hospitals,
there'll be no power to the emergency room,
to the intensive care unit.
And so having the UK have parts of its system,
5G system,
built by Huawei could have that effect on
the US?
Well, no, I'm saying if we were to have Huawei
equipment inside the US
that that ultimatum could be delivered.
But okay.
Germany's looking at this like how vulnerable
will we be
if we have Huawei equipment here?
They haven't made the decision yet.
The British, maybe their health system is
so bad already
that they don't care.
I suppose you would take it to the point of,
well do you want to see this?
The United States would be given this ultimatum,
we'll destabilize all of Europe,
the British banking system,
the City of London will go down and all of
the finance flows
that goes through the City of London
will be effected and that will have a ripple
effect
through Wall Street and around the world.
Well, some people argue that the US
is certainly not offering any 5G alternatives.
So for many people that feels like, well,
it's Huawei or the highway.
No, it's Huawei or Nokia and Ericsson.
Nokia and Ericsson have 5G alternatives.
And it's very interesting:
why are the British not going for Nokia and
Ericsson?
Why are the Germans not going for the Swedes
and the Danes, right?
This is, and now the United States government
is saying maybe we should invest some money
into Nokia and Ericsson
to develop the 5G alternative to Huawei.
You get the impression that the Swedes are
sitting there and saying,
hey, I'm here, look at me, what are you saying
there's no alternative?
I'm sitting right here.
What's going on with that?
Some people make the argument that the only
reason
the US is going after Huawei is because
it's seen as a major rival to US tech in telecom
companies.
What would you say to that argument?
Well, we just said that the United States
amazingly
has no alternative for 5G.
There is no American company that can, producing
5G equipment.
So for anybody to say we're going after Huawei
because it's a competitor to America that
just is false right there.
The alternative to Huawei is Nokia and Ericsson.
The problem with Huawei is not that there's
an American competitor,
the problem with Huawei is that it's the espionage
arm
of the people's liberation army.
They're entirely compromised,
we know they have back doors in their equipment
that
can funnel all the information that passes
over its networks to Beijing.
And that they have been blatantly stealing
intellectual property,
buying off engineer's from rival competitors,
doubling,
tripling their salary, come work for us,
and then violate the nondisclosure agreement
that you signed with your previous employer,
not to disclose their trade secrets.
That's what's the matter with Huawei.
And final question, do you think with the
US putting
so much pressure on Huawei,
the Chinese communist party will try to retaliate.
The Chinese Communist Party takes nothing
lying down.
They've threatened Germany, they've told German
companies,
well, they've told BMW well,
that's a nice factory you have outside of
Shanghai
hate to see something bad happen to it.
Maybe ought to have your government buy Huawei
equipment.
So yes, they're already flashing the dagger,
threatening retaliation against anyone who
doesn't toe the line.
You have to wonder, they've got their equipment
in place
in various countries around the world in the
developing world.
What kind of goods do they have on the leaders
of some of these kleptocracies in Africa?
What kind of goods do they have on a high
officials or bankers,
high government officials or high industry
officials in places like Ethiopia,
I'm just pulling this out of my head,
I don't know if they even have their equipment
installed in Ethiopia.
This blackmail that could be going on that
we don't even know about.
And think about this, no American company
ever voluntarily,
unless it's forced to even discloses when
it's hacked, very rare.
I mean we've heard about Experian,
we heard about Marriott, heard about a couple
other breaches,
but virtually every American company that's
been reported,
has been hacked, has been the victim of a
cyber attack,
they generally don't release this information.
Because it materially affects their earnings,
they could have a bad impact on their stock
price,
makes the executives look bad.
It's like you didn't have the systems in place
to guard against this,
what the hell are you doing?
Right.
So they don't reveal this all the time.
You have to wonder,
what kind of goods does the Chinese Communist
Party have
on how many executives and how many companies?
So retaliation?
The retaliation could be going on already
in the form of extortion or blackmail.
All right.
Thank you very much for joining me today
and telling us about Huawei.
Thank you.