On this episode of China Uncensored,
5 hotspots for war with China.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
War.
It’s like punching your boss at work.
Fun to think about,
but inadvisable to actually do.
That’s why China has always been a “defender
of peace.”
I mean, China even started the China World
Peace Foundation.
...sponsored in part by North Korea.
Wow. Look at this art exhibition in Peace
Garden.
Guarded by a totally peaceful armed soldier.
But not all of China’s neighbors are peaceful
and friendly allies.
In fact, a number of countries are not content
with doing whatever the Chinese Communist
Party wants.
Could war be on the horizon?
Here are 5 places where it’s most likely
to start.
Number 5 Arunachal Pradesh
You might not have ever heard of this place.
Just like you might never have heard about
the four-week war India and China fought in
1962.
But it has to do with this area,
near the border between India and Tibet.
It’s controlled by India.
But the Chinese regime claims the territory
as its own.
This will be a frequent theme in this episode.
In the 1962 war,
China seized part of Arunachal Pradesh.
But after a ceasefire was declared,
Chinese troops retreated back to the old border
lines.
These days it’s kind of like the American
Civil War
in that people love to reenact it for some
reason I’m not entirely clear on.
But in this case, they don’t have a picnic
afterwards.
According to the Times of India,
Chinese troops advance into Arunachal Pradesh
before ultimately retreating about “twice
a year.”
Their last scheduled temporary invasion was
just a few weeks ago.
But ultimately, it’s not really a territory
worth fighting over.
Very few Chinese people live there,
and it’s so high up in the Himalayan mountains
that it’s not the most ideal environment
for long-term occupation.
Maybe that’s why China prefers to send nuclear
submarines into the Indian Ocean
and buddy up with India’s nuclear-armed
rival, Pakistan.
Number 4 The South China Sea
This lovely spot of ocean is home to rich
reserves of natural gas, oil, fishing
and about 5 trillion dollars worth of annual
trade and shipping.
And like the One Ring, everyone wants it.
And their claims overlap.
But of all the countries involved,
China has been the most aggressive in asserting
its claims.
China’s built artificial islands in disputed
waters and put military bases on them.
"So that Island we talked about,
it was a reef, Fiery Cross, in 2006.
Look at it a couple of years later.
You get a sense of the scale of the construction here."
They’ve also built oil platforms.
And Chinese ships have rammed other countries’
boats.
And while most of these conflicts could be
resolved by simple international arbitration,
using, you know, international law,
the Chinese regime has resisted that at every
opportunity.
Now, add to that US presence in the region
and you have a dangerous, tense situation
that could spiral out of anyone’s control.
just like a game of Twister.
Only with nukes.
Number 3 The East China Sea
You know what this has in common with the
South China Sea?
They both have China in the name,
so clearly they belong to China!
That logic does not apply to say, the Indian
Ocean, mind you.
The East China Sea separates China and Japan
two countries that have historically not gotten
along at all.
And the current trouble centers around these
islands,
known as the Senkaku Islands in Japan.
According to a post World War II treaty,
they belong to Japan.
But the Chinese regime considers that Sen-kaka.
They say it’s Chinese territory, and they
call it the Diaoyu Islands.
Mind you, they’re uninhabited rocks.
But they sit on oil reserves.
Tensions have heated up since 2012
when Japan nationalized the archipelago.
Since then China has sent many ships sailing
in or around
the waters surrounding the islands.
Chinese activists have even landed on some
of the islands carrying flags.
Yeah, Taiwan also has a claim.
Which is cool with China
because China also claims Taiwan.
In response, a few days later,
Japanese activists did the same thing.
Then in 2013,
China established an Air Defense Zone over
the islands.
It required that every aircraft entering
must identify itself to Chinese patrols, or
else.
The US and Japan have pretty much decided
to ignore it.
So the Chinese regime keeps pushing the envelope
like a passive-aggressive postal worker.
For example, sending navy ships really close
to,
but not technically within,
Japan’s territorial waters.
The tensions between China and Japan have
gotten so bad,
the conflict has been called,
“the most dangerous standoff since the Cuban
Missile Crisis.”
Number 2 Taiwan
Taiwan has been an independent,
umm…
not country, since 1949.
The island is governed independently,
but the mainland Chinese government has said
it will use force to take Taiwan back
if it ever formally declares independence.
And just to be prepared,
China has about 1,600 missiles aimed at it.
The relationship between both sides has its
ups and down.
For instance, the last President of Taiwan,
Ma Ying-jeou,
did a lot to smooth out relations.
He opened up Taiwan to mainland business and
tourism.
He was even the first leader of Taiwan to
meet with the leader of China.
And yet still, you see this
that’s footage of China’s army doing a
drill
where they take over Taiwan’s presidential
palace.
And now, Taiwan has a new president, Tsai
Ing-wen.
She wants Taiwan to cut economic reliance
on mainland China.
And in her inaugural speech,
even didn’t mention that China and Taiwan
were the same country.
Awkward…
And Number 1 North Korea
Don’t worry, North Korea and China are still
friends.
But North Korea itself could still become
a flashpoint for war involving China.
As long as North Korea stays peaceful in its
Peace Garden,
everything will be fine
for the people who don’t live there anyway.
But North Korean leader Kim Jung-un might
not want peace.
Recently, state media there aired this video,
promising to turn South Korea’s capital
into a “sea of flames.”
Wow, nice CGI.
And if North Korea really re-starts its war
with South Korea,
well, South Korea will fight back.
And its buddy the USA will come to its aid.
And that would put China in a tough spot.
Will they fight alongside North Korea,
like they did during the 1950s?
Or will they stand by and watch the US and
South Korea beat North Korea to a pulp?
But that would mean US and South Korean troops
would soon be stationed right along the Chinese
border.
So the Chinese regime is stuck trying to maintain
a dangerous, unstable status quo.
So what do you think about the 5 hotspots
for war?
Leave your comments below.
And if you enjoyed this episode,
for just 50 cents you can join the China Uncensored
50 Cent Army
by supporting us on Patreon.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see
you next time.