Tear gas, pepper spray,
and rubber bullets
Hong Kong didn’t change China
China changed Hong Kong
But protesters are trying to change both
After more than 100 days of protests
and more than 2000 cans of tear gas,
Hong Kong protests have entered a new phase.
"Chris Chappell here\h in Hong Kong.
We were here back in June,
just as this protest movement just began."
"Chris Chappell here back in Hong Kong.
We were here back in June,
when these protests first began."
After more than 3 months,
a lot of the protesting looks the same.
There’s still broad support in Hong Kong
society,
with people from all walks of life coming
out
Creative protest art can be seen everywhere.
And leaderless, guerrilla style organization
is still the preferred tactic.
Sure, the police have gotten
a little more liberal with the pepper spray.
And tear gas.
And violence.
But protesters still have more or less the
same five demands
they’ve had since the beginning.
But now there’s a new focus of the protests.
They’re going after the big bad,
the final boss—
the Chinese Communist Party.
Some protesters have started calling them
the Chinazis.
Yes, the protests have gone on for so long,
they’ve triggered Godwin’s Law.
Godwin’s Law states that
as an internet discussion goes on,
the probability of comparing your enemy to
Nazis
approaches 100%.
The Party ultimately has the final say
over what happens in Hong Kong.
That means the Hong Kong government
is completely unaccountable to the people
of Hong Kong.”
No matter how many millions protest.
On Saturday night,
the Civil Human Rights Front,
which has organized some of the biggest marches
over the past 100 days,
held an Anti-Authoritarianism Rally.
It marked the 5-year anniversary of the 2014
Umbrella Revolution.
Hundreds of thousands joined.
While the protests were largely peaceful,
a smaller group of protesters smashed
the windows of government offices.
And blocked this major road
near the Hong Kong Legislative Council Office.
Though they did take barriers down to let
firefighters through.
But on Sunday,
it was the Chinese Communist Party
that was at the center of protesters' fury.
“Today is the Global Anti-Totalitarianism
March.
Wait, Shelley, what’s the difference between
Authoritarianism and Totalitarianism?”
“Just wait”
Ok, Totalitarianism has way more tear gas.
The Hong Kong police did not grant a permit
for this march,
making this an illegal assembly.
And so the police have come out in force.
"They fired the tear gas right next to me.
My ear's kind of ringing from that.
But my god, that was loud.
Ear's still ringing.
I don't know why the police suddenly went
off,
but oh man, I'm gonna get this nice and tight."
In fact, the police started firing tear gas
before the march had even started.
When most of the people around were just reporters
and people trying to go shopping.
Until they got mad at the police.
"That's a media liaison.
They're telling us that we need to get out
of here.
They're telling the press to leave.
That they're sweeping the area.
All in all it's a great world anti-totalitarianism
festival."
But Hong Kong protesters don’t see this
as just their fight against the Chinese Communist
Party.
They see it as the world’s fight.
In this open letter,
Hong Kong protesters “call for the free
world to join us
and stand as one against the greatest threat
it has ever seen.”
That threat being the Chinese Communist Party.
And there are signs protesters
are getting the world to pay attention.
At least 40 cities worldwide
have held similar protests this weekend
to support Hong Kong.
“This is extremely gutsy.
The Chinese Communist Party is not known for
taking criticism very well.”
“Watch out for pepper spray!”
Despite the tear gas and pepper spray,
tens of thousands of Hong Kongers marched.
“It’s become more and more dangerous
to come out to these protests.
What keeps you coming out?”
“Oh, it’s so simple.
Because I love this place.
That’s all.”
"Why are you targeting the Chinese Communist
Party
instead of just the Hong Kong government?"
“Because they’re the boss of this event.
Even we already defeat the Hong Kong government,
they still try to control it.
If we do not defeat it,
Hong Kong is over.
"Now the Chinese Communist Party is not known
for taking criticism very well.
Are you worried?"
"We're not worried ’cause...
our ultimate goal is to raise the awareness
internationally,
so other countries will try to help.
Are you worried?"
“I’m not worried.
Because today,
when stand out I have nothing left,
alright, I could die for democracy.
This is what a civilization should does.”
"And do you think you can bring change?”
“We all believe it.
Every protester come out,
we all believe it.”
So the World Anti-Totalitarianism rally
was a complete success.
For about 15 minutes.
Until the police showed up again.
Although, you could say that police
breaking up an anti-totalitarianism rally
is the perfect way for this to end.
“So..aw jeez...the unrest in Hong Kong has
been
an existential threat to the Chinese Communist
Party.
But with the protesters now targeting the
party itself,
it’s anyone’s guess how the Party’s
going to respond.
But no matter how the Party responds,
one thing is for sure.
After the tear gas clears,
the Hong Kong protesters will keep on marching.