On this episode of China Uncensored,
long may Xi Jinping reign!
Seriously, he might be reigning
for a long time.
Welcome back to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Big news for Chinese leader Xi Jinping!
He could become China’s “president”
for life.
“The Communist Party this weekend
announcing a proposal to scrap
the two-term limit for presidents,
meaning Xi Jinping could stay on indefinitely.”
“Changes to the constitution in the last
year
have made Xi the most powerful Chinese leader
since Mao Zedong—
the founder of the People’s Republic—
who died in office,
having never retired.”
Retirement?
Xi is only 64!
It’s way too early to think about retirement.
Yes, as Chinese netizens have point it out,
Xi Jinping has found what he loves
and is sticking with it.
Netizens have always noticed
a more than passing similarity
between Xi Jinping and Winnie the Pooh.
But after this latest news,
some of the Pooh bear memes
on China’s internet
are difficult to decipher.
Hmm, I wonder what this one means...
But weirdly,
Chinese authorities don’t seem to have
a sense of humor about this.
Censors have once again banned references
to Winnie the Pooh on China’s internet.
You know what else they’ve banned?
The phrase “I disagree.”
So fellas, if you’re in China,
now’s the time to hit up your crush on WeChat
and ask her out.
She can’t disagree.
Of course,
if we’re talking Winnie the Pooh,
I’m definitely the wise Owl,
since I predicted this in 2016.
“There’s still more power Xi can grab.
And if he gets it,
then what?
Well, he may use it to stay in power
beyond the year 2022,
when, according to supposed precedent,
he would to step down
because he will have served two five-year
terms.”
“You know, not quite a president,
or a dictator.
More of a presitator.”
You know, there are times
when saying “I told you so”
leaves a bitter taste in the mouth.
This, is not one of those times!
I told you so!
Presitator for life baby!
Pass me some of that honey.
I believe we have a clip
of Xi Jinping’s response.
“Oh I just can’t wait to be king!”
Wow, it’s amazing how much of our childhood
is a metaphor for tyranny.
Now the end to presidential term limits
is not set in stone.
It’s a constitutional amendment proposed
by the Central Party Committee.
It still needs to be approved
later this month by a vote
from China’s National People’s Congress.
So there’s still a good chance that...
haha, no, this is set in stone.
“The National People’s Congress
has never rejected a law that the party
or government has put before it.”
Now that’s called loyalty!
Or maybe Congress is just banned
from using the phrase “I disagree.”
But from a larger perspective,
this move shouldn’t really come as a surprise.
See, this removal of term limits
doesn’t really change the Chinese political
system.
It just exposes what the system
has been all along.
There’s a myth that after Mao died,
the Chinese Communist Party
ruled China through consensus.
No, they actually ruled China
using power struggles.
The goal has always been to
hold onto power as long as you can.
And the guy in charge is the one
who actually has control—
not necessarily the guy with the title.
In the 1980s and 90s,
Deng Xiaoping never held the top title,
but he was supreme leader—
even while Jiang Zemin was nominally
head of the CCP.
And then after Jiang Zemin technically
stepped down as president in 2003,
Jiang hung onto power behind the scenes
throughout the entire ten-year presidency
of the next guy, Hu Jintao.
In fact, 15 years later,
Jiang Zemin is still so powerful
behind the scenes
that Xi Jinping has been using his
anti-corruption campaign to purge
Jiang Zemin’s power base.
So Xi Jinping getting rid of
presidential term limits
is basically just him being transparent
about his plans to stay in power.
CCP politics is often called a “black box.”
It’s like the power struggle within the
CCP
is a wrestling match going on
in a completely dark room.
It’s really hard to see what’s going on.
Now, Xi Jinping is turning on the lights.
On second thought, maybe turn them off again.
I’m not sure anyone wants to see that.
So anyway, the constitutional amendment
that gets rid of presidential term limits
is going to pass,
with a likelihood of roughly 100 percent.
The amendment also gets rid
of vice presidential term limits.
Remember this guy, Wang Qishan?
He’s Eeyore.
Wang was Xi Jinping’s anti-corruption czar.
He was forced to retire from the top Party
leadership,
the Politburo Standing Committee,
last October because of his age.
That seemed like a big loss for Xi.
But it was actually a slick move.
Because technically you don’t have to
be in the Politburo
to hold a high position in government.
So Xi is going to bring Wang back to power...
this time as the new Vice President of the
government.
Or as you might call him, Vice Presitator.
And now, he and Xi Jinping
never have to say goodbye.
There are other changes to
the country’s constitution, too—
besides getting rid of term limits
for president and vice president.
Xi Jinping Thought will also be added—
just like it got added to
the Communist Party’s constitution in October.
The rule of the Communist Party is emphasized,
just to remind everyone that the government
isn’t really the one in charge.
And it also will establish
the National Supervision Commission.
The National Supervision Commission
is basically Xi Jinping and Wang Qishan’s
anti-corruption campaign on steroids.
Already, his campaign has purged more than
1.5 million corrupt Communist Party officials.
Wait, and now it’s time to add the steroids?
How many corrupt officials could possibly
be left to purge?!
Haha, don’t worry, there’s still several
million more.
And this corruption-purging
National Supervision Commission
will have the added benefit
of being above Chinese legal system.
Yes, having it be subject to the rule of law
would just slow it down.
Being outside the law,
it has power to detain people
without having to waste time holding show
trials.
In fact, Xi Jinping has invented
a new kind of detention
just for Party officials.
He’s calling it “liu zhi”.
“Liu zhi is an original creation of China,
which had never been used
in other countries in the world.”
And this liu zhi replaces the previous
illegal system of detaining Party officials,
which was called shuang gui.
The Chinese Communist Party—
finding new ways to throw people in jail
since 1949.
But again, none of this should be surprising.
When Xi Jinping came to power,
he immediately was in the middle
of a life or death power struggle
with former Chinese leader Jiang Zemin.
That’s why he’s spent the last five-plus
years
purging all his rivals tied to Jiang,
and amassing power.
If he didn’t,
he’d get purged himself.
So, has Xi Jinping won now?
Does abolishing term limits mean that
he’s gotten rid of Jiang’s faction
and is now the supreme ruler of the CCP,
just like Mao?
Well, Xi Jinping may have the kitchy merchandise,
but that doesn’t mean he’s just like Mao.
Think about it, why abolish term limits now,
when Xi is only at the beginning of his
second five-year term?
Why not wait for a couple more years,
when he has more power?
Here’s one reason: Xi has no successor.
This is a key part of the CCP’s power struggles.
Deng was powerful enough to appoint
Jiang and then Hu as his successors.
But neither Jiang nor Hu were powerful enough
to appoint the next leader.
So they were forced to compromise.
So now Xi needs a successor,
but if he can’t control who that is,
then he could lose the power struggle.
How?
Well, officials who don’t like Xi
might otherwise just try to wait him out,
hoping the next guy will be better.
But now Xi has abolished term limits.
That’s a signal that he’s in this for
the long haul,
so officials had better fall in line.
But Xi isn’t Mao.
He’s still in the process of consolidating
power.
And there are signs he’s only just getting
to the level of power Jiang Zemin once had.
In a way, the National Supervision Commission
is Xi Jinping’s version of Jiang Zemin’s
610 Office.
Only instead of focusing on detaining
innocent Falun Gong practitioners,
it’s detaining corrupt Party officials.
Which at least is a less bad use
of a scary illegal detention system,
although it would be much better
to not have the scary illegal detention system
at all.
So now that Xi Jinping has managed
to get unlimited terms in office,
and is bringing back his anti-corruption czar,
and is creating up the
National Supervision Commission,
what’s next?
Well it’s kind of hard to tell.
Can someone turn on the lights?
So what do you think of China’s new
presitator for life?
Remember you can’t disagree.
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode
of China Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Do you like these in-depth episodes
on Chinese politics?
We can keep making them because
viewers like you are directly funding China
Uncensored.
Support our team of researchers and writers.
Click the orange button to visit
our Patreon website,
and learn how you can contribute.