On this episode of China Uncensored,
How did the CCP identify American CIA operatives
in China?
I guess the dark suits and glasses gave it
away.
Everything is awesome when you’re in China...
and the CCP tells you it’s awesome.
And finally, America drops a bomb in China:
The new Star Wars movie.
This is
China Uncensored.
Last year we reported the revelation
that the Chinese Communist Party
had more or less successfully executed
or imprisoned the CIA’s entire spy ring
in China.
Now I’m not saying I support CIA operations...
but I’m definitely opposed to the killing
of agents.
Not cool, CCP.
But it was a mystery how the Chinese regime
got the names and details of those CIA informants.
Was it hackers?
Was it a mole?
Was it a hacker mole?
Well, the CIA just arrested a former CIA agent
they think may have been responsible.
53-year-old Jerry Chun Shing Lee
lives in Hong Kong but was apprehended on
Monday
when he traveled to John F. Kennedy Airport
in New York.
Just one more reason you should
never fly into JFK.
But just because there’s a little espionage
and murder between the US and China,
that doesn’t mean we can’t do business
together!
Google has opened its third office in China,
in the manufacturing city of Shenzhen.
You know, Google!
The company that ended its business
operations in China in 2010
because they were sick and tired of
the Chinese regime forcing them
to censor search results.
And of the Chinese regime hacking them.
Lousy hacker moles.
But it’s been eight years—
plenty of time to forget all the bad parts!
It’s like looking back to 2010 and thinking,
“Yeah, The Expendables was
a pretty cool movie, I guess.”
You guess?
Do you not remember how the plot made no sense?!
And how Arnold Schwarzenegger was only in
it
for like two minutes
after being in all the previews?
What a rip-off!
Anyway, Google is good with searches,
but bad with memory.
So they figured it was time for a sequel,
and set up this new office in Shenzhen.
The office itself isn’t a big deal.
It’s just a workspace for Google staff
who are already traveling back and forth to
China.
But it highlights how Google
is expanding its operations there.
Google is pushing to manufacture
more hardware in China.
Google’s also opening an Artificial Intelligence
research center in China.
Which, to me, doesn’t seem so smart.
And Google isn’t the only Western Company
trying to make inroads.
LEGO is partnering with Chinese tech company
Tencent
to make online games.
Obviously LEGO will have to make some changes.
For instance, deviating from the LEGO instructions
will now be a crime.
And the Chinese edition of the LEGO Movie
has no evil government overlord.
It just ends 5 minutes in,
with the Everything is Awesome song.
According to India’s Economic Times,
these satellite photos show a build up
of the Chinese military, including armored
tanks,
along the North Doklam plateau.
That’s very close to disputed territory
between China and Bhutan.
It was the site of a months-long border conflict
between China, Bhutan and India.
Is it already time for another border dispute
between China and India?
We’ll keep an eye on the situation
to see how it develops.
You know what a requirement
for being a lawyer in China is?
Love the Chinese Communist Party.
And if you don’t,
you can’t be a lawyer.
This is ridiculous.
Doesn’t the Chinese regime know l
awyers are incapable of feeling love?
This is Yu Wensheng.
He’s a Chinese human rights lawyer
who has criticized the Chinese leadership.
But several months ago,
he tried to open up his own law firm.
This is what Beijing authorities
told him in a letter:
“Through investigations, this organization
found
you have openly expressed opposition
to the [Communist] Party’s leadership.”
And now they’ve taken away his license.
According to the BBC, since 2015,
“More than 300 lawyers, legal assistants
and activists
have been questioned, and more than
two dozen have been formally investigated.”
And in a move that’s sure not to
anger Muslims around the world,
the “Chinese government authorities
have banned Muslim children from attending
religious events during winter break.”
The parents were furious.
But the kids were like,
“Oh no.
I guess I’ll have to go outside and play.”
Speaking of kids,
remember Ice Boy from last week’s episode?
Well he’s had his 15 minutes of fame.
Because now it’s all about Little Li.
At just 7 years old,
Little Li is already working as a deliveryman,
usually making around 30 stops a day.
This has sparked outrage on Chinese social
media
over child poverty,
something the Chinese regime
really doesn’t want people talking about.
Li’s father is presumed dead,
and his mother abandoned him for her other
family.
He’s being raised by
an old colleague of his father’s who,
you guessed it,
works as a delivery man.
He tried to get Li registered to go to school,
but couldn’t because of China’s
strict household registration program.
Now that the Internet has discovered Little
Li,
the local authorities have moved him to an
orphanage.
Hopefully now Little Li will get to attend
school,
and be bored like all the other kids.
Speaking of poverty,
another Chinese city has admitted
it faked economic data.
Baotou in China’s Inner Mongolia region
actually made about half as much revenue
as local officials had reported.
And finally, in entertainment news,
the Last Jedi bombed so badly in China,
it was pulled from theaters.
They blamed bad reviews.
And the fact that the original Star Wars trilogy
was banned in China for decades.
But I think the real reason The Last Jedi
bombed is,
Chinese people don’t like Porgs.
What do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
That was a lot of stories!
But there’s more to tell!
Head over to ChinaUncensored.tv
where you can see full half hour episodes
of China Uncensored you won’t see on YouTube.
And while you’re there,
click on the link that says support,
to find out ways you can help
contribute to China Uncensored.
Once again that’s ChinaUncensored.tv.