On this episode of China Uncensored,
a very controversial and sensitive topic.
Good thing I can say whatever I...
No!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Well gang,
we’re in trouble.
You may have heard about how YouTube
has rolled out some extremely vague,
nondescript guidelines
for what topics are “advertiser-friendly
content.”
And YouTube says
that if I don’t create
“advertiser-friendly content,”
they won’t place ads in my episodes.
In fact,
YouTube has been taking away ads
across the board
for thousands of YouTube creators.
If a video violates their vague prohibitions,
YouTube removes the ads before and during
the video.
Great!
No ads!
Except that’s how everyone supports their
shows.
Without advertising revenue,
shows like China Uncensored wouldn’t exist.
This story first broke last Wednesday
when big-time YouTuber Philip Defranco
called them out on it.
By taking away monetization it’s a form
of censorship.
Why censorship?
Because those ads are the main way
we supports ourselves at China Uncensored.
That's how we can create episodes for you
three times a week.
So what’s not “advertiser-friendly content”?
According to YouTube’s guidelines,
it includes
“controversial or sensitive subjects”
including “subjects related to war”
or “political conflicts.”
That’s why I’ve been getting emails like
this.
Hmmm…
Maybe YouTube prefers I
praise China’s economic development?
Or maybe I should just cover food festivals?
Ok,
maybe not all food festivals…
Now YouTube has responded to the outrage
from Youtube creators and fans
by saying this is not a new policy.
They’ve just implemented a new policy
that lets you know they’ve stripped your
revenue away
by sending you an email.
YouTube didn’t change their policy?
They used to take your money away without
telling you?
Isn’t that even worse?
But actually,
this is new to me.
This month marks China Uncensored’s
4-year anniversary on YouTube.
And until last month,
not once has a video of mine
had its ads stripped away like this.
But in the past week and a half,
six of my videos have been flagged,
costing the show potentially thousands of
dollars
in revenue.
And guess what?
I only got emails about two of them.
YouTube is still not properly notifying me.
Now technically,
this isn’t censorship.
YouTube still keeps the videos online.
But it’s ad-censorship.
Because without ads,
this show can’t survive.
And doesn’t this ad-censorship incentivize
all YouTube creators
to avoid sensitive and controversial topics?
Hmmm...
I wonder if this has anything to do with Google
trying to get back into China...
Okay,
probably not.
Maybe…
But meanwhile,
the Chinese regime invests an estimated
10 billion dollars a year
in what they call
“external publicity work.”
That is,
spreading its propaganda message to the West.
The Communist Party has a giant billboard
in Times Square,
broadcasting Chinese propaganda 24/7,
365 days a year
since 2011.
They place their propaganda in newspapers
like the New York Times and Wall Street Journal.
Yes,
China Watch is a paid insert
in respectable Western newspapers.
State-run CCTV gives its propaganda news feed
to all the major US TV networks,
telling them
“here’s the latest China news, for free!”
They even created an English language version
of CCTV
and put its headquarters
seven blocks from the White House.
The Communist Party even buys airtime on American
radio stations
without disclosing it.
That’s why I created China Uncensored -
to cut through all that and deliver truthful,
uncensored information about China,
and how it affects you.
But now,
YouTube is cutting off ad revenue
on controversial topics.
I’m not exaggerating when I say
this could kill China Uncensored.
Without income,
I’ll have to stop doing the show for you.
And my YouTube revenue has plummeted
in the last few weeks.
Unbelievably,
it’s less than it was a year ago,
when I had only 120,000 subscribers
and half as many staff to support.
And another challenge is this:
Even on my videos that YouTube doesn’t ad-censor,
I’ve been losing a lot of revenue.
For a typical episode I publish,
about 30,000 of you use ad blockers.
Look,
I get it.
YouTube ads can be annoying.
But it’s how YouTubers like me
can afford to make content for you.
But there is a way you can help keep this
show going.
Support China Uncensored on Patreon.
Patreon is a website that lets people like
you
directly support your favorite creators on
YouTube.
Sort of like how during the European Renaissance,
patrons would provide financial support to
artists
so they could focus on their craft.
I started working with Patreon a year ago,
and the extra income has allowed me to do
things like:
Hire Zach, our researcher;
hire Seamus, our video editor,
so I could make more episodes every week;
travel to South Korea,
hold fan events,
buy costumes and props,
and much more.
But so far,
Patreon has only been a third of our revenue.
YouTube ads have been the majority.
Until now, I’m afraid.
So your Patreon support is more crucial than
ever before.
If you’re already one of my Patreon supporters,
thank you so much!
You’ve been a huge help so far,
and I hope you’ll continue.
And if you can afford it,
please consider expanding your monthly limit,
And if you aren’t a Patreon supporter yet,
please become a supporter now.
Sign-up is super easy;
it takes less than five minutes.
The link is below.
And to commemorate our challenges with YouTube,
I’ve created a new support level:
China Uncensored Uncensorer!
That official title will be yours,
to all of you who contributes 5 cents or more
per episode.
Because if all 30,000 of you who use ad blockers
contribute even 5 cents per episode,
you can make up for it in a big way.
Our most popular level of support,
of course,
is 50 cents -
where you can become an official member
of my 50-Cent Army.
I’ll also give you some cool wallpaper to
download
Check out the even cooler rewards
like music downloads
for people who contribute more.
Now recently,
I asked a few hundred of you in my Market
Research Team
what you’d like to see from me.
And the most common request was:
Behind-the-scenes stuff.
So,
wish granted.
Starting now,
for everyone who supports China Uncensored
on Patreon,
I’ll start posting behind-the-scenes stuff
that only you get access to.
Because your support will keep China Uncensored
uncensored.
So please,
share this video.
Get the word out there that YouTube is censoring
creators
by not placing ads on controversial videos.
And again,
please support the show on Patreon if you can.
The link is below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
And one more thing:
China Uncensored has never had ads,
except the ones YouTube places automatically,
haha less so now.
The only exception was Mania,
the South Korean tailor who gave me suits
and ties earlier this year
in exchange for making that ad -
the kind of ad that goes here,
in what we call the “end card.”
I take the integrity of this show very seriously
and have been reluctant to have
product sponsors for the show,
even though that’s extremely common on YouTube,
and advertisers have been reaching out to
me for a long time.
Now I see that if China Uncensored is to continue,
I’m also going to need to do this.
But I just want you to know
that if you ever see me promoting a product,
it will be something I personally approve.
And never will any advertiser control the
content of the show.
China Uncensored is
and will remain
independent and uncensored.