Canada has a secret deep state
With close ties to China
And it explains how the Chinese military
Nearly found its way into Canada
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
Canada. America’s friendly neighbors to the north.
...panda hugging neighbors to the north!
But like a panda, the soft cuddly exterior\h
hides razor sharp claws and teeth.\h
Canada was planning on inviting the Chinese\h
military over for cold-weather training drills.\h\h
But those drills were canceled\h
after the US freaked out.\h
Why would the Candaian government\h
think it was a good idea to invite\h\h
troops from a hostile Communist Dictatorship?
To find out, I interviewed Cleo Paskal from\h\h
Chatham House & Foundation\h
for Defense of Democracies.
Cleo, thanks for joining me today.
Pleasure. Really happy to have this opportunity\h
to talk about Canada. Usually people never ask.
We care about the Canadians here on China\h\h
Uncensored. Well, okay. So the\h
first big question is, in what\h\h
universe was it decided that the Chinese and\h
Canadian military should be working together?
Okay. Canada's a funny country. We are not\h
probably what you think we are. We are much\h\h
bigger than you think we are. We're the second\h
largest land mass on the planet. We're part of\h\h
NATO. We're a G7 country. We are a real country,\h
a real big, serious country, but we have a lot\h\h
of different approaches internationally\h
that sometimes come out in this sort of\h\h
decision-making. And one of the things that's\h
been going on for a very long time in Canada\h\h
is a deep political and economic linkage\h
to China. This didn't come out of the blue.
This was a tip of an iceberg that goes\h
back to the 1880s when Canada was sending\h\h
missionaries to China and those missionaries,\h
long story short, had kids in China.\h\h
White, Canadian kids who grew up in China, learned\h
Chinese, became very attached to the culture,\h\h
came back to Canada. Then some of them went\h
back and got involved in China during the\h\h
'40s, '30s and '40s. And when they came back to\h
Ottawa, after that, this group who were known\h\h
as the mish kids, the missionary kids, got into\h
the Canadian Foreign Service because they had\h\h
language skills and had traveled, and many were\h
quite idealistic about what was going on in China\h\h
and pushed from within the\h
system for a very long time,\h\h
for recognition of China, as opposed to Taiwan.
This is a very condensed version of that, but\h
there was within the Canadian Foreign Service,\h\h
there was this group of people who were very\h
sympathetic to Communist China. And when Canada\h\h
recognized China in 1970, it was one of the first\h
Western countries to recognize China, among the\h\h
grouping of ambassadors that Canada sent to China,\h
four of them were these former missionary kids.
Well, just a quick question about that.
Yeah, sure. Go.
If the missionaries went during the Qing\h
Dynasty, there was the Qing Dynasty,\h\h
then the Republican period, and then the Communist\h
Party, they didn't see any difference between\h\h
the China that they may have grown up in and\h
what the Chinese Communist Party was doing?
It's a really complicated, tricky question\h
that gets into psychology. So, first of all,\h\h
as missionary kids, they were among the\h
people and were very sympathetic to the\h\h
Chinese people. And a lot of them, one of them,\h
James Endicott, he didn't become an ambassador,\h\h
but became very influential later on, worked\h
initially very closely with Chiang Kai-shek and\h\h
was feeding information to the OSS. And was part\h
of that grouping. And he didn't like what he saw\h\h
that group doing in China. He thought they\h
were starving their own troops, and he thought\h\h
they were baskering people. It was a complicated\h
period and the Chinese, in particular, Zhou Enlai,\h\h
who he became quite close with, were very good at\h
presenting their case. They knew how to talk to\h\h
that sort of a person. And so very effectively\h
co-opted him and others into their cause.
Now, after they came to power in 49, of course,\h
they got rid of a lot of them. They kicked a lot\h\h
of them out of the country. But by that\h
time, I think Endicott left maybe in 48,\h\h
because there was a Chiang Kai-shek hit squat out\h
for him. So he comes back to Canada and he starts\h\h
up a newspaper magazine, which is basically\h
CCP propaganda. So from very early on these\h\h
mish kids who had been considered China experts\h
by the intelligence community at the time,\h\h
were embedded in the system, but also became\h
sympathetic to Communist China. And they\h\h
persisted. They persisted in the system for a very\h
long time. There are other elements to it, but if\h\h
you have any other questions about that, it's an\h
interesting topic, happy to ramble on about it.
I'd be happy to talk more about that on the\h
podcast we're going to do with you on China\h\h
Unscripted. But for now, I think you've\h
provided some interesting context to why\h\h
some in the Canadian government\h
might think military.
That's the only part of it. Just\h
wait, just wait. It gets better. Okay.\h\h
So that's just one bizarre element\h
of Canadian CCP linkages, but\h\h
a whole other part of it is at the same time, you\h
have people within the Canadian community who are\h\h
buying into the whole anti-Americanism, especially\h
with the beginning of the Vietnam War, who also\h\h
get brought into that whole, Canada's a great\h
country, and we're going to go save the world,\h\h
the new missionary type thing. Pierre Trudeau, who\h
was Prime Minister of Canada for a very long time,\h\h
he became Prime Minister, I think in 68. And\h
he was more or less Prime Minister till 84.
And he was really instrumental in\h
recognizing China. He visited China in 1949.\h\h
On his communist tour of the world. He visited in\h
1960 as a labor lawyer. And then when he came back\h\h
and became prime minister, he had\h
this ready coterie of mish kids in\h\h
the civil service. And he himself was\h
this other grouping of international\h\h
lefties who was sympathetic to the\h
cause. And so they came together-
This was Justin Trudeau's father?
Are you ready for the third strain?
Okay.
The third strain is business.
Of course.
Yeah. The third strain involves\h
initially this incredible company\h\h
based out of Quebec called Power Corp, Power\h
Corporation, not a evil empire name at all.\h\h
And they are a massive multi-billion dollar\h
company that does everything. Does a lot\h\h
of money management, does media. It\h
does resources, all sorts of stuff-
Standard mum and pop company.
And that's run by... Well, it is. Because\h
it's a family company and the family is the\h\h
Desmarais family who are incredibly powerful. The\h
Desmarais family have had four people who became\h\h
prime ministers or were prime ministers of Canada,\h
have had some sort of affiliation with Power Corp.\h\h
And when Power Corp saw the opportunities\h
in China, as Trudeau was prime minister,\h\h
was opening up China, Trudeau came together\h
with the Compliance Canadian Administration\h\h
and Power Corp, and they started the Canada China\h
Business Council around 1977, 1978, very early.\h\h
And on the board was CITIC, which is\h
a Chinese government linked company,\h\h
very important company. And on the Canadian\h
side, there were a few, but there was Power Corp,\h\h
there was Bombardier, there was SNC Lavalin.\h
These are three massive Montreal-based companies.\h\h
And the Desmarais Power Corp facilitated CITIC's\h
first major overseas investment out of China,\h\h
which was into Canada through Power Corp. What\h
you're seeing with these military exercises\h\h
is a very small tip of a massive iceberg that's\h
been moving in this direction for 120 years.
And so that's why, even though the documents\h
that came out point to decisions made by the\h\h
Trudeau government, it actually began back in\h
2013 under the Conservative Stephen Harper,\h\h
Prime Minister. So this is not just one party\h
or the other in Canada. This is systemic.
It partially is. But another thing to understand\h\h
when you're thinking about Canada is, you have\h
to think about our foreign policy in the context\h\h
of U.S. Foreign Policy. So what was going on\h
towards China in the U.S. at the same time,\h\h
Scarborough Shoal was around that time. It wasn't\h
as if countries were standing up to China in any\h\h
conceivable way. The initial deal was under the\h
Harper government and it was through a mill-mill\h\h
cooperation arrangement, but Harper\h
since has become very vocal about China.\h\h
And the current leader, we have the party in\h
power now is the Liberal Party and our Prime\h\h
Minister's Justin Trudeau, who's the son of Pierre\h
Trudeau who went to China in '49, '60, '73, and\h\h
soon after Tiananmen Square, he took his two sons,\h
including Justin on a nice little visit to China.
Lovely.
So Harper's kind of switched, but the head of\h
the opposition, which is the Conservative Party,\h\h
Erin O'Toole, who's former Canadian military,\h
is much more direct about standing up to China.\h\h
So yes, it's embedded in the system. Yes, prime\h
ministers for both parties have been involved,\h\h
but currently at this moment, the Conservatives\h
are much more clear about standing up to China.
So the documents about the China Canadian\h
military cooperation have suspiciously little\h\h
redacting, meaning things weren't properly\h
blacked out. Why do you think that was?
It gives me hope actually. If you haven't seen\h
the documents, I suggest you go see them there.\h\h
You can see them at thechinafile.com\h
and full credit to Canadian journalist,\h\h
Ezra Levant from Rebel News for getting them and\h
then releasing them so we could all see them.\h\h
They're about 37 pages and they're really poorly\h
redacted to the point where it almost looks like\h\h
the important bits are being highlighted. There\h
are a lot of very good people in the system,\h\h
who've been trying to get the story out about\h
China being a security problem for Canada for\h\h
a long time, we had the Sidewinder Report\h
was leaked in the late '90s, the Canadian\h\h
Security Intelligence Service put out a report\h
a couple of years ago saying this is a problem.
Richard Fadden, who's former head of CSIS,\h
publicly talks about this all the time.\h\h
Charles Burton, who's an incredible academic and\h
former diplomat talks about it. They're a big\h\h
group of people within Canada who are very, very\h
worried about this and breaking through is hard.\h\h
So having international coverage of what's\h
going on in Canada is really helpful. The\h\h
fact that these China files are being covered\h
by you, makes it more of an issue for Canada,\h\h
which helps the politicians and the\h
diplomats who are trying to maybe say,\h\h
"Look, maybe this isn't such a great idea."
Well, speaking of Canadian politicians, I\h
know Canada's Foreign Affairs Ministry begged\h\h
for the training drills to continue\h
because it would negatively affect\h\h
bilateral ties. And so I got to ask, the\h
kidnapping of two Canadian citizens by China,\h\h
Michael Kovrig, and Michael Spavor,\h
that doesn't affect bilateral ties?
Thank you very much for mentioning them. The\h
background to that is Canada responded to an\h\h
extradition treaty request from the U.S. for\h
Ms. Meng, who's the daughter of the Huawei\h\h
founder and herself is the CEO at Huawei.\h
And we detained her two years ago. And within\h\h
a couple of weeks, China retaliated by taking\h
two Canadians and they're being held largely\h\h
incommunicado in detention in China to this day.\h
And you would think that would be a big deal. And\h\h
some of the Canadian press like The Globe and Mail\h
keep a count of how many days they've been held.\h\h
There's a Christmas card lobby going on now\h
where we're being asked to send Christmas\h\h
cards to the Chinese embassies and consulates\h
to forward to them, just so that the Chinese\h\h
know that people care. And yes, you would think\h
it would affect our engagement with China, but\h\h
it's so deep and so extensive, as a momentum,\h
as an ideology within some of the, I'd say,\h\h
small groups of decision-making,\h
that it's very hard to break through.
Now, in those documents, the Deputy\h
Minister, who's pushing to say,\h\h
"We don't want, don't break off relations with\h
China. If you're going to cancel anything,\h\h
you need to get it cleared by us." He's\h
now Clerk of the Privy Council, which is\h\h
Canada's top civil servant. We have these peculiar\h
names for stuff, still. This is somebody who is\h\h
deep, deep, deep in the civil service. And the\h
idea is they've been bought into this, don't upset\h\h
China, psychology. And if you think about it,\h
how often do you hear China criticizing Canada.\h\h
They'll criticize Australia, they'll criticize\h
even New Zealand, sometimes definitely the\h\h
U.S. but we are the Five Eyes partner that rarely\h
gets any blow back in China [inaudible 00:15:45].\h\h
So that gives you an indication that we are\h
successfully not a problem, whatever that entails.
Until, they kidnapped two Canadian\h
citizens when there's a little-
But even, what are we doing? What came out in\h
those documents was not long after, within a\h\h
year after they'd kidnapped them, we continued\h
the exchanges. The military to its credit is\h\h
the one that canceled the winter training and\h
they canceled it without approval from Global\h\h
Affairs Canada, which is our Ministry of Foreign\h
Affairs, which is what the exchange is about.\h\h
Global Affairs Canada went nuts. They said, "How\h
can you, the military, cancel it without checking\h\h
with us. This is going to affect our relationship\h
with China." But also in the documents,\h\h
there's a list of continuing exchanges,\h
after the two Michaels were taken, including\h\h
Minister McKenna, who's our Environment Minister\h
going to China to talk about climate change.\h\h
We, as a federal government, haven't\h
really, I think, understood China.\h\h
This isn't how you're going to get back\h
the two Michaels. Anyway, regardless-
Clearly.
Yeah.
Sorry. So what is the Chinese Communist\h
Party's ultimate goal in Canada?
We've talked about Conference of National Power\h
before, and Canada has a lot to offer to China.\h\h
It's highly strategically located, especially\h
since China is apparently a near Arctic power.\h\h
It has tons of resources. It's right next\h
to the U.S. We are a Five Eyes partner. We\h\h
have very good high tech. We had a company\h
called Nortel, which was doing cutting edge\h\h
research in a whole bunch of areas that was hacked\h
by almost certainly Chinese-based hackers. And\h\h
coincidentally Huawei built up a lot of its tech\h
profile, not long afterwards with very similar\h\h
sorts of stuff. We had escorted Chinese scientists\h
out of a level 4 bio lab in Winnipeg last summer,\h\h
not this summer, but the summer before,\h
like we have tons, whatever China wants,\h\h
they can probably find a\h
little bit of it in Canada.
Are they going after the poutine?
I think they have some standards.
I beg your pardon. I like poutine.
But I can tell you, currently, everything you'd\h
find anywhere else in the world, you'll find\h\h
in Canada in terms of China. Currently they're\h
trying to buy a gold mine in Nunavut up in the far\h\h
North that is not economically viable, but it does\h
happen to have a port on the Northwest passage.\h\h
And it's a hundred miles away from the NORAD base.\h
It's all the stuff you'd expect. Every single box\h\h
that they can check from any single country, if\h
Canada has it, that's obviously what they want.\h\h
And they want us also to keep quiet about Hong\h
Kong. There are 300,000 Canadians in Hong Kong,\h\h
passport holding Canadians in Hong Kong,\h
and they don't want Canada to become, a\h\h
Hong Kong government, next... And we've got\h
massive crime coming in through Vancouver.\h\h
And we have wheat and we have gold. If we\h
open up the mines where Earth's [inaudible\h\h
00:19:26], we're like the Walmart of countries.
Canada's where it's at.
Yeah.
Are the Canadian people aware of this\h
relationship, what's going on? What's at risk?
China's popularity numbers in Canada are very low.\h
They're single digit. There's an enormous amount\h\h
of anger. And as always, you have to say, to be\h
clear, because it's accurate, this is Chinese\h\h
Communist Party. This is directed at China as a\h
country, not Chinese Canadians. Chinese Canadians\h\h
built the railroad, put up with the head tax,\h
we had a very discriminatory immigration policy,\h\h
but they are a very important part of Canada. And\h
it's clear. Within the population, it's not about\h\h
the guy you went to school with, it's\h
about the Chinese Communist Party.\h\h
And those numbers are high, but by and large,\h\h
Canadians don't care that much about foreign\h
policy. It's not a big topic in the media.
And if it is, then it's about the U.S.\h
And if it's about the U.S., often,\h\h
especially over the last four years, the media,\h
which it tends to be center, center, left,\h\h
like U.S. has been counter of the U.S. And\h
China's been very good at playing that card,\h\h
trying to create divisions\h
between the U.S. and Canada,\h\h
reaching out to disaffected groups within\h
Canada. There was a very weird thing going on\h\h
in the '70s where Black Panthers were coming up to\h
Montreal for acupuncture training. Yeah, exactly.
We're going to have to talk about\h
that more on the podcast, I think.
Yeah. China has been in Canada affecting some of\h
the perceptions of China for a very long time,\h\h
as you saw with the James Endicott story, but\h
by and large now, Canadians are not huge fans\h\h
of the Chinese Communist Party. This military\h
cooperation thing was not popular at all, but\h\h
it's not a major political issue at the moment.\h
So it's hard to get it to sway decision-making.
So what can be done to counter the influence\h
of the Chinese Communist Party in Canada?
As ever, I think you need\h
more information out there,\h\h
more coverage, more understanding. Again, there is\h
some very good media within Canada. Canadian Media\h\h
is the one that broke the story. The Epoch\h
Times is available in French in Quebec now.\h\h
We're getting interesting kinds of coverage,\h
but I think it takes specific events. And we\h\h
are very sensitive often to our allies, our\h
Five Eyes allies. So in the documents, again,\h\h
there was a big question from Global Affairs\h
Canada, about whether we were canceling the winter\h\h
training, because the U.S. is putting pressure\h
on us, or was it one of the other Five Eyes?\h\h
Was Australia upset about this? Or was it just\h
the U.S. And if it's Australia, oddly enough,\h\h
that actually can have more influence than the\h
Americans, because we're used to the Americans\h\h
complaining. If the Australians continue to stand\h
their ground, it becomes very helpful for Canada.
Well, great. Thank you for sharing all that\h
with me. I didn't realize how deep it went.
It's pretty bad. Yeah.
Well, yes. Thanks again for joining us.
Thank you for having me. And as long as the\h
poutine is safe, then I think we're okay.
Definitely.
I strangely feel the urge to order some Poutine.\h\h
If you’d like to hear more from Cleo,\h
check out our interview with her on the\h\h
China Unscripted Podcast, where we go into way\h
more detail. That’ll be out later this week.
Thanks for watching, once again I’m\h
Chris Chappell. See you next time.