Declassified!
Just before leaving office\h
Trump releases a secret document
On countering China in the Indo-Paficic.
Welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
This episode is sponsored by Surfshark.
You should be using a VPN like Surfshark to
protect yourself whenever you go online.\h
As Donald Trump reluctantly hands the keys
to the White House to Joe Biden today, there’s
one thing he’s leaving behind.
A giant painting of himself in the Oval Office!
Just kidding.
I think.
But Trump *is* leaving behind his administration’s
strategy to counter the Chinese Communist
Party in the Indo-Pacific.
The Indo-Pacific is a term that the US government
started using under the Obama administration
to refer to the Asia-Pacific region plus areas
connected by the Indian Ocean.\h
Other countries are also using the term Indo-Pacific,
like Japan, which calls for a free and open
Indo-Pacific.
And Australia, which has their own Indo-Pacific
strategy.
The Indo-Pacific region is home to one third
of the world’s economy, and nearly two-thirds
of the world’s population.
For decades, even centuries, the dominant
power in the region has been China.
But the US has been trying to change that.
And we know that, because just one week before
stepping down, President Trump declassified
his administration’s strategic framework
for the Indo-Pacific.
The document was written in 2018 mainly by
Matthew Pottinger, a former China journalist
and Marine Corps officer who later became
Trump’s Deputy National Security Advisor.
But it’s been kept secret—until now.
To sum it up: The Strategic Framework is largely
about countering the Chinese Communist Party’s
aggressiveness in the Indo-Pacific.
And aggressive, they have been.
From militarizing artificial islands in the
South China Sea...
to sending jets into Taiwan’s airspace...
to trying to take over Indian territory along
the Himalayan border.
And on the diplomatic front, the Chinese regime
has successfully cozied up to governments
that used to be more allied with the US—but
felt the US let them down during previous
administrations.
Like South Korea, which felt the US didn’t
protect them when China punished them for
installing the American THAAD missile defence
system.
And the Philippines, which felt the US let
the Chinese navy take over the Scarborough
Shoal.
And Thailand, which was angry that the US
backed off after the military coup in 2014.
As the US government backed off, the Chinese
Communist Party filled in the gap.
Part of the US strategy to counter the Communist
Party is ideological.
The Trump Administration believes that countries
in the Indo-Paficic region should have national
sovereignty, freedom of navigation, respect
for individual rights, rule of law, and free
markets.
Whereas the Chinese Communist Party believes
that countries should bow down.
“You will respect China’s authority!”
That reference is from 1998.
How does that make you feel?
So in many ways, the US Strategic Framework
is about laying out US beliefs.
But it’s also about action.
One of the goals in the strategic framework
is to create a “security framework with
India, Japan, Australia and the United States”—known
as the Quad.
And the Trump administration did it.
Through a series of collaborations, military
agreements, and joint naval exercises, the
US has helped strengthen the alliance with
these democracies to resist China’s influence.
Another US goal is to enable Taiwan to develop
its own effective defense strategy, and the
ability to engage China on its own terms.
And the US has largely done that, too.
At least when it comes to weapons sales.\h
In 2020 alone, the US approved a 1.8 billion
dollar sale of rocket launchers and artillery
to Taiwan.
Then another 2.4 billion for coastal defense.
Then another 600 million for aerial drones.
Then another 280 million for communications
systems.
2020 was a great year to be an arms dealer.
But it was also a great year to be a US diplomat,
because the US has sent a number of top-level
diplomats to Taiwan.
The message is clear: America won’t let
Taiwan down just because the Chinese Communist
Party is making threats.
And also, it would look really bad if the
next US administration didn’t continue this
policy, hint hint.
But there’s a lot more to this policy.
Which I’ll tell you about after the break.
Welcome back.
Another key part of the US strategic framework
is to “prevent China’s industrial policies
and unfair trading practices from distorting
global markets and harming U.S. competitiveness.”
One of the ways the US has done that is through
putting tariffs on Chinese imports.
Then more tariffs.
And then even more tariffs.
This policy has reduced the US trade deficit
with China—or at least made it grow less
quickly.
It’s also encouraged US companies to pull
out of China—even before the coronavirus.
Those companies are not necessarily returning
to America.
But at least the shift to other countries
has reduced the Chinese regime’s ability
to use unfair trading practices to distort
global markets and harm US competitiveness.
So, objective partially achieved?
A combination of US policy and the coronavirus
has also convinced US allies to pull out of
China.
The Japanese government is forking out half
a billion dollars to get companies to leave
China and return to Japan.
Another key US objective is to “maintain
an intelligence advantage over China” and
protect the US and its allies from Chinese
intelligence activities.
To that end, the US has done a lot.
The Trump administration strengthened the
Treasury Department’s ability to block Chinese
investments that pose a security risk to the
US.
The US has also gone after people at universities
who have been working as spies for China.
And last year, the US closed the Chinese consulate
in Houston, because it was being used to steal
trade secrets.
Plus the FBI has protected Chinese people
living in the US by countering the Communist
Party’s “Operation Fox Hunt” that tries
to force people to return to China where they’ll
be thrown in prison.
So 2020 was not a good year to be a Chinese
spy.
And overseas, the US created a 5G Clean Network
initiative to keep Communist Party espionage
operations out of global telecom networks,
and more than 50 countries have joined.
Plus the US worked with other members of the
Five Eyes intelligence alliance to build a
special coalition to counter Chinese espionage.
The Five Eyes includes the US, Canada, the
UK, Australia, and New Zealand.
And somehow, the Trump Administration even
got other countries to team up with Five Eyes—including
Germany!
And here I’d heard Trump wouldn’t even
shake their hand.
I guess that was wrong.
So this part of the strategic framework has
seen real success.
Also, I had mentioned that some former allies
had pulled back under the Obama administration,
like Thailand and the Philippines.
Well, there’s a section of the US Strategic
Framework about Southeast Asia.
A lot of it is redacted, but it does seek
to strengthen ASEAN—the coalition of Southeast
Asian Nations.
And in particular, it seeks to promote a development
model that provides an alternative to China’s
One Belt One Road.
Now as I mentioned, the U.S. Strategic Framework
for the Indo-Pacific is largely related to
China.
But it’s only one piece of the Trump Administration’s
China strategy.
In fact, the 10-page document repeatedly references
another document, called the “U.S. Strategic
Framework for Countering China’s Economic
Aggression.”
And that one is still classified.
If they showed me, they’d probably have
to kill me.
And that’s not worth it, just to read some
policy report.
There’s also a whole section about North
Korea, plus references to a separate strategic
document about North Korea, which is also
classified.
But I’m not going to get into Korea stuff
in this episode.
This isn’t North Korea Un-Juche’d.
Annyeonghaseyo and welcome to North Korea
Un-Juche’d, I’m your Dearest Leader, Chris
Chappell.
I wonder if that show would get demonetized,
too.\h
But I think the real success of this Strategic
Framework on the Indo-Pacific is not the accomplishments
so far.
It’s that the Trump administration has made
it public—and that puts pressure on future
administrations to stick with it.
It’s basically the policy equivalent of
Trump hanging a painting of himself in the
Oval Office.
I’m lookin’ at you, Joe!
And this episode has been sponsored by Surfshark.
Surfshark is a VPN that lets you protect your
identity when you go online.
It helps you hide your IP address.
That’s important if you’re in China or
another authoritarian country, where internet
police could be watching which subversive
YouTube channels you watch.
Even in free countries, though, giant corporations
and individual hackers may be monitoring the
websites you visit and what you post online.
And with Surfshark’s Camouflage Mode, even
your internet provider can’t tell that you’re
using a VPN.
That helps you stay private.
Plus, Surfshark’s CleanWeb mode lets you
browse the internet free from ads, trackers,
and malware.
So stay safe by using Surfshark.
Try it out with our special deal that includes
83% off of a 2-year plan plus 3 extra months
for free.
Go to Surfshark dot com slash uncensored.
For just $2.21 a month, you can get Surfshark
on all your devices.
So click the link below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.