Every day, China gets closer to invading Taiwan.
And a dangerous kind of warfare
could spell disaster.
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
Please help us. YouTube has been\h
randomly unsubscribing people\h\h
and demonetizing a lot of our videos. So please,\h
hit the like button and share this episode.\h\h
If you’re not seeing notifications for our\h
episodes, we publish new ones every Monday,\h\h
Wednesday, Friday, and sometimes Saturday.\h
Like today. So check back often.\h
You should also share this particular\h
episode because everyone needs to know\h\h
what the Chinese military is doing against\h
Taiwan. It’s called gray zone warfare.\h
And it has many in Taiwan’s military—and the\h
US military—worried about the future of Taiwan.
The Chinese Communist Party has been\h
solidifying its grip in the Asia Pacific. First,\h\h
it militarized artificial\h
islands in the South China Sea.
Then it squashed the freedoms of Hong Kong,\h\h
using brutal policing and a\h
draconian national security law.
All that remains is Taiwan. The Chinese Communist\h
Party claims Taiwan as part of its territory.\h\h
The independent government—and\h
military—of Taiwan, say otherwise.
China’s communist regime has threatened to use\h\h
military force to invade Taiwan,\h
but there’s a problem with that.\h
First, the geography. The Strait\h
of Taiwan is difficult to cross,\h\h
80 miles wide at the narrowest point.
Weather conditions mean an amphibious invasion\h
could only be launched in April or October. And\h\h
remember, Taiwan has had decades to fortify any\h
and all possible landing sites along the coast.
But despite the challenges,\h
Taiwan is still a major prize\h\h
and a top priority for\h
China’s Communist leadership.
Politically, once they control Taiwan,\h
then the People’s Republic becomes the\h\h
undisputed China. And in the eyes of the\h
Chinese regime, there can be only one.
“For [Xi Jinping], democratic Taiwan is now the\h
last outpost of resistance to his dream of a\h\h
unified and rejuvenated China that\h
can displace the United States as\h\h
the major power in the Asia-Pacific region.”
That’s because if the Chinese military\h
can successfully conquer Taiwan,\h\h
they would have a commanding\h
position in the region.
They would control what’s\h
called the first island chain.
The Chinese military could then dominate\h
shipping lanes, crippling Japan and South Korea,\h\h
and give the Chinese Navy\h
access to the Western Pacific.
That could essentially make the Chinese Communist\h
Party the dominant power in the Pacific,\h\h
instead of the United States.\h
And all of that is why China is using a\h
dangerous new tactic to fight Taiwan: gray\h\h
zone warfare. It’s a way for the PLA to defeat\h
Taiwan’s military without ever firing a shot.
Since just mid-September, “Chinese warplanes\h
have flown more than 100 of these missions.”
These are missions where the PLA\h
fly aircraft around and even into\h\h
Taiwan’s air defense identification\h
zone. Sometimes multiple times a day.\h\h
Even though no shots are fired, Taiwan has\h
to scramble jets each time in response.
According to the Pentagon, China has more than\h
2,000 fighter jets, bombers, and warplanes.
Taiwan only has 400.\h
“Over time, fuel costs, pilot fatigue\h
and wear and tear on Taiwanese aircraft\h\h
will threaten the readiness of the island’s\h
air force if this pressure continues.”
Besides the psychological toll,\h\h
Gray Zone Warfare is also designed to\h
enact a financial toll on the defenders.
The numbers we’re talking about here are insane.\h
In October, Taiwan’s Defense Minister said\h\h
they had to scramble their air force nearly 3,000\h
times in 2020. That cost 900 million dollars.
And it’s not just a battle for the skies.
From January through November of 2020,\h
Taiwanese ships launched 1,200 missions\h\h
to intercept PLA ships. That’s an increase\h
of about 400 missions from the previous year.
They’re basically trying to push the\h
Taiwanese military to the point of exhaustion.\h\h
And sap their will to fight.\h
There is another benefit of gray zone\h
warfare for the Chinese Communist Party.\h\h
It allows the PLA to gather intelligence,\h
on not just Taiwan’s defenses, but also\h\h
Taiwan’s and its allies’ submarine activity\h
in the area. That includes the United States.\h
And as Taiwan’s military gets more and more worn\h
out, the Chinese Communist Party is throwing the\h\h
entire Communist state apparatus into building\h
up its own military. That’s why, according\h\h
to a retired Taiwanese military chief, for a\h
Chinese invasion—“It’s only a matter of time.”
It’s important for people to know what the Chinese\h
Communist Party is doing. But YouTube has been\h\h
soft censoring China Uncensored—by demonetizing\h
our videos, secretly unsubscribing people,\h\h
and not notifying people when we release new\h
videos. So join us in the fight, what I call\h\h
the China Uncensored 50 cent army. They’re\h
viewers like you who contribute as little as\h\h
a dollar an episode on the crowd funding website\h
Patreon. That’s patreon.com/ChinaUncensored
As a thank you to them, I answer\h
their questions on the show.\h\h
And today’s question comes from 50 Cent Army\h
member...Logan! “Any truth to China having energy\h\h
blackouts and falling steel production\h
due to there ban on Australian coal?”
Well, it’s 100% true that\h
there’s a coal shortage in China\h\h
that's causing the worst blackouts in a decade.
And it’s also true that the Chinese regime has\h
been using trade to attack Australia. Australia\h\h
has been standing up to the Chinese Communist\h
Party—even calling for an investigation into\h\h
the origin of the coronavirus. The Communist\h
Party hates this. So it’s basically banned\h\h
loads of Australian goods—from barely,\h
to wine, lobsters, and yes coal.\h
But the Party denies that the shortage\h
is due to their ban on Australian coal,\h\h
noting that most Australian coal\h
is used for steel production.\h
Are they telling the truth? Maybe. Even if\h
the coal shortages aren’t caused by the ban\h\h
on Australian coal, that ban isn’t helping\h
the situation. Coal prices are soaring,\h\h
but the Communist Party remains\h
determined to punish Australia.\h
China’s energy shortage is also affecting steel\h
production. And even worse, BitCoin mining!
China clearly went a step too far.\h
If only they hadn’t banned lobsters,\h\h
they could burn them for fuel! And then\h
all the steel would smell delicious!
Thanks for your question Logan.\h
And thank you for supporting\h\h
truly the most insightful\h
China analysis out there.
And thank you for watching. Remember to\h
like, subscribe, and share this episode.\h\h
Once again I’m Chris Chappell. See you next time.