China has more than a billion people...
And Communist Party officials came up with
a brilliant plan...
to use them to make money.
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
The People’s Republic of China has the world’s
second biggest economy.
It wasn’t always like that.
But over the last several decades,
Chinese communist officials have gotten really
good at making money.
See, back in the 1950s,
Chairman Mao Zedong told his officials
to kill rich people and take their stuff.
But that only went so far, because eventually,
China ran out of rich people to kill.
So in the early 2000s,
three-legged money toad and Communist Party
leader Jiang Zemin
led a brilliant new scheme.
It combined the best elements of communism
AND cut-throat capitalism:
Kill *dissidents,* and take their *organs.*
And then sell those organs to rich people
at state-run hospitals,
like this one.
And it turns out that you can make some *serious*
money this way.
You know, they say you can’t put a value
on human life.
But in communist China, that value is up to
$852,000.
Now this money-making scheme looks too horrible
to be true.
And that’s one reason why people don’t
believe it’s happening.
But the proof keeps coming out.
There have been investigations into organ
harvesting since 2006.
But they didn’t get much attention.
Then a group called the China Tribunal
held a series of hearings about it starting
in 2018.
They asked for evidence and testimony
on whether forced organ harvesting was happening
in China.
And in particular, they looked at whether
Falun Gong practitioners
and Uighurs were being targeted.
Falun Gong is based on an ancient Chinese
spiritual practice.
It has exercises that look a bit like Tai-Chi.
And its core philosophy is “Truthfulness,
Compassion, and Tolerance.”
Falun Gong became super popular in China in
the 1990s,
until Jiang Zemin realized there were like
100 million people practicing.
And so he remedied that with this.
And this.
Take that “Compassion”!
The Uighurs are a Turkic ethnic minority
who live mostly in China’s far west Xinjiang
region.
There are about 10 million Uighurs,
and they’re mostly Muslim.
Islam is unrelated to Falun Gong spiritually.
But from the Communist Party’s perspective,
it’s the same problem:
There are lots of Uighurs,
and they believe in something other than the
Comminist Party.
So the Party remedied that with this:
Concentration camps.
I bring that up because on March 1, 2020,
the China Tribunal issued a final judgment
about whether the Chinese regime organ harvesting
from these two groups of people: Falun Gong
and Uighurs.
It came after two long years of personal testimony
and pouring through evidence.
And long hearings that practically nobody
watched...
...and statements hardly anyone read about
because Western media like the New York Times
were too busy getting paid by Chinese state-run
media
to run advertisements that look like articles.
Anyway, on March 1,
the China Tribunal issued this 562-page Judgement
that *we* read through so you don’t have
to.
It concluded, among other things,
that “Forced organ harvesting has happened
in multiple places
in the [People’s Republic of China]
and on multiple occasions for a period of
at least 20 years...
AND continues to this day.”
It says the victims are mostly Falun Gong
practitioners.
And that Uighurs are also sometimes victims,
and could be China’s living organ bank for
the future.
That’s the Chinese Communist Party for you.
Always thinking ahead.
It finally makes sense why Chinese authorities
have been collecting DNA from all the residents
of Xinjiang.
I’ll note, by the way,
that the China Tribunal was led by a panel
of 7 experts
from several countries.
It was chaired by Sir Geoffrey Nice.
He’s the attorney who led the prosecution
of the former Serbian dictator Slobodan Milošević
for war crimes back in the 1990s.
And none of the people on the panel
were Falun Gong practitioners or Uighurs.
Nor were any of them YouTube celebrities
who could have told them that nobody wants
to read a 562-page report about mass murder!
So I’ll just give you the highlights of
the mass murder.
Here are some of the reasons the China Tribunal
concluded that the Chinese Communist Party
really is killing people for their organs.
One: There are extraordinarily short waiting
times for organs.
You can literally schedule an organ transplant
in two weeks,
to take place on a certain day.
In America, you might wait months or years
for some guy
to die in a motorcycle crash.
In China, the doctors just kill him for you.
Two: The Communist party routinely tortures
Falun Gong practitioners and Uighurs.
It’s not a big leap from torturing people
to simply killing them.
And if you also sell their organs,
it’s a great way to make money.
Three: China built a massive organ transplant
infrastructure
starting in 2001.
That’s when the number of annual transplants
began to boom.
So they were building new hospitals and training
new transplant doctors...
but China didn’t create its *voluntary*
organ donation system until 2010.
So... that’s super weird.
And even today,
there are very few voluntary organ donors
in China.
And that’s tied to number four:
Chinese authorities don’t execute enough
criminals
to account for the number of transplants.
The data suggests that Chinese hospitals
do between 60,000 and 100,000 organ transplants
per year.
But China only carries out fewer than
4,000 court-ordered death sentences each year.
So: There aren’t enough criminals to execute,
and China’s voluntary organ system only
started nine years
after the transplant boom,
and is still really small.
That leads to only one conclusion:
Chinese hospitals have been killing
tens of thousands of additional people every
year
who aren’t criminals OR voluntary donors.
The China Tribunal did, by the way,
invite the Chinese government to join in
and present their own testimony.
The Chinese government did not respond
at any point during the two years.
But one of the interesting things about having
a formal,
open process like the China Tribunal is that
it’s a forum
for people to submit testimony,
who otherwise might not have their voices
heard.
One person who submitted testimony was Didi
Kirsten Tatlow—
a former New York Times reporter.
Tatlow had tried to do a series of investigations
into China’s forced organ harvesting—
but her editors shut her down.
As a New York Times reporter in 2016,
she was invited to an event held at Beijing
Hospital,
where state health officials talked about
China’s organ donation program.
Over lunch, she overheard a conversation
between two Chinese transplant doctors,
which suggested they were being told they
could no longer use prisoners of conscience
for organ harvesting.
But when she told her editors she wanted to
investigate further,
and do a series of stories about Chinese hospitals
using prisoners of conscience for organ translpants,
it became clear to her that
“the issue was unwelcome” at the New York
Times.
Now on top of the conclusions from the China
Tribunal,
there’s this very long, very detailed,
and frankly kind of boring report published
last November
in a fancy peer-reviewed medical journal.
It says “a variety of evidence points to
what the authors believe
can only be plausibly explained by systematic
falsification
and manipulation of official organ transplant
datasets in China.”
And that “[This] is often incentivized by
large cash payments.”
And you wonder why forced organ harvesting
isn’t getting much media attention.
All the smart people who research this stuff
make it sound super complicated.
So let me put it simply—
because this video is not made for just graduate
school students:
The Chinese Communist Party is lying about
the data.
They’re killing people for their organs.
And they’re making lots of money.
And if you think,
“Maybe this stuff happened before,
but it couldn’t possibly still be happening,”
consider this:
even amid the deadly coronavirus outbreak,
Chinese hospitals are still doing suspicious
organ transplants.
“The CCP ask for applause for its double
lung transplant on a coronavirus victim.
But the fact that two matching lungs were
found in a few days
raises new suspicions of organ harvesting.”
So at this point, there’s really no other
conclusion you can make.
Unless you’re the New York Times,
and just quash the reporting.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And now I’ll answer a question from one
of our Patreon supporters
who contributes so we can keep making episodes
like this.
Mike Murphy asks:
“President Trump issued an edict that all
Covid-19 information
be channeled through Mike Pence.
Mr Pence advocates prayer power as one defense
tactic.
Will you consider creating a YouTube channel
called USA Uncensored?”
Thanks for your question, Mike!
Because it allows me to plug my other TV show,
America Uncovered.
Yes, every week I do another entire show,
just like China Uncensored,
but about topics related to America.
And last Thursday,
I published an episode that should answer
your question.
It’s called “Coronavirus:
Did Trump Make the US Less Safe?”
So watch that episode,
and tell me what you think.
Thanks Mike.
And thank you to everyone watching.
Be like Mike and support China Uncensored
by contributing through our Patreon website.
That’s patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
Our awesome supporters like Mike help us
keep making episodes like this.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.