Human-Animal Hybrids at the Wuhan Institute
of Virology
Hong Kong is a delightful police state
And the Chinese Communist Party Celebrates
its 100th birthday
That and more on this week’s China news
headlines
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
Well we have a doozy of a story for you today.
So by now you know how the US was partly funding
gain of function research at the Wuhan Institute
of Virology, where many suspect the coronavirus
pandemic leaked from.
Just a reminder, gain of function research
is where you make a virus more deadly or contagious
to humans.
Supposedly this research is done to prevent
pandemics.
Not working so well, is it?
But anyway you might be wondering, how did
researchers at the Wuhan Institute of Virology
take bat coronaviruses, and make them contagious
to humans?
Well, their answer was human-animal chimeras!
That’s an...artistic depiction.
A human-animal chimera is what you get when
scientists inject an animal with human cells,
or engineer them with human DNA, so the animal
has certain human characteristics.
For example, a lot of research is done on
humanized mice.
No Seamus, you know what I meant.
Humanized lab mice.
Thank you.
Scientists like to test things on these humanized
animals before giving a drug or vaccine to
actual humans.
In some cases, the humanized animals are actually
used to create biological drugs, like certain
cancer drugs.
That itself isn’t news.
Scientists began creating humanized animals
way back in the 1980s.
Presumably after a little inspiration.
And at the Wuhan Institute of Virology, the
famous bat woman Dr. Shi Zhengli , had been
working with humanized animals for more than
a decade.
Here’s a paper from 2008,
talking about using chimeras for coronavirus
research.
What is news is that we’ve learned researchers
at the Wuhan Institute of Virology were specifically
infecting humanized mice with bat coronaviruses
in early 2019...
and they were trying to see if they could
get the bat coronaviruses to infect human
tissue.
I wonder if they were successful?
But of course we may never know for sure,
because the Chinese Communist Party is preventing
any investigation into the Wuhan Institute
of Virology, and they destroyed a lot of the
lab’s research last year.
So we have no idea if their research was connected
to the coronavirus that became a global pandemic.
But at this point, the more I listen to “the
science” the more terrified I become!
This is how we get Planet of the Mice!
But with that out of the way, this week on
July 1, the world wished the Chinese Communist
Party a happy 100th birthday.
And there’s a lot to celebrate.
Not only has the Chinese regime killed way
more people than any other regime in history,
but it’s also actively made the world a
worse place.
Global pandemics are just the tip of the iceberg.
As US Representative Mike Gallaghersaid on
Twitter, “The atrocities we're seeing in
Xinjiang, Hong Kong, and Tibet today are not
a new development.
From the very start, brutalizing its own population
was hard-wired into the CCP's core DNA.”
Which is why he led a bipartisan resolution
in the House of Representatives to send the
CCP a birthday card, condemning China’s
gross violations of human rights.
And considering the Chinese Communist Party
is literally harvesting the organs of prisoners
of conscience, when I say gross human rights
violations, it covers all meanings of the
word gross.
But July 1st has an even more special meaning
to the people of Hong Kong.
Not only is it the 100th birthday party for
the CCP, it’s also the 24th anniversary
of when China took control of Hong Kong in
1997.
And the one-year anniversary of the national
security law that took away Hong Kong’s
freedoms.
Now you might have heard the national security
law resulted in a mass exodus of Hong Kongers
from the city.
I’m happy to say that’s coming to an end.
Because in April authorities passed a law
that could be used to stop people from leaving
the city.
Why would they want to leave?
Hong Kong is becoming a delightful police
state.
Which is what a senior journalist for the
now defunct pro-democracy newspaper Apple
Daily found out when he was arrested at the
airport this week.
As pro-Beijing lawmaker Alice Mak said, “If
it’s a police state, why not?
I don’t think there’s any problem with
a police state.
When we say a police state, I will view the
other side, that is the emphasis on security.”
Let’s just hope Alice Mak doesn’t have
a secret world like Alex Mack or else she’ll
be in big trouble.
But to help in the transition to becoming
a police state, Hong Kong’s security chief,
John Lee has been promoted to the number 2
official.
There’s certainly a lot to celebrate.
But please don’t, because Hong Kong police
have refused to allow a rally marking the
handover.
And it’s not just Hong Kong winning at human
rights.
China overall has the best human rights in
the world!
I’ll show you how after the break.
Welcome back.
To mark the 100 year anniversary of the Communist
Party, the Communist Party released a white
paper about how great human rights are in
China.
“For a hundred years, the CPC has always
put people first, applying the principle of
universality of human rights in the context
of the national conditions.”
Yeah, human rights aren’t universal.
Each country decides for itself what human
rights mean.
The West shouldn’t force its values on China.
The Uyghurs are very happy living in their
police state paradise.
So stop talking about them.
How does China define human rights?
China’s white paprs says “It regards the
rights to subsistence and development as the
primary and basic human rights, and believes
that living a life of contentment is the ultimate
human right.”
Like how the Great Leap forward resulted in
so much food production, people had *too much*
to eat, and then had to fast to lose weight.
Unfortunately, 45 million people accidentally
ended up fasting to death.
We just did an episode about the Great Leap
Forward, so check it out if you’d like to
learn more.
Good news!
The CCP is bringing its version of human rights
to the rest of the world.
According to rights group Safeguard Defenders
, the UN is helping China expand its global
policing.
Are you saying we can all benefit from the
wonderful kind of police state they have in
Hong Kong?
The United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime,
essentially the UN’s anti corruption body,
has “signed a cooperation agreement with
China’s National Supervision Commission
– its massive extra-judicial policing force
- and is refusing to release the secret content
of this agreement.”
And everyone loves a secret, so how could
that be a bad thing?
Now don’t get crazy.
China’s National Supervision Commission
is only targeting a small minority of the
world’s population.
Only about 300 million people.
It exists outside of any country’s judicial
system, so it’s basically a way to make
people disappear.
You know, like a magic trick.
Everyone loves magic tricks.
Especially University students.
Especially Chinese university students studying
in Australia.
That’s why the Party is keeping a close
eye on them.
So they, or their family back home in China,
can also disappear at any time.
That’s according to a new report by Human
Rights Watch.
Despite studying thousands of kilometers away
from China, many Chinese and Hong Kong students
in Australia are harassed and intimidated
into censoring their speech and actions.
'I have to censor myself.
I come to study in Australia and still I'm
not free.'
'There were attempts to dox me, and someone
leaked the name of the building I was living
in.'
'If you protest against the Chinese Communist
Party abroad they will find people you love
to make you pay.'"
Yes, the Chinese Communist Party has a special
kind of magic.
That magic also includes manipulating American
businesses into serving Beijing's interests.
More after the break.
Welcome back.
According to an upcoming report from the the
House Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence,
“U.S. businesses are receiving guidance
and direction from Chinese officials to influence
business operations, investment strategy,
and strategic directions.”
I don’t know, sounds a bit far-fetched to
me.
In unrelated news, Nike’s CEO says 'Nike
is a brand that is of China and for China.'
Must be all that forced ethnic slave labor.
Nike is a brand *of* China’s forced labor,
and *for* China’s authorities.
Nike: Believe in something, even if it means
sacrificing everything.
Of course since the Nike CEO says Nike is
a brand that is of China and for China, I
guess that means it’s not the brand of America.
Sss we should probably all stop buying it.
But if the Chinese Communist Party has its
way, Nike won’t be the only company continuously
kowtowing to the Chinese regime.
Every company, and government really should
as well, if they know what’s good for them.
That was one message from Xi Jinping’s speech
celebrating the Party’s anniversary.
That was after a week of celebrations that
included a very normal art performance
That did not look anything like a dystopian
Apple ad.
Or North Korea on steroids.
In his speech at Tiananmen Square, Xi Jinping
said that “We will never allow any foreign
force to bully, oppress, or subjugate us.
Anyone who would attempt to do so will find
themselves on a collision course with a great
wall of steel forged by over 1.4 billion Chinese
people.”
That’s at least according to the official
translation.
But as others pointed out, the original Chinese
is a bit bloodier than that.
The term Xi used literally means people would
have their “head broken and blood flowing”--
which sounds a little more violent.
So a better translation might be that people
who try to cross the Chinese Communist Party
will have their skulls crushed against a great
wall of steel.
Now that’s going back to the Party’s bloody
roots.
So with that, let’s all wish the Chinese
Communist Party a sweet goodnight on its 100th
birthday party.
It will be easy to sleep in the quiet, dark
night—since China is facing its worst power
shortage in a decade.
I mean, as long as all the threats of crushing
your skull don’t keep you awake.
And now it’s time to answer a question from
a member of the China Uncensored 50 Cent Army,
fans who support us and our efforts to expose
the truth about the Chinese Communist Party,
by contributing through crowd funding website
Patreon.
Mark Hewitson asks, “Do you think CCP is
making bitcoin crash so THEY can buy them
all up at a cheaper rate?
That’s an excellent question.
China recently shut down over 90% of its Bitcoin
mining.
And that’s just the latest in a series of
restrictions aimed at curbing crypto in China.
The result was a huge drop in the value of
Bitcoin, as well as other cryptocurrencies.
A big reason the Communist Party is doing
this is to promote its own digital currency.
But I really wouldn’t be surprised if many
top Party officials are using the crash in
Bitcoin prices to buy it up.
Even if your average Chinese person is forbidden
from buying Bitcoin, top Party officials love
to do things like that to increase their wealth,
and especially transfer their ill gotten fortunes
into a form that can’t easily be taken by
the Party.
After all, just because we’re communists,
doesn’t mean we can’t make a little money,
right?
Thanks for your question and your support,
Mark.
And a big thank you to everyone who supports
China Uncensored on Patreon.
We could not do this show without you.
So thank you for joining us in the fight to
expose the Chinese Communist Party to the
world.
If you’re interested in joining, head over
to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
You’ll get a bunch of cool perks, including
the chance to have me answer your question
on the show!
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next
time.