Taiwan is under constant threat from China.
Not just the military
But also infiltration in its democracy.
How is Taiwan resisting?
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Taiwan is on the front lines of a battle
with the Chinese Communist Party.
And few people understand that like DPP Legislator
Wang Ting-Yu.
He’s Chairman of the legislature’s
Foreign Affairs and National Defense Committee.
I sat down with him in Tainan
to discuss the tactics the Communist Party
is using to destroy democracy,
and how Taiwan can save the Indo-Pacific region
from a dangerous authoritarian state.
Well, thank you for joining me today.
Yes, thank you for your time.
Yeah, you bet.
So how is the Chinese Communist Party trying
to infiltrate Taiwan?
They try to do this for decades.
More than 40 years.
And [inaudible] the technology development
they have new way
to do the old tricks.
For example, in Taiwan, they have three basic
tactics
to penetrate Taiwan society.
First using their economic power to seduce,
to lure Taiwanese businessmen,
become their investment and then using all
these economic condition
to tie the Taiwanese businessmen, making them
follow,
cherish the relationship with the communist.
You need a relationship to do your business
in China.
Then you need to be a good friend.
You need to show your good will, step-by-step.
Then they can use,
inaudible] using the businessmen to influence
policy making.
Second way, they are using some we call psychological
warfare.
They are using their air force, navy, go around
Taiwan Island.
It's not only try to shaking Taiwanese will,
try to show their muscle to block those help
from United States
in Guam Island or Okinawa and our neighborhood
country
and to try to tell Taiwan,
"Listen to us.
You can have the relationship to do business
to make money.
If you don't listen to us, listen to Chinese
communist,
you will face the missiles, you will face
the crisis,
all the possibilities to create a tiny war
that
will destroy your stock market, will influence
your life."
And the third away, is ongoing now and I'm
afraid maybe
they are doing this in all the democratic
country around the world.
They try to use in some they call education,
that using some literature, cultural engagement.
Try to ask Taiwanese primary school, the deans,
the principals,
the students, come to China.
The only thing you need is just buy the ticket.
Everything they will take care of that.
It's interesting that some of these tactics
you're talking about,
because with some differences it does sound
very similar to things
the Chinese Communist Party is doing in the
United States as well.
They're doing that too.
For example, if your Capitol Hill try to pass
a law favor Taiwan,
maybe their ambassador will protest it himself,
but they will try to ask for some big company
in the United States,
try to influence your lawmakers, they're doing
that.
Sometimes they will buy advertisement in cable
TV,
try to create some kind of voice to interfere
democracy function,
because Chinese communist they know one thing.
In North Korea or China, this kind of country,
the head is the most important,
the leader, that one, dictator, Xi Jinping,
Kim Jong-Un.
They are the most important.
They are everything.
But in our country as a democracy country,
election by people, we create the power to
[inaudible],
to steal, to control this country.
So if you can influence the rule of the game
of election,
you will control democracy country.
So they tried, they know that.
So they tried using money to contribute,
donate some money to some certain guy,
tried to beat democracy by democracy way.
And I'm happy to observe these two years,
the United States,
Trump administration, Taiwan, Japan, Australia,
Canada,
they all notice this situation is quite serious.
We have a lot of plan and program.
We cooperate together since maybe two years
ago.
Well, it seems to me that if the rest of the
world
wants to understand what the Chinese Communist
Party is doing
in their own countries,
they really need to look at Taiwan.
Yeah.
Taiwan, we are in the front line.
The cyber attack, through internet attack
our government,
attack our traffic control system, attack
our civil system.
Every month more than 45 million times.
Cyber attacked every month 45 million times.
That's insane.
And the content, disinformation attack,
each day almost 1 million.
Each day?
Each day, almost 1 million spread in [inaudible].
They are using VPN,
maybe send fake news or disinformation from
China,
but they will jump to Mexico,
then Mexico to Taiwan,
something like that.
And that amount create chaos,
especially during election.
They were manufacturing some half real, half
fake,
then totally fake, and through these [inaudible]
from [inaudible],
the inside of our country has [inaudible],
we call [inaudible] system.
We catch that, share that spread.
Then some TV station, mass media, they are
their allies, partners.
Using that kind of rumors, gossips, fake news,
become a true news,
broadcasting to TV then people will believe
in it.
Well, I know the Democratic Progressive Party
recently passed the anti-infiltration act.
What is that bill about?
We call it national security lawmaking process.
We have two major part.
The first major part is focused at spying
or military
or some similar warfare.
So we fix our crime law.
We made China, to become Chinese spy,
we put them on our crime law, is life sentence
to death penalty.
We increase the penalty.
And we fixed our national security law.
If you are helping Chinese communist
to develop their organization in Taiwan,
then before maybe only under two years,
now it's more than seven years to life sentence.
So, that law is especially focus at the spy
sabotage.
And then the second part is one we just passed.
This is, we call Democracy Protecting Law.
In a democratic, in a democracy society,
we encourage people to vote, to become a candidate,
to donate to a candidate you favor, to speak.
You can have a parade.
You can have a demonstration on a street.
You can lobby, you can lobby for the law you
want.
You can sending out or receive all different
kinds of informations.
All this behavior is democracy itself.
We encourage them to do that.
But, if this normal democracy behavior got
polluted by your enemy,
do we need to forbid that?
In Taiwan we have law to regulate political
party,
military, and the government cannot own media.
You cannot own media.
Media must be owned by people,
cannot be political party, military or government.
We have struggled decades to establish this
law,
for about 10 years ago.
So if Taiwanese military, Taiwanese government,
Taiwanese party cannot own media,
can we allow our media owned by Chinese Communist
Party?
PLA?
Certainly not.
So we just passed a law.
We just regulate that behavior.
If you receive Chinese communist money, order,
authorization,
to donate to certain party or candidate
using their illegal money to interfere our
normal democratic behavior,
then you violate the law.
So that's sort of how the Chinese Communist
Party
uses democracy to undermine democracy.
Yes.
We have observed this.
We try to establish a law system
but we don't want to choke the democracy itself
because the freedom and democracy is what
we are proud of.
That was Taiwan's [inaudible.]
So we can not have a law, otherwise we will
just become a North Korea.
That will be easier.
But we don't like that.
So we have a lot of debating,
arguing and using a lot of time.
Then we regulate five behavior.
This five behavior also authorized or sponsored
by Chinese communist,
by our foreign enemies, then you break law.
We have an example.
To drink alcohol it didn't break a law.
To drive a car, you don't break a law.
But if you drink alcohol and then drive a
car,
you break a law.
Something like this.
So if you are doing business with Chinese
communist,
even you get money from Chinese government.
Yeah, you didn't violate any law.
You become a [inaudible] candidate,
you donate money to some party or candidate,
you lobby for your law, your favorite,
you want to send in some information, and
it's okay.
But if you got ordered and get money then
to become a candidate
or to sponsor or to sabotage some demonstration,
parade or to spread some fake news, then you
break this law.
And according our [inaudible],
the majority of Taiwanese people support to
establish this
[inaudible] because they all worry about this.
Well I know there's been some pushback to
the anti-infiltration act f
rom Taiwan's other dominant political party,
the KMT.
Why is that?
KMT they are in...
To this law, they are in awkward position.
Voters, they say they want this law
because they know Taiwan need this.
Beijing doesn't.
Of course they don't want this law.
Obviously.
And KMT, Kuomintang,
they are China friendly party
and they have strong relationship and the
connection with China.
So they are in some awkward condition.
They want to win the election, they need votes,
but if they don't follow
or don't cooperate with their friends in Beijing,
maybe something bad will happen
because they have too many things in Communist
hands.
So as I recall that day we try to pass it
alone.
KMT, their legislator come inside to [inaudible],
sit on the ground, yell some slogan,
then put a mask on and keep silence for five
hours.
Then the law passed.
They didn't resist,
they didn't try to stop the lawmaking process,
but they are showing their attitude that they
don't like this law.
But they know if they using physical conflict
to stop the law,
they will lose the trust of voters.
So democracy.
Democracy win.
Yeah.
So as chairman of the foreign affairs and
national defense committee,
what are some other national defense issues
you think the Taiwan government should be
concerned about?
This is a big question because we have a lot
of thing need to catch up with.
In Indo-Pacific or Oriental Asia, there are
four potential crisis.
These four potential crises,
if something bad happened will kill the economy
globally.
North Korea, East China Sea, Taiwan Strait,
and the South China Sea.
These four potential crises,
not only influence the regional politics
but also influence the global economy,
and Taiwan plays important role in three of
these four.
So we have a lot of discussion with the United
States.
I always told my friend in Capitol Hill, I
say,
"Once Taiwan secured then the Pacific will
be secured.
Once Taiwan stabilized, this region will be
stabilized."
So how to stabilize it.
We Taiwanese, we know this country is my home.
The only one has a responsibility to protect
Taiwan is ourself.
We cannot rely on Americans or the other friends.
Friends can help, but we need to depend on
ourselves.
And what we need, we don't have enough high
technology weapon.
Since 2013 PLA, Chinese People's Liberation...
Army.
They have modernized their equipment.
They put a lot of money in their air force
power and the naval power.
They want to be a world superpower.
We want to defend our home.
It's different kind of strategy consideration.
We don't need to build Taiwan so big to against
China.
We just need enough power to protect Taiwan
and to fulfill our responsibility in East
China Sea, Taiwan Strait,
and the South China Sea.
We own the largest Island in South China Sea.
We have, I cannot give you detailed figures,
we have hundreds of our young men and woman
posted in South China Sea.
So we need underwater equipment like submarine
and we are building it on our own.
And I do believe we, from now on, within three
years,
we will have the first made by Taiwan, most
modernized submarine.
I believe so.
And since our friends help we are going to
have the first M1A2T,
the battle tank.
What my army using...
The tank we are using now, is 40 years ago.
World War II.
And after 20 years we've eventually we got
the F-16 V,
so this is [inaudible], and the past three
years
we have new regulation and a new pension system.
We increase the military,
those young men and women, we increase their
payment.
We increase their retired pension,
so try to stabilize our military.
So this is insights to strengthen our own
power and using Taiwanese
we have some strengths under control.
We built a lot made in Taiwan weapon system
to protect our seashore,
something like that.
But for DPP, in the future, for the coming
four years,
what we need or actually what this region
need,
because if you believe Taiwan stabilized,
then you can stabilize this region,
what our need is, we need more opportunity
to cooperate with our international friends.
Well, so what would you like to see happen
as far as US-Taiwan relations?
Maybe invite Taiwan to join RIMPAC.
You know RIMPAC is a military exercise.
Nothing big deal, but in Asia, Taiwan and
North Korea
are the only two countries never got invited.
Taiwan and North Korea.
Those two countries usually aren't mentioned
in the same sentence.
But now United States, they cancel the invitation
to China last time.
So I hope this year,
every two years they have a RIMPAC military
exercise.
I hope we can got invite.
It's kind of simple.
It's also real.
It means we are partners.
We are in the system.
Once the system strong enough, the conflict
will not happen,
or will happen only in [inaudible] situation.
All the power they got even, unless situation,
the crisis, only crisis that wont happen.
Some serious conflict.
So for the 2020 I do believe we will have
more opportunity
to have some special occasion.
Our young military, young men, young ladies,
can have the opportunity to train with United
States armies.
And maybe according to the United States,
MDAA or Taiwan Travel Act, yeah,
you can send some kind of a ship, come to
Taiwan,
mercy medical ship, not battleship.
Try to using this kind of hint to tell someone,
"Don't do something stupid.
You cannot afford it."
So if we keep sending this message,
"Don't do something stupid, you cannot afford
it."
Now that will be very good strategy to stabilize
Indo-Pacific,
make this place become a democracy
and a friend and allies and that the economy
can be keep prosperous.
So what the signal we need, you need to not
bilateral discuss,
and we are working on that,
hoping it's going to happen in this year.
Thank you for joining me today.
Yeah, it's [inaudible].
Thank you.