Could Chinese soldiers…
be about to get a major headache?
And the US lifts Taiwan travel restrictions.
That and more on this week’s China news
headlines.
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
Before I begin, did you know YouTube has been
secretly unsubscribing people and demonetizing
a lot of our videos?
You can help the show by hitting the like
button and sharing this episode.
If you’re not seeing notifications for our
episodes, we publish new ones every Monday,
Wednesday, Friday, and sometimes Saturday.
So check back often.
Life’s hard for a Chinese soldier.
Most of the time, you’re not actually doing
any real training.
You’re studying Communist Party ideology—singing
propaganda songs, performing propaganda skits,
and going through ideological “reflection
sessions.”\h
And when it comes to actual training—I’m
not entirely sure what playing hot potato
with a live grenade is supposed to accomplish.
Other than make for highly trained soldiers.
I’m sure Taiwan is terrified.
So given the state of the PLA, when you see
reports that China has developed a helmet
with a self-destruct system, one that could
be controlled remotely to blow up the soldier
if they fall into enemy hands, it might seem
easy to believe.
But as far as we can tell, that story is not
true.\h
Here’s where the story came from.
On December 27, Chinese state-run media China
Observer, published a report about Chinese
troops in Tibet being equipped with a new
individual digital combat system.\h
Then a website called 123 Military Observation
Room, which seems to be some kind of military
news blog, picked up the story.
In their headline, they claimed that the system
could self-destruct if captured by the Indian
army.
They also said that “heavily injured soldiers,
who do not want to be taken captive, can activate
the mechanism to defend his or her dignity
as a member of the military, while preventing
the enemy from obtaining information about
the system.”
So that makes it sound like the “self-destruct”
wouldn't just destroy the combat system, but
it would also “self-destruct” the soldier.
And the article also claimed that the self-destruct
could be activated remotely by the command
center if they lost contact with a soldier.
\h
As you can imagine, this story that seemed
to claim that PLA commanders could remotely
self-destruct soldiers, caused an...explosive...reaction
online.
Netizens were incredibly angry.
The reaction was so explosive that the article
ended up self-destructing.
It’s been pretty much censored from the
Chinese internet.\h\h
But where did this article get their information?
They said it was from the PLA’s website,
but we couldn’t find anything like that
on there.
So it’s likely either exaggerated or completely
made up.
Fake news with Chinese characteristics.
The problem is, that article started being
picked up by overseas Chinese news websites,
and then translated into English, and so now
you may have seen claims that Chinese soldiers
have helmets that can blow them up.
Again, as far as we can tell, that’s not
true.\h\h
I’m sure that’s a relief for all of the
PLA soldiers currently playing grenade hot
potato.
The State Department has radically changed
the US Taiwan relationship.
Secretary of State Mike Pompeo said in this
statement, “Taiwan is a vibrant democracy
and reliable partner of the United States,
and yet for several decades the State Department
has created complex internal restrictions
to regulate our diplomats, servicemembers,
and other officials’ interactions with their
Taiwanese counterparts.
The United States government took these actions
unilaterally, in an attempt to appease the
Communist regime in Beijing.
No more.”
The Chinese Communist Party is furious.
My favorite state-run media, the Global Times,
suggested Pomepo may “toll the knell”
for Taiwanese officials.
Weird expression.\h
Anyway, the editorial says that “Those who
infringe China on core interests will be doomed.”
Ok, that’s pretty clear.
And it does certainly raise some questions
for the coming Biden Administration.
Going back on America’s current support
for Taiwan would look like Biden is abandoning
a democratic ally to get in good with a communist
authoritarian regime—confirming the fears
a lot of people have about so-called “Beijing
Biden.”
So will Biden continue with the Trump Administration’s
tough-on-China polices?\h
Pompeo is definitely trying to force Biden’s
hand.
The U.S. Ambassador to the United Nations
Kelly Craft was supposed to make a trip to
Taiwan this week.\h
But Pompeo said all travel was cancelled because
of “transition efforts with President-elect
Biden’s team”.
So Pompeo is definitely trying to lay it all
on Biden.
But it's not just Pompeo standing up to the
Chinese Communist Party.
Australia has rejected a multi million dollar
Chinese buyout of an Australian builder because
of security concerns.
The Chinese Company, state-owned China State
Construction Engineering Corporation wanted
to buy a controlling share of the Australian
builder ProBuild.
Blocking the buyout may be a wise move.
Because over in the US, the Defense Department
has blacklisted China State Construction Engineering
Corporation—since it has links to the People’s
Liberation Army, which is the military arm
of the Chinese Communist Party.
I know, a Chinese state-run company with links
to the Chinese military?
You’re shocked.\h
Speaking of explosive news, guess which American
has been exposed as a lobbyist for a Chinese
surveillance company?
The answer, after the break.
Welcome back.
You may remember former US Senator from California
Barbara Boxer.\h
After retiring from government, Boxer joined
a Washington DC based lobbying firm.
And one of that firm’s clients is Hikvision.
If that name rings a bell it’s because in
2019, the US unfairly blacklisted Hikvision,
simply because it helped the glorious Chinese
Communist Party do mass surveillance—I mean,
security—for the Uyghur people.
Geez, what’s wrong with a little facial
recognition to stop crime before it happens?
Anyway, in the great American tradition of
former politicians becoming lobbyists, Baraba
Boxer joined this lobbying firm.
And to represent their client Hikvision, she
had to register as a foreign agent.
When that was exposed in the press this week,
it raised a lot of eyebrows.
And then Joe Biden’s inaugural committee
returned the $500 donation Boxer had made
to his campaign.
For Joe Biden, it’s just not worth being
caught up in a scandal involving a Chinese
state-controlled company.\h
At least not for just $500.
And speaking of the persecution of Uyghurs,
the UK has taken steps to remove Ugyhur forced
labor from British supply chains, accusing
China of torture and barbarism.
And so has the US.
The Trump administration has now banned the
import of all cotton and tomatoes from Xinjiang.
America’s pro-Beijing tomato lobby is outraged.
“Independent researchers and media reports
have linked dozens of the world’s most prominent
multinational companies to workers or products
from Xinjiang, including Apple, Nike, Kraft,
Heinz, and Campbell Soup.”
And don’t try claiming that your Xinjiang
tomatoes are actually Beijing tomatoes.
This ban includes products that have been
shipped to another region or country to disguise
the fact that they’ve actually come from
Xinjiang.\h
But how will the US government know where
the products are originally from?
Pollen analysis.\h
And more good news, human rights lawyer David
Mattis has won the Global Humanitarian Leader
of the Year Award for his work exposing organ
harvesting of prisoners of conscience in China.
I mean, who else was going to do it?
Obviously not the New York Times.
Mattis’s award comes from the human rights
group Canadians in Support of Refugees in
Dire Need.
And no, they aren’t talking about Americans
seeking refuge in Canada.
And if you thought it was bad last year when
China locked down 11 million people in Wuhan
because of the coronavirus—now it’s twice
as bad.
More on that after the break.
Welcome back.
The coronavirus is getting worse in China.
22 million people have been put on lockdown.\h
“More than 22 million people in all have
been ordered to remain inside their homes—double
the number affected last January when China’s
central government locked down Wuhan.”
Huh, that’s the opposite of the message
last week in the New York Times, about how
China handled the coronavirus so well that
people there have more freedom than people
in the West.\h
Yes, Chinese people have the freedom to move
around and lead a normal day-to-day life.
Unless they try to move around and lead a
normal day-to-day life.
Of course the entire world is suffering from
the coronavirus, or as I call it, the CCP
virus, since it spread because of a Communist
Party coverup.\h
But people aren’t just suffering from the
CCP virus itself.
They’re also suffering from CCP Virus tests
and vaccines.
The Chinese vaccine Coronavac is being tested
in Brazil, but its efficacy rate is only just
above 50%.
That’s far lower than the Chinese company
initially claimed.
Compare that to the two main vaccines made
by US companies.
Those have an efficacy rate of 95%.
Meanwhile, two US Federal agencies have learned
nothing from the past year.
Because they’ve been pushing Chinese Covid-19
tests—despite warnings that it’s a security
risk.
How could a coronavirus test be a security
risk?
Well, it was created by BGI, China’s leading
genetics company.
And there are concerns that the tests could
give Americans’ DNA data to a Chinese company.
Some of the genetic data from BGIs gene sequencing
machines gets stored on Huawei equipment.
Yeah.
And get this—“The U.S. Commerce Department
sanctioned two of BGI’s subsidiaries earlier
this year, saying they provided technology
to collect and catalog the DNA profiles of
China’s persecuted Uighur population.”
So kind of a problem, huh?
Well, nevertheless, BGI “enlisted a foundation
tied to a former U.S. president—George H.W.
Bush—and used a company linked to the United
Arab Emirates’ top spy to promote its efforts.
A prominent New York real-estate lawyer threatened
to complain to California’s governor if
state health officials there didn’t use
BGI’s tests.”
Am I only the person who isn’t corrupt?!\h
Clearly, I need to sell out.
Last week, I told you about how the Chinese
Communist Party is continuing to block a World
Health Organization investigation into the
origin of the coronavirus in Wuhan.
And Canadian Prime Minister Justin Trudeau
is criticizing that.
Here he is on Canada’s City News.
“There’s certainly going to be a time
for necessary accountability and understanding
exactly how the world ended up plunged into
this terrible, terrible situation and the
role China had to play in this as the origin
of the virus is going to need to be known.
For China to not cooperate and not participate
in that is unfortunately very predictable,
given the recent stances by the Chinese government
on collaborating with international authorities,
but [it’s] not going to be able to protect
them from making sure that the truth does
come out.”
Wow.
Now hearing that from Trudeau, was very shocking
for me.
Until I realized the truth: This Trudeau is
not the same as this Trudeau.
The one with the beard is from a mirror universe!
Simple Star Trek logic!
Wait a minute, does this mean we’re in the
evil universe?
Oh yeah, that actually makes total sense.
Which brings me to Uncle Roger, aka comedian
Nigel Ng.
You might know him as the fried rice guy.
Anyway, he has apologized and deleted a video
featuring a YouTube star who in the past has
criticized the Chinese Communist Party.
Apparently Uncle Roger’s video got flagged
in China—or possibly he got pressure from
Chinese sponsors or business partners.
So he took it offline and made an NBA-style
apology, saying “I wasn’t aware of his
political thoughts and his past incorrect
remarks about China.
This is my negligence.”
That YouTuber with dangerous thinking is Mike
Chen from Strictly Dumpling.
What were Chen’s past incorrect remarks
about China?
Well, he’s made a few.
For instance, this post from June on Instagram
of Tank Man says “Today, on the 31st anniversary
of Chinese troops opening fire on protesters
in and around Tiananmen Square.
The people of HK are facing a similar standoff
over freedom, democracy and basic human rights.”
What an incorrect remark about China!\h
Now at no point in the joint video with Uncle
Roger did Chen talk about any of these political
topics.
The problem is that in the past, in totally
unrelated posts, Chen had expressed concern
over Chinese Communist Party’s human rights
abuses.
And this just goes to show how deep the CCP’s
censorship reaches overseas.
Uncle Roger doesn’t live in China.
He’s not political.
He didn’t ask Mike Chen any political questions.
But simply because Chen is a person who has
political views that support freedom for the
Chinese people, Uncle Roger felt pressure
to self-censor.
Now, Uncle Roger is hardly alone.
This is something that multinational corporations
do all the time, like we’ve constantly been
talking about on this show.
But it feels more personal when it’s someone
you liked doing it.
Hong Kong pro-democracy activist Agnes Chow
even dressed up as Uncle Roger for Halloween
last year—where she did a video review of
Hong Kong police.
So this latest self-censorship from Uncle
Roger has got to hurt.
On the bright side, Agnes Chow probably doesn’t
know about what Uncle Roger did... because
Hong Kong police put her in prison.
That’s not a joke.
Anyway, I for one can’t wait for Uncle Rogers’
next video on how to eat boot fried rice.
If you add enough MSG, you can barely even
taste the boot you’re licking.
And speaking of censorship, YouTube has been
demonetizing a lot of China Uncensored videos.
I know this is technically not censorship—but
it has a similar effect: It discourages us
from making content that criticizes the Chinese
Communist Party.
But we refuse to self-censor.
And we can afford to only because of direct
support from viewers like you—members of
the China Uncensored 50-Cent Army who support
us through Patreon.
And as a thank you to them, I answer their
questions on the show.
Today’s question comes from...
Drew McTygue: “Will the CCP attempt to seize
control of the moon?”
Oh Drew, you’re thinking too small.
I mean, yeah, the CCP is talking about building
a moon base.
And just to be clear, China’s space program
is run by the military.
But who cares about the Moon?
The CCP has much bigger space plans.
Like a space station.
Since NASA isn’t allowed to work with China.
But China’s real prize is Mars.
After all, Mars is the red planet.
Thanks for your question Drew.
And thank you for watching.
Be like Drew and support China Uncensored
on Patreon at patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
Remember to like, subscribe, and share this
episode.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.