On this episode of China Uncensored,
North Korea is messing around again.
And China is sending over the troops.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
If you haven’t heard, one of these Koreas
has a crazy cult running the show.
Uh, okay, I guess it’s both Koreas.
But unlike South Korea,
those in North Korea can’t so easily oust
their leader,
Kim Jong-un.
Not that they would!
They love him!
They’re required to.
The Kim dynasty began when Kim Il-Sung
seized control in 1948.
And ever since,
the Kim family have been seen as gods.
North Korea has no religious holidays.
But make no mistake,
this is a time of worship.
Last week, there was a fantastic celebration
marking the 75th birth anniversary of his son,
Kim Jong-il.
And yeah, the celebration was... ill.
They have really good taste in music.
And of course nothing says celebrating your
father’s birth
like launching a missile.
Here’s the current leader paying his respects.
Aww, he was the good son.
Not at all like his no-good older half brother,
Kim Jong-nam—
the one with crazy ideas
like reform and market-opening.
Kim Jong-nam completely ruined the celebrations
last week
by accidentally getting injected with poison
at a Malaysian airport,
and then dying on his way to the hospital.
I’m kidding of course.
The celebrations weren't ruined.
South Korea on Wednesday,
saying it suspects a pair of female agents
from Pyongyang
were behind the murder of Kim Jong-un’s
half-brother,
and that they used poison to kill him.
Over in China,
the current leadership actually liked Kim
Jong-nam,
especially his ideas about Chinese-style market
reform.
Reforms like those could have made North Korea
less crazy
and also less dependent on China for aid.
That may be why Kim Jong-nam
was under de facto Chinese protection.
Fun fact: So were his wives, plural.
Kim Jong-nam apparently had two separate wives
and families
in different parts of China.
Anyway, rotund North Korean leader Kim Jong-un
didn’t like his older half-brother Kim Jong-nam.
Daddy gives little brother a country for his
birthday,
older brother gets jealous
and says it’s being run badly,
little brother sees him as a threat and assassinates
him.
It’s your classic sibling rivalry.
So the combination of North Korea’s missile
test
and the high-profile assassination
is causing a bit of stress for China’s leaders.
Now, the Chinese military has sent 1,000 additional
troops
to the border with North Korea,
according to the Hong Kong newspaper,
Oriental Daily News.
That’s very worrisome...
I didn’t think you could use the term, Oriental.
What’s that Shelley?
Ah.
I can’t.
Anyway, China-North Korea relations aren’t
going well.
I’ve mentioned before that Chinese leader
Xi Jinping
has been moving China away from decades of
historical closeness
with North Korea.
And this has been a bad week for Xi Jinping.
First, the missile launch.
Basically, if North Korea can launch a missile
into the Sea of Japan,
they’re just as capable of launching one
at Beijing.
Then there’s the loss of face.
China had status as the go between—
the country that still had ties with North
Korea,
but could also help the rest of the world
put pressure on it.
Well, it’s clear now that the Chinese regime
has pretty much no sway
over the North Korean regime.
And then there’s something called THAAD.
It’s a missile defense system
the US wants to build in South Korea.
The Chinese regime doesn’t want the US military
so close by building a missile defense system,
especially one that could also be used
to track Chinese missiles.
But now it’s increasingly clear that China
can’t be relied on
to reign in North Korean missile tests.
So it’s all the more excuse for the US and
South Korea
to go ahead with THAAD.
And so when you’re the leader of China,
and all this happens,
you send troops to the border with North Korea.
This is not a first.
Last year,
a South Korean news service reported
that 2,000 additional troops had been sent
to the border
ahead of a possible 5th nuclear test.
Which happened.
And there was no war.
But just like Kim Jong-un’s belly,
this can’t go on forever.
So what do you think of the deteriorating
relationship
between China and North Korea?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Be sure to share it with your friends and family.
Especially your older half-brother.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.