Is China Becoming More Communist?
Xi Jinping is pushing Marxism
And all levels of Chinese society have to
follow.
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Have you ever looked at yourself
in the mirror and thought,
“Am I really the best Communist I can be?”
Trick question,
the great proletarian revolution
doesn’t need your bourgeois mirrors.
But that is the question Chinese leader
Xi Jinping is asking.
The Chinese Communist Party
is the largest Communist Party in the world,
with 90 million members.
But every now and then you need
a reminder of what got you there.
Of how incredible Communism is.
I mean, 100 million people dead in 100 years,
that’s quite an accomplishment.
But today in China,
people just don't seem to have
the devotion to Marx and Communism
the way they once did.
For example,
97 percent of Chinese companies are privately
owned.
China has a third of the world’s billionaires.
And China’s official state-run trade union
is set up specifically to make sure workers
don’t collectively bargain.
So it looks like China got a little off the
Marx.
That’s why over the past several years,
Xi Jinping has made a push to get everyone
excited about Communism again.
Assuming they were in the first place.
Ok, there were definitely times when people
were a little *too* excited about Communism.
Now, I’m not saying that Xi Jinping
wants another Cultural Revolution.
But it’s hard to be the head of the Communist
Party
when it seems like most people in China
don’t really believe in Communism anymore.
And what better way to get people back on
your side
than with a big top-down state directive!
Xi Jinping has been pushing all levels
of Chinese society to study Marxism.
Or more specifically,
socialism with Chinese characteristics.
In a speech marking the Chinese Communist
Party’s
95th anniversary, Xi Jinping said,
“History tells us the Chinese people’s
choice of
the Communist Party to lead them
toward the civilization’s great rejuvenation
has been correct,
and that the party’s path of socialism
with Chinese characteristics is also correct.”
He also said that
“Marxism must be the basic,
fundamental, guiding principle
or the Party would lose its soul and direction.”
I mean we wouldn’t want
the officially atheist Communist Party
to lose its soul, now would we?
And Xi Jinping is leading by example.
In 2017, a few days after“winning” a second
term
as the General Secretary of the Communist
Party,
Xi and other top Party leaders
headed to Shanghai,
raising their fists to honor the birthplace
of the Chinese Communist Party and its founders.
According to Willy Wo-Lap Lam,
an adjunct professor at the Chinese University
of Hong Kong,
it was “a reinstatement of the commitment
of the party
in this so-called ‘new era of socialism
with Chinese characteristics’
that they would stick to
original values of the founding fathers.
That means definitely no move away
from orthodox Marxism, orthodox Maoism.
No taking up of Western values.”
I mean, other than the fact that Communism
originally came from the West.
A few months later,
Xi Jinping made some major changes to the
constitution.
First, he added his very own
Xi Jinping Thought on Socialism
with Chinese Characteristics for a New Era
to both the Communist Party’s constitution,
and China’s state constitution.
Then, he added to the state constitution that
“The leadership of the Communist Party of
China
is the defining feature of socialism
with Chinese characteristics.”
This new clause officially gives the Communist
Party
direct control over the Chinese government.
Ok, it definitely already had control over
the government.
But now it’s in the constitution,
which makes it legal.
Think of it like,
China has a government system,
but the Chinese Communist Party’s own system
is a parasite that’s latched onto the government
and controls it from above.
Kind of like the Goa’uld from Stargate.
And now that’s written into law.
And since the Constitution also says
“The socialist system is the basic system
of the People’s Republic of China,”
What that really means is that
China is officially a one-party state
led by the Chinese Communist Party,
and anything else is illegal
according to the Constitution.
Glad we got that cleared up.
Xi Jinping is also putting more pressure
on China’s 90 million Communist Party members.
Besides requiring them to be atheists,
“Xi also ordered ‘the broad masses of
party members,
cadres and especially senior cadres to study
well
and apply well [the Communist Manifesto].’”
State-run media has also recently warned them
to stick with Marx and not ghosts and spirits.
“Resolutely prevent not believing in Marx
and Lenin
and believing in ghosts and spirits,
not believing in the truth and believing in
money.”
Wait. I have no idea what I’m supposed to
do.
Am I supposed to believe in money or not?
And does that mean money is a superstition,
like ghosts and spirits?
I’m so confused.
Anyway, it’s not just Party members.
They haven’t forgotten the children either.
“For China’s gen-Xers and millennials,
the Party is in danger of being written off
as just another corrupt old boys’ club.”
Which is why the Party has spared no effort
in trying to make Communism cool again.
Whether it’s a Karl Marx rap.
A Karl Marx talk show
Or a Karl Marx anime!
Yes, absolutely none of these things
are driven by market demand.
Just like Marx would have wanted.
Xi has also been stressing ideological education
in school.
“Xi highlighted the guiding position of
Marxism
in ideological and political classes,
saying China’s education should serve the
people,
the Party’s governance
and the development of socialism
with Chinese characteristics.”
And they start ’em young.
“Starting with toddlers,
Xi said China must ‘nurture generation after
generation
[of young people] who support Chinese Communist
Party rule
and China’s socialist system.’”
So it’s for these reasons you see headlines
like these—
suggesting that China’s thriving liberal
democracy
was somehow subverted by Xi Jinping.
Except—that’s not really what’s going
on.
Most of these changes are superficial.
Xi Jinping is pushing for people to study
Marxism-Leninism.
But it’s not that he actually wants to return
to the days of collective farming and killing
landlords.
Fun times—
but those days are over.
See, there’s a lot more to communism
than redistributing wealth.
The nature of a communist regime
is to control everything in society.
Ever since the Chinese Communist Party
took power in 1949...
...it has controlled every organization;
rewritten history;
manipulated the news;
monitored all levels of society;
stopped people from speaking out;
prevented people from believing in God or
Buddha;
and re-educated or killed people who don’t
agree.
Those things...have not actually changed
since the economic reforms of the late 1970s.
So China is still communist in pretty much
every sense.
What about the economy?
Sure, China no longer has collectivization,
where everyone works and lives on communes.
But the state still owns all the land in China,
state-run enterprises control all the major
industries,
and Chinese officials still intervene in the
economy
all the time.
All of these things mean that the state
pretty much still controls the means of production.
Chinese people are allowed to make money now,
but they can only get rich if their company
does what the Party wants.
And that’s why—
even with all the ideology that Xi Jinping
is pushing—
China is not actually becoming *more* communist.
If anything,
it’s just becoming more *visibly* communist,
especially to those of us outside China.
But even if it’s not making China more communist,
why is Xi Jinping pushing Marxist ideology,
anyway?
Well, there are a few possibilities.
One is that Xi is a true believer in communism.
That when he publishes articles
on dialectical materialism,
he actually means it.
Which, I don’t know.
This guy has the kind of poker face
that got him to the top of the Chinese leadership.
Who knows what he’s really thinking?
Maybe it’s “I heart dialectical materialism.”
Another possibility is that Xi’s push for
Marxism
is a way to silence his critics.
Xi has amassed tremendous personal power.
He’s the strongest Chinese leader in a generation.
But right now, if it looked like
he was going to abandon the Party
and really make himself Emperor,
or as I like to say, Presitator,
the Party would tear him apart.
So by cloaking everything he does to gain
power
in the language of the Party,
Xi makes it harder for other Party officials
to criticize what he’s doing.
“Do you have a problem
with dialectical materialism, Li Keqiang?
Didn’t think so.”
And a third possibility is that
Xi Jinping’s push for Marxism
is a compromise with hardliners in the Party.
Let’s not forget about the ongoing
internal power struggle in the Party,
featured in my favorite soap opera,
General Hostility.
Remember that trip to Shanghai I mentioned?
Shanghai is more than just where
the Chinese Communist Party was founded.
It’s also the power base of Xi’s biggest
political rival
Jiang Zemin.
Xi wanted to remove presidential terms limits
so he could stay in power forever.
Like Skeletor.
But it looks like in order to get that through,
he had to go to Jiang’s homebase
and publically reaffirm his faith in the Party.
In other words,
it’s Xi Jinping submitting himself to the
Party—
not him taking over the Party.
“Dialectical materialism is the best!
Because the Party says so.”
We’ll have to see how this all plays out.
But ultimately,
even though it might look like Xi Jinping
is pushing communist values—
China never really got less communist.
It’s been communist all along.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And before you go,
I’m going to answer a question
from a fan of the show who supports China
Uncensored o
n the crowd funding website Patreon.
Ethan Fredsti asks,
“What would happen if Xi Jinping pulled
a Gorbachev?
Well that’s the million ruble question
everyone has been asking since Xi came to
power.
At the beginning,
some people hoped he would be a great reformer.
But I don’t think true reform is possible
with the Chinese Communist Party in charge.
The Party saw what happened to the Soviet
Union—
and they’re terrified of that happening
in China.
In fact, Xi made a speech back in 2013
where he blamed Gorbachev
for the fall of the Soviet Union,
and said that “nobody was a real man,
nobody came out to resist.”
So if Xi Jinping started acting like
he was setting himself up to be a Gorbachev
and dissolve the Party,
it’s very likely he’d be squashed
by the giant Party machine.
And not the good kind of Party machine—
like a disco ball or cotton candy machine.
The bad kind—
the kind that kills you if you don’t comply.
Like a very bad cotton candy machine.
As Forbes writes—
and I think this is pretty accurate—
“Xi isn't so much solidifying One Man Rule
as he is solidifying One Party Rule,
with himself at the head of the Party.”
And that’s an important distinction to make.
Thanks for your question, Ethan.
And to everyone else, thank you for watching!
If you’d like me to answer your question
on the show,
all you have to do is contribute a dollar
or more
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
You’ll also be helping keep China, uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.