On this episode of China Uncensored,
China’s military is being shaken up!
And Xi helped!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Chinese leader,
Head of the Chinese Communist Party,
Chair of the Central Military Commission,
and Commander in Xi-ief of the People’s
Liberation Army,
Xi Jinping, is a military mastermind.
He’s bringing change to the military.
With groundbreaking ideas.
He’s decided that he wants the military
to be
“combat ready.”
Imagine!
A military ready to fight.
Certainly a break from tradition.
According to state-run China Daily,
in a meeting with commanding officers this
week,
Xi said he wants the army to focus on
“building ‘new-type’ fighting capabilities.”
I know “new type”
is kind of an odd way to put it,
but remember,
Xi Jinping is in his 60s.
Imagine him like your grandpa
talking about all this “newfangled technology”
you young people have.
I bet Xi calls Twitter "Bird Talk."
And he probably calls Facebook
"that stalker thing started by the guy
who awkwardly tried to get me to name
his unborn child."
Look, it sounds much better in Chinese.
Anyway, what Xi Jinping is really talking
about
is the military’s electronic,
information and space operations.
Militarizing space.
What could go wrong?
But the main purpose of his meeting
with PLA commanders this week
was this:
reshuffling the military into
“a new, condensed structure
of 84 military units”
The military,
as you may imagine,
is kind of a big deal.
An even bigger deal
is who controls it.
And Xi Jinping has been wrestling former Chinese
leader
Jiang Zemin for it.
Xi has purged several top generals
loyal to Jiang.
And even granted himself
the new title of commander in chief,
something that, yes,
the Chinese military did not have before.
He also is streamlining the military,
laying off 300,000 soldiers
in favor of cutting-edge technology.
Those high tech weapons will be a bit more
loyal.
And maybe, even love him.
This is just the latest restructuring,
and there’s more to come.
China Daily points out that
“The previous four top PLA departments－
staff, politics, logistics and armaments－
were dismantled.”
This shake up will help Xi break
Jiang Zemin’s grip on the military.
But it might also net him a few more
enemies in the armed forces.
Not to worry.
Xi’s got that covered.
Because the restructuring
also means promotions!
“All 84 of the new units’ commanders
have or soon will be promoted
to a rank of either major general in the Ground
Force,
Air Force and Rocket Force,
or rear admiral in the Navy.”
You get a promotion!
Everybody gets a promotion!
But one thing the restructuring didn't change
-
everybody still has to remain loyal
to the Chinese Communist Party.
And according to this totally unexpected
article from Xinhua,
"Chinese military servicemen have unanimously
voiced
strong support for President Xi Jinping's
instruction"
and pledged to "build an indestructible army"
In fact, the PLA Army said they would
"uphold the leadership of the CPC Central
Committee
with Xi as the core."
The PLA Navy said they would
"build a powerful force to protect
China's maritime rights."
The PLA Air Force said they would
"strive to become a force of integrated air
and space capacities
competent for both offensive and defensive
missions."
And the PLA Rocket Force said they would
"denounce the evils of truth and love,
and extend our reach to the stars above!"
What's that Shelley?
Oh.
Sorry.
That was PLA Team Rocket.
My mistake.
The Rocket Force said they would
"eradicate the influence" of those
corrupt guys from Jiang's faction
and "concentrate on building an invincible
army."
And finally, the PLA Strategic Support Force
said they would "make major innovation breakthroughs
and cultivate a high-end talent pool."
Well, I guess we all know which is the lamest
force
in the PLA.
Come on, Strategic Support Force.
Other PLA forces are pledging to be invincible.
Step it up.
Anyway, judging from these heartfelt,
unforced statements,
I think Xi may just have himself
a much more loyal military now.
Just in time for heightened regional tensions!
I'm sure that "super-mighty preemptive strike"
sounds much better in Korean.
So what do you think of
Xi’s promotional military tactics?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
I hope you’re also checking us out on
Amazon Fire TV, Roku, and Apple TV.
Yes, China Uncensored is now on
all those platforms.
Well, except for Apple TV in Hong Kong and
Taiwan.
Apple seems to be so afraid of offending
the Chinese regime,
they removed the China Uncensored app there.
If you think that sucks,
please sign our petition.
The link is below.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.