China has a plan
To conquer the high seas
Can the US stop it before it’s too late?
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I'm Chris Chappell.
Joining me today is Captain Jim Fanell,
the former Director of Intelligence and Information
Operations
for the U.S. Pacific Fleet,
that's the U.S. Navy.
Thanks for joining me today.
Thanks Chris, happy to be here.
So China is talking about these blue economic
passages
and according to Chinese state run media,
these are harmless ocean trade routes
that will connect Oceania and Africa and Europe.
So is that really true?
Are they harmless?
It sounds really benign,
but I think it's not just economic development
of extension
into the maritime domain of their belt and
road initiative.
I think it's part of a larger strategy that
China has
for returning China to what they believe is
their rightful role
and place in the world,
their great rejuvenation in the achievement
of the China dream.
So are we talking imperial ambitions here?
It kind of...
To say that it comes across as conspiracy
theory,
but it certainly seems like that's the seeds
of what they're sowing today
and they'd been working on for the last few
years,
at least in the South Pacific.
Well, I know you were recently in the South
Pacific.
What did you see there?
What we saw was we went to Kiribati
and the Solomon Islands and Bougainville,
and what we saw was in at least those first
two countries,
their governments had switched recognition
from Taipei to Beijing,
diplomatic recognition.
These are tiny island nations.
They're atoll nations in the Melanesian
and Polynesian and Micronesian area of the
South Pacific
and they've switched their recognition
right after the Chinese apparently have paid
off
a few of their members of parliament and bribed
some people
and attempted to bribe others,
and so it seemed,
and then come in with a big infrastructure
packages
and purchases to try to essentially tell the
locals in these areas
if you align with us, you'll make yourselves
rich.
So what did you see on the ground in places
like the Solomon Islands or Kiribas,
how are the people reacting to this
Uniformly, the people in Kiribas and in the
Solomon Islands,
the sense that we got was that they felt like
they had been
betrayed by their governments, not consulted.
We talked to one dear lady in Tulagi who,
in that society,
that Metro-lineal ownership of the land.
So she was a landowner and a very nice woman
and she said,
"We were betrayed.
We weren't consulted.
This is not a decision that we agree with."
And we heard the same things in Guata Canal
and in some of the parts of care boss Bougainville
hasn't gotten to that quite step yet.
But clearly their sentiments were in terms
of principles
and the things that they believe in,
they're more aligned to our way of thinking
in the Western democracies
than they are with, they said,
"We're not communists.
We don't like communism,
but if they offered us money,
and nobody else offers us anything,
then that's what we're going to have to do."
But in terms of Kiribas in the Solomons,
it was very clear that they felt like these
people
had taken these bags of money in the middle
of the night
and then changed the vote.
And now I even heard this morning
from a contact in the Solomon's
that there's a little bit of buyer's remorse
going on.
Really?
Yeah.
So-
That happened fast.
Yeah.
Because there was talk before these agreements
that,
"Oh man, once the Chinese come in, we're all
going to,
check your bank account.
It's going to, you're going to have
thousands in there in your bank account."
And it really hasn't materialized yet.
Well I see how that's a problem for Taiwan,
but is that really bad?
China's giving these places,
that are very poor, all this economic developments.
How do you argue against that?
Well, on the face of it,
it wouldn't seem bad and it's actually
for some of the local nations,
if nobody else is going to help them,
then why not accept these kind of offers?
Because they're some of the places are in
destitute poverty,
but the concern that we should have is that
these islands
in their strategic geographic location present
the same kind of challenge that we saw 80
years ago
when Japan took all these islands through
military force.
So China is using a different model right
now,
which is to come in with soft power
and economic power and diplomatic power.
You know, part of it is designed to isolate
Taiwan,
but part of it is to extend this,
essentially what I called an iron bar,
through the South Pacific and it would essentially
separate Australia and New Zealand from the
rest of the world.
Now, as an American maybe some people would
say,
what do we care if Australia and New Zealand
are isolated?
How would we get our Vegemite?
Exactly.
And kangaroos, how will we see kangaroos?
So there's an issue there,
but there's a larger strategic issue which
is to say that
in the event of a crisis or a concern that
America
would have in the region,
we would need to have some kind of basing
for military forces
like we did in World War II, and Australia
and New Zealand
present that as an option for us.
So from a purely military standpoint,
having Australia and New Zealand cut off makes
it much harder for us
to deal with defending Taiwan or defending
Japan from Chinese aggression
in a large scale conflict.
So China is essentially extending its control
of the Pacific region?
Yeah this is cementing their position in,
but if they are able to establish these line
of islands
that are aligned to them diplomatically
and then in the future allow them to bring
in military forces.
So you think military is what comes next?
Not the next step.
I mean, I think the next step is you're going
to see
much more presence of their fishing fleet
because China needs to feed their population,
and this waters of the five degrees North,
five degrees South of the equator is called
the tuna belt.
There's a lot of tuna there that helps feed
people,
and these are prime waters.
These small island nations can't control their
exclusive economic zones
because they just don't have large navies,
they don't have satellites and things to know
who's in their water poaching.
So I think the Chinese will,
when they come in with their fishing fleets,
they will also bring their state oceanic administration
and the Chinese Coast Guard
and the people's armed forces, maritime militia.
This will all be brought in together and part
of the package will be,
we'll help you surveil your EEZ
to make sure that other countries aren't poaching.
Which, it'll be a smooth way they do that,
but that once they start information sharing
with these nations
it will be another layer of entrenchment.
So it seems like in the very near terms,
it's actually going to hurt the people of
these Island nations
because they're going to be short of fish.
I think what'll happen is,
is that China will be smart about it
and they'll probably help them build fish
canneries,
ports, and things of that nature,
and they'll probably give them a slice of
the profit,
or in some sense.
So there'll probably be a boost initially
in money,
but it won't be the full amount of the resources
that these nations,
if they could develop themselves in a free
and open,
and transparent commercial opportunity,
could reap in the long term.
So at what point do you think the Chinese
Navy would get involved?
Well, we've already seen reports that Chinese
Naval vessels
making trips down to Australia and New Zealand.
We've had reports in the last couple of years
of Chinese
long range aircraft flying out of the South
of China,
Southern China into the Philippines
and refueling and then going on down to New
Zealand.
So, I'm not saying that there's going to be
military aircraft
flying in and out of Guadalcanal and Honiara,
and things of that nature in the next couple
of years,
but the idea is that they're setting the seeds
for these infrastructure projects
that would allow them to build ports.
And if they do like they did in Vanuatu,
they built this 800 a meter long pier for
a small country
that didn't really need it,
well what could go in there?
And as I think 60 Minutes Australia reported
last year, y
ou could put a Chinese aircraft carrier in
there, easily.
So China is trying to develop its own blue
ocean capabilities?
Well they have been developing
their own blue water ocean capabilities
for the last decade,
and this is just another place where it can
be expanded into.
So I know some people would say,
what's the difference between the U.S. Navy
ruling the oceans
versus the Chinese Navy ruling the ocean?
What would you say that?
I would say that our Navy doesn't bully and
harass people
and take their islands,
their territory in their exclusive economic
zone,
like China did with Scarborough Shoal in 2012,
or build seven islands down in the Spratly
Islands
and inside the exclusive economic zone in
Malaysia,
the Philippines and Vietnam.
There's been reports that Chinese actors in
South Luconia Shoal
blowing up things and taking their markers
that say
this is a Malaysian atoll and blowing it up
so then they can put in a Chinese flag.
So those are just random examples,
there's other examples where the Chinese are
challenging people,
military ships, in the Taiwan Strait
saying you can't travel through the Taiwan
Strait.
Everyone in the world knows that's an international
passage,
yet China wants to say that you can't go through
there
unless you ask my permission.
So that kind of attitude in their response
to the international court
or the permanent court of arbitration case
in 2016
where they said this is a farce
and we're not going to follow the court's
ruling.
These are all signals of an attitude that
says,
we get to do whatever we want.
And then let me just add one more,
we also have these cases of U.S. and other
aircraft
being lased out in Djibouti and in the East
and South China sea
by Chinese vessels, Chinese forces.
Lased as like-
Shining a laser in a pilot's eyes,
there's only one reason you'd do that,
to blind the guy and then he crashes and dies.
So it's a very serious provocation
and we kind of haven't held them accountable
for that.
So how much of a concern is this actually
because can the Chinese Navy really rival
the United States?
Well as I've said in other forums,
I think the Chinese Navy does rival the U.S.
Navy
inside the Asia Pacific,
inside the second island chain in terms of
the number of platforms
that they have that can shoot missiles to
sink our fleet,
anti-ship cruise missiles from the surface
ships,
from their submarines, from their aircraft,
land-based cruise missiles,
land-based ballistic missiles that are designed
to kill carriers
like the DF-21 and DF-26.
So, China's built a layered defensive capability
to keep the U.S. Military at arms length from
the Taiwan contingency,
the Senkaku's contingency,
and any contingency in the South China Sea.
I think what we're going to see over the next
decade
is them extend that counter intervention strategy
beyond the second island chain,
so to really keep American forces from even
getting from Hawaii into the Guam area.
Also, what would that mean for the world if
the U.S.
is denied access to basically the entire Western
Pacific?
Well, it would be denied in a conflict,
on a daily basis wouldn't mean anything initially.
But in the event of a conflict where China
said,
we're tired of America or we don't like what
they did with Hong Kong,
the Act that the Congress passed and the President
signed
where they say that's unacceptable and we're
going to show you,
they could block off something or they could
isolate something
or they can conduct a quarantine or a blockade
of some place
and essentially starve somebody out if they
wanted to.
And we'd be hard pressed to break that without
escalating the situation,
so they could use it as a ratcheting up technique.
A part of the salami slicing strategy that
we haven't really seen.
We've seen them incrementally inch forward
in geographic areas,
in statements and postures, but we haven't
actually seen them
do it in a more militaristic way.
I know these blue economic passages,
it's not just in the South Pacific,
it's also going up to the Arctic,
it's going to Europe, to Africa.
What's happening in those other branches of
this?
Well we're seeing,
I mean they've really been focused.
The first one was from the South China sea
into the Indian ocean
and then up into the Mediterranean and in
the Baltic.
I was up on a ship in the Baltic,
a Chinese ship that routinely sends ships
up there,
exercise with the Russians up there.
So they've made inroads into Europe,
OCEA has been meeting with the French and
the Italians
and they've signed some agreements for the
belt and road initiative,
ports in Genoa and ports in Trieste.
I expect to see more ports in France
come under some kind of an agreement.
I wouldn't be surprised if that would happen.
You have the base in Djibouti.
Remember for years they said,
we don't have it, we're never going to have
any overseas military bases.
I mean you can pull out,
reams and reams of analysis from think tanks
in this town
that said that would never happen, and yet
there it sits.
So what else are we seeing that they're doing
on the West Coast of Africa,
down on the East Coast of South America,
in Argentina and Brazil.
Where else are they expanding so that they
can have
the presence to be able to operate?
I think it's coming and we've just been reluctant
to predict the future,
even though they tell us what it is.
Yeah, I was thinking that a lot of the things
the Chinese Communist Party is doing in like
the Solomon Islands,
it sounds very similar to Mauritania in Western
Africa.
Same fishing things, same...
It's a model, they have a model and it seems
to be pretty effective.
So what does all this mean for your average
American?
Well, what it means is that, at the end of
the day,
if you don't address this in another 20 years,
30 years,
by 2049 China will have established a system
of governance
that will allow Beijing and the Chinese Communist
Party
to control the levers of power.
And what it will mean in real terms is instead
of having
the market dictate how many iPhones we make
or how many cars we build or how many jackets
we buy
or how many shoes we have made,
you're going to have some bureaucrat in Beijing
doing a scientific development process on
his abacus telling us,
okay, this is the goal.
We need to produce this many of these and
this many of these
and this many of these.
And then there's another segment of the government
that's reviewing the people in other places
and saying,
Oh, that guy he forgot to do this, and he
didn't do that.
So we're going to lower his score and he can't
travel anymore.
Or his kid can't get into this university,
or he can't get this kind of goat cheese at
this store
because he's had too much in the last three
months.
So this is the kind of world that, it sounds
crazy,
but this is the way they want to control things.
The social credit system.
I mean you can just imagine that being exported
even though they deny that they want to export
it.
It seems pretty clear that if you're going
to expand your belt and road
and have all this control everywhere,
that you're not going to, your system can't
work.
You know, they talk about they're pushing
forward into AI and big data.
They want all of this data to come in.
Well what for?
If it's only for market forces?
No, it's going to be more than that.
So what can the U.S. do about this?
Well, we first have to do,
what I think this administration has done
is recognize
that China is a strategic competitor.
So we've said that the national security strategy
and the national defense strategy
and now we're starting to have our senior
leaders
talk about the difference between the United
States and China
and PRC in terms of their values
and in what we stand for in individual liberty
and freedom.
Whereas the Chinese Communist Party
stands for the Chinese Communist Party.
And so they are the be all end all of everything
and we need to tell the world that there's
a choice there.
Now I know that the administration, some people
have said,
well we're not asking people to make choices
between U.S.
and the PRC.
And that's a fine thing.
I think what we're doing is saying
you have to decide about the values, though.
Who you want to be associated with.
And I think that we have a long track record
in human history
that our system of freedom is more attractive
and more appealing to people innately.
And it's gives people a better opportunity
to have a higher quality of life and more
satisfaction.
That message needs to be continued.
On a defense, security standpoint,
we need to retool our military to move it
away from
a focus on the middle East
to a focus on being able to keep the sea lanes
open
and trade in economies going.
So as much as people say the administration
is isolationist,
I don't see that because they say they want
to build up the Navy.
In Simi Valley yesterday or the day before,
the new National Security Advisor, O'Brien,
talked about the administration's commitment
to getting to a 350 ship Navy, not in decades,
but sooner than that.
So there's a desire by the administration
to build up the Navy.
And there's only one reason for that.
And the reason that we want a big Navy is
to ensure that
the Chinese or then the Russians and the Soviet
Navy
don't control these things
and put a damper on international trade between
these nations.
So I think we're on the right track.
I just think it's really hard to move the
ship of state.
And we have a lot of commitments globally.
And we've had a mindset since Desert Storm,
since 1991,
that has said the Middle East is an existential
threat.
And I think that things in the middle East
are dangerous.
But I, I think that after 30 years and the
infrastructure
that we've established with the Homeland Security
and other places that allowed us to say, okay,
we've got, we've got a handle on the Middle
East
and terrorism much better than we did before
9-11,
but what we don't have a handle on right now
is competing and being able to deter Chinese
aggression
in the Indo pay comm arena.
And I'm concerned that if we don't address
it now,
we won't be able to address it when it concerns
the Mediterranean or the South Atlantic.
Well, so what happens in the next five or
10 years
after this administration?
Well, this is American domestic politics.
I mean, you need sustainment of this view
of,
if you buy into this,
and I mean I recognize that many people may
not,
but I think a lot of, obviously the administration
does,
and there seems to be, you hear reports about
bipartisan agreement
on things like the Hong Kong act and,
and other things like that-
The Uyghur Bill.
Yeah, exactly.
So we need to capitalize on this emerging
bi-partisan efforts towards China
and it needs to be sustained.
So you say a lot of these island nations,
they share the same values as the United States,
but I mean, as you say, values don't pay the
bills.
What can be done on the ground?
So I think the administration is moving out
in certain areas
and trying to incentivize our commercial interests
to help in these areas.
And they've got a number of things that they're
working on.
But from my perspective, this is a big issue.
And all these islands have similar problems
in terms of infrastructure and being able
to monitor their EEZ's
and to reap the harvest of the resources that
they have,
whether in the water or on their islands and
they need help.
And what the United States should do with,
I think for other nations, Australia, New
Zealand, Japan, and Taiwan,
is to band together and develop some kind
of what
I would term a Marshall plan, find some person...
I don't know if it's preferably a military
person,
but maybe you need somebody that's going to
be able
to lead a large group like this,
but to have these nations come together and
do something
outside of their typical bureaucratic morass
and break above that to say,
"Hey, we're in a kind of a crisis like we
were in world war II
where Germany was devastated.
The Soviets were pressing in and these people
needed food,
they needed sustenance, they needed infrastructure."
And George Marshall, the general of the army
developed a plan
to come in and help rescue them.
And some of it was we brought in our own stuff
and our own food
and things of that nature,
but it was also coming in and helping the
German people
just have the ability to rise themselves up
and rebuild Germany.
The Germans did that.
Okay?
We could do something similar in this area
here,
which would just moving in that direction,
labeling it and moving in that direction
and combining the talents of our five nations.
Maybe the Japanese build harbors,
maybe the Australians take roads,
maybe the U.S. does I.T., Whatever it is.
But something like that where we're all kind
of covering a wedge,
covering an area that then could then show
and demonstrate not only to these,
first to these islands that, Hey, you know,
the Western world is really here and they,
they're doing it again.
Like they did 80 years ago,
they're coming to help us and then we need
to train them.
We don't just need to give them fish,
we need to train them to learn how to fish.
And that's nothing new for me.
But you've heard that,
and we should be doing that across all these
areas.
And then it also sends a larger signal to
the rest of Asia,
which is to say, Hey, you know,
America said they're committed to the Pacific.
They say they're a Pacific nation,
here they're actually doing something and
it's helping people.
I think this is a way to help answer that
question
about why should I choose the PRC or why should
I choose the U.S.?
Why should I choose the Chinese Communist
Party
or why should I choose freedom?
So, but this is not an easy thing to do.
And the bureaucracies in each of our governments
are very difficult
because we have established protocols and
concerns
and there's concerns about, well,
we're not going to spend as much money,
dollar for dollar would against China.
We're not going to compete in that arena.
And I'm not suggesting that we compete dollar
for dollar.
What I'm suggesting is we compete idea for
idea,
innovation versus some somebody in the Chinese
Communist Party
with a schedule that's figured out, okay,
here's,
here's how we can do this and we're going
to mandate it down to them.
I think we can do this.
We just need to say it's important.
So with everything you're saying about China's
global ambitions,
doesn't this come from Xi Jinping?
Like he won't be in power forever?
Like maybe after Xi Jinping,
it won't be as much of an issue.
Yeah.
So I think there's a school of thought inside
the China hands community that's focusing
on Xi
and kind of blaming Xi as the cause,
root cause of what's going on right now,
and that the belt and road in this economic
passages
and the militarization of the Chinese
is all because of Xi and what he's doing in
Jin Jiang.
All these things that we track, that you track
and your team.
But my belief is, what I've seen from the
evidence is that,
this blue economic passages, they predate
Xi they go back to...
I saw pictures on Chinese warships from 2012
that depicted
a Dragon's head coming out of the mainland
of China
with three arrows, one to the polar area,
one into the South China Sea into the Indian
Ocean
and one end to the South Pacific.
That was on a Chinese worship in Sydney in
2012, okay.
That was to inspire Chinese sailors to be
pumped up about their mission.
Okay.
Well, those pictures were probably developed
in 2011 or 2010 you know,
well before Xi Jinping was in power.
So my belief is that this is part of the long
trajectory
that's unbroken since Ziyang, Jiang, Hu, Xi,
and whoever's next,
they're all marching towards to return China
to its rightful place in charge of the world.
So this isn't Xi Jinping.
This is an existential threat of the Chinese
Communist Party?
Correct.
Now Xi is chosen to break with past practice
of how you expose yourself.
At least the Chinese Communist Party
being exposed for their truer attentions.
So maybe he stepped off too early,
we can debate that,
but clearly he's not the only guy that's doing
this.
And when he goes away,
it's not going to change that trajectory.
There's still going to be intent upon that.
So they haven't been deterred is the real
issue.
We've had 40 years of engagement that has
told them, eh,
we're not going to do anything.
So do whatever you want.
That's got to change.
All right.
Thank you very much for joining me today.
It's a pleasure to have you on.
Thanks Chris.
Appreciate it.