The Biden Administration finally meets with China
Is Biden striking a tough stance?
Or is China running the show
That and more on this week’s China news headlines
Welcome to China Uncensored. I’m Chris Chappell.
This week marks the first\h
high-level meeting between\h\h
the Biden Administration and Chinese\h
officials. And a lot is at stake.
But first, I got to tell you, YouTube has been\h
demonetizing us a lot. For this show to continue,\h\h
we need your support on the crowd funding website\h
Patreon. For as little as a dollar an episode,\h\h
you can help us continue to uncensor China.\h
Visit Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored for more.
So as I said, this is the first showdown\h
between the Biden Administration and China.
The meeting happened in Alaska. This is\h
a big deal. Biden (Corner Box) has not\h\h
made his administration’s China policy\h
clear yet. He’s still reviewing a lot\h\h
of Trump administration China policies,\h
from bans on Chinese apps like WeChat.
To tariffs.
To even whether to label the Chinese Communist\h
Party’s persecution of Uyghurs as genocide.
Some people have the impression the\h
Biden Administration is soft on China.\h\h
That’s because of past China failures\h
from key administration officials,\h\h
as well as the fallout from\h
the Hunter Biden scandal.\h
But President Biden doesn’t\h
want to be seen as soft.\h\h
So in the lead up to the first meeting, the\h
Biden Administration struck a tough stance.
Secretary of State Antony Blinken made his\h
first trip to Asia. And it was all about China.\h
First stop was Japan. Blinken was joined\h
by US Secretary of Defense Lloyd Austin.
A warning to China from U.S. Secretary\h
of State Antony Blinken on Tuesday,\h\h
as he cautioned it against\h
using "coercion and aggression".
Blinken was specifically calling out the\h
Chinese regime’s actions in the South China Sea.
“We're united in the vision of a free and open\h
Indo-Pacific region, where countries follow the\h\h
rules, cooperate whenever they can, and resolve\h
their differences peacefully. And in particular\h\h
we will push back if necessary when China\h
uses coercion or aggression to get its way.”
China was obviously not happy about that.
But then he was off to South Korea.\h
Where he had a pretty similar message.
“China is using coercion and aggression to\h
systematically erode autonomy in Hong Kong,\h\h
undercut democracy in Taiwan, abuse\h
human rights and Xinjiang in Tibet\h\h
and assert maritime claims in the South\h
China Sea that violate international law.”
And speaking of Hong Kong,\h\h
the Biden Administration has just\h
announced their first Chinese sanctions.
They’re sanctioning 24 Chinese\h
and Hong Kong officials over\h\h
the latest crackdown on Hong Kong’s Democracy.
Which is great news. However, these\h
officials were already sanctioned by Trump.\h
“All of these officials, who include senior\h
Chinese lawmakers and Hong Kong-based security\h\h
officials, had already been hit with\h
sanctions by the Trump administration.”
Trump’s sanctions froze the US assets of these\h
24 officials, banned them from entering the US,\h\h
and stopped Americans from doing\h
business with these officials.\h
Biden’s sanctions now also punish\h
any foreign financial institutions\h\h
that conduct business with these officials,\h
even if those institutions aren’t American.
The new sanctions were made\h
under the Hong Kong Autonomy Act,\h\h
bipartisan legislation that was passed last\h
year. The Trump administration had also used\h\h
that act to sanction many high ranking officials,\h
including Hong Kong chief executive Carrie Lam.
We did an episode last year on why\h
these sanctions are so powerful.
It’s nice to see Biden and Trump\h
agreeing on so many things.\h
But the Biden administration’s ramp up to this\h\h
high-level meeting wasn’t just about\h
Hong Kong. Days before the meeting,\h\h
the US government also approved the export\h
of sensitive submarine parts for Taiwan.
That will help Taiwan protect itself\h
from a potential Chinese invasion.\h\h
Unless those sensitive submarine\h
parts are screen doors.
A big question on everyone’s mind\h
is how Biden will handle Trump’s\h\h
tariffs on China and the phase one trade deal.\h\h
But according to National Security Advisor Jake\h
Sullivan, that won’t be a focus in the talks.
Instead he suggested the talks will focus\h
on big picture strategy and American values.
At a White House press briefing, he said, “This\h
is our effort to communicate clearly to the\h\h
Chinese government how the United States intends\h
to proceed at a strategic level, what we believe\h\h
our fundamental interests and values are, and\h
what our concerns with their activities are.”
I hope that clear communication involves\h
telling the Chinese government to:\h\h
Stop. Committing. Genocide.
And after the break, Apple may be getting\h
nervous about slave labor in China.
Welcome back.
It looks like Apple has cut ties\h
with the Chinese company Ofilm.\h\h
They make selfie cameras for the iPhone. And\h
may have been using slave labor from Xinjiang.
Apple’s massive supply chain\h
has a lot of links in China.\h\h
That’s why Apple has lobbied so hard against\h
the Uyghur Forced Labor Prevention Act.\h
Meanwhile, Ofilm told investors\h
it had lost a “particular\h\h
overseas client” but didn’t name the client.
So why did Apple drop Ofilm?\h
Well, according to reports,\h\h
Apple dropped Ofilm a few months ago. That would\h
have been after Ofilm was listed in this report\h\h
as a company that used Uyghur slave labor.
So good on Apple for doing something about it. But\h
considering how widespread Uyghur forced labor is,\h\h
Apple will need to do a lot\h
more than drop one supplier\h\h
to make sure its iPhones aren’t\h
made with some kind of slave labor.
Speaking of the Uyghurs, Australia joins Turkey\h\h
in refusing to call China’s\h
persecution of Uyghurs a genocide.
I mean, you don’t want to be seen as doing\h
business with acountry that commits genocide.\h\h
So just don’t label it genocide.
So despite the 3 billion dollars lost in the\h
trade war China launched against Australia...
clearly there are still enough people\h
in the Australian government who\h\h
hope to one day get rich\h
again by working with China.
And some good news for people who still want\h
to travel to mainland China for some reason.\h\h
It’s easier to get in, as long as you get\h
vaccinated. But only with the Chinese vaccine.
At least one of the Chinese vaccines\h
is only about 50% effective. But hey,\h\h
the Communist Party would rather people use their\h
vaccine and be more at risk, than the alternative.
But remember, everyone, according Chinese\h
state-run media, vaccine nationalism is bad.
But if you do get into China after\h
taking one of their vaccines,\h\h
no word yet on whether or not you’ll\h
be exempted from the anal swabs.\h
And now it’s time for me to answer a question from\h
a member of the China Uncensored 50 cent army,\h\h
fans who support the show on Patreon.
Today’s question comes from:
Arpanet-at-Cern “Hey Chris, any update on\h
when/if the China Uncensored merch store\h\h
will be back? I'm still itching to\h
grab some for my friends and family.\h\h
Also, great job as always to you and the team.”
Great question! We actually do have a merch\h
store on our website, ChinaUncensored.tv.
But it’s only in soft-launch. You can buy one\h
of our t-shirt designs now. But we’re waiting\h\h
to do a big public launch until after we get\h
our new China Uncensored logo and graphics.
That’s being done by the same team that\h
made the America Uncovered graphics.\h\h
Once we have that done, we’ll do a video\h
about the merch store. So stay tuned.
And remember, the reason we’re\h
able to update our graphics is\h\h
thanks to the amazing support\h
from viewers like you on Patreon.\h\h
Because of YouTube demonetization, we\h
wouldn’t have enough money to run the show,\h\h
let alone improve the look of it. So a big thank\h
you to everyone who contributes on Patreon.
If you’d like to join Arpanent\h
at Cern as a member of the China\h\h
Uncensored 50 cent army, head over to\h
Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored to learn more.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.\h
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.