China is pushing a Coronavirus scam
While the disease spreads in the Middle East
And around the world
That and more on this week’s China news
headlines.
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
This week’s China news headlines.
An update on the coronavirus disease,
also called COVID-19.
It’s now spread to at least 47 countries.
But the World Health Organization
is declining to call it a pandemic.
Cool.
Just like they declined to call it
a global health emergency a month ago.
Now a pandemic means that a disease
is spreading around the world.
And the W.H.O. used to have specific criteria
for declaring a pandemic.
And with outbreaks in China,
South Korea, Italy, and Iran,
COVID-19 would likely have met those criteria.
But the good news is,
now the W.H.O.’s criteria for pandemics
is a lot more...vague.
According to the director general,
the coronavirus is not a pandemic because
there
hasn’t been “uncontained global spread”
or “large-scale severe disease or death.”
Instead the head of the W.H.O. says these
are
“epidemics in different parts of the world.”
I mean, South Korea is reporting record daily
spikes
and Japan is closing all schools.
It’s spreading throughout the Middle East,
With Iran having the highest death toll outside
of China,
And the guy in charge of fighting it in Iran
was infected.
Coronavirus cases are also surging in Italy.
And spreading from Italy to the rest of Europe.
And it’s in Latin America now.
But thank goodness it’s not a pandemic yet.
However, official numbers of new coronavirus
cases
are down in China.
Unfortunately, that might just be because
the Communist Party
has a coronavirus scam—
changing the definition of what an infection
is.
They’ve changed the definition 6 times so
far.
So what does it mean that the numbers are
going down?
According to an expert
at Johns Hopkins Center for Health Security,
“There are two possibilities —
the draconian social distancing measures China
has taken
are really driving down the number of cases...
or health officials are changing their view
of what constitutes a case.”
Kind of like how the Party lifted
millions of people out of poverty,
by changing the definition of what poverty
meant.
Most of those people are called “low-income”
now.
Problem solved!
But one thing we can all confidently count
on
is the lack of medical supplies since everything
is made in China.
The Coronavirus is hitting the Chinese economy
hard.
Factories are struggling to start up again
after being shut down.
Only a third of Chinese small businesses are
open.
And migrant workers,
a critical part of the Chinese economy,
can’t move throughout the country
because of quarantines and border restrictions.
You know what that means?
Now’s the right time to buy Chinese stocks!
And JPMorgan says the Chinese economy
will grow in the second quarter.
I mean, just think about
how much money can be made in China!
There’s probably no downside at all!
Especially if you don’t learn from history!
I wish I knew how to quit you.
Well then why don’t you?!
The Trump Administration is considering
punishing Chinese state-run news organizations
operating in the United States.
That’s in retaliation for China
kicking out three Wall Street Journal Reporters.
Which itself was possibly retaliation for
the US labeling
Chinese state-run media operatives of China’s
communist state.
Which...they are.
Some of them are part of the Chinese Communist
Party’s
Central Propaganda Department.
Others are directly under the Party’s Central
Committee.
Reporters with state-run media in the US
have been accused of essentially spying for
the Communist Party.
That’s why the new punishments the Trump
Administration
are considering may include, “expelling
journalists
who have contact with intelligence agencies.”
Then again, I have to say,
my opinion of Chinese state-run media really
changed
after China Daily called China Uncensored,
a “leading Western media outlet.”
Also, “disgraceful anti-China garbage,
which seems to have come out of a gossip rag.”
Sorry Global Times.
I think China Daily is my new favorite Chinese
state-run media.
Two major Apple shareholders pushed for a
proposal
that would force Apple to disclose censorship
requests
from China and any other country.
“The motion, set to be voted on
by the company’s investors [this week],
was prompted by numerous allegations
of Apple kowtowing to Beijing
and blocking apps from being used by Chinese
customers.”
That includes Apple removing VPNs at Beijing’s
request.
So that Chinese people can’t access
the outside internet on their iPhones.
But good news for Apple!
The votes are in and...
Apple will not be held accountable.
Apple’s major shareholders are all large
corporations,
which themselves mostly have investments in
China.
So really, this helps everyone not be held
accountable.
But there is at least *some* good news this
week.
On February 19,
you saw our episode about how the Chinese
Consulate in New York
put up an exhibit about Tibet in the Queens
Public Library—
full of all sorts of propaganda.
Well, this week,
thanks to unrelenting pressure from local
Tibetans,
and also possibly China Uncensored
pestering library officials for comment,
the Library took the exhibit down.
Tibetans can finally celebrate a victory
against the Chinese Communist Party.
Tibetans in exile, at least.
And that’s it for this week’s China news.
Now it’s time for me to answer a question
from a fan who supports China Uncensored
on the crowd funding website Patreon!
Today’s question comes from Joe King
“Chris, do you think that while the plaque
will be placed into the box for shipping,
our cherry blossoms of joy will spread their
petals
above the google exec's dew of shameful tears?”
I think that’s my favorite question ever.
So, China Uncensored just hit 1 million subscribers.
Supposedly that means YouTube will send us
a plaque like this.
This comes after YouTube and Google
have been suppressing the show.
Subscribers have been secretly unsubscribed.
People don’t get notifications of new episodes,
even when the notification bell is on.
Videos have been demonetized, age-restricted,
or taken down with no explanation.
China Uncensored rarely turns up in suggested
videos,
and for years, if you tried to search China
Uncensored,
the suggested text would be China Uncensorship
pollution,
which is definitely a real thing.
We struggle to even get our t-shirt merchandise
approved.
And yet despite all this,
China Uncensored has continued to grow,
even as the revenue from YouTube continues
to plummet.
This has been possible because you
are watching and sharing the videos
and you continue to support the show
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
So YouTube and Google have failed to stop
us,
and that’s all because of you.
So I can only imagine that plaque
will be bathed in a gentle mist
of the tears of those Google execs
who still long to get back into China.
That is if they ever ship it to us.
I’m not going to hold my breath.
Thanks for your question and your support,
Joe King.
And if you’d like to join the China Uncensored
50-cent army,
head over to patreon.com/chinauncensored to
learn more.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.