On this episode of China Uncensored,
China and North Korea may no longer be BFFs,
but Kim Jong-Un has a new best friend, so
there.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
For decades, North Korea and China were besties.
Together like peas and carrots.
Like rice and gochujang.
But recently, China has been spending
a bit too much time with the US,
and they keep talking about North Korea
behind its back,
about how it’s been getting all nuclear lately.
And now China’s telling North Korea
that maybe they can't even be friends anymore.
Poor Kim Jong-Un must be so sad!
But fortunately, he might have made a new
friend.
A big, strong, manly friend.
No, not me!
Vladamir Putin!
They have so much in common!
Think about it.
Putin’s an outdoorsman...
...a friend to the animals...
...and beloved by children.
That’s a perfect match for Kim!
He’s an outdoorsman...
...friend to the animals...-ish
...and the children, they...
Hey, how come they’re not smiling?
Maybe because they were told they're
all going to summer re-education camp.
Don't worry kids,
it'll be great.
Talent shows!
Archery!
Making arts and crafts for export
in exchange for food!
And don't forget
that classic summer re-education camp tradition,
staying up after curfew
to try to sneak across the river into China.
Makes me miss my summer camp days.
But anyway, back to Russia.
As ties between China and North Korea deteriorate,
Russia has been stepping in to fill the void.
And it’s not so unusual.
After the Second World War, Russia—
well, the Soviet Union—
was North Korea’s sugar daddy.
With its support,
North Korea became strong,
with an economy that was even stronger
than US-backed South Korea.
But that relationship fell apart
after the Soviet Union had a big breakdown
in the early ’90s.
And without Soviet subsidies,
the North Korean economy collapsed,
and they kind of stopped being able to feed
everyone.
That’s when China came in
and their relationship became close.
Like, really close.
But now that China’s new leader
is making new friends,
Russia’s back for the friendship rebound.
Actually, Russia's been trying for a few years
now.
In 2014, Russia forgave North Korea
about $10 billion dollars of debt.
Proving that authoritarian regimes can be
more forgiving
than your average student loan provider.
I probably should have gotten Russia
to finance my Master's degree.
Moving on,
then Russia and North Korea declared 2015
to be
the “Year of Friendship.”
And in 2017,
for the third year in a row,
Russia beat out China as North Korea’s bestie.
When Kim sent out New Years greeting cards,
“At the top of the list was Russia,
followed by China.”
“Dear Putin, Happy New Year.
I like your horse.
Love, Kim.”
Of course it’s not just a show of friendship.
Russia is again providing real economic benefits
that help prop up the North Korean regime
in the face of declining support from China.
According to the US political intelligence
firm, Stratfor,
“When China recently threatened
to cut off fuel exports to North Korea
if it conducted its sixth nuclear weapons
test,
Russia hinted it could replace
at least some of that supply.”
And according to Reuters,
“Russia has already taken over
the supply of jet fuel to North Korea
after China halted exports two years ago.”
Now state-run North Korean airline Air Koryo
will have fuel again.
New tagline:
We’re not the worst airline anymore!
And the Kremlin isn't just helping North Korea
with air travel.
Later this month,
a new ferry service between these two cities
is scheduled to launch,
carrying potentially 200 passengers
and 1000 tons of cargo
six times a month.
Now you might be wondering,
what kind of passengers go between
North Korea and Russia?
Well, slaves might be a more accurate term.
There’s an estimated 30,000 North Korean
“workers” in Russia,
and almost all of their earnings
go to the North Korean regime.
It’s one of the few sources of income
for North Korea.
That, and selling drugs out of its embassies,
which is a real thing.
So why is Russia moving closer to North Korea?
What can there possibly be in it for them?
Well, Russia wants to take over China’s
role,
holding North Korea’s leash.
For over a decade,
China presented itself as the only country
that had any possible sway over North Korea.
If the global community had any illusions
about forcing a change there,
they’d have to go through China.
That gave the Chinese regime
a lot of international leverage.
Russia would love to be able to expand its
influence
in the Asia-Pacific region.
And if by getting close to North Korea,
Russia could do that,
well, wouldn’t that just be grand?
There’s one hitch.
It didn’t work for China—
because ultimately,
North Korea did whatever it wanted.
Russia may also find that
despite all its good will,
North Korea will continue to do what it wants.
Ouch.
And what does China think about all this?
Well, you know how it is sometimes
in international relations.
You're best friends with a neighboring country,
mostly because the two of you grew up together,
fought wars together,
but now that your best friend
is getting totally obsessed
with launching nuclear weapons,
you're not sure you have
all that much in common anymore.
You're making new friends,
and there's only so much room for crazy in
your life.
But now Russia is moving in
and trying to be even better friends
than you were with North Korea.
And that hurts a little.
Not that you and Russia were super close.
But you always stood together
against the United States,
like on the UN Security Council.
And now everything is getting complicated.
And North Korea...
well, you're never going to be that close
again.
But maybe there's still a way
to save some part of the friendship.
At least for international leverage purposes.
So you know what -
next time you have a party,
Russia and North Korea are invited.
So what do you think of Russia
trying to replace China as North Korea’s
BFF?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
See you next time.