Taiwan: a beautiful country full of amazing experiences
This tiny island nation is home to a thriving economy and Britch culture
But there's one thing Taiwan has that's unlike anything else in the world
Wait 7-eleven, you told me you were taking me to an authentic Taiwan experience
7-eleven is an authentic Taiwan experience. It's not like anything else in the u.s
You're not gonna be able to try watery hotdogs here. You have to try new things.
You know, I don't like trying new things.
I promise it'll be fun.
That's what you said about the South China Sea
That was fun.
It was.
All right, let's go
Shopping time
To make this more fun slash terrifying we decided to pick out items for each other to try.
Oh man, this is going to be great
All right, Shelly what have you done to me this time?
Okay, we're gonna start with a little aperitif of
juice milks
Juice milks.
Yes, they're actually
famous in
Taiwan for having watermelon milk and papaya milk.
Must be hard to milk a watermelon.
Yeah, I mean it is milk
They just want to make sure you understand
It's it's cow's milk.
It's an interesting smell
Yeah, it's like somebody's stuck a piece of watermelon.
Thoughts? You like it?
I'm sure it does a body good.
Papaya milk.
Actually really like this one!
Okay, this one is like the famous one, papaya milk.
All right. Well after having
juice and juice now, we'll try actual juice, multi juice.
Juice milk, and I'm not sure what kind of juice
Very citrusy smell
Swallow
Doesn't count if you don't swallow the food
It's like a jolly rancher... milk.
We're off to a good start.
So 7-elevens in taiwan have a bunch of like bits and bobs floating around
So is that the technical term?
I think so. I really scalded myself getting these so I just wanted you to know and I worked
hard to get them.
Thank you very much, and I don't want to put that in my mouth
Yeah, well, we have some hot dog, now that we've cut them open this filled with it's filled with something.
I think this is the
traditional Taiwan delicacy chicken testicles.
That's not a chicken testicle
No?
I've eaten chicken testicles. And that's not...
Shelly there's so much. I don't know about your past
Good crunch
Exactly where I was mean, it's time like a like a hot dog. All right
Chicken testicle
It's not a chicken testicle.
It is chicken though
And finally
Mango shrimp.
Is that...?
cheese?
Actually, you're allergic to mango right? I should maybe make sure it's not mango before I kill you a mistake
Good news is it's definitely not mango
Tastes like shrimp with little hard poppy balls of something
What have I done?
Fish eggs.
Fish eggs... and cheese.
Don't know why I took another bite.
Let's move on
So what fresh horror is this?
You know crispy dried squid mouth.
Squids have beaks. They don't have mouths.
All right, so it's crispy dried squid beak.
These actually are the beak.
Yes, what part of this don't you understand?
This is an actual squids mouth.
Did you think it was like lying on the package?
I thought it might have been a mistrans-
It's the only snack that bites back
It's like an Eldritch Horror in your mouth.
Hail Cthulhu.
Stop eating them, Shelley.
What? They're good!
So, what's this?
Well since you thought squid mouths were so funny, how about some spicy chicken gizzards?
Love chicken gizzard.
You do?
Yeah
I see you're not eating them.
Crunchy right
You're right that's a little crunchy.
Good, right?
Feel like I trolled myself.
So Chris, I know that was a little weird a little maybe you want some like classic American Oreos, ah
Looks like they've done
something with Oreos
All right. Sounds good
It's a good way to make an Oreo
Hey
Still tastes like the chicken gizzards
Perhaps a Ritz cracker
This looks disgusting.
No
Processed cheese is good in any country.
It's the cheese is weird and like overly salty and the crackers.
This is the best tasting thing we've had.
That's terrible
Give me the chicken gizzards
All right, I think it's time for a food break and we need to wash it down with some
asparagus juice.
It doesn't smell like what it smells like after you've eaten it, asparagus.
It's its own unique smell, I've never smelled this before.
It smells like corn
No, there's a hint of asparagus there. All right
And garlic.
That's pretty damn good. Yeah, I would I would buy this if they sold a what
What is this?
It's refreshing it's sweet...
And also sour. Why is it sour?
It's like it's got vinegar in it. I don't know what's going on. I'm so confused.
I feel a rash forming
I'm starting to regret this but these are chicken flavored Cheetos.
Well, they certainly surpassed the look of Cheetos
Okay, why are these sweet?
I don't taste the sweet.
My gosh, there's too many weird flavors in my stomach right now.
I feel horrible
How you holding up, Shelly?
My stomach hurts.
Mine, too
But good news is the great flavor of coconut and corn has finally been married together
This treat...
Covered in a fine white powder. How is it? Ooh...
It's salty.
So I was expecting it to be sweet, but it is so salty.
This is very unsettling
Mmm, you know, if you come to Taiwan?
Maybe don't go to 7 Eleven.
They're potato chips
What's the trick?
They're salted egg potato chips.
I bet they're sweet
I don't taste any like salted egg in essence.
Hmm too bad, you know
Not really, but I'm keep eating this for some reason.
Once you have one, you can't stop it just one. That's a slogan
Just opening the bag
I was overwhelmed by shrimp smell.
You really got to bring your A game here, Chris. Shrimp fries, really?
I didn't know they look like fries so, you know, it's
fries on the bag.
Also I grew up eating these. If you're trying to gross me out with shrimp fries...
I just ended up trolling myself in this episode.
I mean this feels like a nice palate cleanser after like the corn coconut
wafer roll.
Actually, I agree
Hmm. I feel like I could eat all kinds of things more. Oh
Good
What's next?
This is a German style smoked sausage.
When I got it I didn't realize there'd be so many things on it.
So I mean, it looks like it's
fresh hotdog bun
but it just has been sitting in the bag for God knows how long.
I - there's like ketchup on it and mayonnaise or something and I
didn't see that.
Oh my god, wait, wait wait, we have to show this because it's like look how small that is.
Hey, Shelly.
It's what you do with it. It's not the size
Well...
It's so good, yum.
After you
Oh, oh
Wow. Oh, wow. It really is the worst
It's just the worst the old ketchup and mayonnaise.
Think I won.
Good Lord
This is harder than going for three days to the South China Sea.
I was less nauseous on the open ocean.
You're getting this right you're getting this
Excellent now I win
Let's send us home. I got us a cheesecake.
I'm pretty sure it's not a cheesecake. It's a cheese,
space, cake. It literally looks like there's a piece of cheese on top of that
You sound like you've been through
an ordeal Shelley.
So moist.
I hate that word.
Moist
Cheese space cake. Oh my god. There really is a piece of cheese on top. Yep
Yeah, it's cheesecake
Sweet little salty
That's fighting everything else I put in my stomach over the past half hour.
Well, we survived.
We did. Well, we don't know. We you know poison sometimes takes up 24 hours you set in
So if you're in Taiwan
Be sure to visit a 7-eleven. They actually have many delicious things
I mean, we literally tried to choose the worst things to troll each other. So we now regret that deeply yeah, yeah
As long as you just like stick to one thing
You'll probably be okay, but Shelley, well, I was in 7/11
I did see one thing that you can only get in a
Taiwanese 7-eleven. If you can't get in the US then I think you will like hold out your hands and close your eyes
Keep them closed. There you go.
Sailor Moon!
For when you're fighting evil by moonlight, uh-huh winning love by daylight. There we go
Nine-year-old. We would have been a static
What about current?
Yeah, pretty happy. Collect them all
All right, I am obviously
Tuxedo Mask. So I'll take that.
No, Shelly, that's not...
This is what she thinks of me
Well, thanks for tuning in to this special episode of China Uncensored.
Again, I'm Chris Chappell.
I'm Shelly Zhang.
See you in Taiwan
We're gonna go be sick now