Chris Chappell here.
On this episode of China Uncensored,
I thought I'd get out of New York City.
Come down to Washington DC, the nation's capitol,
For one.
Very.
Important reason.
Another thing happening in DC today:
A rally marking 17 years since the Chinese
Communist Party
began its brutal persecution of the Falun
Gong
a popular meditation practice.
But like most people in the country right now,
I’m finding it hard to stay focused when...
OH MAN IS THAT A PIKACHU?!
But 20 minutes later,
my phone was almost out of battery,
so I decided to do the next best thing
check out this rally.
The house of representatives has formally
recognized
the persecution of Falun Gong practitioners
by the Communist Chinese regime.
We have sent a message loud and clear
to the Chinese Communist Party
that we call on China to immediately stop
its inhumane and unethical practice of organ
harvesting.
So, it’s been a big year for Falun Gong.
After a decade knowing that practitioners
in China
were being killed en masse for their organs,
people are finally talking about it.
What do you think of the organ harvesting of Falun Gong practitioners?
I had no idea until I talked to one of the gentlemen with it earlier.
I had never heard of Falun Dafa in my life.
I didn't know this was going on in China.
So this has been like a real education thing, so I want to check out.
This is what happens when people aren’t
watching enough China Uncensored.
But even if it isn’t common knowledge,
the tide is changing.
Earlier this year,
a documentary about organ harvesting, Human
Harvest,
wins a prestigious Peabody Award.
Then, The US House of Representatives
passes a resolution condemning organ harvesting.
Then, this report comes out.
It contains 680 pages of evidence that the
Chinese regime
has been murdering prisoners of conscience
for their organs.
Maybe even more than a million.
And inside China,
things have been changing as well.
Because with all this international attention,
guess who doesn’t wanted to be blamed for
persecuting Falun Gong?
Chinese leader Xi Jinping.
And Xi’s whole anti-corruption campaign
right now
just happens to be targeting his political
rivals,
who just happen to be the people
who followed former Chinese leader and mummified
toad,
Jiang Zemin to persecute Falun Gong.
So it’s convenient that China’s organ
transplant official
called out Jiang’s former right hand man,
and live-action Thwomp, Zhou Yongkang,
as the “big tiger” responsible for organ
harvesting from prisoners.
Which of course makes Xi’s people look blameless.
And Xi’s anti-corruption campaign
has already arrested a huge number of officials,
including more than 150 with the rank of vice-minister
or higher,
many with ties to Jiang Zemin.
Most recently, reports say that Jiang’s
son has been put under house arrest.
And it looks like China’s propaganda chief,
who is Jiang’s highest ally still in power,
may be targeted next.
And Xi’s anti-corruption investigators just
announced
they were looking into the 610 Office,
the organization that Jiang created to persecute
Falun Gong.
It seems like Xi Jinping is truly out, to
catch ‘em all.
Do you think if you made,
held this rally at a Pokemon gym,
that a lot of people would show up.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.