On this episode of China Uncensored,
China's master plan to rule the world...'s
financial system.
Hello and welcome to China Uncensored,
I'm your host Chris Chappell.
If you've been watching this show for a while,
you know that China has plans for world domination.
What's that, Shelley?
OK.
So more accurately,
Chinese leaders are trying to give China more
global influence
be it with money, politics, or Confucius
to counterbalance what it calls "Western hegemony."
China's view is that the 21st century should
belong to China.
But, according to my favorite Chinese state-run
media,
we in the West are just too arrogant to see
it.
There are some problems with this plan, though.
And one of them is that the rest of the world
doesn't really want to trade in China's currency,
which is called the yuan,
or the Renminbi.
And you need a dominant currency to be a global
hegemon.
Gotta rule 'em all!
So whose currency dominates?
Well, here's one indication.
Every five years,
the International Monetary Fund determines
what's awkwardly called the Special Drawing
Rights,
or SDR.
Think of the SDR like a basket that contains
a few different countries' currencies.
It's made up of specific amounts of US dollars,
euros, British pounds and Japanese yen.
And then the basket itself acts like a unit
of currency that countries can trade.
The IMF picked these four currencies for the
SDR because of their stability,
as well as the fact that a lot of countries
actually hold them as part of their foreign
exchange reserves.
But now,
there's a new kid in town.
The Chinese yuan.
On November 30th,
the IMF announced that the new SDR basket
is going to have some Chinese currency in
it, too.
"The IMF's executive board decided that the
Renminbi qualified for the SDR basket and
existing criteria."
So what's going to happen when this takes
effect next October?
Well there's only so much room in the basket.
So now, something's got to make way for Mao.
In the new SDR,
the yuan will make up an even higher portion
than the pound or yen.
Some media are saying that the yuan could
eventually rival the US dollar.
This is a huge move by the IMF.
Partly because China is the only non-democracy
to be included in the SDR.
And that's a big concern for some people
because of the heavy-handed approach China
sometimes takes.
"Just the difficulty I think is that maybe
in the light of some of the extreme policies
that the government have been implementing
with regards to financial markets in China
such as devaluing the yuan,
such as making institutions not being able
to sell their shares for a certain number
of months,
quite extreme policies that are taking place,
maybe suggesting that China is not quite ready
for this."
See?
China isn't ready for this.
It's going to completely destroy...
Wait.
What's that Shelley?
Roll the rest of the clip?
"You know, if the IMF can bring China in and
consult with them on the kind of policies
that are being used in more developed countries,
China can be brought on board and be shown
the benefits of doing so.
It has only got to be a positive in terms
of Chinese reforms."
Wait, so it's a good thing?
Shelley, I'm getting mixed messages.
Can you just come over here and help sort
this out?
Sure, Chris.
So China's inclusion in the SDR:
Danger to America, or Extreme Danger to America?
Uh, neither, Chris.
This could actually be a good thing.
The US government has been frustrated for
a long time with the way the Chinese government
manipulates its currency.
And now getting into the SDR has forced China
to clean up its act somewhat.
And if Chinese leaders want to continue to
make the yuan more influential,
they will have to make reforms that will eventually
allow the yuan to be traded at a fair price
determined by the international market.
Ahh, so, China thinks it's getting more power,
but it's a trap.
Like what happened to Jafar.
"You wanted to be a genie?
You got it."
"What?"
"And everything that goes with it."
"Noooooo!"
Well... sort of.
It's true, there are a lot of constraints
that come with being a global reserve currency.
For example, now China is supposed to be more
transparent and enforce regulations.
But China wasn't tricked into it like Jafar
was.
I think Chinese leaders were just ready to
make the sacrifices.
So what benefits does China actually get from
the yuan being in the SDR?
It'll probably encourage more countries to
use yuan in their foreign transactions.
It'll also make it easier for China to borrow
money.
But the biggest effect is symbolic:
It raises China's prestige.
It's a double-edged sword, though,
because this will also probably push up the
value of the yuan.
And that will make it harder for China to
sell its exports.
That's not good news in the short term,
because China is an export-driven economy
that's already in a slowdown.
But in the long-term it's healthier for the
Chinese economy if there's less artificial
control over the currency.
So, this could eventually be a good thing.
So what does this mean for the US dollar?
It doesn't really affect the dollar at all.
What really makes a currency powerful is whether
people actually want to use it in business
transactions.
The vast majority of global payments are still
made in dollars or euros.
This year, only 2.8 percent of global payments
were in yuan.
So again, it's mainly symbolic.
For the American economy overall,
it's better if the yuan goes up in value.
So this could eventually be a good thing.
So China's currency isn't the greatest threat
America's ever faced?
Shark attacks are a greater threat.
Shark attacks are as big a threat as China?!
All right, everyone out of the water!
Thanks, Shelley.
Meet me later today at the beach.
Bring your harpoon.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below,
and subscribe for more episodes of China Uncensored.
Once again, I'm Chris Chappell.
See you next time.