Chinese Media Threatens Missile Strikes on
Australia
China targets climate activist Grerta Thunberg
And the US describes China using the G-word.
That and more on this week’s China news
headlines
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
This episode is sponsored by Daily Pnut.
The news can be a tough pill to swallow.
That's why Daily Pnut gives you a daily dose
of news in equal parts humor and substance.
Speaking of entertaining and substantial news...
Tensions between China and Australia are at
an all time high.
The Chinese Communist Party launched a trade
war with Australia a year ago, after Prime
Minister Scott Morrison called for an investigation
into the origin of the coronavirus.
Why would the world need an investigation
anyway?
Everyone knows the coronavirus didn’t come
from China.
It’s clear that the virus came from the
US army...
Making frozen food…
Out of auto parts packaging.
See?
Case closed.
But a year after Australia’s call for an
investigation, the Chinese Communist Party
has still refused.
And they’re still mad about it.
This week, my favorite Chinese state-run newspaper,
the Global Times said China should be ready
to launch a devastating missile strike on
Australia.
In this op-ed,
Global Times Chief Editor Hu Xijin writes,
China should be ready to make “long-range
strikes on the military facilities and relevant
key facilities on Australian soil.”
That could happen, should Australia do anything
foolish like send troops to defend Taiwan
from a Chinese invasion.
Last month, a top Australian security official
warned of China beating the drums of war.
He didn’t specifically say China, but it
was clear enough.
Which is ridiculous.
As the Global Times says, “China loves peace.”
Especially the pieces of Australia left after
a Chinese missile strike!
China also just suspended its economic dialogue
with Australia.
But keep in mind, you can’t think of Hu
Xijinas some rogue newspaper editor.
Among Chinese state-run media, the Global
Times is the most hawkish, over-the-top mouthpiece
of the Chinese Communist Party.
But it’s still a mouthpiece.
This is part of the Party’s year-long attempt
to terrorize Australia into submission.
Make it seem like a fight would be so bloody,
there’s no point in even having the fight.
The truth is, when you stand up to a bully,
they tend to back down pretty quick.
But the Global Times is on a roll this week.
They’re also targeting Greta Thunberg.
You see, according to this new report from
the Rhodium Group, China produces more greenhouse
gases than the rest of the developed world
combined.
And climate activist Greta Thunberg finally
had some harsh words for China.
She said China is “ruining future and present
living conditions.”
Enter the Global Times to say Thunberg isn’t
knowledgeable enough to understand climate
change.
She’s also a puppet of Western politicians.
It also describes her as “the Swedish teenager
who skipped school for so-called climate protests”.
This is not the first time Thunberg has run
afoul of the Global Times.
Last year it was for her support of Hong Kong
protesters.
The Global Times said she was “ignorant”
“Despicable”
and “nothing but a clown.”
I wonder why powerful men are so scared of
Grerta Thunberg?
Wait, I get it.
I’m scared of her, too.
And after the break, Chinese state-run media
makes up lies all the time—but this one’s
hilarious.
Welcome back.
It’s not just the Global Times that had
a week of winning it.
State-run China Daily posted this video to
Twitter to promote China tourism.
Wow, beautiful.
Except the video is not from China.
It’s from the Swiss Alps.
And you might think, ok so they misidentified
the country.
People make mistakes.
But it gets worse.
“The Chinese communist propaganda version
of the video was slightly edited, including
flipping the image horizontally, making colour
corrections, and seemingly doctoring a stick
into the dog’s mouth.”
Wow, they did a good job with the stick.
(
Not a good job with the propaganda.
And state-run Xinhua has registered as a foreign
agent in the US.
It only took less than three years for them
to get around to it.
They had been ordered to back in 2018.
Xinhua joins two other Chinese state-run media—CGTN
and China Daily—as being registered foreign
agents.
That means they’re required to disclose
their annual budget and expenditures to the
US government.
Let’s hope that Xinhua’s budget disclosures
are more accurate than China’s other statistics.
The National Bureau of Statistics finally
released their 10-year census data.
Earlier Western media reports said that China’s
population fell for the first time in 50 years.
But now, after weeks of delay, the official
statistics show that China’s population
actually rose.
Imagine that.
Some China analysts have noticed something...funny...about
China’s latest statistics.
A sudden unusual bump in the population growth
rate in 2020.
All of this is to push back against the idea
that China is facing a demographic crisis,
which it is.
I talked about that crisis in an episode last
week.
More developments in the South China Sea.
The Philippines has flagged nearly 300 incursions
by Chinese militia boats.
The government of the Philippines says it
has logged what it calls "illegal incursions"
into its waters by 287 boats with Chinese
militia aboard.
The country's task force on the South China
sea said in a statement that the incident
may prompt possible diplomatic actions.
Yes, diplomatic action like...being reluctant
to confront China.
Meanwhile, Taiwan is denouncing China’s
shameless lies.
Specifically about refusing Taiwan access
to the World Health Organization.
China prevents Taiwan from having access to
the WHO, because, as China’s foreign ministry
said, “Nobody cared more for Taiwan’s
people than the Chinese government.”
Taiwan’s Foreing Minister Joseph Wu responded
by saying “After what Beijing has done to
Xinjiang, Tibet & Hong Kong, no sane person
would believe it could take care of Taiwan’s
health needs or otherwise.
Thank God we aren’t under China’s control!
Please help us keep it at a distance.”
Now that’s one form of social distancing
I can get behind!
That and social distancing because of my crippling
anxiety around people in general.
And US Secretary of State Antony Blinken has
decided to make the Chinese Communist Party
very unhappy this week.
He said, “There is no reasonable justification
for Taiwan’s continued exclusion from [The
World Health Organization].”
And he demanded the WHO allow Taiwan to attend
an upcoming WHO meeting, the World Health
Assembly.
You know, being that Taiwan is part of the
world.
But Blinken didn’t stop there.
He also announced the State Department is
sanctioning a Chinese official involved in
the persecution of the Falun Gong spiritual
group.
China broadly criminalizes religious expression
and continues to commit crimes against humanity
and genocide against Muslim Uyghurs and members
of other religious and ethnic minority groups.
Today, I’m announcing the designation of
Yu Hui, former office director of the so-called
Central Leading Group Preventing and Dealing
with Heretical Religions, of Chengdu, for
his involvement in gross violations of human
rights, namely, the arbitrary detention of
Falun Gong practitioners.
Blinken made the announcement as part of the
release of the State Department’s 2020 International
Religious Freedom Report.
And Blinken also specifically used the word
“genocide” to talk about the persecution
of Uyghurs in Xinjiang.
It shouldn’t actually be a big deal to use
the word genocide to describe China’s genocide—which
meets every definition of genocide under the
UN Convention on Genocide.
But sadly, the US is still one of the few
countries to officially use the G-word.
So props to Blinken for having the B-word.
And after the break, Hong Kong is going after
journalists.
With a bat!
Welcome back.
Nearly a year ago, Beijing passed the Hong
Kong National Security Law.
It aims to take away as much freedom of speech
and press as possible, while still pretending
that Hong Kong has its own autonomous government.
But when laws aren’t enough to stop the
free press, sometimes a more direct approach
is needed.
This is The Epoch Times.
It’s one of the last independent Chinese-language
media in Hong Kong.
Last week, a Hong Kong reporter for the The
Epoch Times was attacked by a man with a bat.
“The assailant hit her with the bat more
than 10 times before fleeing in a car.”
Takes a big man to beat a defenseless woman
with a bat.
The Epoch Times is a newspaper critical of
the Chinese Communist Party.
Last month, its Hong Kong printing press was
attacked by men with sledge hammers.
And the US State Department, along with other
US lawmakers, have condemned the assault.
Meanwhile, Hong Kong chief Executive Carrie
Lam is pushing for laws to stop so-called
“fake news.”
Those will likely be aimed at stopping pro-democracy
media like the Epoch Times and Apple Daily
from criticizing the Chinese Communist Party.
On Monday, we’ll have a longer episode about
Hong Kong’s crackdown on the media.
And also we’ll have the Epoch Times reporter
who was attacked join us on our weekly podcast,
China Unscripted.
Yes, we also do a podcast every week.
In more Hong Kong news, Hong Kong legislators
have officially passed a patriotic oath law.
Certain high level lawmakers and public servants
have to swear an oath of loyalty to China—and
now the law adds district councillors to that
list.
But that’s not all.
The law also includes ways that people could
be disqualified for breaching their oath.
“Including by refusing to recognise China's
sovereignty over Hong Kong, supporting independence,
seeking foreign interference, ‘insulting’
a flag, as well as ‘endangering national
security.’”
Insulting a flag, huh?
Hey flag.
You look funny.
Well, guess I’m never going to be a Hong
Kong local district councillor.
The Biden Administration is reversing a Trump
era blacklist of Chinese phone company Xiaomi.
The Trump Administration had put it on a trade
black list because of links between Xiaomi
and the Chinese military.
Seven other Chinese companies were put on
the same blacklist.
But Xiaomi sued, and won in a US court.
“Soon after the victory, Reuters reported
that other Chinese companies placed on the
same blacklist were considering similar lawsuits.”
A fantastic development.
See, by law, all Chinese companies have to
work with the Chinese military.
They call it civil military fusion.
And now, Chinese military-linked companies
like Xiaomi will be able to sell their hardware
devices in the US again—to unsuspecting
consumers.
And this episode is sponsored by Daily Pnut.
If you want more daily news—that goes beyond
what we cover in our weekly headlines episode—check
out Daily Pnut.
It’s a bunch of fast, timely news stories,
selected for you and available to read on
your phone, tablet, or computer.
Reading Daily Pnut is an easy way to filter
out the noise and learn more about the world
news that matters.
Join more than 250,000 other readers.
Education and entertainment—delivered right
to your inbox, every morning.
And the best part is, it’s free.
So sign up for Daily Pnut now.
Use the link in the Description below.
I’m Chris Chappell, thanks for watching.