Uyghur ex-officials
Are given the death sentence
Over a Uyghur textbook
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
It’s no longer a secret that China is giving
“special treatment” to ethnic minorities
like the Uyghur Muslims in Xinjiang.
In the last few months, countries around the
world have started calling that special treatment
genocide.
And last month, the US and its allies sanctioned
Chinese officials for genocide.
“Genocide” includes separating Uyghur
families and throwing them into concentration
camps.
Or forcing birth control on Uyghur women to
suppress the population.
And let’s not forget killing Uyghurs and
harvesting their organs.
And then there’s the cultural genocide.
Like silencing the Uyghur language.
For example, in the internment camps, Uyghurs
are forced to speak Mandarin and not their
native language.
You see this?
Why this is just a language class.
Today’s lesson: How to say “Thank you
Chinese Communist Party, for giving me all
of this free re-education.”
But it’s not enough for Uyghurs, including
Uyghur children, to learn Mandarin.
They also need to learn Chinese Communist
Party propaganda, with a hearty dose of historical
revisionism.
What happens if they’re not learning to
love the motherland?
The death sentence.
The Chinese regime has recently handed death
sentences to Uyghur former officials for “writing
and publishing school textbooks designed to
‘split the country’”.
Two former education officials were given
suspended death sentences, while five more
Uyghurs, including book editors, were given
long prison sentences, some up to life in
prison.
Now in China, a suspended death sentence means
it could be changed to life in prison instead.
Which is the...good news?
So what were these men’s crimes?
They were accused of adding separatist ideas
to Uyghur language textbooks for elementary
and secondary school kids, starting in 2002.
Those textbooks were then used in Xinjiang
for more than a decade—before authorities
changed their minds in 2016, and decided they
were in fact separatist books that harm young
people.
“25 million copies of the textbook were
printed and distributed in Xinjiang.
And tens of thousands of Uyghur educators
have used it for 13 years, causing extremely
serious harm.”
The son of one of the imprisoned book editors
pushed back on the Chinese regime’s claims.
He points out that these textbooks were approved
by the state for 13 years.
And he says “China is trying to erase history
and write a new narrative.”
Whaaaaat?
Erasing history and writing a new narrative?
Does that sound like something the Chinese
Communist Party would do?
But the Party is going even further to rewrite
the history of Xinjiang.
I’ll show you how after the break.
Welcome back.
Former Uyghur education officials have been
thrown in prison for an old textbook featuring
no-longer-approved history.
And now Chinese state run CGTN has released
a documentary film about them—a full hour
of villainizing these “two-faced” Uyghurs.
Murat Sheripjan says even the term “two-faced”
doesn’t properly describe such persons.
They are the enemy, the enemy in the shadows”
The documentary of course includes televised
forced confessions from these “enemies in
the shadows.”
The idea was to use the power given by the
Party and the people to spread our ethnic
chauvinist sentiments and extremist errors
among more Uyghur people.
It was meant to control their minds, influence
them in childhood in order to turn them into
separatists.By framing these Uyghur officials
as hardened criminals, Chinese state-run media
is attempting to justify the Party’s genocide
of the Uyghur people.
They had to do it to fight terrorism, guys.
Terrorism like, showing a medal worn by a
historical figure.
Take this graphic for example.
The national emblem is that of East Turkistan.
It shouldn’t appear in textbooks at all.
The East Turkestan Republic was a short-lived
state that occupied the upper west region
of Xinjiang briefly from 1944-1949.
The man pictured in the textbook was one of
the presidents of the East Turkestan Republic.
But no one is supposed to know that.
We shouldn’t be teaching this history at
all!
Especially since, according to Chinese state-run
media, there has never even been an East Turkestan
state.
Really, it’s much safer for society if children
lose all connection with their cultural roots.
This is the legend of seven heroic Uyghur
girls.
It’s all fabricated.
Han Chinese soldiers trapped them at a cliff
and they jumped to their death to defend their
homeland.
It’s meant to incite ethnic hatred and it
will misinform the students.
Look, everyone knows that the only true Chinese
history is the one where the Han Chinese are
the heroes.
The documentary claims that these Uyghur textbooks
are directly responsible for what the documentary
refers to as the July 5th Incident.
But the outside world calls the July 5th Incident
the “Urumqi Massacre”—because Chinese
soldiers massacred people!
It happened after ethnic riots broke out in
Xinjiang’s capital, Urumqi, in 2009.
“According to witness reports, an estimated
1000 or more people, most of them ethnic Uyghurs,
were shot dead during that one and a half
hour period of time.”
And after massacring a bunch of Uyghurs, the
Chinese Communist Party imprisoned thousands
more.
And they locked down the entire Xinjiang region
for months—including cutting off the internet
entirely.
But maybe the Chinese Communist Party is onto
something here.
Children’s books are definitely the main
source of terrorism and separatism.
And the only solution is to lock up an entire
ethnic group.
At least until the Chinese regime writes new
children’s books.
Like “Horton Hears a Separatist and Reports
Him to the Neighborhood Committee.”
“Where the Wild Splittists Are.”
“James and the Giant Hegemon.”
Or my personal favorite, “Oh the Re-educational
Places You’ll Go!”
See, with these two-faced officials safely
behind bars, the Chinese Communist Party can
finally lead the Uyghurs to a brighter future,
with patriotic children’s textbooks.
This is Part One of the first grade’s Uyghur-language
textbook.
Here's the national emblem, and the national
flag, and the statement “We are Chinese”.
Here is the flag-raising ceremony.”
What are we telling the students with these
pictures?
They should know that they are citizens of
the People’s Republic of China, that Xinjiang
is an inalienable part of the motherland.”
What a happy ending.
Everything is rectified.
And the Uyghur children can learn to dance
like the happy ethnic minority they’re supposed
to be.
Which means it’s a perfect time to watch
China’s new hit musical inspired by the
Hollywood movie La La Land.
It’s called “The Wings of Songs”, and
showcases the beautiful rich life of ethnic
minority groups in Xinjiang.
Including all of their happy ethnic dancing.
I mean, it totally works.
It’s just like the Sound of Music, but in
the end Captain Von Trapp joins the Nazis.
And now it’s time for me to answer a question
from a member of the China Uncensored 50 Cent
Army—fans who support the show on the crowd
funding website Patreon.
Ringleader asks, “Hey Chris, how would "Xi
the Poo" react if the U.S. and/or the U.K.
established a full embassy and/or military
base in the free and independent country of
Taiwan?”
Well I know how they would feel.
The feelings of the Chinese people would be
deeply hurt.
What would the Communist Party do about it?
Right now, there’s not a whole lot they
can do.
They would make a big stink about it.
The Foreign Affairs ministry would make all
kinds of statements, there’d be angry tweets.
And you know what, there might even be some
sanctions.
Some US officials might not be allowed to
travel to China anymore.
I also imagine there would be a continuation
of military maneuvers around Taiwan, that
would quietly shrink over time.
Because even though Xi Jinping might say the
US and China are equal now...
...the truth is a little different.
However, if the US shows weakness, and the
Chinese regime is able to take over Taiwan,
the power would shift.
If the Chinese regime manages to even partially
replace the US dollar with its own currency,
the power will also shift.
We just did a full episode about that.
The Communist Party’s goal is to replace
the US as the world’s biggest superpower.
There’s still time to stop that from happening.
But not a lot of time.
Thanks for your question Ringleader.
And thank you for watching.
Be like Ringleader and support China Uncensored
through the crowdfunding website Patreon.
Go to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
The link is below.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.