Problems at a Chinese nuclear reactor
A record number of Chinese jets harass Taiwan
And more arrests in Hong Kong
That and more on this week’s China news
headlines
Welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Starting off our great week in China, there
may have possibly been a leak at a nuclear
power plant.
French power group EDF said on Monday it had
been informed of a build-up of inert gases
at its plant in China, and had called for
a meeting with its Chinese partner.
CNN also reported that Framatome, the EDF
unit which designed the reactor, had warned
of an "imminent radiological threat."
Okay, it is true there is a potentially dangerous
issue at the Taishan Nuclear power plant.
But according to the Chinese Communist Party,
everything is fine.
State-run China General Nuclear Power Group,
the majority owner of the joint venture with
EDF said in a statement on its website on
Sunday that operations at the nuclear power
station met safety rules and the surrounding
environment is safe.
See, it’s safe!
Would the Chinese Communist Party ever lie
to the world to cover up a dangerous leak?
Yet despite the assurances, the US is apparently
still looking into the nuclear plant leak.
The French company warned that “The Chinese
safety authority was raising the acceptable
limits for radiation detection outside the
Taishan Nuclear Power Plant in Guangdong province
in order to avoid having to shut it down.”
See?
China doesn’t have to lie about the data.
They can just change the definition of how
much radiation is safe!
Problem solved.
But here’s a hint that there may still be
a small problem.
As CNN put it, “It is unusual that a foreign
company, [Framatome], would unilaterally reach
out to the American government for help when
its Chinese state-owned partner is yet to
acknowledge a problem exists.”
Yeah, especially when it’s a French company.
Since when do the French ask for help from
the Americans?
Ultimately, this situation is pretty typical
for joint ventures in China.
The foreign company often realizes too late
their Chinese counterparts aren’t as honest
or cooperative as they’d like.
Especially when it has to do with a Chinese
nuclear plant that was supposed to be a propaganda
symbol.
It was “the first of its type in the world
to enter operation in 2018, after delays hit
similar projects in Finland and France”.
Is it possible that the Chinese Communist
Party may have cut some corners to get this
nuclear plant up and running?
Nah.
Speaking of cutting corners, a gas pipeline
in China exploded.
It destroyed a busy market in Shiyan city
in central Hubei Province.
As of this recording, Chinese state state
media say 25 people have died.
But we all know how honest China is about
statistics.
Especially when it involves local government
screwups.
But as I said in a recent episode about enormous
sinkholes opening up throughout China,
the Chinese Communist Party tends to care
more about the look of a city than the lives
inside the city.
Corners get cut.
And coming up after the break, the G7 tries
to counter China.
Welcome back.
The G7 is a group of the most powerful economies.
They had their annual meeting and awkward
family photo last week.
A big part of that meeting was about countering
China.
We did a full rundown of their plan on our
other channel, America Uncovered.
Yes, we have another channel.
But the G7 this year also talked about China
issues that it ignored in the past—Taiwan,
the East and South China Seas, and human rights
abuses in Xinjiang and Hong Kong.
Obviously China is not happy.
Foreign Ministry Spokesman Zhao Lijian said,
“The U.S. is ill and very ill indeed.
The G-7 had better take its pulse and come
up with a prescription.”
That sounds like a swipe at President Biden
being old and confused.
But the Communist Party isn’t just upset
at the G7, they’re also mad at NATO.
NATO called China a global security challenge.
Something they haven’t done before.
We’re talking baby steps here.
NATO only expressed concern about China’s
growing military.
While NATO still considers Russia a threat,
China merely presents challenges.
But even that was enough to infuriate the
Chinese regime.
Which responded that “China is actually
a force for peace but will defend itself if
threatened.”
Which is like a burglar saying he’s all
about protecting private property, and if
you try to take anything from his sack he’ll
knife you.
China once again proved how devoted it was
to peace this week, by sending a record 28
fighter jets toward Taiwan.
That was in response to G7 leaders calling
for a peaceful resolution to the Taiwan-China
issue.
The problem is, the Chinese Communist Party
is never about peace.
It’s about leaving the world in pieces.
Meanwhile, the US sent the aircraft carrier
Ronald Reagan to the South China Sea, along
with two guided missile destroyers.
The US said it was part of routine freedom
of navigation operations in international
waters.
Chinese state media called it “cold war
baiting”.
Unlike flying fighter jets toward a country
they’ve threatened to invade.
Last month, a botched marathon in China resulted
in 21 deaths.
An investigation was launched into why organizers
ignored extreme weather warnings.
And now the Communist Party chief who was
responsible has mysteriously died.
Well it wasn’t that mysterious.
He fell from a building.
Don’t worry, local police say it wasn’t
homicide.
But they also aren’t saying it was suicide.
How many other options are there?
Was he just walking on the roof of a building
and slipped?
Speaking of mysterious deaths, a top Communist
official at a University in Shanghai was stabbed
to death.
Yes, universities in China are all overseen
by a Party official.
This one was stabbed to death by a fellow
professor.
But details are sparse because Communist Party
run media don’t really like talking about
Communist Party officials being murdered.
Instead they prefer to focus on how much the
Chinese people love the Communist Party!
After all, “International polls have indicated
over and again that Chinese people’s approval
ratings of the CPC and the government rank
the highest worldwide.”
Wow, how do they manage?
Well, the secret is, “EVERYTHING IS FOR
THE PEOPLE.”
And yes, state media wrote that in all caps.
Speaking of communist run newspapers, the
New York Times!
(They conducted a rare interview with the
Chinese scientist potentially involved in
the coronavirus lab leak.
The virologist is Dr. Shi Zhengli.
She’s known as China’s bat woman for her
research on bat coronaviruses.
Like the kind she was doing at the Wuhan Institute
of Virology.
That was getting US government funding approved
by Dr. Fauci.
To do research making coronaviruses more contagious
and deadly.
Did I mention the Wuhan Institute of Virology
had known safety issues?
Or that some scientists have been saying for
over a year that there are signs the coronavirus
was engineered?
Anyway, as the New York Times says, “The
idea that the virus may have escaped from
a lab had long been widely dismissed by scientists
as implausible and shunned by others for its
connection with former President Donald J.
Trump.”
But now that Trump is impeached, and out of
office, and banned from social media, can
we *please* start investigating the truth
of a deadly virus that was never actually
connected to Trump in the first place?
It turns out, still no.
That’s why the New York Times interviewed
the virologist at the center of all this—to
dismiss the idea once and for all.
“Dr. Shi has denied these accusations, and
now finds herself defending the reputation
of her lab and, by extension, that of her
country.”
You see, saying the coronavirus may have leaked
from a lab is racist and xenophobic.
The New York Times says Dr. Shi “could barely
contain her frustration”.
“I don’t know how the world has come to
this, constantly pouring filth on an innocent
scientist.”
I’m glad the New York Times is still doing
the propaganda work of the Chinese Communist
Party.
But you know who isn’t doing the CCP’s
work?
Romania.
They just banned Chinese telecom Huawei from
the country’s 5G network.
Every US administration, from Obama, to Trump
to Biden has warned about the risk of Huawei.
The fact that these three guys agree on anything
tells you something.
And more and more countries have been joining
the US in banning Huawei from 5G networks.
It’s part of what the US State Department
calls the Clean Network.
Just another Trump era initiative the Biden
Administration is carrying on.
And...Hong Kong police have arrested more
democracy advocates.
I’ll tell you why after the break.
Welcome back.
Over in Hong Kong, people celebrated the two
year anniversary of the 2019 anti-extradition
protest.
It launched months of protests against the
Chinese Communist Party and its growing control
of Hong Kong.
And of course ended with the Hong Kong national
security law.
Which was pretty much everything they were
protesting against.
Which is why this anniversary was celebrated
by police arresting people for commemorating
it.
But that’s not all!
Hong Kong police have had a busy week.
Hundreds of police raided the offices of the
Apple Daily, a pro-democracy newspaper.
They also arrested the editor-in-chief and
other executives.
Police said Apple Daily was violating the
national security law by “publishing articles
which called for sanctions on Beijing or [Hong
Kong].”
When other media tried to ask the police which
Apple Daily articles violated the national
security law, the police refused to answer.
It’s almost like they’re trying to make
all Hong Kong media afraid of publishing things
that could get them arrested.
Police also froze Apple Daily’s assets.
So it’s not clear how long the paper can
keep going.
But Apple Daily defiantly printed half a million
copies the day after the police raid, with
the message that “everyone has to hang in
there.”
Meanwhile, Jimmy Lai , the founder of Apple
Daily, is being put on trial.
He faces life imprisonment.
For what?
Why, for violating the national security law.
Somehow.
Something to do with colluding with foreigners.
To do something.
Look, they don’t need a reason.
On the bright side, the American anti-Communist
organization, the Victims of Communism Memorial
Foundation , awarded Jimmy Lai a top honor
for his lifelong commitment to democracy in
Hong Kong.
Hopefully he can accept the award in person
one day.
But if he ends up in prison for life, they
also will present Jimmy with this very nice
cake.
Jimmy, we put a special ingredient in the
But I’m happy to say I won’t need to bake
a cake for Hong Kong activist Agnes Chow . She’s
been released from prison.
She never should have been in prison in the
first place.
That’s according to the Congressional–Executive
Commission on China , a bipartisan group of
U.S. lawmakers.
They tweeted “A more appropriate action
to commemorate the 2nd anniversary of 2019
Hong Kong protests would have been to drop
charges against those who participated in
those protests & release all other political
prisoners.”
Which sounds to me like...these hostile foreign
forces have been colluding with everyone in
Hong Kong!
China’s gonna have to lock up everybody
now!
I’ve got a lot of baking to do.
But first, it’s time to answer a question
from a member of the China Uncensored 50 Cent
Army, fans who support us and our efforts
to expose the truth about the Chinese Communist
Party, by contributing through crowd funding
website Patreon.
Mika Ranta asks “That sinkhole looks like
PhotoShop or something.”
Ah, Mika is referring to this thumbnail image
from our recent episode China’s MASSIVE
Sinkholes Are Swallowing Cars and Buses.
A lot of people asked me that actually.
It does look photoshopped, doesn’t it?
After all, it's kind of hard to believe this
is real.
It’s real.
Sometimes things that happen in China are
beyond belief.
Thanks for your question and your support,
Mika.
And a big thank you to everyone who supports
China Uncensored on Patreon.
We could not do this show without you.
So thank you for joining us in the fight to
expose the Chinese Communist Party to the
world.
If you’re interested in joining, head over
to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
You’ll get a bunch of cool perks, including
the chance to have me answer your question
on the show!
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next
time.