China readies its military
After Chinese leader Xi Jinping
Vows to take Taiwan
But the US may have a different idea.
Plus...
I have a beard!
Welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
The Chinese military is preparing for war.
Again.
In fact, for a country that hasn’t seen
real combat
since a brief war with Vietnam in 1979,
China seems to be preparing for war a lot.
At least once a year it seems.
I mean, it’s good to be prepared, right?
You never know when a war might sneak up behind
you
and suddenly happen through no fault of your
own.
But these “preparation for war” headlines
aren’t necessarily that alarming by themselves.
After all, the US military talks about
combat readiness all the time,
which is essentially being prepared for war.
But could there be any indication about a
specific war
that the Chinese Communist Party is possibly
getting ready for?
“Taiwanese independence would be a disaster.
Those are the words of Chinese President Xi
Jinping,
who made the comments in a speech on Wednesday
in Beijing.
Taiwan is China's most sensitive issue
and is claimed as a breakaway province of
a ‘one China.’
And in his speech,
Xi said China will strive to lead Taiwan to
a bright future under Beijing's rule.”
Yes, the future looks bright for China and
Taiwan,
and unrelatedly, Xi Jinping called on the
PLA to,
you guessed it, prepare for war.
But I’m sure this preparing for war stuff
doesn’t have
anything to do with Xi’s speech on Taiwan.
Actually, it does.
It’s pretty much a warning.
Xi gave his speech about Taiwan
on the 40th anniversary
of the major change in China’s Taiwan policy.
In 1979, the Chinese Communist Party
stopped saying it would “liberate” Taiwan,
and instead said it would “peacefully reunify”
with Taiwan.
By force if necessary.
By the way,
even the word “reunification”
is a pretty clever propaganda term.
In Chinese, the term is actually “unification.”
But if you translate it as “reunification”
that makes it seem like Taiwan
was historically always a part of China.
Which is not true.
Now even though Xi’s speech
caused a lot of controversy,
it wasn’t technically a change
in the People’s Republic of China’s
current policy toward Taiwan.
In fact, the language was less harsh
than a speech Xi gave as last March,
when he said China was ready to fight
a bloody battle against its enemies.
And for the military to prepare for war…
which, again, he says ALL THE TIME.
But this year, he struck a different tone.
“Chinese people don't attack Chinese people.”
Which has been true exactly...
never, in Chinese history.
I mean...Mao.
Xi Jinping actually had lifted that line
from a 1995 speech about Taiwan
given by his biggest political rival,
former Chinese leader Jiang Zemin.
Which is kind of like Tupac lifting a line
from Biggie.
Look them up on Wikipedia.
There were also other goodies
sprinkled throughout Xi Jinping’s speech.
Like when he said China, quote,
“achieved a great victory in frustrating
the Taiwan independence movement
and other separatist activities.”
Which sounds to me like he wants bragging
rights
for illegally interfering in Taiwan’s recent
elections.
Now Xi’s not technically taking credit.
But I mean, if you want to give him credit...
Xi also mentioned the One Country,
Two Systems model a bunch of times.
That would mean Taiwan can become part of
the Communist People’s Republic of China,
but would still get to keep a degree of political
autonomy.
One Country, Two Systems.
It would be totally fine, Xi Jinping says.
“After peaceful reunification,
Taiwan will have lasting peace
and the people will enjoy good and prosperous
lives.
With the great motherland's support,
Taiwan compatriots' welfare will be even better,
their development space will be even greater,
they can stand more upright in the international
community
with more confidence,
they will be safer and they will have more
dignity.”
Yeah, just like Hong Kong!
The one country two systems policy is in action
there,
and it’s worked great!
Well, except for a few minor things,
like multiple pro-democracy figures being
harassed,
jailed, and kicked out of office.
Oh, and prominent foreign activists
being banned from visiting Hong Kong.
Oh, and a bunch of broken promises
about letting people there vote.
Plus Chinese state security spying on foreign
journalists.
But otherwise, it’s great!
And yet, for some reason,
Taiwan’s President Tsai Ing-wen
just doesn’t see it like that.
First, I must emphasize that
we have never accepted the "1992 Consensus."
The fundamental reason is because
the Beijing authorities' definition of the
"1992 Consensus"
is "one China" and "one country, two systems."
The speech delivered by China's leader today
has confirmed our misgivings.
Here, I want to reiterate that Taiwan
absolutely will not accept "one country, two
systems."
The vast majority of Taiwanese
also resolutely oppose "one country, two systems,"
and this opposition is also a "Taiwan consensus."
In fact, even though Xi Jinping’s speech
wasn’t a departure from Chinese policy,
Tsai responded with a public break from the
1992 consensus.
The 1992 consensus established that Taiwan
and China
both agree that there is only one China,
and that Taiwan is a part of it,
but each side has their own interpretation
of what “China” means.
Essentially, each side claims that
they are the one true China.
The Chinese Communist Party doesn’t mention
this whole “interpretation” part
when they talk about the 1992 consensus,
just the part where Taiwan agrees it’s part
of China.
Now since President Tsai was elected in 2016,
she had never openly acknowledged the 1992
consensus.
And her party, the DPP,
has historically not accepted it.
But now Tsai is actively and publicly rejecting
it.
She said, “I myself expect all of Taiwan’s
political parties
to clearly state, ‘We reject “one country,
two systems.’
And there’s no need to talk about the 1992
consensus anymore,
because this term has already been defined
by Beijing
as ‘one country, two systems.’”
And Taiwan is even now, well...preparing for
war.
Maybe you guys have more in common than you
think.
And it’s really breaking Xi Jinping up.
No wonder Xi Jinping said “Taiwan is so
close,
yet so far away.”
Xi Jinping just wants to reunify with you,
Tsai.
How can you be so cruel?
But not only has Tsai taken a stronger and
stronger stance
against the People’s Republic of China,
she’s also now calling out the international
community.
“When a country that does its best
to practice democracy and shared international
values
faces threats and violation,
I believe that this is also a violation of
democracy
and those values.
If the international community does not speak
out for
and support Taiwan while it is facing such
a situation,
we have to ask which country will be next.”
But while democracy and human rights is nice
and all,
don’t you know how much money China has?!
But even though the US has official diplomatic
ties
with the communist People’s Republic of
China,
the US has for decades also had strong,
unofficial, but positive ties with Taiwan.
Last November,
two US sailed two Navy ships
through the Strait of Taiwan,
a third time for the year.
Last year also saw the Trump Administration
setting up a 255 million dollar defacto embassy
in Taiwan.
And, on the last day of 2018,
Trump signed into law the Asia Reassurance
Initiative Act.
The section on Taiwan focuses on the US’s
commitment
“to counter efforts to change the status
quo
and to support peaceful resolution acceptable
to both sides of the Taiwan Strait.”
And to regularly sell weapons to Taiwan.
You know, in case anyone over there
decides to prepare for war.
So look out, Xi Jinping.
Because if you get too aggro,
you might just end up with Trump jumping in
the middle.
And things would get...interesting.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And before you go,
it’s the time you’ve all been waiting
for,
when I answer questions from a member of my
50 cent army,
fans who support China Uncensored
through the crowd funding website Patreon.
Lee Lhasa asks,
“Do you think under the present presidency
the US
would come to Taiwan’s aid in event of an
invasion?
Well, first of all,
I think it would be very difficult for China
to ever even launch an invasion of Taiwan.
But should it ever happen,
I’m fairly confident the United States would
get involved.
Decades of US policy has shown strong support
for Taiwan.
In a recent episode I talked about the island
of Kinmen,
which is only a few miles off the coast of
Mainland China—
but is administered by Taiwan’s government.
In the 1950’s, the Chinese military
actually bombarded the island,
specifically to see if the US
would actually get involved.
And the US did.
And as I mentioned, the Trump administration
has shown a lot of support for Taiwan,
and I think that will continue
despite the resignation of James Mattis,
who was a staunch supporter of Taiwan.
The real risk to Taiwan is a gradual
cultural and economic invasion.
The United States would be powerless
if the Chinese Communist Party were able to
successfully promote its interests in Taiwan
to the extent that there is
a strong enough force for unification
coming from inside Taiwan.
But remember,
even if Taiwan does someday get back together
with China,
that doesn’t mean that it’s the Chinese
Communist Party
that’s going to be in charge.
Thanks for your question, Lee.
And if you’d like your question answered
on the show,
join the China Uncensored 50-Cent Army on
Patreon.
Remember, most of our revenue comes from you
guys.
And as a way of saying thanks,
I’ll give you some cool perks,
as well as answering your questions on the
show.
Thanks for watching.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.