On this episode of China Uncensored, you called
the Chinese police…
…and won!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I'm your
host Chris Chappell.
So, you know who's incredibly awesome?
You!
Now there are some people out there who think,
"Oh, what can I do? I can't make a difference
in this world."
Not my viewers!
Last week, when I found out that police in
China abducted my friend Ben Hedges' mother-in-law,
I asked you to take action.
"So get out your phones my precious 50-Cent
Army, and give police chief Yu Changjun a
call, and tell him to release Sheng Xiaoyun."
Oh, and call you did. Many of you emailed
me your stories.
Here's just a taste.
This one comes from viewer Sasha Ganapolsky.
Yesterday I gave the officer a call which
he answered a few seconds later.
My friend Lily speaks Mandarin so I asked
her to say "Release Sheng Xiaoyun."
He then said, "Who are all of these people?"
with a voice like he's tired of it.
Lily then said, "People who want justice in
China."
He then said, "Ugh stop calling me!" And hung
up.
Beautiful. Well done.
Very well done, in fact,
because I just got word from Ben that his
mother-in-law was released yesterday.
And one of the police officers in the detention
center apparently told her they got a lot
of calls demanding they let her go.
Well done, my 50-Cent Army!
And although that warm, squishy feeling you
have inside right now is probably enough,
I've also sent each of you who called the
police and emailed me about it a special gift.
So check your email.
And to everyone who called, or gave their
support in other ways, congratulations and
thank you.
Together, we made things better in China.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell, and this is
China Uncensored.
Hi everyone, I’m Ben Hedges.
And I’d just like to say a really big thank
you to everyone who called into the police
and helped to get my mother-in-law released.
It means a lot to me and my wife and our family.
Thank you very much.
This is the episode we recorded last week,
but I just want to remind you that now that
she’s been released, you don’t need to
call the police station anymore. Thanks.