On this episode of China Uncensored,
how the Chinese military's theft is costing
America trillions of dollars a year
hi welcome to China uncensored
I'm your host Chris Chappell
as I always say:
good artists copy, great artists steal
which means there's no greater artist than:
"we sampled them from them but it's not the
same base line"
sorry I was actually talking about:
economic espionage by members of the Chinese
military
yes the Chinese military
it's perhaps the world's most prolific and
successful thief
of course the Chinese government denies it
I wanna stress that the Chinese government
resolutely bands and cracks down on any form
of hacking activity
this position is consistent and clear
right...
the Chinese government cracks down on its
own military
anyway by now it's widely known that:
hackers associated with the Chinese government
have repeatedly breached the computer systems
of U.S. companies
but how does that translate into actual profits
for Chinese companies and losses for American
ones?
introducing: Technology Transfer Centers
As early as 2001 the Chinese Communist party
started building a systematic mechanism
to not only steal intellectual property from
foreign companies
but also to reverse engineer that technology
and make it available to Chinese companies
that then can use it to out-compete the same
foreign companies they stole the technology
from.
although this has been going on for more than
a decade it's only recently that we've understood
the missing link of how this works
there are actually three pieces to China's
nationwide system of economic theft
the first piece is the Chinese military
they hack, they spy, they steal
whatever it takes to obtain raw information
like blueprints, data, trade secrets and so
on
the second piece is the transfer centers
they have trained experts process this raw
information into step-by-step designs that
are actually usable
the third piece is Chinese companies
some of them are state-owned
some are private
many of them are run by people with party
or military connections
they get the designs from the transfer centers
and use them to make Chinese versions of foreign
products
let me give you an analogy
it's the Iowa State Fair and grandma chapel
has won first prize for her famous apple pie
now folks from all over come to buy her delicious
pastry
one day she's in her kitchen baking when my
golly
she notices two Chinese tourists taking photos
through the window
well shucks they look friendly enough
the next day these friendly folks stop by
her pie stand and tell her how much they love
her pie
and that they just be tickled to take a few
pies back home to their friends in China
well sure
little does grandma know what these two tourists
are planning
they take her pies to the transfer center
run by the beijing new oriental Culinary Institute
where they're analyzed by foreign trained
pastry chefs
and reverse engineered into a step by step
recipe
then the recipe is sold to a Chinese company
so it's a year later
grandma chapel is setting up her pie booth
again at the Iowa State Fair
but this time there's a new competitor selling
apple pies that taste almost the same
but for half the price
poor grandma can no longer compete
obviously this is just a made-up example
my grandma's from California not Iowa
but this kind of thing really does happen
like how in june 2011 employees of American
superconductor Corp discovered
that their design for the computer chips that
run wind turbines had been stolen
the company's biggest customer "china sinovel
win group"
had suddenly stopped using the American chips
to run its turbines
and instead began using knock off ones based
on the American source code
since this theft also robbed American superconductor
of its biggest customer
it lost more than eighty percent of its stock
value within six months
this kind of thing doesn't just happen sometimes
it happens constantly on a massive scale
in december 2007 the Chinese government literally
wrote economic theft into its national economic
plan
back in June I interviewed cyber-espionage
expert joshua philipp
today he published a groundbreaking article
in The Epoch Times
that for the first time reveals the scope
of China state-authorized technology transfer
centers
Josh thank you for joining me again to help
me further undermine china
so your article exposes these technology transfer
centers
what's the big deal about them?
right, so when people talk about Chinese cyber
espionage,
they often talk about the cyber attacks or
the spies steal the technology
or they mentioned vaguely the Chinese companies
are profiting from this
the transfer centers are the place between
the two of those
that process the stolen technology from the
military and then pass them to the relevant
Chinese state-run industry
so they're sort of the the in between that
reverse engineers what is stolen
exactly and the funny thing about them is
they don't even try to hide it
if you read their doctrine
if you read what they even say about their
companies
they, I mean they call themselves China's
National Technology Transfer Centers
this is totally open
open, open, functioning through Chinese universities
or under Chinese companies
_________________________________________________________________________________________________________--------------
or illa ties the Chinese military
and nobody seems to talk about them
the Technology Transfer Centers exist throughout
the entire Chinese system
they exist in the military
they exist on the government side of the Chinese
regime under the state council
they exist under universities
they exist under businesses
so this is an incredibly powerful organization
you're talking about
well it's not just an organization
this is something the CCP set up
something the ccp created and then encouraged
people to duplicate
as a system that just permeates the entire
Chinese economy
as a way to steal and process stolen information
this is a system that is massively larger
than what anyone today is thinking about
when they when they talk about Chinese espionage
for some reason
it's crazy
this is the missing link in understanding
the Chinese system for economic theft
they have a step-by-step process for stealing
information
for processing the information
and for drawing a profit from the stolen information
- how many Americans are being affected by
this?
well this this affects every American
this is something that not only affects U.S.
innovation
that not only affects U.S. companies and taxpayers
and services supported by taxes
it also affects our basic ability to innovate
and to benefit from what we create
in your article you quote Casey Fleming
who is the chairman CEO of black ops partners
corporation
and he gives a number that this is costing
the U.S. five trillion dollars a year
which is about a third of the country's GDP
that's so much freaking money
how is that possible?
what Casey is talking about is the potential
market value over a ten year lifespan
so basically not just what information was
stolen
but what value would that have had when it
actually went to market
across a 10-year span of market value
we're talking about five trillion dollars
a year
so in that 10-year period it would be about
five trillion dollars every year
that's right
and he's looking not just at reported cases
which is where things get out of whack
because most companies don't want to report
cyber-attacks
Casey's working with companies that have been
victims
and who don't report that they've been attacked
because they don't want to cause their shareholders
to freak out
they don't want to cause customers to freak
out
they don't want to get their CEOs fired
which has happened to, I think, Target, and
quite a few other companies that have reported
cyber attacks
so it's basically "blame the victim"
so Casey is seeing a different side of this
he's seeing the number of cases that have
not been reported
he's looking at cases of stolen technology
that we don't know about
so why don't we just hack China and steal
their ideas?
right
so there are some companies that have asked
permission to launch counter attacks
and they've been told not to do so
it's because we are a country of laws and
we can't get away with that kind of stuff
but this is something I hear a lot
What right does the U.S. have to criticize
China for this?
isn't the U.S. the biggest cyber aggressor
in the world?
U.S spying is just spying
it's just listening to conversations
it's listening to high-level dialogue
and its trying to analyze strategies and opinions
on the west
it's trying to figure out: are you planning
to attack us,
are you really our friends?
are you plotting against us behind our backs?
it's that kind of stuff
this is the kind of stuff that every spy organization
in the world is engaged in
the stuff China is doing is that,
in addition to actually stealing things from
other countries
and then taking that stolen information and
using it to undermine that country
thanks for joining us Josh
thank you
that was all really really scary
I provided a link in the description below
where you can read Josh's article
let me know what you think
thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored
I'll see you next time