On this episode of China Uncensored,
it was a real coup.
For China!
Hi, welcome back,
I’m Chris Chappell.
China and Zimbabwe.
Couldn’t be closer.
Just look at Zimbabwe leader Robert Mugabe
and Chinese leader Xi Jinping
on his 2015 trip to Zimbabwe.
Now there’s a close friendship.
That’s why Xi Jinping said,
China is Zimbabwe’s all-weather friend.
At least that’s what Mugabe told reporters.
He also famously said that
“We have turned east,
where the sun rises,
and given our backs to the West,
where the sun sets.”
Mugabe was even awarded
China’s Confucius Peace Prize.
Yeah, Mugabe’s a pretty popular guy.
They call him the Grand Old Man of African
politics.
Well, at least that’s what he calls himself.
He’s 93 years old—
been elected president
for nearly 40 years in a row,
can you imagine!
Oh, and the military,
they love him!
Why, just last week,
the Zimbabwe military swarmed the capitol,
and headed to the state-run broadcaster
to deliver this important message:
"Comrade R G Mugabe and his family
are safe and sound
and their security is guaranteed.”
Safe and sound,
you see that’s just...okay,
that sounds a lot like the military
just staged a coup.
Clearly, this caught everyone off guard.
“Rumblings of a coup that could oust Mugabe
began just 24 hours after the head of the
army,
General Constantino Chiwenga,
threatened military intervention
to end a purge of his allies
from Mugabe's government.
"When it comes to matters
of protecting our revolution
the military will not hesitate to step in."
Okay, maybe...
no one should have been caught off guard.
In fact, the situation is being compared
to what happened in China almost 40 years
ago,
the fall of the Gang of Four.
During the final days of Mao Zedong’s life
in 1976,
four high ranking leaders,
including Mao’s wife,
were viciously vying for power.
They wanted to replace
the grand old man of Chinese politics
when the old man died.
Ultimately they were all purged themselves
and executed.
And in Zimbabwe,
it’s believed Mugabe’s wife Grace
and three others have been purging opponents
to seize power after Mugabe dies.
But if the Zimbabwean military
thinks it can just waltz right in and seize
power,
they’ve got another think coming.
Remember,
China is Zimbabwe’s all weather friend.
At least, that’s what Mugabe said.
I’m sure China is throwing
all their weight and influence behind him.
I mean, the Chinese government awarded him
that Confucius Peace Prize after all.
What’s that Shelley?
Oh Mugabe rejected it
because it wasn’t from the Chinese government
at all?!
Well, umm...I’m sure the CCP still went
to bat for him.
“We hope the relevant parties in Zimbabwe
appropriately handle their internal matters."
Okay, they’ve thrown Mugabe under the bus.
And that was just an official statement.
Look at how my favorite Chinese state-run
media,
the Global Times is handling it.
Why look,
the sun is shining after a storm.
“We have good reasons to believe
that as Zimbabwe enters the post-Mugabe era,
China will see an improved environment
to cooperate with the country.”
Mugabe, betrayed by the east,
where the sun rises.
The CCP hasn’t thrown Mugabe under the bus.
They threw him under a tank.
Although the Chinese Communist Party does
probably
like all the tanks on the streets of Zimbabwe.
They get a sense of nostalgia.
Yeah, that really looks like Zimbabwe
just had a military coup.
Now normally this is when conspiracy theorists
the world over
start talking about how the CIA was really
behind it.
But this time,
it may be a Chinese knockoff.
As the Guardian puts it,
“The world may just have witnessed
the first example of a covert coup d’etat
of the kind once favoured by the CIA and Britain’s
MI6,
but conceived and executed with the tacit
support
of the 21st century’s new global superpower.”
That superpower—China.
Yes, the Chinese regime
didn’t just throw Mugabe under a tank.
They dug a pit,
filled it with spikes and acid,
threw him in
and then drove over it with a tank.
You see, two weeks before this all went down,
that Zimbabwean general who threatened a coup,
and then eventually carried it out,
was in China.
According to an international relations specialist
at the University of Cape Town in South Africa,
“It should not be too surprising if [Chiwenga]
wanted to ensure political changes
would not anger China because of
the close ties between the countries.”
China and Zimbabwe go way back.
The Chinese Communist Party funded
Mugabe’s African nationalist/Maoist guerilla
fighters
in the 1970s.
And China was one of the first countries
to establish diplomatic ties after Zimbabwe
became independent in in 1980.
Since the West viewed Mugabe as a despot
whose bad economic policies and penchant for
violence
ruined one of Africa’s most promising states,
Mugabe has increasingly turned to China for
support.
The Chinese Communist Party isn’t bothered
by leaders
with a penchant for violence.
So despite Western sanctions,
China became, “Zimbabwe’s biggest source
of foreign currency
and top trading partner,
having invested in more than 128 projects
in the African country
between 2000 and 2012.”
China has also repeatedly blocked sanctions
on Zimbabwe and Mugabe.
In recent years,
China has given Zimbabwe over
1 billion dollars worth of low interest loans.
The Chinese yuan is even an official currency
in Zimbabwe.
But then some problems came up.
According to this research paper,
...the Chinese regime was supporting former
vice president
Emmerson Mnangagwa as Mugabe’s successor.
In fact, “he received ideological and military
training
in Beijing and Nanjing in the 1960s.”
Except he was purged by Mugabe’s wife.
On top of that, over the past year, Mugabe,
“declared a new raft of laws
which put the economic rights of Zimbabweans
above those of foreign investors,
including China.”
Could the Chinese regime
have been getting worried about its investments
there
and gave some level of support to a military
coup
that was backing Mnangagwa?
Now that Mugabe has officially resigned
and is no longer president for life,
I guess we’ll never know for sure.
Mgnangagwa, by the way,
is not a good guy, either.
His nickname is “The Crocodile.”
He’s a former head of Zimbabwe’s secret
police,
and is believed to have orchestrated a massacre
that killed 20,000 civilians.
And good news.
The Crocodile was sworn in today
as Zimbabwe’s interim president.
Meanwhile in China,
scholars from the Chinese Academy of Social
Sciences,
which has some very close ties to the Communist
Party,
have been wheeled out to talk about
how bad a job Mugabe had been doing,
saying “Zimbabwe was careening off a cliff,”
and hinting that the next leader of Zimbabwe
should open the country up.
But you know who’s been really upset
by this whole thing?
Venezuela.
Another country with lots of economic deals
with China
that are under threat because of corruption
and economic turmoil.
I wonder if they’re getting a little nervous?
So did China know of or give approval
for the Zimbabwe coup?
Or are they just using it to their advantage?
Let me know what you think
in the comment section below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
After a while, crocodile.
You know I’ve always thought I’d make
a really good president for life.
I mean, just check out all the great work
I’ve done
on ChinaUncensored.tv.
Politics, economics, scandals…
I’ve covered it all!
Check it out at ChinaUncensored.tv
and cast your vote for me today!
It’s mandatory.