On this episode of China Uncensored,
State-run media says sexual harassment
is only a problem in the West.
And racism?
Oh, it’s not a problem in China, either.
And finally,
Game of Thrones has nothing on the Chinese
Communist Party.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
This week, the hashtag #MeToo
took social media by storm,
raising awareness about the massive problem
of sexual assault and sexual harassment
that pretty much every single woman
has had to deal with.
Well, I shouldn’t say every woman.
Because according to Chinese state-run media
China Daily,
sexual harassment is just a Western problem.
Now, sure,
the occasional survey may give alternative
facts,
like that it happens to 30 percent of Chinese
college students.
Or to 70 percent of female Chinese factory
workers.
And there was that video
of a woman being assaulted that went viral.
In fact, in response to that China Daily article,
a lot of women came forward specifically
to say they were sexually harassed in China.
But when have facts ever stopped state-run
media
from saying anything?
As the Guardian puts it,
“Chinese state media often works to portray
problems in the west
as nonexistent in China,
highlighting cases of police brutality,
mass protests and high-profile cases
of violence against women overseas.”
But after such a fierce backlash,
China Daily did finally respond...
by mysteriously losing the article.
Fortunately, nothing is ever truly deleted
from the internet.
The original article claims that,
“Chinese men are taught to be protective
of their women.”
Of course they are!
When your country has a severe shortage
of women because millions of baby girls get
aborted...
...you need to be protective of the ones you
have left.
In other news, run!
Run for your lives!
I’m just kidding, there’s no escape.
Because China’s very first space station,
the eight-and-a-half-ton Tiangong-1,
will be crash-landing somewhere on Earth
in the next few months.
And we have no idea where or when.
Most of it will burn up upon reentry.
Though there will be some 200-pound chunks
that might crash on the surface of the planet.
But don’t worry,
71% of that surface is water!
In other news, just kidding;
don’t run for your lives!
Because any reports you may have seen
comparing the inner workings of the Chinese
Communist Party
with Game of Thrones are completely exaggerated.
My favorite Chinese state-run media the Global
Times
wants you to know very specifically
that those biased Western media are wrong,
and that the Party Congress going on right
now
has nothing in common with everyone’s favorite
ruthless political brutal bloodbath.
Don’t tell that to Students for a Free Tibet
though.
They held a protest outside the Chinese consulate
in New York
ahead of the Party Congress.
And specifically, there was a bloodbath.
Let’s just say not all Tibetans are celebrating
the CCP’s “liberation” 60 years ago.
They’re demanding the CCP stop killing Tibetans
and destroying their culture.
But I don’t know about that.
I mean, it seems to me the CCP loves Tibetan
culture...
when they can parade it around as an example
of China’s eternally happy ethnic minorities.
Or maybe they’re just happy to have escaped
The Great Hall of the People.
Speaking of unironically celebrating culture,
there’s a museum in Wuhan, that—
according to Shanghaiist—
had an exhibit comparing black people to animals!
You know, because the photographer
thought their faces looked the same.
The exhibit has been removed
following complaints of racism.
But this is just the most recent
in a long string of casual racism in China.
Just last Friday,
WeChat had to apologize for translating
the Chinese word for “black foreigner”
to...well, I’m not going to say it.
It reminds me of that laundry detergent commercial
last year.
The one that showed how well it cleaned,
by turning a dirty black man
into a clean Chinese man.
I’m sure they had the best of intentions.
And coming up after the break,
we’ll take you live to Beijing for our
on the ground coverage of the National People’s
Congress!
Want more great China Uncensored content?
Sure you do!
Then go to ChinaUncensored.tv.
Every Friday, we upload a complete half-hour
episode,
before it gets chopped up and put on YouTube.
So go to ChinaUncensored.tv now to check it
out.