According to recent wargames.
The US Military gets crushed by China and
Russia
It’s a Major anniversary for Tibet
And the Chinese regime is cracking down on
more religious believers
That and more fun stuff
on this week’s China news headlines.
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Subscribe to our YouTube channel
for the latest China news,
and click the notification bell icon.
That way, you get an alert
each time we publish a new episode.
This week’s China news headlines!
The US spends about 600 billion dollars a
year on the military.
More than the next 7 biggest spending countries
combined.
All right!
USA number one!!!
So that means the US can win any war, right?
The answer is...uhh, maybe not?
That’s at least according to recent wargames.
The simulation was US, or blue forces,
against China and Russia, or red forces.
Very appropriate color choices.
In our games when we fight China or Russia
and we've written about this in unclassified
forms,
blue gets its ass handed to it,
not to put too fine a point on it.
We lose a lot of people,
we lose a lot of equipment and we usually
fail to achieve our objective
of preventing aggression by the adversary,
which is a headline.
Uhh, yeah, it is.
In fact, here’s that headline.
Now I know you might be shocked by this.
Don’t worry, you wouldn’t be the only
one.
The House Armed Services Committee was also
shocked.
“The members of Congress who are on
the House Armed Services Committee in the
SAS
they were shocked they were going holy moly
I didn't have any idea it was this bad.”
“Holy moly I didn’t have any idea it was
this bad?!”
I mean, “I didn’t have any idea it was
this bad”
is not what I want the House Armed Services
Committee saying!
So why is it so bad?
It turns out, if the US were to get into
a conventional war with Russia or China,
US bases, and in particular
their satellite and communications network,
are vulnerable in ways the US is not prepared
to deal with.
Take, for example, the F-35.
It’s an unstoppable 100 million dollar warplane...
that becomes pretty much useless
if a Russian or Chinese ballistic missile
blows up the aircraft carrier it’s sitting
on.
In every case that I know of the F-35
rules the sky when it's in the sky
but it gets killed on the ground in large
numbers.
So in the first five days of the campaign
we're looking really good
but after the second five days
it's not looking so hot.
Those are the things that the wargames show
over and over and over
and so we need a new American Way of war,
without question.”
At this point I’d just like to say,
I for one, welcome our Russian and/or Chinese
overlords.
I’d like to remind them that as a trusted
TV personality,
I can be helpful in rounding up others
to toil in their underground uranium mines.
So what would this new American way of war
look like?
Well, for the low, low price
of just $24 billion dollars more a year,
you can find out!
For twenty four billion dollars a year
I will assert that if we focus that on the
right stuff
we can move the needle against China and Russia.
What’s the right stuff?
Mostly missiles apparently.
Including missiles to shoot down enemy missiles
and drones.
But it would also include research and development,
as well as hardening US communications networks.
Because, as was pointed out,
you can spend all you want to get
as many planes in the air and ships in the
sea,
but a billion dollar ship that sinks
because you didn’t cough up for a million
dollar decoy
is probably not good.
But I get it,
$24 billion dollars is a lot to add to our
defense budget.
That’s why I have my own foolproof plan.
I can simply use my security blanket.
Since I was a little boy,
all I’ve had to do was hide under it
and then the bad things can’t get me.
Which is why I’m going to do
the rest of the show underneath it.
This week marks...
what’s that Shelley?
Fine, I’ll take it off.
For a few minutes.
This week marks the 60th anniversary
of the Dalai Lama’s escape from China in
1959.
Obviously this anniversary was marked
by protests and demonstrations from Tibetans
all over the world.
And the Communist Party continues to say
it did nothing wrong in Tibet.
State-run Xinhua said life is so much better
in Tibet now
since the Communist Party took power,
and that the Dalai Lama’s “separatist
plots
are doomed to total failure.”
Shelley, are you sure I can’t do the episode
under my blankie?
Fine.
The US Ambassador-at-Large
for International Religious Freedom
says the Chinese regime is at war with faith.
In a recent visit to Hong Kong,
Sam Brownback criticized the Chinese regime’s
persecution of the Uighur ethnic minority
of Xinjiang.
“The Trump administration is deeply concerned
and considered it a deliberate attempt by
Beijing
to redefine and control these Muslim minority
groups,
[their] identity, culture and faith.”
Brownback also called out the situation in
concentration camps
where more than a million Uighurs are being
held.
“We’ve been putting out very clearly that
this is
a horrific situation that’s taking place
in Xinjiang,”
But that’s ridiculous,
according to Chinese state-run media.
They’re not concentration camps.
They’re concentration camps!
Where Uighurs can concentrate,
on learning job skills!
“The centers are targeting the source of
Xinjiang's
violent incidents with jobs and education.”
Hmm, looks more like a sweatshop.
But yes, these vocational training skills
are combating Muslim extremism.
I mean, you don’t know how bad it was in
Xinjiang
before these camps.
“In southern areas of the Xinjiang Uighur
Autonomous region,
women were not even allowed to wear
a dress or wear makeup.”
Wow, sounds just like the rest of China
during the Cultural Revolution.
That wasn’t extremism!
So clearly the West is just twisting things
to undermine China.
In his speech, Brownback also talked about
the persecution of Christians.
But that’s justified, because Western powers
are trying to use Christianity to subvert
China.
At least, according to the head of
the Communist Party-run official Protestant
church.
And for Christians who don’t belong to state
approved churches—
the Communist Party is shutting their churches
down,
jailing their pastors,
and even rewriting the Bible.
Brownback basically called out the fact that
“The Chinese government attacks
believers of nearly every faith,
in every region of China.”
But that’s just because the Communist Party
is trying to fill out their religious persecution
Bingo card.
In addition to the Uighurs and Christians,
Brownback talked about how the Party
is persecuting Tibetans and Falun Gong practitioners.
Only one more and they get Bingo!
Who will the lucky group be?
What?
Zoroastrianism?
Well that’s not going to work.
I guess they’ll just have to start over
and keep persecuting until they win.
Of course you won’t hear about that
on Chinese state-run media.
Especially if you’re in the US.
Because the US head of China’s
state-run CCTV has left the US.
Her name is Ma Jing.
I think it’s time to update her LinkedIn
profile
to “fled the country”
On CCTV’s American TV broadcast,
it goes by CGTN—
or China Global Television Network.
Change the name,
and no one will find out what it really is,
mwhaha.
The CGTN headquarters in the US is in Washington
DC,
about 7 blocks from the White House
CGTN reaches 30 million households in the
US.
But the Justice Department has been asking
CGTN
some pretty uncomfortable questions
about its links to the Chinese state.
CGTN has maintained the Chinese government
absolutely does not tell them what to broadcast!
Sure, their news stories have to meet
the state censorship guidelines,
and they have no independence,
but technically that’s not the same thing!
The issue is,
according to the Foreign Agents Registration
Act,
Ma Jing needed to disclose
her working relationship with the Communist
Party.
But that’s hard, because the Communist Party
likes to keep those relationships kind of
secret.
I mean, it’s not soft power
if it's all exposed to the sun light
for everyone to see.
It kind of, dries out and gets crumbly.
So the answer is simple.
Flee the country.
Works every time.
And before you go, now is the time I answer
a question
from a member of the China Uncensored 50-Cent
Army—
fans who support the show with a dollar or
more per episode
through the crowd funding website Patreon.
BlueFox asks,
“Chris, does the US have any counters
to the Chinese and Russian as well as other
countries
threat of EMP weapons?”
Well, as we learned today,
the US may not be so prepared for that.
China and Russia are building electromagnetic
pulse,
or EMP, weapons.
Basically they disrupt electronic equipment.
Which is why this American only relies on
his guns.
And I’ve got excellent gun control.
But for the rest of the US military,
or even the entire infrastructure of the United
States,
EMP weapons present a serious potential problem.
Obviously I don’t know the details
of the inner workings of the US military.
But since this is such a widely known issue,
I can only assume some kind of steps are being
taken.
But we won’t know how successful they are
until as they say, push comes to shove.
Which is why,
in the worst case scenario,
I have a surefire fallback.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.