On this episode of China Uncensored,
pack your bags,
we’re going to space!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your Interplanetary Explorer Extraordinaire,
Chris Chappell.
Space: the final frontier.
And guess which country is going to conquer it?
After all,
the legendary Chang’e flew to the moon
several thousand years ago,
which definitely makes the moon a part of
China’s sacred territory.
Wait,
is that a nine-dash line?
Take that, Neil Armstrong!
But as Neil knows,
getting to space ain’t easy!
In fact,
it’s harder than fighting a slew of monsters,
climbing the sacred Mount Kunlun,
finding the Queen Mother of the West,
and convincing her to give you the elixir
of immortality
that will take you to the heavens!
First of all,
if you fly an airplane high enough,
there’s no more air.
And once you’ve lost the air under the wings
that give the plane lift and control,
well, flight becomes much, much harder.
That’s why,
despite the great technological advances we’ve
made as a species,
the best idea humanity has come up with for
getting into space
involves strapping yourself to a massive explosion.
And not surprisingly,
that can go wrong.
For example,
SpaceX,
a privately owned aerospace manufacturer
and space transport services company,
can make a nice video showing how simple interplanetary travel is.
But when you actually put a rocket on a launch
pad,
things can go bad quickly.
That was an unmanned rocket, FYI.
Space tourism is certainly ambitious.
But when it comes to making the impossible
only very improbable
no one beats China.
From the people who said they wanted to build
an underwater train to America
and a trillion dollar space laser,
but who still can’t design a good jet engine
without stealing from other countries—
comes one of the most ambitious plans in the
space tourism industry:
A 20-person spaceplane.
Yeah,
that is the most ambitious plan out there.
A reminder that we’re still 200 years away
from building The Enterprise.
The state-backed China Academy of Launch Vehicle Technology
unveiled this at the International Astronautical Congress
in Guadalajara, Mexico.
And while 20 passengers may not sound like a lot,
it is for a spaceplane.
For context,
Blue Origin’s New Shepard spacecraft,
which is a competitor,
is being designed for just six passengers.
The Chinese spaceplane design is also big.
The largest design weighs in at nearly 100
tons
with a 40-foot wingspan.
The American space shuttle by comparison
was just 82 tons.
The design team claims
test flights will begin in two years,
and payload launches in 2020—
the same year Mission to Mars takes place.
So someone’s prediction was off by a few
years.
Spaceflight expert Roger Launius
at the National Air and Space Museum in Washington, DC
is a bit skeptical of China’s plans.
He told New Scientist,
“It’s not explained how that will be accomplished.
And the fact that they think they can test
fly in the next 2 years
is remarkable.”
One of the things that make China’s space
plane concept unique
is that it will all be one piece.
Like footie pajamas.
It won’t have a separate booster unit
like America’s old-fashioned space shuttle,
nor will with be carried into the air on a
separate craft,
like Virgin Galactic’s SpaceShipTwo.
Basically,
it will take off like the rockets of yore,
but land like a space shuttle,
following these comforting circular bright
red lines.
But anyway,
I’m all for progress in space exploration—
whether the innovation comes from China or
other countries.
But I'm not sure about this whole space plane idea.
You see,
the space plane designers say each ticket
will cost $200,000 dollars or more.
And that could make the airline industry want
to get involved.
Suddenly,
you’re paying ten grand
for each piece of checked luggage,
you'll have to take your space suit off
to get through the full-body scanner,
and an upgrade to business class
will cost you 100,000 frequent flyer light-years.
That's no way to travel.
But all that is years ahead of us.
Meanwhile,
China’s space program has lost control of
the Tiangong 1 space station
which is due to crash somewhere on on Earth
next year.
Just something to look forward to.
So what do you think of China’s ambitions
space plane design?
Leave your comments below.
Please share this video with your friends,
and check us out of Facebook, Twitter, and Instagram.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.