Game of Thrones Finale Shocker
A song for the trade war
And what can happen when a Chinese company
owns an American dating app.
That and more on this week’s China news
headlines.
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
This week’s China news headlines.
After 8 years, Game of Thrones has come to
an end.
And I haven’t seen a show finale create
controversy like this...
...since the end of Lost.
But to everyone disappointed by how Game of
Thrones ended,
let me tell you,
you should at least be grateful that you got
an ending.
Because fans in China did not.
Chinese censors blocked the finale
on the Tencent web streaming platform.
Why?
Because of technical difficulties.
That is, technical difficulties with the US-China
trade war.
Yeah, China restricting Game of Thrones was
a terrible idea.
“Game of Thrones is one of the most popular
shows in China,
with the season being viewed more than
‘550 million times on Tencent Video
during the most recent season.’”
That decision is going to make millions of
Chinese people
finally realize they’re living under an
authoritarian regime.
I mean, sure,
Tiananmen Square Massacre, or whatever,
but people have been waiting 8 years for that
series finale!
What’s that, Shelley?
Chinese people just watched pirated versions
of the finale.
Ok yeah, should have seen that coming.
Unlike the ending of Game of Thrones.
Of course, with the US China trade war heating
up,
the Chinese regime is launching an all-out
propaganda campaign.
Like accusing the US of bullying China.
But sometimes the official propaganda organs
need a little help from the people.
Which is why a retired Chinese official
wrote a catchy anti-US trade war theme song!
Trade War! Trade War!
Not afraid of the outrageous challenge!
A trade war is happening over the Pacific
Ocean!
Wow, Mr. President, pack it up,
the US can’t compete with this level of
bad karaoke music.
“‘Trade War,’ is set to the tune of
an anti-Japanese song
from the 1960s film ‘Tunnel War’—
in which a Chinese town defends itself from
invasion.”
The song went viral in China,
getting over 100,000 views on WeChat.
Wait a minute.
100,000 views on WeChat?
WeChat has 1 billion users.
100,000 views is not viral!
This is starting to sound like a setup
to get unwitting Western media to report on
the song.
But the trade war isn’t just being compared
to the fight against the Japanese.
My favorite Chinese state-run media The Global
Times
is is comparing the economic trade war
to the actual Korean War of the 1950s.
And you know how that ended.
“Maybe some in the US believes that the
Korean War was a draw,
but if you know the history well,
you will understand it was a symbolic military
victory
of China against the US.”
Yes, nothing screams victory,
like sending wave after wave of Chinese troops
to their deaths
to force a draw.
But that’s not the perspective you’d get
from watching Chinese movies about it.
According to Radio Free Asia,
the Communist Party’s Propaganda Department
issued an order requiring CCTV to air anti-America
movies
everyday during prime time.
Most of them were set during the Korean war.
“The films portray North Korea as a righteous
nation
and the United States as an evil imperialist,
and contain scenes of Chinese soldiers
opening fire on their ‘American enemies.’”
Not a bad strategy to turn the Chinese people
against America.
Except of course for one small flaw.
You banned the finale of Game of Thrones!!!
There have also been calls on Chinese social
media
to boycott US products.
This strategy worked when China and South
Korea
had a dispute a few years ago.
But then messages suggested boycotting McDonald’s
and KFC—
and Chinese people were like nahhh.
Meanwhile a Chinese embassy official tweeted
the reason Trump hates the Chinese company
Huawei.
It’s that the Huawei logo looks like an
Apple cut into pieces.
There are two things that make this tweet
slightly unfortunate.
One, he’s using Twitter which is banned
in China.
And Two, he made the tweet on his iPhone.
Now that’s truly cutting.
But perhaps more US companies
should be banned from working with China.
For instance—Grindr, the gay dating app.
It’s owned by a Chinese company.
Well, according to a Reuters exclusive,
Grindr’s Chinese owner,
“gave some Beijing-based engineers access
to personal information of millions of Americans
such as private messages and HIV status.”
Talk about the potential for blackmail.
The Committee on Foreign Investment in the
US
has now told the Chinese company to sell Grindr,
because they consider Chinese ownership of
the app
to be a national security risk.
I wonder why.
Of course not all US companies are having
a hard time in China.
Oreo is doing quite well, thank you.
I mean, it’s basically the cookie version
of the Yin-Yang symbol.
But more specifically,
they will be releasing “six new flavors
of Oreo cookies,
including Chaozhou-style barbecued-pork pastry
and honey red-bean cake.”
Sorry folks, those flavors will only be available
in China.
And a promotional video for Oreos has gone
viral.
It shows the Palace Museum at the heart of
Tiananmen Square
being made out of cookies.
Unfortunately for the company,
the Chinese foreign ministry released a statement
saying
the video proves Oreos have been a part of
Chinese territory
since ancient times,
and has seized control of the business.
From now on Oreos will only be red and yellow,
and taste like the bitterness of the struggle
against American imperialism.
Former Vice President
and current presidential candidate Joe Biden
has been criticized on the campaign trail
for being soft on China.
And now reports are questioning
his son Hunter Biden’s ties to China,
including how he became a very rich man
at the same time his father was negotiating
with China.
That’s according to the 2018 book “Secret
Empires:
How the American Political Class Hides Corruption
and Enriches Family and Friends.”
“The vice president is negotiating
a bunch of very sensitive issues with the
Chinese,
including the South China Sea,
trade, tech transfer, etc.
Shortly after they return to the US,
Hunter Biden’s firm receives a $1 billion
private equity deal
from the Chinese government.”
And according to the Intercept,
Hunter Biden’s investment company in China,
Bohai Harvest RST,
has invested in facial recognition technology
that’s being used to monitor Uighurs in
Xinjiang.
Nothing to see here, folks.
But not everyone is so thrilled about the
Chinese government.
A local Fox News station in Los Angeles
got ahold of undercover footage of Falun Gong
practitioners
being abused in Chinese labor camps.
I can’t actually show it to you,
because YouTube would probably age-restrict
or demonetize this video.
But I’ll provide the link below.
They did an excellent 9-minute report
and I encourage you to watch it.
Canada is sending a delegation to China to
appeal
for the release of two Canadians.
The two Canadians were accused of spying,
but it's much more likely their detention
was retaliation
for Canada detaining Huawei CFO Meng Wanzhou.
They’ve been in jail for months.
But the delegation might not do much good.
According to Canada’s former ambassador
to China,
the relationship has gotten so bad,
Chinese leader Xi Jinping
won’t even pick up a call from Trudeau.
The hardest part for Trudeau?
Wondering when he’ll get to hold those pandas
in his arms again.
What a tragic loss for all peoplekind.
In a sign that maybe Hong Kong isn’t doing
so well,
two Hong Kong activists had to flee—
and were granted asylum in Germany.
The two pro-democracy activists were involved
in a 2016 protest that turned violent.
They jumped bail and turned up in Germany,
recently disclosing they were granted asylum
status.
One of them said,
“If the German government thinks that
the Hong Kong judiciary is independent,
they would not grant me refugee status.
It’s because they think that Hong Kong
uses the judiciary to persecute Hong Kong
people.”
This of course is happening as Chinese officials
are really encouraging Hong Kong
to pass new extradition laws.
The laws would allow the easy extradition
of people
from Hong Kong to Mainland China.
The kind of laws that would,
I don’t know, make two Hong Kong pro-democracy
activists
feel like they need to flee the country
because they won’t get a fair trial.
And that does it for this week’s China news
headlines.
Before you go,
it’s time for me to answer a question from
one of you—
a fan who support China Uncensored
with a dollar or more per episode,
by contributing through Patreon.
Today’s question comes from:
Joel Neatrour
“May I have China Uncensored's permission
to appropriate Pepe the Pooh in social media?”
Ahhh, Pepe the Pooh.
One of my favorite creations from the show,
and a great illustration by our video editor
Seamus.
It’s a horrendous-slash-delightful mashup
of Pepe the Frog and Winnie the Pooh,
creating the ultimate in China meme trolling.
Anyway, yes, you have my permission.
Spread Pepe the Pooh far and wide,
to the deepest corners of the Internet.
Fill the 4chan forums with it.
Even 8chan.
Tweet it.
Instagram it.
This is China Uncensored’s gift to humanity.
Treasure it.
I’ve put a download link in the Description
below.
Thanks for your question, Joel.
And thanks to everyone watching!
We could not make this show without your support—
whether it’s supporting us through Patreon
or just watching and sharing the show
with your friends and family.
So thank you from me and everyone
on the China Uncensored team.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.