On this episode of China Uncensored,
the People’s Daily is totally not making
"inappropriate and erotic online content."
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored. I’m your
host, Chris Chappell.
And this is the People’s Daily.
The official newspaper of the Chinese Communist
Party.
It's where people go to get the specific policy
directives of the Party leadership.
And this is the People's Daily Online.
The official website of the official newspaper
of the Chinese Communist Party.
And it's a little more...market oriented.
You know, being in the newspaper business
is hard.
Sure, the People's Daily is partly paid for
by the state and doesn't have to pay taxes,
but financial stability doesn't guarantee
eyeballs.
And when you're tasked with spreading China's
soft power around the world,
well, you can't do that if people aren't watching.
So People's Daily Online is taking a…unique
approach to attracting an audience.
Like this photo essay called “Women can
be heartthrobs too:
Beauties seen doing split in bamboo groves
in [Eastern] China.”
Here they are, a local aspiring girl band,
who just happen to be innocently practicing
their dance routines
in the middle of a bamboo forest.
While dressed in leotards.
And extremely small tutus.
How fortunate that the People’s Daily photographer
just happened
to stumble across these gazelles in the wild.
Here they are, in their natural habitat,
employing the well-known stretching technique
of making kissy faces at each other.
And in a forest full of vertical bamboo poles,
they of course need to gently stabilize each
other to get a full extension.
Wow, those two are really leaning into that
stretch.
As the People's Daily so eloquently says,
"Their intimate interactions would make one
blush just by one glance."
I assume they mean we're blushing
because of the girls' exquisite, completely
natural and unstaged artistry, of course.
You know, when Mao said that “women hold
up half the sky,”
I didn't realize he meant they should be holding
it up with their legs.
And if the People's Daily is producing such
informative and high quality journalism on
this girl band,
I can't wait for next year's International
Women's Day reporting.
Maybe they'll have a full spread!
This is just one of many similar photo galleries
on the People’s Daily Online.
But when it comes to non-state-run borderline
pornographic content,
the Chinese regime has a little different
stance.
“If you had said to me what is China going
to ban,
eating bananas seductively would have been
fairly low on my list.
Like I didn’t know that was a thing until
this story.”
But it is! Or was.
“Seductively eating bananas” is the latest
victim of China’s internet censorship.
And yes, you are looking at CCTV’s facebook
page.
Because clearly, while some things should
be banned for your average Chinese citizen,
it’s okay when your government does it.
So while this is inappropriate,
this is totally fine.
Just like how Twitter and Facebook are banned
in China,
but if you want more wholesome content like
this,
“Please follow People's Daily on Twitter
and Facebook.”
At least the People's Daily allows comments
on this article.
Which I recommend you do not read.
So what do you think about banning fruit eating
as seedy behavior.
Will it be a fruitless effort?
Is it just too appealing?
Let me know what you think in the comment
section below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell. See you
next time.