The biggest political event in China!
But it’s a real snoozefest.
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Subscribe to our YouTube channel
for the latest China news,
and click the notification bell icon.
That way, you get an alert
each time we publish a new episode.
It’s that time of year again!
The biggest political event in China!
The Two Sessions!
3,000 delegates descend on
the Great Hall of the People in Beijing.
Even representatives of all
the 56 happy ethnic minorities.
First, there’s the meeting of the NPC,
or National People’s Congress.
And as you can see, loads of NPCs are there.
Second, there’s a meeting of the CPPCC,
or Chinese People's Political Consultative
Conference.
It's sort of an advisory body
to the Chinese Communist Party, and...
Ok, I can see your eyes glazing over.
I mean, am I the only one who finds
high level Chinese political discourse interesting?
Am I the only one who enjoys spending hours
meticulously reading through NPC work reports?
I mean, listen to this kind of action!
“The acceleration of the economy was matched
with targets for power consumption,
shipping, and other materials.
The resident consumption level rose by 2.1
percent,
which is equal to basic international
revenue and expenditures."
Oh great, even the translator fell asleep.
Okay, the Two Sessions are incredibly boring.
I mean, the most interesting thing going on
was literally a soldier standing still.
Even the clapping for Chinese leader Xi Jinping
was monotone.
That’s why, my favorite way
to gauge the impact of the Two Sessions
is through what I call the Yao Ming index.
I’m referring of course,
to Chinese basketball star Yao Ming,
who’s a member of the CPPCC.
Looks like he *really*
Enjoys.
Being there.
Fortunately, the Communist Party
has finally become self-aware-ish
about how boring the Two Sessions are.
So, this year, they’ve tried to spice things
up.
And what better way,
than by having a white guy on state-run media
tell us about the Two Sessions
using terrible green screen technology!
“It’s widely known that the key to China’s
success
is its system of democracy.
Which results in political stability and vitality.”
“How exactly does China's democratic system
work
and how can its people's voices be heard?”
Well, as Mr. Quisling explains,
the secret to Chinese democracy is the Two
Sessions.
“NPC deputies and CPPCC National Committee
members
consist of top leaders,
renowned economists,
entrepreneurs, artists, sportsmen,
and representatives from all walks of life.
As President Xi Jinping said,
‘Democracy is not a decoration,
but a means of solving problems.’”
I wonder what life choices lead a man to do
that job.
Anyway, are you excited for the Two Sessions
yet?
No?
Okay, well using a white guy clearly didn’t
work.
Let’s try two white women with more interesting
accents!
That’s sure to appeal to...
whoever the target demographic is for these
things.
“It’s that time of year again,
the biggest annual event in Chinese politics.
Yes that’s right.
The two sessions are just around the corner.
And Roisin and I are about to test our know-how.”
Oh boy!
I wonder what we’re going to learn about
the Two Sessions.
“A highly expected draft law will be submitted
to
the upcoming plenary session of the NPC.
Which of the following statements
is most relevant to that law?”
Hmmm...Looks like they’re not excited about
this quiz, either.
OK, well time to bring out the big guns then.
A completely spontaneous,
absolutely not government backed,
Two Sessions rap song.
“Eject all the rapaciousness like shaking
off nephrolithiasis,
longing the hanging gardens so we turn the
entire space into oasis.
We've got two sessions, we've got two session.
For the fragrance we're blessing, to the world
we show our affection.
See we've got two sessions let me show you
Chinese manners.
Tramp the bygone cession we're the fortitude
presence.”
How could anyone think the Two Sessions are
boring, now?
Sure, if you listen to the whole thing it
doesn’t actually explain the Two Sessions.
Plus it sounds like someone tried to create
a rap
using SAT-vocabulary Mad Libs.
But it’s definitely the first rap song
to use the word “nephrolithiasis”,
also known as kidney stones.
And listening to that rap is like trying to
pass one.
Now Quartz quotes a culture editor
who calls the rhymes “hilariously awkward”—
but asks, “what really rhymes with ‘supercomputer’”?
Umm, challenge accepted.
Yeah, uhhh, this one goes out to that lovable
Pooh bear—
Xi Jinping.
Sendin’ probes to the moon, got my super
computer.
On the high speed rails,
I’m a super commuter.
Shopping all day,
like I’m a wealthy consumer.
I can pack it all up, in a suitcase scooter.
What’s that shelley?
My rhymes are smelly?!
Fine, I guess it’s harder than it seems.
Of course this isn’t the first time the
Party
has used music videos to impart important
ideas.
There’s everyone’s favorite Belt and Road
song!
“The future’s coming now.
Oh oh oh oh.
The Belt and Road is how.
Oh oh oh oh.”
And who could forget about this gem from 2015?
“If you wanna know what China’s gonna
do,
best pay attention to the shi san wu.
The shi san wu.
The shi san what?
Anyway, what were we talking about?
Oh right.
The Two Sessions.
It’s so boring I let myself get distracted.
Anyway, it’s probably important
for understanding the political direction
of China,
but it’s going on for an entire two weeks
so...yeah,
let’s wrap this up.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.