A new virus is spreading in China.
Are Chinese authorities covering it up?
And do you need to be worried?
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
This episode is sponsored by Surfshark.
Because you should be using a reliable VPN
whenever you go online.
There’s a new virus spreading in China.
It appears to cause pneumonia, and in some
cases, death.
The new virus is a coronavirus.
It’s in the same virus family as the common
cold,
and as SARS,
the deadly virus Chinese authorities covered
up back in 2003.
It’s called a coronavirus because it’s
like ads for Corona beer:
They cover up how terrible it will make you
feel.
The first confirmed case of the new coronavirus
appeared on December 31
in the Chinese city of Wuhan.
Never heard of Wuhan?
It’s just another small central Chinese
city...
of 11 million people.
“Many of the cases were connected to the
Hua-nan Seafood Market,
which also sold live poultry and exotic animal
meats.”
Exotic animal meats apparently includes...
Live ostrich, live civet cat, alligator tongue,
and good old-fashioned dog meat.
What could go wrong?
So how widespread is the new virus?
It’s complicated.
First, let’s go to our trusted source:
Chinese state-run media.
On Wednesday,
they reported that the number of confirmed
cases was 543 in China.
I expect those numbers to go up by the time
you’re watching this.
There have also been several cases abroad,
including one in the US.
But fear not!
According to my favorite Chinese state-run
media,
the Global Times,
the virus is preventable and controllable.
Just like democracy in China.
Chinese state-run media released
this footage of doctors in protective gear.
It’s all very sanitary.
There’s even a doctor claiming patients
have been cured.
“Up until January 17 there have been 19
patients
who have been cured of this (virus) and left
the hospital.
This pneumonia caused by a new coronavirus,
in general, can be cured.”
So again, you have nothing to worry about.
Which is why authorities in Wuhan have imposed
a semi-quarantine on people traveling in and
out of the city.
And at least 17 people have officially died
of the coronavirus so far.
That would make it less deadly for now than
SARS.
But you might want to worry about the official
numbers.
The “543 cases in China” statistic comes
from
the same state-run media and government agencies
that covered up SARS in the early 2000s.
Meanwhile, in London,
the MRC Centre for Global Infectious Disease
Analysis
estimates that there are more than 1,700 cases.
And that’s just in the city of Wuhan.
One expert told the BBC that
“For Wuhan to have exported cases to other
countries
would imply there would have to be
many more cases than have been reported.”
Don’t worry,
he added that it’s “too early to be alarmist.”
I’ll let you know when it’s time to be
alarmist.
That’ll probably be next week.
That’s because Chinese New Year begins this
Saturday, January 25.
It’s the peak of China’s annual travel
season—
and the world’s largest human migration,
where Chinese people will take an estimated
3 billion trips.
That will include an estimated 7 million overseas
trips.
This is potentially a huge problem.
Especially now that Chinese authorities have
confirmed that
human-to-human transmission is happening.
It’s not just for people who visit exotic
animal markets anymore.
So the big question here is,
have Chinese officials been covering up the
spread of the coronavirus?
Yes.
The answer is yes.
On January 16, a little over two weeks after
the first reported case in Wuhan,
there were still only 41 confirmed cases of
the virus in China.
And they were only in Wuhan, nowhere else
in China.
That was according to Chinese authorities.
But there were already three confirmed cases
in Thailand and Japan.
Again, that’s part of the reason these scientists
estimated
the number of cases was much higher than reported.
Meanwhile, as official Chinese state-run media
was being censored,
rumors about the virus started on Chinese
social media,
and went, uh, viral.
This WeChat text thread claims that
"All the information about the infection is
being locked down."
This one claims that hospitals won’t even
give you the test
that would identify the virus.
And this one says,
"I asked a doctor, it's true.
Four people were deceased just in his ward,
numerous medical staff were infected."
Now again, these are just rumors.
But people spread rumors like this when
they don’t trust the authorities or the
media.
And then rumors like this can cause panic.
Then on Monday,
Chinese state-run media reported that Chinese
leader Xi Jinping
said China will “resolutely curb” the
outbreak of the virus.
On the same day,
the official number of confirmed cases of
the coronavirus
suddenly tripled.
And the virus also suddenly spread from Wuhan
to several Chinese provinces.
And the official number has kept increasing.
Not to mention, only after Xi’s announcement
did Chinese officials
also confirm that there was human-to-human
transmission.
Funny how that happened.
Almost as if Xi Jinping had given permission
to stop the coverup that totally never happened
in the first place.
And this exposes a fundamental weakness
of the Communist Party’s rule in China.
In a system so obsessed with top-down control
and scapegoating,
lower-level officials are incentivized to
cover up things
that could be politically bad for them.
Things like the start of a possible pandemic
in your city
from a sketchy market that sells dogs and
ostriches.
How do they cover it up?
The Guardian reported on one case where
the relatives of a woman who died of pneumonia
were told by doctors that she probably had
the coronavirus.
But she hadn’t been screened for the virus
before she died,
and the hospital pressured the family to cremate
her quickly.
So she didn’t officially count as one of
the almost 300 confirmed cases.
If you don’t officially count the patients,
they don’t have the virus, right?
Similar cases have been posted on Chinese
social media,
and then those posts got censored.
But now that Xi Jinping has said that China
must “resolutely curb” the outbreak,
that could mean that the cover-up will stop.
After all, Chinese authorities said on Tuesday
that “lower-ranking officials who covered
up the spread of the virus
would “be nailed on the pillar of shame
for eternity.”
Ouch.
On the other hand, this might mean the cover
up will get worse.
Because now all those officials have to cover
up the fact that
they had previously covered up the spread
of the virus.
I mean, no one wants to be nailed on the pillar
of shame for eternity.
And again, people in China
think that the government and media are lying
to them,
which causes more anger and panic.
What do you think about the Wuhan coronavirus
cover up?
Leave your comments below.
And this episode has been sponsored by Surfshark.
When you go online, everything you do is being
tracked and logged—
by the websites you visit and your internet
service provider.
And in many cases, by the government.
And if you’re in an authoritarian country
like China,
this kind of tracking can put you at risk
of surveillance and even arrest.
That's why you should use a VPN like Surfshark
to protect your identity.
When you use Surfshark’s CleanWeb mode,
you’ll be protected from ads, trackers,
and malware.
Plus with Surfshark,
you can connect as many devices as you want.
Try it out with a 30-day money back guarantee.
Plus Surfshark has a special discount for
China Uncensored fans.
Go to https://surfshark.com/uncensored
and use code UNCENSORED
to get 83% off a 2-year plan and one extra
month free.
Protect yourself online today!
Click the link below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.