The Chinese Communist Party\h
Is crushing Australia’s economy
Will Australia stand up to China?  Or back down?\h
Welcome back to China\h
Uncensored. I’m Chris Chappell.
Have you ever wondered what the\h
world would be like if Twitter had\h\h
never been invented?\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h\h
Perhaps President Hillary Clinton would be\h
preparing for her second term in office.\h
But that’s not the world we live in. Instead,\h\h
Twitter was invented. And it’s\h
become an important diplomatic tool.\h
And if you’re thinking that’s a\h
terrible idea, you would be right.
Relations between China and Australia took another\h
hit on Monday (November 30), after Prime Minister\h\h
Scott Morrison demanded a fake image posted on a\h
Chinese official's Twitter account be taken down.
Morrison called a media briefing to condemn the\h
post which showed an Australian soldier holding\h\h
a knife to the throat of an Afghan child,\h
and said Canberra was seeking an apology\h\h
from Beijing.
\h\h
The Chinese Communist Party was probably\h
caught off guard by Morrison’s demands,\h\h
because the Communist Party is usually the one\h
that demands apologies from everyone else.\h
Which is why China responded that\h
it was sorry...that Australia sucks.
This was the tweet in question, from Chinese\h
foreign ministry spokesperson Zhao Lijian.
This is not a real photo. It’s a photo\h
illustration created by a patriotic\h\h
Chinese artist whose work has been\h
boosted by Chinese state-run media.
Both the tweet and the image are\h
about a recent independent report\h\h
commissioned by the Australian government. After\h
a four-year investigation, the report found that\h\h
Australian special forces soldiers may have\h
committed up to 39 murders in Afghanistan.\h
Those 19 soldiers are now facing\h
investigation for their alleged war crimes.\h
This has been a huge scandal for Australia.\h
The government has pledged to appoint a special\h\h
investigator to prosecute the cases and\h\h
an independent oversight panel to make\h
sure the government implements changes.\h
Australia has also apologized to Afghanistan.
But as far as the Chinese\h
Communist Party is concerned,\h\h
this is a great opportunity\h
to tear down Australia!\h
Zhao Lijian’s tweet is the latest example of\h
what’s being called “wolf warrior diplomacy.”\h\h
Named after the nationalistic\h
Wolf Warrior action movies.
Wolf Warrior diplomacy really began after Chinese\h
diplomats started joining Twitter. Of course.
Yes, Twitter has somehow managed\h
to make Chinese propaganda\h\h
worse. I didn’t think that was even possible.\h
But then again, twitter makes everything worse.
Zhao Lijian became the most famous wolf\h
warrior diplomat, after he tweeted back\h\h
in March that the US military could\h
have brought the coronavirus to China.
Which sparked a lot of media coverage.
Frankly, I don’t think we should call this wolf\h
warrior diplomacy. That makes it sound tough and\h\h
cool. These Chinese officials are just sending\h
aggressive tweets to get a rise out of people.\h
So let’s call it what it\h
is: Troll Face diplomacy.\h
Yes, Zhao Lijian and his fellow\h
diplomats are just internet trolls.\h
And like all internet trolls, they\h
love the attention they’re getting.
Now that the Chinese Communist Party has\h
triggered Australia, the Party is doubling down.
But as hard as the Chinese Communist\h
Party is trying to pwn Australia,\h\h
the incident they’re mocking them for actually\h
shows a fundamental difference between\h\h
China’s authoritarian communist state\h
and Australia’s liberal democracy.
The Australian government started an independent\h
inquiry into the war crimes allegations.\h\h
The report was released publicly.\h
There will be further investigations,\h\h
and the individual soldiers involved, the\h
military, and the Australian government itself\h\h
will all face consequences for their\h
actions. And the public will know about it.
It’s a big contrast to how the\h
Chinese Communist Party treats,\h\h
for example, any criticism of their\h
suppression of Uyghur Muslims in Xinjiang.
But this incident is just the\h
latest in a long string of things\h\h
that have gone wrong between China and Australia.\h
I’ll tell you what those are after the break.
Welcome back. Relations between China\h
and Australia have been facing a\h\h
sharp downturn. And China, to no one’s\h
surprise, says it’s all Australia’s fault.
Obviously it’s because Australia just can’t\h
appreciate China’s goodwill because Australia\h\h
is so evil, according to my favorite\h
state-run media the Global Times.
Yes, the Chinese Communist Party has\h
so much goodwill towards Australia.\h\h
Goodwill that they express through:
ramping up a huge trade conflict with Australia;
threatening Australian journalists;
and warning Australia over its\h
alliances with other countries.
How could Australia be so\h
ungrateful towards such goodwill?
China’s “goodwill” towards Australia started\h
earlier this year after Australia led calls\h\h
for an international investigation\h
into the origins of the coronavirus.
Which makes sense, since the Communist\h
Party is so touchy about the subject\h\h
that they’re still trying to insist\h
that the coronavirus came from Italy.
Or maybe India.
Definitely not from China.
But that coronavirus investigation is hardly\h
the only problem that China has with Australia.
In fact, last month, the Chinese embassy\h
gave Australian media a list of 14 reasons\h\h
why China is mad at Australia.
Here’s the full list.
It includes everything from banning Huawei\h
and ZTE from Australia’s 5G networks,\h\h
to “incessant wanton interference in China’s\h
Xinjiang, Hong Kong, and Taiwan affairs.”\h
It even includes things that the Australian\h
government isn’t directly responsible for,\h\h
like an Australian think tank publishing a\h
report on China’s use of Uyghurs as forced labor.
And negative news reports on\h
China from Australian media.\h
I mean, if the Chinese Communist Party has\h
complete control over China’s think tanks and\h\h
media, then the Australian government should\h
control their own think tanks and media, too.
But the real problem that the\h
Communist Party has with Australia\h\h
goes deeper than that. And I’ll tell you\h
about it after this commercial break.
Welcome back. The current conflict between\h
the Chinese Communist Party and Australia\h\h
actually goes back to 2017.\h
That’s when the Australian\h\h
government finally realized the extent of\h
the Chinese Communist Party’s infiltration\h\h
in Australian politics and society, and\h
they started to stand up for Australia.
Australia was the first Western liberal\h
democracy to expose the Chinese Communist\h\h
Party’s influence operations. And that\h
was a huge problem for the Party.\h
And Australia made meaningful changes\h
to counter China’s interference,\h\h
including passing\h foreign interference laws.\h
Of course, that doesn’t mean that China’s\h
influence operations in Australia are over.\h\h
They are definitely still going on.
And we’ve talked about those a lot on this show.\h\h
We even traveled to Australia\h
back in 2018 to cover the issue.\h
But Australia’s actions over the years\h
have had a huge ripple effect. It started\h\h
the conversation about China’s influence\h
operations in other liberal democracies.\h
And the Chinese Communist\h
Party cannot let that happen.\h\h
Australia has stood up to\h
the Chinese Communist Party,\h\h
so the Party must crush Australia—or other\h
countries might start getting ideas, too.
And the main way that the Party can\h
crush Australia is economically.\h\h
By destroying their exports to China.
Like coal.
And wine.
And lobsters.
So once again Australia becomes a test case\h
for dealing with the Chinese Communist Party.\h\h
Will they continue to stand up to China, or\h
will they back down in the face of pressure?
It’s not going to be easy.
Especially when you have experts\h\h
warning that an all-out trade war with China\h
could cost Australia 6 percent of their GDP.
So wouldn’t it be a better idea for Australia\h
to repair its relationship with China?
They could make a friendly gesture, like\h
joining China’s Belt and Road Initiative.
What could go wrong?\h
Look, it will be hard for Australia to stand\h
up to the Chinese Communist Party on its own.\h\h
Which is why its allies should stand by them.\h
New Zealand is joining Australia\h
in denouncing China’s tweet.
And America is stepping up to the plate, too. Look\h
at this tweet from the National Security lCouncil.
“Australian wine will be featured at a White\h
House holiday reception this week. Pity vino\h\h
lovers in China who, due to Beijing’s\h
coercive tariffs on Aussie vintners,\h\h
will miss out. Hashtag Aussie\h
Aussie Aussie Oi Oi Oi!
Wow, I can’t believe I just read that out loud.\h
Good for America for supporting Australia.\h\h
Could we just do it...not on Twitter?
And now it’s time for me to answer a question\h
from one of you, a supporter of the show\h\h
on the crowdfunding website\h
Patreon. Roy E Fitts asks:
Hey Chris, new patron here. if Biden\h
does win the white house do you\h\h
think the news and proof about the organ\h
harvesting that's been getting attention\h\h
will be silenced and or discredited\h
by the Biden administration?
The reality is that the Biden Administration\h\h
wouldn’t have to actively silence or\h
discredit the organ harvesting issue.\h\h
All they would have to do is ignore it, the\h
same way that previous administrations have.
The Chinese Communist Party has been\h
harvesting organs from prisoners of\h\h
conscience for more than 20 years now.\h
And the evidence of that keeps growing.\h
But it’s much easier for governments,\h\h
and corporations, and people to ignore\h
that evidence. Because if it were true,\h\h
then we couldn’t treat China like a normal country\h
that we should all be doing business with.\h\h
And based on our recent episode looking\h
at Biden’s foreign policy advisors and\h\h
their views on China, I wouldn’t hold my\h
breath for the Biden administration to\h\h
go around talking about organ harvesting\h
and why it should be stopped.\h
Roy, thanks for your question. Your\h\h
extremely depressing question. And thank\h
you for being a new patron of the show.
If you’d like to support China Uncensored just\h
like Roy, join our 50 cent army on Patreon.\h\h
Visit Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.\h
You know, Youtube censorship\h
has been getting worse lately.\h\h
And we took a risk with this episode by\h
showing you Zhao Lijian’s tweet earlier,\h\h
which could get this episode age restricted\h
by Youtube. So thank you again for watching,\h\h
sharing, and supporting the show. We\h
wouldn’t be able to do this without you.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next time.