Hello?
Hello.
Are you…?
I’m Gina Shakespear,
from the YouTube channel Declassified.
Yeah, I know Declassified.
But...why are you here?
This bloke let me in.
You mean Matt?
That blonde guy with the blue eyes?
Yeah.
That’s the one.
Right.
So what are you doing at my desk?
Well, I’m doing some research for Declassified,
about Chinese Communist Party subversion of
the US.
And I figured China Uncensored would be the
place to go.
So...you infiltrated my studio, and hacked
into my computer?
Actually, the blonde guy gave me the password.
Matt!!
Well, since you’re already here, did you
find anything good?
Yeah, I’ve put together 5 Ways China is
Subverting the United States.
Great, let’s take a look.
Alright.
We’ll start with…
Number 5: Government officials
The Chinese Communist Party wants to get in
good
with US government officials.
And if that doesn’t work,
they put pressure on them.
For example,
they’ve got people like US Senator Dianne
Feinstein.
China’s former leader Jiang Zemin
spent years building a relationship with her.
World’s most uncomfortable karaoke night.
Yeah.
Feinstein’s husband enjoyed big business
profits in China.
And meanwhile,
Senator Feinstein supported legislation
like giving China most favored nation status
to increase trade.
Also, her driver was allegedly a Chinese spy.
Feinstein is a pretty obvious case.
But not every US official is like that.
No, sometimes it takes more pressure.
Like last summer,
California state senator Joel Anderson
wanted to pass SJR-10.
It was a state resolution condemning the Communist
Party’s
persecution of Falun Gong practitioners.
But then, the senate suddenly blocked it right
before it was about to come to a vote.
It turns out, a bunch of senators received
a threatening email that morning
from the Chinese Consulate in San Francisco.
It warned them about SJR-10,
saying it could “sabotage the friendship
and sustainable development between California
and China.”
Right.
Because passing a law through a democratic
vote...
that’s what sabotage is.
Friends don’t let friends call out
each other’s human rights abuses, Chris.
And this kind of pressure happens all the
time.
Anyway, moving on to...
Number 4: Businesses
The Chinese Communist Party has been
pretty successful at pressuring American companies.
For years, one of the rules of doing business
with China
is that foreign companies have to share their
technology
with local Chinese companies.
You’d think that companies wouldn’t make
these kind of stupid deals.
Yeah, except they’re scared that if they
don’t,
their competitors will.
So a lot of companies feel like they have
no choice.
Fortunately, the US government has recently
called China out on this.
Because when it happens on a large scale,
it becomes a big drain on the US economy.
And of course,
if a company resisted sharing their technology
with China,
the Chinese military would—
how should I put it?—
enforce the sharing anyway.
IP theft costs America hundreds of billions
of dollars a year,
maybe trillions.
And we haven’t even talked about
the subversion they do from inside the US,
which is directly planting spies—
especially in the tech industry.
Chinese employees can be pressured to be part-time
spies,
and provide information or technology to their
handlers
who work for China’s Ministry of State Security.
Sometimes they do it because there’s pressure
on their families inside China,
or they do it for patriotism,
or just for the money.
Non-Chinese employees can also do it for the
money, too.
So the US loses a lot of technology to China.
At least we get entertaining Chinese knockoffs,
like the iPnoho6.
You can’t make this stuff up.
Number 3: Universities
Universities in the US love having
international students from China.
They pay full tuition.
And of course,
it’s a great way for Chinese students
to get introduced to American culture.
Except...a lot of them aren’t really integrating
that much.
Yeah, that’s one problem.
And the Chinese Embassy and consulates
try to maintain a tight grip of these students.
For example, they set up
the Chinese Student and Scholar Associations.
On the surface,
they’re about welcoming and caring for Chinese
students.
But they’re also ways to track and monitor
students,
and make sure they hold the “correct”
political views.
Like that Taiwan is a province of China.
And that people who criticize human rights
abuses are anti-China.
People like you, Chris,
who undermine China’s harmonious society.
Strangely, no one says that your Declassified
channel
is undermining America’s harmonious society.
That’s because America can handle truth
bombs, Chris.
Anyway, there are other ways the Chinese Communist
Party
is subverting American universities.
Like the Confucius Institutes.
As Confucius said,
“Political power grows out of the barrel
of a gun.”
Or maybe that was Mao Zedong.
That’s not too far from what they’re teaching.
Confucius Institutes give money to Chinese
universities
to host their Chinese language classes.
But in the course material,
they present a pro-communist view of China’s
development.
And of course they conveniently avoid sensitive
topics.
“Teacher, how do you write the characters
for ‘Free Tibet’?”
And there’s another way American universities
are being undermined.
“Some people in academia have submitted
to a sophisticated global censorship regime.”
One student told The New Republic,
“I would not willfully do anything that
would endanger
my ability to get a visa to China in the future.”
In other words, don’t be like Chris Chappell.
Speaking of which…
Number 2: Journalism.
As you know, the Chinese Communist Party
has the “Three Warfares” doctrine.
And the first “warfare” is about shaping
public opinion,
both inside China and around the world.
For example, they allow big media companies
to set up bureaus in Beijing and Shanghai.
But in exchange for access,
they have to avoid politically sensitive topics.
And reporters are restricted about
which places they can visit inside China.
Big booming cities, yes.
Polluted cancer villages,
not so much.
And if reporters cross the line,
they get kicked out of China.
So news organization can self-censor,
just like some academics do.
And over time, American public opinion on
China
gets skewed in favor of Beijing’s narrative.
You even get American media publishing opinion
pieces like this:
I mean really,
all America needs to do to become superior
again
is silence public opinion,
take away rights,
and throw a million people in re-education
camps
for their religion.
Of course, foreign newspaper reporters in
China
don’t usually praise the Communist Party
directly.
That’s the job of state-run China Daily.
Like when they put these paid inserts into
influential newspapers like the Wall Street
Journal.
C’mon, who wouldn’t want another Great
Leap Forward?
It only killed like 45 million people.
And speaking of propaganda...
Number 1: Meddling in US Elections
We always knew that the Chinese Communist
Party
wants to direct US policy towards China.
But now, US officials have started talking
about
the Chinese Communist Party trying to
influence US elections, as well.
“China has initiated an unprecedented effort
to influence American public opinion,
the 2018 elections,
and the environment leading into the 2020
presidential elections.
To put it bluntly, President Trump’s leadership
is working;
and China wants a different American President.”
But the Chinese Communist Party’s influence
operations
are different from countries like Russia.
Here’s one example.
One of America’s biggest exports to China
is agricultural products, like soybeans and
pork.
When the Chinese regime put tariffs on US
soybeans and pork,
farmers--who were more likely to vote for
President Trump--
were also the most affected.
And then when Chinese state-run media place
ads in US newspapers
calling the US-China trade war the “Fruit
of a President’s Folly,”
well, they want those farmers to change their
minds about Trump.
For an authoritarian regime, the Chinese Communist
Party
is surprisingly good at manipulating democracy.
Well, we don’t yet know all the ways that
the Chinese Communist Party is influencing
US elections.
Hopefully US officials will say more about
that in the future.
Well, that’s a pretty scary list, Gina.
It is.
And I think Vice President Mike Pence
did a good job of summing it all up.
“The Chinese Communist Party is rewarding
or coercing American businesses,
movie studios, universities, think tanks,
scholars,
journalists, and local, state, and federal
officials.”
But the real question is,
how can we influence American businesses,
movie studios, universities, think tanks,
journalists,
and government officials?
I guess everyone will have to watch China
Uncensored.
And what can Americans do to learn more about
this?
Well, viewers can see more about that
on my YouTube channel, Declassified,
where you can learn about all sorts of topics
related to the US and US politics.
So click the link below, and head over to
Declassified to learn more.
Once again, I’m Gina Shakespeare, thanks
for…
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell, thanks for
watching China Uncensored!
Declassified.
More power!
More power?
Yeah.
Declassified!
Thank you for watching China Uncensored - Declassified!
Once again I'm Chris Chappell, thanks for watching this episode of China Uncensored.
Declassified.
NO! FORCE!
Once again, I'm Gina Shakespeare, thank you for...