what the next u.s president is going to do in\h
terms of china policy is obviously a somewhat\h\h
relevant issue and it's an issue that the\h
chinese communist party has been considering\h\h
right which is obviously they haven't loved the\h
last four years of u.s china policy and not just\h\h
the chinese communist party but there's a lot of\h
corporate interests that would really like to see\h\h
things go back to the way things were before the\h
trump administration as well right i mean not just\h\h
corporate interests i think there's universities\h
who want to work with chinese universities\h\h
um confucius institute think tanks uh you know\h
like there are a lot of people who are invested in\h\h
um u.s china engagement so definitely and\h
we've seen the king of uh u.s china cooperation\h\h
henry kissinger rear his head again you know\h
he's 97 years old i was just wondering how old\h\h
he was yeah yeah i mean he he he doesn't look\h
young but i mean he's he's in good shape for\h\h
a 97 year old it's amazing what adrenochrome\h
can do am i right i don't know what that is\h\h
is it something that's going to bring\h
us down like a weird rabbit hole again\h\h
let's carry on okay look like i don't know what\h
it is but like in context i know it's one of\h\h
those things that you would find on 4chan\h
no no no is this an alex jones reference uh\h\h
let's just say it's a reference to uh maze\h
runner my favorite movies okay okay so it's\h\h
something totally different i thought it was\h
going to be something that like alex jones\h\h
sells on his show wow like that's\h
what i thought okay uh wow if he does\h\h
i mean who knows what's in super male\h
vitality uh so uh what a us china policy\h\h
no no we have to go back to kissinger because yeah\h
well i mean that is u.s china policy but go on\h\h
i mean he is responsible in large part for\h
decades of u.s china policy i mean i think even\h\h
trump had gotten advice from kissinger like i\h
think he's advised pretty much every sitting\h\h
president since nixon wow on china policy so\h
yeah and also i think that his china policy\h\h
in the 1970s was based on the the geostrategic\h
needs of the us at the time in the height of\h\h
the cold war or the soviet union was perceived\h
as a very serious threat the soviet union was\h\h
funding these kind of communist cells around\h
the world and kissinger and nixon hoped that\h\h
by establishing warmer ties with communist china\h
it would be a counterbalance to the i guess at\h\h
the time arguably worse communism the soviet union\h
well i mean it was also that the us was directly\h\h
competing against and in the cold war with\h
the soviet union and china was kind of\h\h
not directly involved right they didn't\h
have the kind of military they have nowadays\h\h
yeah i mean i i think that at the time the chinese\h
communist party wasn't really a threat i mean\h\h
yes the u.s had kind of you know had been involved\h
in the war over gene men the little taiwan island\h\h
that had been bombarded with shells and stuff by\h
mainland china but like besides that there wasn't\h\h
that level of conflict and there certainly\h
wasn't a concern that china had a modern\h\h
military well i mean they were still just\h
got done killing a bunch of their own people\h\h
yeah and they still haven't stopped that tree they\h
really haven't tried so they haven't stopped but\h\h
they killed different people now well so\h
the point is like you're saying that maybe\h\h
at the time the sort of kissinger\h
style school of thought about how\h\h
the u.s should deal with china may have made\h
sense but in the 21st century it's stupid
so kissinger came out and said at the\h\h
uh bloomberg new world forum new economic\h
forum the bloomberg news new world order
hidden agenda okay do you want\h
to get us banned from youtube\h\h
oh gosh no uh i i should say this is\h
a result of them going on vacation\h\h
and me staying here and working i'm a little\h
on edge okay i need a break maybe we should\h\h
take the coffee away it's a hot chocolate with\h
espresso that's so coffee yes but with sugar
all right we're off to a good start okay\h
so at the bloomberg new economic forum\h\h
which by the way the the funniest thing about that\h
is you go to their website and one of the first\h\h
things you see is like a little like qr code in\h
the corner that's like join the conversation about\h\h
the bloomberg new economic forum on wechat which\h
the us is called a national security threat uh\h\h
and then you scroll down and it's like leadership\h
and then it's henry kissinger and hank paulson the\h\h
former us treasury secretary uh and which there's\h
tony blair was there former uk prime minister uh\h\h
hank paulson was with which bank before he became\h
treasury secretary i don't know but if i had to\h\h
guess goldman sachs no well there's just so many\h
goldman people end up becoming treasury secretary\h\h
but anyway does anyway he was one with one of\h
the big banks yeah yeah so it was really you know\h\h
just like a picture and the bloom\h
of course it's michael bloomberg\h\h
and they had um this is the third year of the\h
bloomberg new economic forum and the first year\h\h
it was held in singapore in the second year was\h
held in beijing so you kind of get a sense of\h\h
what this is all about from all\h
this so uh what did kissinger say\h\h
why don't you tell us shelley i don't have the\h
exact quotes in mind he was quoted i think i\h\h
sent this link to you because it was um in cgtn\h
or like it was like a chinese state-run media\h\h
that was quoting kissinger saying that the us\h
and china need to go back to cooperating again
you