On this episode of China Uncensored,
it’s time for the UK to finally do something
about Hong Kong!
Well, first: tea time.
But then they’ll definitely
do something about Hong Kong.
Hi, welcome back to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
In October, British citizen
and human rights advocate Benedict Rogers
tried to visit Hong Kong—
where he had lived from 1997 to 2002.
But this time when he landed at the airport,
Hong Kong immigration denied him entry.
My favorite Chinese state-run media,
The Global Times, called Benedict Rogers
“a threat to China’s sovereignty, safety
and interests.”
I wish they’d say that about me.
Anyway, Benedict Rogers has now set up
an organization called Hong Kong Watch
to monitor the Chinese Communist Party’s
encroachment on Hong Kong’s freedoms
and rule of law.
Under a treaty with Great Britain
called the Joint Declaration,
Hong Kong is supposed to be
independently governed until the year 2047.
But according to Mr. Rogers,
that’s not what’s happening.
So I traveled to Washington DC
to have a chat with him about
the future of Hong Kong and China.
Benedict, thank-you for joining us
in Washington DC.
I'm very happy the US government
let you into the country.
I hear that doesn't always happen for you
in every country you visit.
That's right.
A few governments for reasons
I can't begin to imagine
have not let me into their countries.
I know, what you're talking about.
In October 11, 2017,
you were denied entry into Hong Kong.
Tell us a little bit about that.
About three days before I was due
to fly to Hong Kong from Bangkok
I received a phone call from a person in Britain.
A British person who I know well who's a friend,
who's sympathetic on these issues.
He had received a phone call
from the Chinese embassy telling him
that they had become aware of
my intended visit to Hong Kong,
and asking him to ask me not to go.
There was a to and fro of messages.
I took advice on what to do.
The advice from everyone I spoke to
was I should go ahead,
because essentially this was an attempt
to intimidate me into not going.
Did you not care at all about
the feelings of the Chinese people?
The Communist Party asked you not to go.
I care very much about the feelings
of the Chinese people.
I don't care so much about the feelings
of the Chinese Communist Party,
and the two are very different.
It was Chinese people that I was
seeking advice from who said,
"We want you to come.
We think probably this is an attempt
to intimidate you, and it's bluff.
Were you surprised when you got to Hong Kong
and they actually stopped you?
I was surprised.
Obviously I knew it was a possibility
from these warnings.
But I had hoped that in the end,
Hong Kong's autonomy would be intact.
Clearly it wasn't.
It seems like it really backfired on them,
because your story made international headlines.
Even Hong Kong's chief executive, Carrie Lam,
further dug a hole for herself by saying
at this point they would even consider banning
Hong Kong's former governor, Chris Patten.
That's right.
What was extraordinary was,
I think in news terms a story like this,
had it just been the denial of entry
to a British human rights activist,
serious enough.
But that story probably would have run
for a day or two and then the news cycle
would have moved on to other things.
But Carrie Lam kept the story going.
Did you send her a thank-you card, by the
way?
I have written to her.
Not exactly along those lines…
Hong Kong and China are supposed to
have this One Country Two Systems policy
where Hong Kong gets to keep its own freedoms
and rule of law.
Clearly that hasn't been going so well.
How long do you think until it will just be
a “One Country, One System”?
Well I think it's rapidly heading in that
direction…
"How long will it be?",
I think part of the answer is it depends on
the response of the international community,
and particularly my own country, Britain.
If Britain and the international community
take a stand for the principles set out
in a treaty actually between Britain and China,
the Joint Declaration,
then maybe we can hold off the day
when it just becomes another Chinese city.
But if the international community doesn't
act,
then that day will come sooner rather than
later.
You're British?
I couldn't tell.
My accent doesn't give it away.
A few weeks ago,
British Prime Minister, Theresa May,
made a trip to China.
Before the trip she said she would bring up
human rights issues in Hong Kong.
So, on a scale of 1 to 10,
how did she do?
I would say probably about four...
Downing Street did say before she went to
China
or when she was on her way
that she would raise these issues.
Of course, she only raised them privately...
It seems there's a problem
that when these issues are kept private,
it becomes sort of a propaganda boon
for the Communist Party...
It sort of sets a precedent to other people,
do you think?
Other politicians and even businesses,
that it's best to stay quiet if
the leaders of countries are not doing this.
It does set that precedent,
which I think is very dangerous.
I think that, of course there's also the precedent
of corporations giving in to China,
or even apologizing to China.
Mercedes Benz and Marriott.
Alright.
Name 20 more examples.
Yes, exactly.
Yes, I very strongly favor having these
private discussions where you go into more
detail,
but making public statements as well.
I think, firstly
I think China needs to be confronted publicly.
But secondly,
I think for our own domestic audience at home,
that provides a level of accountability.
Do you think there is any meaningful change
the British government can make in Hong Kong?
Yes.
I think there definitely is.
Britain has both not only moral responsibilities,
but a legal responsibility under the
Sino-British Joint Declaration, which is a
-
Which they have called, I forget their exact
term,
but they called it some archaic historical
document
that has no relevance.
That's right.
Yes, the Chinese said that.
But I mean, that's wrong.
It's a living treaty.
It's valid for the first 50 years after the
handover.
It's lodged at the United Nations.
I think the challenge for the international
community is,
if China takes that view over one particular
treaty,
what does it mean for all its other treaty
obligations?
Tell us a little bit more about your organization,
Hong Kong Watch…
Essentially a group of us came together in
London,
very concerned about the shockingly low level
of awareness in our own parliament,
and among our own public,
about what's happening to Hong Kong.
We felt there was a need for an advocacy organization
to speak out for Hong Kong...
We exist to speak out.
To carry out research into the
erosion of freedoms in Hong Kong,
and to provide a voice to inform and educate
and advocate for Hong Kong.
Well considering you're doing this,
do you think you'll ever get back into Hong
Kong?
I hope so.
I think it would be a positive sign if that
happens.
But there have been three attempts
to get the Hong Kong government
to give an answer to this question.
The British government minister, Mark Field,
wrote to Carrie Lam.
The lawyer Albert Ho
wrote to the director of immigration.
Then I personally wrote to Carrie Lam.
On all three occasions
the response is ambiguous at best.
I guess more importantly,
do you think I even can go back to Hong Kong.
Well, that's a good question.
Having interviewed me you really might not
be.
You and the master criminal Joshua Wong.
Exactly.
Well if we ever are able to go back to Hong
Kong
at the same time,
I know a great place that serves basically
macaroni and cheese with a slice of pig cheek.
Oh.
It's out of this world.
That sounds excellent.
Well thank-you very much for joining us today.
Best of luck with Hong Kong Watch.
Thank-you very much.
What did you think of Mr. Rogers coming to visit our neighborhood?
Leave your comments below!
And who would you like to see us interview next?
Once again, I'm your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time!
You know, we interview all kind of important
people.
Check out our website, ChinaUncensored.tv,
where you can see our interviews
with government officials,
human rights activists,
and of course,
super criminal Joshua Wong.
Once again that’s ChinaUncensored.tv.