well have you considered that maybe this genius\h
side is just a form of chinese communist party\h\h
efficiency i mean they get rid of their ethnic\h
minorities they get rid of religion and they make\h\h
a profit from selling the organs i mean it kind of\h
all wraps up nicely that's very dark yeah i mean\h\h
of course you will not find allies in those\h
technocrats who see the the the chinese model\h\h
as a solution but keep in mind that every\h
genocide in history has been justified not in\h\h
not calling it a genocide but using some excuse\h
of course the nazi tried to exterminate the jews\h\h
because they were you know parasites because\h
they were ruining the germany's economy so we\h\h
don't hate the nazis said we don't hate jews as\h
such well some something as they said also they\h\h
hadn't brought that but you know generally\h
speaking we we don't have a problem with\h\h
jews as such but jews are those people who are\h
ruining the country so for the sake of my country\h\h
i will get rid of that it's a technocratic uh\h
solution it's a technocratic approach the nazi\h\h
were the the most efficient uh rats and the soviet\h
unions so and and the soviets were the same and\h\h
maoists and chinese nowadays are the\h
perfect technocrats they they find\h\h
technical solution to what they perceive as\h
a problem so falun gong people are considered\h\h
enemies of the state they are growing too much\h
it's a movement that goes beyond the control of\h\h
the state so it's a theoretical threat to the\h
state plus we need some some supplies in for a\h\h
human transplant okay that's the solution to\h
go and harvest it's a technical it's a cynical\h\h
technical um answer if the technocrats\h
in the west who support the chinese model\h\h
uh don't understand that or even worse they\h
if they uh cover that they're they're they are\h\h
they're doing the same basically they are covering\h
it would be like you know saying that hitler was\h\h
just you know fixing the german economy it would\h
be the same i mean i'm just thinking about how\h\h
when people talk about china being ruled by\h
technocrats or you know the communist party\h\h
being technocrat well like that it's it's said\h
it's such a powerful thing a positive thing i mean\h\h
it's such i said as like it's a positive thing to\h
be a technocrat and you're pointing out that this\h\h
is actually a terrible like cold-blooded way to\h
look at the world yeah well of course it became\h\h
it even it depends on what what is the meaning\h
you gave to words i use technocrats in a very\h\h
peculiar way probably uh there is a there is a a\h
full um tradition of technocratic thoughts going\h\h
back to the of late 18th century um\h
basically basically very basically\h\h
saying that we don't care about spiritual problem\h
moral problem ethical problems religious problem\h\h
all these are alienations this is the language of\h
marx by the way uh what we care of are practical\h\h
problems and practical solutions so\h
what works is good not the reverse\h\h
i'm not looking for what is good and that and\h
try to put that at work but it if it works\h\h
it's good i mean there is a i can document a\h
tradition of technocratic thought using the the\h\h
using these this idea so you know the technocrat\h
is that man who sees problems only as technical\h\h
problems and he gives or here he or she gives\h
only technical solution they say value free\h\h
but they mean you know i basically\h
don't care about values human values so\h\h
if this is the meaning and i'm using technocrats\h
again in in the in this way and we have examples\h\h
when if i if i point out at the chinese model\h
as such as working and i say i don't care\h\h
they kill people it works right they they're\h
killing millions of people thousands of people\h\h
who cares it works so it's good that is the\h
meaning of of tech of a technocrat for me\h\h
uh well it's not something good uh again this\h
is why i called the nazis the best attackers\h\h
because they they they address things\h
uh from a materialistic technical level\h\h
uh they found a working of course you\h
know eradicating who uh people would work\h\h
if you if you have too many uh if you if you\h
have an economic problem and you don't have a\h\h
food for everyone and you see we are too many\h
uh and i say and the technocratic approach in\h\h
the sense that i'm using the world will be you\h
know let's kill these people and get rid of them\h\h
it works of course you're reducing the number and\h
the food you have will be enough for everyone but\h\h
it's completely immoral if you don't look\h
at that and if problems are only technical\h\h
problems so solutions are only technical you\h
can find a working model but they are immoral
you