On this episode of China Uncensored,
why can't "disputed territory" just be code for,
"I wanna get next to you?"
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Tensions are getting worse
between India and China.
For those of you who need a quick catch-up,
Chinese troops began building a road
in disputed territory with Bhutan.
Bhutan asked the Indian army to come over
and stop the Chinese troops,
and now the two biggest powers in Asia
are at each other’s throats.
China and India.
Not Bhutan.
Bhutan is the smallest power in Asia.
Anyway, Chinese state-run media i
s becoming more and more aggressive,
saying India had better check itself,
or there’s gonna be war.
And this article says Indian Prime Minister
Modi
is gambling with India’s destiny...
...because Chinese troops would kill every
single Indian soldier.
Indian troops are still on the border,
but China and India can’t seem to agree
how many.
Chinese sources are saying 53,
but New Delhi says around 350
have been stationed there
since the border dispute began.
And inside India,
the conflict has sparked a grassroots movement
to boycott Chinese goods.
“There should be a boycott of Chinese products,
and if some people do not boycott,
then they are traitors.”
Meanwhile, the Dalai Lama has suggested
that perhaps the two sides ought to sit down
and resolve their disputes like adults.
I’m sure the Chinese Communist Party
is going to listen to him.
And proving that once again individuals
are more rational than governments,
an Indian boxer defeated a Chinese boxer
in a major match,
and dedicated the victory to peace
between the two nations.
...after literally just punching
his Chinese opponent in the face.
The Indian winner offered to return
the championship belt to the Chinese boxer
to ease tensions along the border.
He said, “I hope for peace in the border
and the message is about peace.”
The Chinese Foreign Minister rejected his
offer,
responding that China is already a land of
peace,
and anyway the championship belt has been
part of China's sacred territory since ancient
times—
so give us the belt now or war is inevitable.
We’ll be right back.
Want to watch more China Uncensored episodes
before they come out on YouTube?
Of course you do!
We put full half-hour episodes on our website
every Friday afternoon.
Click the link now to visit ChinaUncensored.tv.
See you there.