On today's China Uncensored
the most racist thing you'll see on YouTube.
Today.
Probably.
Hello and welcome to China Uncensored, I'm
your host, Chris Chappell.
First, a warning.
What you're about to see next
is one of the most painfully awkward things
we've ever shown you.
Including that time former Chinese leader
and human hypnotoad Jiang Zemin
dance-yelled at Hong Kong reporters for asking
him a question.
Former Miss Oregon USA and Apprentice contestant
Jennifer Murphy
released a video on Youtube of her performing
a song
for the pink carpet launch of her business,
Jennifer Murphy Beds.
Hmm, you know what?
Maybe I too could be ninja.
I want to be ninja!
I want to be neenja!
I want to chop, chop, chop chow down
Take chow down to Chinatown.
I want to be NEENJA!!
And it goes on for an excruciatingly long
4 minutes and 29 seconds.
It's about as cringeworthy as Rebecca Black's
Friday video,
but at least that company didn't produce something
this racist.
I love Chinese food!
Yeah!
You know that it's true.
I stand corrected.
I don't know what, uh, inspired, Jennifer
Murphy
to pen her ode to wanting to be a Neenja.
Maybe she's a fan of Breakfast at Tiffany's,
or bad Kirsten Dunst cover songs.
I think I'm turning Japanese, I think I'm turning Japanese, I really think so.
But I do want to address some of the factual
inaccuracies in Jennifer Murphy’s song.
Neenjas, by which I assume she means Ninjas,
are Japanese.
But they don't do karate moves.
And are therefore unlikely to chop people
down to Chinatown.
Which is Chinese.
And as a practitioner of Shanxi Seven Star
Praying Mantis kung fu,
let me just clarify that it is possible to
learn Asian martial arts
without also learning a racist Asian accent.
When I shuo zhong wen,
I'm not making fun of Chinese people.
That's my own authentically bad Chinese pronunciation.
Which I apologize for.
Now, I don't think we should pile on Jennifer
Murphy, here.
Don't hate, educate.
Or something.
But it does show the extremely simplistic
way that many people view Asia.
There are so many countries in Asia with such
rich cultures,
that shouldn't be mashed up into one big chop-suey
stereotype.
That would be like reducing America to some
kind of giant machine-gun filled Disneyland.
I stand corrected.
You know, my favorite part of that website
is that they're proud sponsors of the Boy
Scouts of America.
But back the point.
Yes, Asian cultures are different and cool.
But we should learn about them instead of
stereotyping them.
Look, I put actual effort into my fascination
with Chinese culture.
Did Jennifer Murphy read Dream of the Red
Chamber?
Or Romance of the Three Kingdoms?
I don't think so.
Hmmm, Cao Cao looks a little different in
that version.
For more on this topic,
we go to China Uncensored humor ninja, Shelley
Zhang.
Greetings, Chris-san.
Uh, greetings. What's that on your face?
It's my ninja mask.
That's not a ninja mask, that's a facekini.
Well now it's not a ninja mask, after you
told everyone.
Should I...not tell them?
Isn't that educating the Jennifer Murphys
of the world?
Yes, exactly.
Chris, the Jennifer Murphys of this world
don't want to be educated.
It's like Confucius said,
"Everything has its beauty, but not everyone
sees it."
So...they should just go on mixing up all
of their Asian stereotypes?
As Sima Qian said,
"History is not what it seems."
It's all mixed up already.
Take ninjas.
The original ninjas weren't some guys sneaking
around
in black costumes killing people with throwing
stars.
They were more like undercover agents
who dressed up as farmers to blend in and
get information.
It's like being in the CIA.
How many CIA agents have desk jobs, right?
Yeah, I can relate to that.
The \hWestern idea of ninja assassins came
from a mix of Japanese legends,
a James Bond movie,
and Hong Kong martial arts flicks.
But like Mencius said,
"Once you know the truth, it's not fun anymore."
No one wants to dress like this for Halloween.
I guess that's true.
What's with all of the...Asian stuff you're
doing?
This?
Oh I'm just getting ready for the opening
of my new business venture Chris.
Madame Ming's Oriental Emporium and Opium
Den Restaurant.
Don't worry, it's not real opium.
Madame Ming?
Alliteration.
Plus no one can pronounce my last name correctly.
Why would you let people use your culture
as window dressing?
Chris, from the time I had to change my name
in kindergarten
so the other kids would stop pulling their
eyelids back and making ching chong noises,
I knew that people would only make fun of
my culture
or use it as decoration.
Why shouldn't I use that to my advantage?
I see it as part of my heritage.
Really?
Yes, my American heritage.
Just like our founding fathers reclaimed Yankee
Doodle
and made an insult into a patriotic song,
I'm reclaiming all of this Asian stereotype
stuff.
Someone called me a chink broad the other
day on the internet.
10 years ago, I would have been really hurt.
Now, I'm still hurt,
but you know what?
Chink broads is a great name.
That's what I'm calling my new podcast.
As Sun Tzu said,
"Don't get mad, get even."
Wow good for you.
Wait, Sun Tzu didn't say that.
No kidding.
Wait have all of your quotes been fake?
Yep.
So you're basically trolling people.
Trolling is such a crude, Western, surface-level
word, Chris.
I am giving them the chance to enlighten themselves
to the subtle and mysterious wisdom of the
East.
Ok, but the people you're "enlightening" won't
get it.
That's true, Chris.
But as Laozi once said,
"The Dao that can be told is not the eternal
Dao;
The name that can be named is not the eternal
name."
Is that…
Yeah, that one's real.
Ok, but what does it mean?
Yeah, no idea.
Wow, you’re right!
I think I prefer the fake
but easy to digest versions better.
Thanks, Shelley.
Wow, cool!!!!
What do you think of the ninja song?
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I'm Chris Chappell, see you next time.