A Chinese man in lockdown
posted about starving for 10 days
Now he’s been jailed for 10 days.
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
Tonghua, China: A small city you’ve probably
never heard of in China’s northeastern Jilin
Province.\h
And by small city, I mean it has 2.3 million
people.
Tonghua is part of China’s rust belt.
Basically it’s China’s Detroit, but even
worse.
And with 3 times as many people.
And thanks to the coronavirus, aka the CCP
Virus, things there are going badly.
Like starvation level badly.
The city has been under lockdown since mid
January.
And not like “oh no, we can’t go to the
gym” kind of lockdown.
Like “stay in your apartment, don’t go
outside under any circumstances” kind of
lockdown.
In January, after 49 residents tested positive
for Covid, “a downtown section of the city
became the most locked-down place in China.
City officials taped apartment doors shut
in entire housing complexes practically overnight.”
Here’s part of what one resident who goes
by Mr. Liu posted on the social media platform
Toutiao.
“I’ve starved for nearly ten days.
Luckily a kind person had shared some food
with me, but that was 3 days ago.”
“The whole city has been restricted from
leaving without any prior notice.
My building’s been quarantined for ten days,
with no food, nothing.”
“I support the country, I support the government,
but please hurry and provide emergency relief!
Truly too many people are starving.
I’m nearly starved to death.
I’m not exaggerating!
They only care to protect their officials,
but don’t even care to provide food for
the sake of their public image!”
“I hope this post can reach the attention
of the county leadership!
Thank you everyone!
I take full responsibility for my words!”
The Public Security Bureau in Tonghua City
responded by posting a screenshot of that
social media post with the word “FAKE”
stamped across it.
And then, to help Mr. Liu, who’d been starving
for 10 days...they put him in jail for 10
days.
Why?
Well according to the police, he was lying.\h\h
“Liu was lying for attention and views,
knowing that he had food at home and had received
living supplies from the community grid staff,
but he fabricated false facts such as ‘I
was hungry for almost ten days…’”
“Liu’s behavior has constituted slander
and disturbing the peace.
As a penalty, Liu has been detained for ten
days and fined 500 yuan”, which is around
$80 US dollars.
Hey, at least when you’re in jail, they
feed you.
Maybe.
But Mr. Liu’s post was not unique.
He’s one of literally thousands of people
who complained on social media that they were
running out of food and medicine.
One resident wrote: “The true situation
is: My children are there and are about to
run out of food.
Many food delivery apps won’t deliver for
2 or 3 days!
There’s panic because of the lack of supplies!
There’s a severe shortage of medical workers!
We can’t hold on much longer!
No one will pick up our calls!
Which department could we call for help?!
I ask the national government for emergency
assistance!”
And this person says...
“Everyone please pay attention to Tonghua
City’s lockdown!\h
1.
There are over 200 confirmed cases.\h
2.
Necessary goods are in extremely short supply.
3.
Medical workers are overloaded and short staffed.
4.
The lockdown has caused many people to not
have enough food.
5.
There’s been no response to people’s problems.
6.
The country and society are not paying attention.”
And then there’s this hopeful post...
￼
“I hope this comments section doesn’t
get blocked, so that netizens can hear the
voices from Tonghua City, and check whether
these policies are being implemented.”
Well, the comments section did get blocked.
So you see, Mr. Liu’s so-called ‘fabricated
false facts’ may not be so fabricated.
Tonghua City is going through a sudden and
severe lockdown.
There’s just very little media coverage.
And we know how bad it is, because the mayor
of Tonghua actually made a public apology
for the abrupt lockdown and failure to give
citizens enough warning.
And it’s not often you see a Chinese government
official apologizing.
And even Chinese state-run media have started
publishing articles to cover their butts—like
this one about how the government is planning
to provide daily necessities to 110,000 families
“amid criticism of sluggish supplies delivery”.
But at least finally people there can get
some real...ugh, vegetables!?
Gimme a break.
And anyway, state-run media’s claims might
not even be true.
Shocker, I know.
Here’s a video of a resident on the 4th
floor of an apartment sharing supplies with
a resident two stories up.
Which you probably wouldn’t need if the
government were actually delivering all the
food they promised.
\h
The local Public Security Bureau may not be
doing a good job providing food.
But they are at least good at punishing people
for spreading information.
To scare other people from complaining online,
they released a video of Mr. Liu’s apology,
where he ‘admitted’ to illegally spreading
rumors.
“After this whole situation.
I recognize my errors.
I should not have spread false information
during the virus pandemic.
I also should not give the civil servants
an unnecessarily hard time.
I recognize this is my fault.
In the future, whether it’s in public or
on the internet, I will not impulsively say
whatever, and I will avoid any factually inaccurate
discourse.
This is certainly a problem that I have.
I will be sure to change my— I will be sure
to pay attention to what I say.
Uhmm…
And that said, I also hope, uhmm, my comrades
will uhh, punish me lightly for seeking attention.
Thank you everybody.”
Well that’s a pretty vague apology.
Maybe because he doesn’t even know what
he’s apologizing for.
His social media post was merely a last resort
after being ignored by the authorities—despite
his post saying “I support the country,
I support the government.”
But in communist China, even if you support
the government—that doesn’t mean the government
will support you.
And now it’s time for me to answer a question
from a viewer who supports China Uncensored
on Patreon.
Joshua Wyss asks:
“Chris, in your recent video about Xi JinPing's
daughter you said to stop giving the CCP money
through investments and buying Chinese products.
Do you think we should also avoid tourist
travel as well?”
Yes.
Stop traveling to mainland China.
I don’t know why anyone would travel there
now, given that they can arbitrarily detain
people.
But even outside of that, if you visit China,
everything you buy, all the money you spend
on train tickets and tourist attractions—a
part of that is going to support the Chinese
Communist Party.
The Communist Party is committing genocide...and
genocide ain’t cheap.
If you like Chinese culture, may I suggest
you visit the vibrant, friendly, democratic
country of Taiwan.
Which is also full of delicious night markets.\h
You know, after we can all travel again.
Thanks for your question, Joshua.
Be like Joshua, and join us on Patreon.
Go to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored to learn
more.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.