Is Hong Kong descending into chaos?
Or parties?
Either way, the Chinese Communist Party
Is threatening to intervene.
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
The situation in Hong Kong is getting out
of control!
At least according to the Chinese Communist
Party.
It makes sense.
If the Party gradually steals away Hong Kongers’
freedoms
without anyone noticing,
everything is going according to plan.
If people stand up for themselves,
the situation is totally out of control!
And obviously, the best way to bring it under
control,
is for Beijing to get involved
in some unspecified but threatening manner!
“A senior Chinese official in charge of
Hong Kong affairs
warned that Beijing would intervene if the
local government
proved unable to contain the violent protests.”
He said the protests,
“have clear characteristics of a color revolution.”
So, let’s check in on those violent protests.
Ok that looks less like a color revolution
and more like a color-ful laser show.
And sing along.
Which turned into a dance off!
Hey, it’s friend of the show Tom Grundy,
editor in chief of Hong Kong Free Press.
That, uhh, violent protest was in response
to
the arrest of a university student.
Plainclothes police arrested him for what
they called
buying an offensive weapon.
That weapon...was a laser pointer.
Protesters have used laser pointers to disrupt
police cameras.
The fear is that police will later identify
protesters
and arrest them for rioting.
Those fears...are justified.
The city of Hong Kong has been in turmoil
for two months.
It’s because of the Chinese Communist Party’s
attempts
to gradually remove Hong Kong’s democracy
and freedom.
Protests in Hong Kong have been heating up.
Earlier this week,
protesters lit a bonfire outside a Hong Kong
police station.
Police responded with tear gas.
And one protester responded with a molotov
cocktail—
the most offensive kind of cocktail.
Well, after an Espresso Martini.
This week also saw a thousand lawyers taking
to the streets in protest.
That’s the second time lawyers have marched
in the streets since June.
So many lawyers,
that truly is terrifying.
And it’s not just lawyers.
Over the last two months,
there have also been protests from mothers,
retirees, aviation workers,
government employees, and bankers.
Yes, the bankers are out on the streets!
This truly is chaos.
On Monday, there was also a general strike
and protests throughout the city,
despite Hong Kong Chief Executive Carrie Lam’s
warning
that protesters were going down “a path
of no return.”
During the strike,
Hong Kong police fired 800 canisters of tear
gas in one day.
Which was impressive,
since they had only shot 1000 tear gas canisters
in the previous two months combined.
I’m old enough to remember when
police firing 150 tear gas canisters in a
day
was a record.
That was less than two months ago.
On the plus side, these protests
have been a boon for the tear gas industry.
And if you’re wondering why some protests
seem to end in tear gas,
and others end in dance parties,
I have noticed it seems to depend on
whether or not the police show up.
Interesting.
But the situation in Hong Kong will only get
worse.
Protesters are already calling for another
protest this weekend.
And they’re using lightsabers as a play
on laser pointers.
Meaning now, Hong Kong protesters will face
their greatest enemy yet—
a copyright lawsuit from Disney.
And may I just remind everyone that Google
and YouTube
have taken to instantly demonetizing,
and in some cases age-restricting,
our Hong Kong videos.
That’s why we need your help.
Share this episode with your friends and family.
Because YouTube won’t.
And now I’ll answer a question
from a fan who supports China Uncensored
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
We couldn’t afford to keep making China
Uncensored
if it weren’t for the support of fans I
call my 50-Cent Army.
Joe King asks,
“Chris, does the weather pattern around
Taiwan mean
there is only a certain time of year
it is possible to try an invasion?”
Actually yes.
According to Taiwan expert Ian Easton
of the Project 2049 Research Institute,
there are only two narrow windows of time
each year
that it would be possible to move large numbers
of Chinese troops
by boat across the Strait of Taiwan.
I mean, if invading the island of Taiwan were
easy,
the Party probably would have tried by now.
As it is, despite all the talk of invasion,
the Chinese Communist Party probably would
find
the whole prospect far too risky,
especially when there’s turmoil in Hong
Kong,
which is a problem much closer to home.
Thanks for your question, Joe.
And if you have a question for me
you want to hear answered on the show,
sign up to join the China Uncensored 50 cent
army,
by supporting the show with a dollar or more
per episode.
Again, YouTube is demonetizing us so much
we would have to shut down the show
if it weren’t for your support.
And to everyone,
thanks for watching!
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.