bjbj,(,( First Dead Pigs, Now Angry (Plague-Ridden)
Birds Visit Beautiful Shanghai! Hello and
welcome to China Uncensored, I m your host
and visionary shaman, Chris Chappell. The
gods are angry! At least, you d be forgiven
for believing that if you re, say, a Chinese
villager who lives somewhere near Shanghai.
First, tens of thousands of local pigs died
and fell into the Huangpu River under mysterious
circumstances. Then, you start hearing about
new cases of the dreaded bird flu, striking
dead four people in the region and two nearby.
But for sophisticated, middle class urban
types, it s a godsend Shanghai s finally catching
up in the rankings for top cities facing imminent
apocalyptic disaster! After all, for years
Asia biggest and most prosperous city was
Tokyo, where the city s most popular form
of recreation is watching itself be crushed
by space moths or decimated by bioengineered
pseudo-mystical cyborgs that are trying to
obliterate mankind. Or something like that.
That one went a little over my head, to be
honest. Anyway, in comparison, a river full
of pork and a new strain of deadly super influenza
seem almost mediocre. But China s authorities
don t seem to mind, they ve reported on both
stories, without even seeming to try for a
massive cover-up. The news coverage was a
little slow, and it lagged behind public reporting
on Weibo and other websites, but still; the
news actually reported something big, bad
and dangerous happening in China. That s like
Russian news agencies reporting that Vladimir
Putin throws like a girl. Of course, it s
worth looking at some historical context.
When the crisis over SARS hit in late 2002,
news was relentlessly suppressed until so
many had been infected that it would have
been very hard not to acknowledge the problem.
Eventually, thousands caught the disease and
hundreds died, and the failed cover-up gave
the Chinese regime a major publicity black
eye. This television station was one of the
very few media that initially broke news of
the SARS crisis. Now Chinese citizens using
Weibo and similar tools are also able to push
official media into reporting on some stories
but only the facts that they absolutely have
to. But when it comes to problems that no
one has publicized online, or that are totally
censored from the Internet, there s still
no guarantee the Communist Party will even
acknowledge their existence. For instance,
are there any unknown bird flu cases besides
those already reported? Did those pigs communicate
any diseases to humans? Who knows! So for
Shanghai residents, the best way to stay safe
might be to keep your cell-phone handy, take
pictures of any weird animal corpses you come
across, and try to get them online before
the black vans show up. As for those outside
China, why should we care about a few censored
epidemics here and there? After all, Shanghai
s so far away, and germs are really, really
small it seems VERY unlikely that they could
travel all the way to somewhere I d be affected.
Well, that s it for today! Hate to run, but
I ve got to get to the arrivals terminal at
JFK airport. hC~; [Content_Types].xml #!MB
;c=1 _rels/.rels theme/theme/themeManager.xml
sQ\}# theme/theme/theme1.xml G$$DA : BR \{i5@R
V*[_X ,l\Y Ssd+r] 5\|E Vky- V4Ej 6NGU s?^V
* 7;wP EBU` 5VD
GGHPXNT, /M,W m2iU [[v _Xtl theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.rels
6?$Q K(M&$R(.1 [Content_Types].xmlPK _rels/.relsPK
theme/theme/themeManager.xmlPK theme/theme/theme1.xmlPK
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.relsPK
<a:clrMap xmlns:a="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/main"
bg1="lt1" tx1="dk1" bg2="lt2" tx2="dk2" accent1="accent1"
accent2="accent2" accent3="accent3" accent4="accent4"
accent5="accent5" accent6="accent6" hlink="hlink"
folHlink="folHlink"/> Ryan Mitchell Normal.dotm
Chris Microsoft Macintosh Word PICT) z$>H
g9g9c g9g9^ kZkZs o\{kZg9o\{ o\{o\{w o\{o\{s o\{g9
4kZc g9kZc g9o\{^ o\{g9Z kZg9c kZo\{c kZ&o\{w
o\{kZo\{w o\{kZo\{c kZkZw kZkZg9o\{g9s kZo\{g9o\{o\{c
o\{g9s kZg9 o\{kZw kZkZs g9o\{w g9g9Z o\{kZs g9kZg9kZs
kZkZs kZkZ^ kZkZo\{s kZkZ kZo\{kZo\{o\{kZZ o\{kZg9g9s
g9kZg9s kZo\{w o\{kZ^ o\{kZ^ g9kZc g9g9o\{ g9o\{c
o\{NsR g9g9w kZg9kZs kZkZo\{^ g9kZ^ g9g9w g9g9c
o\{g9g9kZs g9kZ^ o\{kZs o\{kZw kZo\{o\{^ o\{*w o\{kZs
o\{kZs o\{o\{s o\{o\{g9o\{kZs kZkZw o\{kZw o\{kZw
o\{g9 o\{g9 kZg9o\{o\{c g9g9kZ 4g9V g9g9Z o\{g9V
kZkZg9Z o\{o\{^ g9o\{V o\{g9^ g9o\{kZg9g9Z kZkZg9c
g9kZg9c g9g9c g9o\{ kZkZ^ g9g9o\{Z o\{o\{s o\{o\{^
o\{o\{s kZkZs o\{o\
s kZkZw o\{o\{s g9g9o\{s o\{g9s o\{o\{w o\{o\{ 4g9g9w
g9g9\{ o\{o\{kZ^ g9g9s g9kZo\{g9g9c o\{g9kZkZZ
o\{kZg9g9s g9g9\{ kZg9c g9kZs g9o\{o\{kZkZc g9o\
o\{g9g9Z g9o\{c o\{kZc g9kZZ g9o\{c g9g9Z g9o\
g9kZg9c o\{kZkZw g9kZo\{o\
g9o\{o\{kZkZo\{s g9o\{o\{kZs o\{kZg9w o\{o\{ g9kZkZR
g9g9c kZo\{ o\{o\
o\{g9^ o\{kZ o\{kZc g9kZkZg9g9kZg9Z o\{o\{s o\{kZw
o\{o\{s kZo\{g9\{ g9o\{o\{w o\{o\{^ o\{kZs o\{o\{kZ o\{o\{
o\{o\{s o\{o\{g9o\{o\{s g9g9s o\{g9w o\{o\{s o\{o\{s
g9o\{s kZo\{^ kZg9c o\{g9o\{kZ g9o\{ g9kZo\{c o\{kZ^
kZkZV o\{kZg9c g9g9w o\{kZg9c kZg9c o\{g9c g9g9^
g9g9kZZ g9o\{ o\{o\{^ o\{o\{ o\{o\
kZo\{s o\{o\{w o\{g9s o\{g9w o\{kZc kZo\{s o\{g9s
o\{g9s g9g9o\{kZg9g9o\{s kZo\{o\{kZkZc o\{kZkZ g9kZg9kZc
kZo\{ kZo\{kZc o\{g9c "o\{Z Bg9R g9NsZ g9NsV g9kZg9o\{^
g9kZZ g9g9^ kZg9s o\{o\{s o\{o\{ o\{o\{w kZg9w o\{kZ
o\
kZo\{c kZo\{s g9g9 g9g9kZc kZg9o\{c &g9V o\{g9g9^
g9g9c o\{o\{Z g9g9kZkZc g9g9Z kZg9c g9kZ g9-c
kZg9s g9kZkZg9c g9g9o\{Z g9kZkZg9g9kZg9kZg9^
g9g9c o\{g9c &o\{w o\{o\{w o\{o\{s kZo\{o\{w o\{o\{w
kZo\{o\{kZo\{o\{s o\{o\
o\{g9s g9g9o\{s kZg9c o\{g9o\{g9g9o\{g9g9o\{o\{c
(g9R o\{kZV kZg9c g9o\{ g91\{ g9kZZ g9g9c g9o\{^
kZg9g9o\{c kZg9g9c g9g9o\{g9kZc g9o\{ o\{o\{w kZo\{w
o\{o\{ o\{o\{kZ o\{&s o\{kZs o\{kZkZs kZo\{g9kZo\{s
o\{g9s kZg9s o\{o\{ g9kZo\{g9g9kZg9kZg9o\{kZg9s
kZg9Z g9g9kZo\{g9 g9g9kZo\{g9s g9g9s kZo\{g9g9kZkZg9g9kZo\{c
Title Microsoft Word 97-2004 Document NB6W
Word.Document.8