On this episode of China Uncensored,
now you can eat like Mao Zedong!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored. I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
Now you might be wondering...where’s Chris?!
Why isn’t he in his studio?!
And why isn’t he wearing a tie!
Well, today, I thought I’d try something
a little different.
Recently I asked viewers to fill out a survey.
And one thing 41.8% of you told me is that
you’re interested in Chinese cooking!
So today, I’m going to teach you how to
cook a famous Chinese dish!
And by that, I mean I’m going to let someone
who actually knows what they’re doing teach you.
This is Cici Li, host of Food Paradise.
Hi!
Today Cici and I are making a type of Hongshao
Rou, or Red Braised Pork Belly.
Hongshao Rou was the favorite dish of the
Great Helmsman himself—Chairman Mao Zedong.
Even as 30 million of his people were starving
to death during the Great Famine
he helped cause,
Mao managed to enjoy the best food out there,
and that’s Hongshao Rou.
Not just because it’s delicious,
but also because Mao never brushed his teeth
and by the time he was older they were so
rotten he could only eat soft foods.
Incidentally, when Mao’s doctor expressed
concern about his dental hygiene,
Mao replied, “A tiger never brushes his
teeth.”
Which I fact-checked.
And it turns out tigers do sometimes clean
their own teeth.
But anyway,
there’s a lot of regional varieties of Hongshao
rou out there.
And all of them are soft and delicious.
Mao Zedong was from Hunan province,
so he liked the spicy style Hongshao rou.
But today, Cici and I are going to cook a
different style
an even more delicious style.
It’s from Zhejiang province.
And here’s the story behind it.
During the Song Dynasty,
there was a famous poet named Su Dongpo.
In China, he’s known for creating the bold
and unconstrained style of poetry
known as Háofàng, or “heroic abandon.”
But in the West,
if he’s known at all,
it’s for his bold and unconstrained style
of pork belly known as Dongpo rou.
Now like most famous Chinese poets,
Su Dongpo liked to drink.
A lot.
And as one among many versions of the story
goes,
one day Su Dongpo told his chef that he wanted
a bit of meat and a bit of wine.
But the chef misunderstood,
combining the wine and pork before cooking
the hongshou rou.
It was a weird mistake to make, but it turned
out to be a delicious one.
And so this dish became a thing,
and it was eventually named in Su Dongpo’s
honor.
Of course, it’s impossible to verify this
story.
But it would be awesome if today we’re enjoying
the fruits of a drunken poet’s mistake
900 years ago.
So anyway, today Cici and I going to show
you how to make Dongpo rou—or Dongpo style
braised pork belly.
So click here or in the info bar to head over
to Cici’s channel, Food Paradise.
See you on the other side.
Why are you still here?
Look at this delicious Dongpo rou!
How could you not want to watch us make this
for you?
Seriously. Click here.