On this episode of China Uncensored,
is Australia being infiltrated
at all levels of society and government
by a highly organized network of Chinese spies?
Or is Australia just being racist?
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Something’s rotten in the state of Australia.
And I’m not talking about Vegemite.
I’m talking about racism.
The Chinese Embassy has accused
the Australian media and government of having,
“a Cold War mentality,”
“racial prejudice,”
and “anti-China hysteria and paranoia.”
Why?
Well, let’s listen to this report
from Australian media in June.
“A joint investigation by a team of journalists
from Four Corners and Fairfax Media
has exposed a concerted campaign
by the Chinese government and its proxies
to infiltrate the Australian political process
to promote its own interests.”
I’m not seeing any racism here so far.
Okay, but Prime Minister Malcolm Turnbull
just announced new laws targeting Chinese
Australians.
And it’s got China’s Foreign Ministry
seething.
“We were shocked at what Turnbull had said.
Such comments pander to certain
irresponsible reports in Australian media,
they are full of prejudice against China.”
Yeah, just listen to what Turnbull said
at the beginning of the month.
“I want to be very clear,
we have focused on the activities
of foreign states and their agents in Australia,
and not the loyalties of Australians
who happen to be from another country.”
Wait, so he’s specifically stating
that the issue is not about questioning
the loyalties of Chinese Australians.
I’m not seeing the racism there, either.
Could the Chinese Communist Party be,
I don’t know,
using racism to distract everyone
from the actual facts?
But would they really do such a thing?
After all,
China’s state-run People’s Daily
said that the Australian government should
“uphold the principle of truth from facts.”
Well, let’s take a look at the facts.
This December marks 45 years
of bilateral relations between
the People’s Republic of China and Australia.
According to the New York Times,
“China has long treated Australia
as a laboratory for soft power experiments,
flexing its economic muscle,
sending students to study at its universities
and creating organizations with close ties
to the Communist Party.”
That was also the gist of the Fairfax Media
and Four Corners reports earlier this year.
However, what China failed to realize
is that by sending its citizens to study in
Australia,
they’d end up with—
let’s be honest here—
the most confusing English accent.
I mean, “Chocco”?
“Bickie”?
“Macca’s”?
I rest my case.
Anyway, in response to media reports exposing
the CCP’s attempts to influence Australia,
the Turnbull government is proposing laws
banning foreign campaign donations,
and requiring transparent registration of
foreign agents.
The laws are actually modeled after
similar laws in the United States.
They make it illegal
to support foreign intelligence agencies,
leak information,
and steal trade secrets,
with offenders facing 15-20 years in prison.
Notice that none of that specifically targets
China.
It’s just that,
considering which foreign powers
are actively trying to infiltrate Australia,
China will be most affected by the new laws.
Take a specific case for example:
Australian Parliament Member Sam Dastyari
—
whose face answers the question
“What if Mr. Bean ate too many Tim Tams,
ran for office,
then resigned in disgrace?”
Media are now calling Sam Dastyari
“Shanghai Sam”—
but there’s nothing funny about that.
Because the media reports I just mentioned
uncovered thousands of dollars worth of
campaign contributions made to Dastyari
by Huang Xiangmo,
a Chinese billionaire with questionable ties
to the Chinese regime.
Now while that all was very sketchy,
under Australia’s old campaign contribution
laws,
“sketchy” was perfectly legal.
In fact, Huang Xiangmo gave
almost 2.7 million dollars
to the three biggest Australian political
parties
over the course of four years.
At least a million of that was raised
by Dastyari for his Australian Labor Party.
But earlier this month,
it came out that
Huang Xiangmo and Dastyari’s relationship
went deeper than anyone expected.
At a press conference with Chinese media in
2016,
Dastyari contradicted his own party’s stance
on the South China Sea.
No one knew exactly what he said,
just that Chinese media started reporting
that he was saying Australia
should butt out of the South China Sea conflict—
which was the opposite of what the Labor Party
had just said the day before.
The Labor Party was saying the Chinese regime
should abide by a recent ruling by the Hague
rejecting China’s claim to a big portion
of the South China Sea.
After some controversy,
Dastyari said he took “a foreign policy
question
he shouldn't have taken,
mumbled it and answered it incorrectly."
But you know, he only mumbled some answer,
that’s not really all that bad, right?
It’s just in keeping with his Mr. Bean persona.
And so he began to build up his career again.
Except a recording of that conference just
came out.
And it sure doesn’t sound like mumbling.
“The Chinese integrity of its borders
is a matter for China,
and the role that Australia
should be playing as a friend is to know,
that with the several thousand years of history,
thousands of years of history,
where it is and isn’t our place to be involved.”
You know, thousands of years of history!
China’s borders are China’s business!
Australia should just butt out.
Why, that sounds just like
the official Communist Party line!
And we now know that a few weeks
after Dastyari “mumbled” that response,
he also kind of accidentally stumbled his
way
to Huang Xiangmo’s mansion and alerted him
that
“his phone was probably being tapped
by security agencies.”
As in, “Hey the Australian authorities are
watching you.
You might want to use a burner phone
for all your illegal activities.
Just saying.
As a friend.”
What a lovable klutz.
Just like Mr. Bean.
Dastyari is also accused of trying to
pressure another member of his own party
to cancel a meeting with a pro-democracy activist
while she was in Hong Kong.
And now that all this has come out
and there are calls for Dastyari
to resign from Parliament,
he is once again parroting
the Communist Party line.
But this time, about racism.
“I expect Turnbull and the Liberals to smear
me,
but for he and his colleagues to suggest
that I am not a true or loyal Australian
is incredibly hurtful—
and hurtful to all overseas-born Australians.”
Dastyari is referring to the fact
that he was born in Iran,
which is definitely relevant to the fact
that he’s accused of selling out to China.
But anyway, Shanghai Sam is resigning now,
saying he won’t return to parliament in
2018.
Unfortunately, he isn’t one of a kind.
Australia’s security agency ASIO
just “identified 10 state and local political
candidates
linked to Chinese intelligence agencies.”
ASIO didn’t name names,
but did indicate that at least one of the
people
was elected and is still in office.
He or she is probably getting their
“I was just mumbling” defense ready.
Anyway, Australia is like the canary in the
coal mine.
Other countries need to take a look
at what’s happening because it’s not just
Australia.
In the coming months,
there will be a lot more coming out
about the Chinese Communist Party’s
attempts to influence Western countries.
And it seems the US is taking notice.
But there’s something that Western media
and governments should be careful about.
After these stories broke in the Australian
media,
there have been legitimate instances of racism
and harassment of Chinese people in Australia.
And that’s a shame.
Not just because racism is bad.
Which it is.
But expressing prejudice against 1.2 million
Chinese Australians also plays
right into the Chinese Communist Party’s
hands.
Let’s not forget that the first victims
of the CCP’s
infiltration into foreign countries
are the Chinese people living in those countries.
They are the first ones to be infiltrated
and influenced,
not to mention silenced, by the Party.
The CCP’s United Front Work Department
has a special division dedicated to targeting
overseas Chinese to, uh,
“maintain” their loyalty.
And then when the CCP’s actions
cause a backlash toward normal Chinese Australians,
the Chinese regime changes tactics,
trying to act like it’s the defender of
overseas Chinese,
heroically protecting them
from a racist Australian government and media.
In this case,
I think the Australian government and media
have been for the most part very careful
to not be racist against Chinese Australians.
Sure, that hasn’t stopped the CCP
from making their accusations.
But, like the People’s Daily said,
we can all judge the “truth from facts.”
So what do you think about Australia’s
new foreign interference laws?
And what do you think about the Chinese regime’s
claims of racism?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Don’t hurt the feelings of the Chinese people.
Visit ChinaUncensored.tv.
We upload full half hour episodes
you won’t see on YouTube.
Learn about interference from the Chinese
regime,
before even world leaders do!
ChinaUncensored.tv.