On this episode of China Uncensored,
I wonder what China will buy
with its new military budget.
The US sends an Aircraft Carrier to Vietnam.
And finally, the sky isn’t falling.
That’s just China’s out of control space
station.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
First, an update from last week.
The Chinese military got the big pay raise
they were asking for.
175 billion dollars.
That’s a jump from last year.
But it still can’t compare to the United
States.
The Pentagon is asking for one of
the biggest budget boosts in US history.
“We will have a military like we’ve never
had before.
We’re going to have an incredible military.”
I assume that means we’re finally getting
Jaegers.
The increase in China’s military spending
comes along with China keeping
a projected GDP growth
of six and half percent this year.
At least, that’s what Chinese premier
Li Keqiang announced.
Think they’ll succeed?
Well, considering Li Keqiang also once said,
“China’s GDP figures are ‘man-made’
and therefore unreliable,”
...I’d say yes,
they have a pretty good chance
of hitting that six and half percent target.
US Secretary of State Rex Tillerson
has criticized Chinese investment in Africa.
“Chinese investment does have
the potential to address
Africa's infrastructure gap
but its approach has led to mounting debt
and few, if any, jobs in most countries.
When coupled with the political
and fiscal pressure,
this endangers Africa's natural resources
and its long-term economic,
political stability.”
Recently, the Chinese Communist Party
has been using what’s called
the One Belt, One Road Initiative
to offer big loans to developing nations
around the world.
But the Party has been offering
infrastructure loans to African countries
for years.
It’s been called a new form of colonialism.
In particular, it’s been a great way
for the Chinese regime to drain
African countries of their natural resources.
But it still has been unable to make inroads
into the wealthiest African nation:
Wakanda.
The Communist Party would love to get
their hands on some of that sweet,
sweet vibranium.
A US aircraft carrier visited Vietnam,
and, unlike last time,
it didn’t kill anyone.
This is the first carrier visit to Vietnam
since the fall of Saigon in 1975.
It’s a four day port of call.
Crew will visit a hospital and center
for victims of some rather nasty weapons
used by the US during the Vietnam War.
Like Agent Orange.
That sounds like fun.
The reason the US and Vietnam
are burying the hatchet,
or the Agent Orange as it were,
is because Vietnam is at least
less upset at the US than at China.
The Chinese regime has been
aggressively expanding in the South China
Sea,
in waters claimed by Vietnam.
And considering the violent history
between China and Vietnam over
the last, say, thousand years,
Vietnam is having flashbacks.
Of course Chinese state-run media
says they totally don’t care.
Totally.
And it’s not just Vietnam.
The Chinese regime has angered
a lot of its neighbors because of
territorial conflicts in the South China Sea.
But at least the Chinese Communist Party
cares deeply about the region’s environment.
That’s why they’re building a marine park.
My favorite state-run media
the Global Times wrote,
“Protection of unique and rich resources
in the South China Sea has always
been given great importance,
especially when some of the resources,
such as coral reefs,
are very fragile.”
And the Chinese regime really does
care about protecting the coral reefs.
Especially now that the coral reefs
in the region are almost complete gone.
Because they were destroyed
by the Chinese regime.
And the most powerful man, Xi Jinping,
may have another title added to his growing
list—
one that already includes General Secretary
of the Communist Party,
President of the nation,
and Commander-in-Chief of the military.
His newest title:
Living Bodhisattva.
That’s a sort of buddha-on-earth,
who carries out acts of compassion
to help mankind.
Ok, this may not be his official
Communist Party title—
remember, they’re atheist.
But the Party secretary
of the largely Tibetan province of Qinghai,
Wang Guosheng, said that Tibetans who live
there
have been saying they view Xi Jinping
as a deity.
I mean, it makes sense.
Xi Jinping
is incredibly powerful.
He just granted himself the role
of president-for-life.
People have photos of him in their homes and
even churches
And he can use supernatural powers to generate
GDP growth.
Ok, so in Chinese,
it’s kind of like calling someone
“a living saint”
so Party Secretary Wang
might not have been that serious.
But it was still some impressive brown-nosing.
Especially since it’s also a slight dig
at the Dalai Lama.
Traditionally the Dalai Lama
is considered the living reincarnation
of a specific bodhisattva.
And Party Secretary Wang said that
the Tibetans see only Xi Jinping
as a living bodhisattva.
Ooo, burn.
And just a friendly reminder.
China’s out of control space station,
called Tiangong-1, is expected to crash land
somewhere on Earth in the next few weeks.
Usually when a satellite falls out of orbit,
it mostly burns up in the atmosphere.
But according to the US funded Aerospace Corporation,
“There is a chance that
a small amount of Tiangong-1 debris
may survive reentry and impact the ground.”
Where will it fall?
Aerospace uses this map to show
where it’s most likely to land.
The highest probability is in the yellow areas.
Hey, wait a minute,
I’m in one of the yellow areas.
What’s that, Shelley?
The odds of it hitting anyone
are a million times smaller
than winning the lottery?
Oh good.
I think.
If you do end up having
a close encounter with Tiangong-1,
there may be a highly toxic
and corrosive fuel on board,
so please, don’t touch the debris
or inhale any vapors it may emit.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode
of China Uncensored.
Once again, I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Well the Chinese Communist Party
is certainly rotten.
But you know what never goes bad?
Food from Thrive Life.
Thrive Life sells freeze dried meals
that stay fresh.
And if you order through the link
in the description below,
China Uncensored gets a cut.
I wouldn’t ask you to eat their food
if I didn’t also personally love it.
So support your belly and China Uncensored
by buying some delicious food from Thrive
Life.
The link is below.