Trump declares a national emergency.
It’s been dubbed the ‘Huawei ban’.
What does this mean for security?
And how will this affect Huawei’s global
ambitions?
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Last week, US President Donald Trump signed
an Executive Order
saying no way to Huawei.
Well technically, it doesn't actually say
that.
What it does say is "Executive Order on Securing
the Information and Communications Technology
and Services Supply Chain."
But a title like that is totally un-tweetable.
So everyone's just calling it the 'Huawei
ban.'
To be fair, Trump's executive order doesn't
actually name Huawei.
But everyone knows who he’s talking about.
It’s like that time in college when the
dining hall
took away all the waffle makers
because somebody kept breaking in at 2am
and stealing waffles.
Dave.
Anyway, Huawei is the world’s largest provider
of networking gear
and the world’s number two smartphone vendor,
behind Samsung.
For years, congressional committees, the FBI,
the NSA,
and others have flagged close ties between
Huawei
and the Chinese Communist Party.
Last year, the US government banned...
the US government...
from using equipment made by Huawei
and the other big Chinese telecom company,
ZTE.
That was over security concerns.
But the new executive order took that ban
a big step further.
First, Trump declared a "national emergency."
And before you think,
“Here Trump goes again,
declaring another national emergency,”
it’s actually pretty common.
Obama declared 13 national emergencies.
George W. Bush declared 14,
and Clinton also declared 14.
So really, there are a lot more national emergencies
for President Trump to declare before his
term is up.
He’s probably got a list.
Anyway, here’s how Trump’s current national
emergency works.
The Executive Order itself stops the use of
IT goods and services
from all companies subject to “foreign adversaries”
that pose “unacceptable risks” to national
security.
Then, the Commerce Department effectively
labeled Huawei
as belonging to one of those “foreign adversaries”—
i.e.
China—
by putting Huawei and 72 of its affiliates
on the Commerce Department’s “Entity List.”
The Entity List is a trade blacklist.
Anyone on it is barred from buying
parts and components from US companies
without getting the US government’s approval
first.
And that approval is no easy thing.
That's because the ban has a so-called
"policy of presumption of denial."
Meaning, it's a no unless there's a really,
really good reason to say yes.
And \h"the U.S.
Government has determined that there is
reasonable cause to believe that Huawei
has been involved in activities contrary to
the national security
or foreign policy interests of the United
States."
So I'm guessing Huawei purchases are generally
going to be a “no.”
"All the witnesses could you please raise
your hand
if you'd use products or services from Huawei
or ZTE?
None of you would.
You obviously lead intelligence services,
so that's something of a biased question.
Raise your hand if you would recommend that
private American citizens use Huawei
or ZTE products or services?
None of you again are raising your hand.
Thank you for that."
Senator Cotton raises an important point.
Or I assume he did because I was distracted
by the way that he kept mispronouncing Huawei.
It’s Huawei, with an H, people.
It’s not Wah-Wei.
Stop saying it like that!
Ahem.
Now if you're wondering what
the heads of US intelligence services know
about Huawei
that the average person does not,
here's FBI Director Christopher Wray.
“It provides the capacity to maliciously
modify or steal information,
and it provides the capacity to conduct undetected
espionage.”
Simply put, officials are worried that Huawei
will help the Chinese regime spy on the US
or attack America’s cyber infrastructure.
How might Huawei do that specifically?
One way is “that companies like Huawei
might sell products compromised by ‘back
doors’
that allow Chinese government hackers
access to data or surveillance."
Although frankly,
I’m more concerned that if we put all our
technology
in the hands of equipment made in China,
one day it will simply stop working.
And when we try to reach customer service,
we keep getting redirected to the Chinese
consulate.
And they don’t even have our package!
Now, back in 2011 and 2012,
Vodaphone did find hidden backdoors in Huawei
equipment.
And there have been other reports of Huawei
backdoors.
But it’s not clear whether Huawei
purposefully included these backdoors,
or whether they were accidental security flaws
resulting from bad design.
Either way is bad.
So is there smoking gun evidence that Huawei
is putting back doors into its technology,
designed to allow it to spy on users?
No.
But there’s plenty of reason to believe
they would be motivated to.
Like Huawei's uncomfortably close links
to the armed wing of the Chinese Communist
Party—
the People's Liberation Army.
"Huawei is the PLA.
And if the senior executives of Huawei don't
like me saying that,
then bring it.
You are—and I would love to have discovery
on this one—
you are the People's Liberation Army."
I know what you’re thinking.
Steve Bannon, he’s probably just trying
to rile people up
by mispronouncing Wah-Wey
and mentioning the PLA.
It turns out, no.
Bannon just doesn’t know how to pronounce
Huawei, either.
Also, the founder and CEO of Huawei, Ren Zhengfei,
was an engineer with the People's Liberation
Army.
And last year for the 40th anniversary of
China’s
so-called “reform and opening-up,”
Ren Zhengfei was hailed one of 100 “excellent
private entrepreneurs”
who “firmly safeguard the leadership of
the Chinese Communist party.”
So much for being a totally independent private
company.
But the Trump administration’s moves have
already hamstrung Huawei.
For now, the Commerce Department’s Entity
List has had the biggest effect.
That’s the one that prevents US companies
from selling to Huawei.
According to Bloomberg,
top US tech companies have already begun to
cut off
the supply of microchips and other technology
to Huawei.
Chinese state-run media has gone on the defensive,
saying the Huawei ban is nothing
and we’ll be totally fine without chips
from American suppliers,
and really, who wants Made in America chips
anyway?
Huawei's chip arm HiSilicon said last Friday
it's been prepared for the scenario
that it could be banned from purchasing U.S.
chips and technology.
HiSilicon says it's been "vigorously investing
in self-developed technologies,
and is able to ensure a steady supply of most
products
to make sure Huawei will be able to continue
serving its customers."
Or, as HiSilicon president said in a letter
cited by Straits Times,
“now is the time for ‘all the spare tyres
in the safe’ to become useful.”
Ok, firstly, who keeps tires in a safe?
Secondly, what does a microchip company do
with tires, anyway?
I think what we really need is a ban on stupid
metaphors.
Anyway, Huawei's CEO also insisted that Huawei
is totally ready for the ban—
while also briefly noting that “the company's
annual revenue growth
may undershoot 20 percent.”
That’s a lot to... “undershoot”.
It’s like, if you’re flying from New York
to San Francisco,
and you undershoot by 20%,
you’ll end up in Battle Mountain, Nevada.
And no one wants to end up in Battle Mountain,
Nevada.
It’s the Armpit of America.
And while Chinese media are saying 'there's
nothing to see here',
the Chinese Foreign Ministry sure is crying
foul.
“We call upon the U.S. to stop using the
excuse of 'security issues'
to indiscriminately suppress Chinese companies,
and provide a fair,
just environment devoid of discrimination
for Chinese companies
investing and operating in the U.S.”
Yes, it’s very unfair for the US
to discriminate against Chinese companies.
How could a country just outright ban
foreign tech companies from operating in their
market.
So unjust.
And on a totally unrelated note, Google.
One of numerous American tech companies
that has been blocked from the China market.
Google announced it would cut Huawei off from
some of the Android software that Huawei runs
on.
Specifically, Huawei won't be able to license
the Android operating system with Google services,
and will instead have to use a bare-bones
open-source version of Android.
And that means Huawei is in trouble.
"Half of all of its shipments are sold outside
of China
and all of those shipments depend on Google
services
being present on them.
If they're not present on them,
no matter how good anything Huawei comes up
with is,
they're going to have a really hard time
selling devices outside of China a
nd that is the essence of the problem."
One tech industry consultant said,
“It will be like an instant kill switch
for Huawei’s ambition
to overtake Samsung in the global market.”
But Huawei has a little more time to figure
it out.
Because earlier this week,
the Commerce Department issued a temporary
license
that allows Huawei to do business with US
companies for 90 days.
That means if you have a Huawei phone,
you can get your Android updates until August!
And after that,
Huawei will roll out its own software.
I hear that when you use Huawei Maps,
no matter where you are in the world,
you’re still within the nine-dash line.
So what do you think about the Huawei ban?
Leave your comments below.
And while you’re here,
it’s time for me to answer another question
from a fan who supports China Uncensored
with a dollar or more per episode—
through the crowdfunding website Patreon.
xXAMightyStormXx asks:
“...I've been thinking of getting a Huawei
phone
and just google pro chinese stuff on it
to make sure that I get to be in
the good foreigners for china bracket in the
CCP
Do you guys think that would work?”
Well, if you get a Huawei phone,
you might not be able to do much Googling
on it after all.
But as for the idea of a foreigner saying
pro-CCP things
on your phone to get in their good graces,
don’t bother.
You’ll waste your time
because no one will bother monitoring you.
And unless you’re actually working for a
Chinese company in China,
it’s not going to help you get promoted.
Now if you want to do it much more publicly,
maybe someone will notice and get you a job
working for Chinese state-run media,
where you can spend all day posting stories
about pandas.
It’s hard to imagine a worse job.
Thanks for your question.
And thanks for watching China Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.