On this episode of China Uncensored
The true meaning of democracy with Chinese
characteristics
Hello and welcome to China Uncensored
I'm your host Chris Chappell
If you were watching the lamestream media last year
you probably heard a lot of nonsense like this:
India is surely the biggest democracy on this planet
The world's most populous democracy
India - they are the world's largest democracy by a mile
The only country larger than them at all is
not a democracy
Or is it?
Fortunately, my favorite Chinese state-run
newspaper Global Times
is here to set the record straight
In this recent article entitled:
which country is really the world's largest
democracy?
The answer to that obviously is China
The author Han Zhen explains that China's
National People's Congress system
is in fact a democracy
not only should we criticize the false nature
of western democracy
he writes
but we must clarify the democratic nature
of our country China
as Han Zhen describes it
China is a democracy because the government
gives every ethnic group and social class
an opportunity to take part in policymaking
and the selection of leadership
It's true
You may have heard that China is a one-party
dictatorship
but there are in fact eight other political
parties
under the Communist Party's United Front department
five of them even have the word democracy
right there in their names
representatives from these parties occupy
about twenty-five percent
of the seats in the National People's Congress
See?
Multiparty Democracy and unlike any ineffective
so-called democracies in the West
China's congressional representatives are
loyal
They've passed every single bill put before
them in the last 60 years
most of them unanimously
See?
China knows how to get things done
Simply change the definition of what it means
to be a democracy
and voila
you have the world's largest democracy
And if that's not Democratic enough for you
China's nearly 1 million villages hold direct
elections for village chief
and to ensure that the village chief represents
the true interest of the people
the Communist Party appoints its local party
secretary to oversee him
or in most cases the party secretary IS the
one who gets elected
which is just more efficient
so as you can see this all follows China's
Constitution
which clearly sets forth China's democratic
system
under the leadership of the Communist Party
of China
and the guidance of Marxism-Leninism and Mao
Zedong Thought
the Chinese people of all nationalities will
continue to adhere
to the People's Democratic Dictatorship
Speaking of Mao Zedong Thought who better
to explain China's democracy
then chairman Mao himself?
A man still so revered that his portrait watches
over Tiananmen Square
The last resting place of his own decaying
corpse
Anyway Mao thought that the rest of the world
was corrupt
In his selected works he wrote
After the outbreak of the Second Imperialist
War
i.e. the Second World War
there is hardly a trace of democracy in many
of the capitalist countries
which have come or are coming under the bloody
militarist dictatorship of the bourgeoisie
well obviously a democracy under capitalism is bad
and so are bloody military dictatorships
that much we can all agree on
so chairman Mao, tell us what kind of government
China ought to have
Let's see
democracy is shared by the common people
by which Mao means: the peasants and the farmers
Check!
The bourgeoisie i.e the middle class, are
not allowed to own things privately
Check! - obviously
and it's led by the working class i.e blue-collar
factory types
Check!
Mao was right
China is a democracy
Take that!
800 million voters in India
So what do you think about China being the
world's largest democracy
Leave your comments below and be sure to subscribe
for more episodes
Once again I'm Chris Chappell
See you next time!