While Venezuelans starve
President Maduro struggles to maintain
his grip on power
And a Chinese tech company
Is giving him the tools
to keep tabs on every citizen
Welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Be sure to subscribe to our YouTube channel
for the latest China news,
and click the notification bell
so you get an alert when we publish a new
episode.
Ah, Venezuela.
The socialist paradise that has it all.
Bonfires.
Outdoor fitness.
And a great national weight loss plan.
Plus a lovable dictator
who can dance his way into your heart.
Ha, ha, who would want to oust him?
No, seriously, tell me now!
Who wants to oust him?!
And to that effect, Venezuela,
the country that has it all,
now has one more thing to add to the list:
Mass government surveillance.
And guess which country is helping Maduro
build it?
Ok, you don’t have to guess.
It’s China.
In case you haven’t heard,
the Venezuelan economy has tanked.
There have been mass protests against Maduro,
and last month this man, Juan Guaidó,
said Maduro is not legitimate,
and declared himself the country’s interim
president.
Maduro does not agree.
In fact, a major reason Maduro is still in
power
is thanks to support from the Chinese Communist
Party.
There’s the financial support,
measured in billions of dollars...
and of course,
all the guns.
Well, to be fair,
a lot of those guns come from Russia, too.
Guns that may or may not be used in
all those extrajudicial killings that are
happening.
And if that’s not enough to help Maduro
maintain power,
the Chinese Communist Party has also provided
him
with the tools to recreate the same kind of
mass surveillance system they have in China.
In 2016, Maduro revealed this:
a national identity card called the fatherland
card.
Surely a fatherland card couldn’t be anything
sinister!
To be fair, Maduro almost called it
the Happy Sunshine Rewards Card
but decided that would be even more sinister.
Maduro has pushed the fatherland card hard,
saying it’s essential to “build the new
Venezuela.”
Which I imagine still has Maduro as president.
18 million Venezuelans now have a fatherland
card.
That’s more than half the population.
And the guess what?
The Fatherland Card is actually a chip card
created by China’s state-linked company
ZTE.
It’s same kind of smart card technology
Chinese authorities use inside China
to track people's social, political,
and economic behavior.
Just to give you an idea of
what kind of wonderful company ZTE is,
their largest stakeholder and largest client
are both the Chinese government.
And two years ago,
ZTE was forced to pay a billion dollar settlement
to the US Commerce Department after
violating US sanctions on Iran and North Korea.
In fact, ZTE might right now
even be violating US sanctions
by working with the Venezuelan government.
This is the trustworthy, upright company
behind Venezuela's fatherland card.
So what does the fatherland card do?
According to an investigation by Reuters,
the fatherland card database
“stores such details as birthdays,
family information, employment and income,
property owned, medical history,
state benefits received,
presence on social media,
membership of a political party
and whether a person voted.”
Does it know who you voted for?
No, of course not!
Would this guy deceive you?
That man loves salsa.
Also dancing.
But whether the fatherland card tracks
who you voted for or not,
it can definitely tell whether you’re the
type of
good quality citizen who voted
in last year’s rigged election.
You now also need the fatherland card
to receive public benefits,
like medicine, pension, and food relief.
In fact, one 76-year-old diabetic told Reuters
that a doctor refused to give him his insulin
prescription
because he didn’t have the card.
The doctor also called him “Right Wing.”
Remember kids,
if you don’t do everything
your socialist dictator asks of you,
you’re a right-wing menace to society.
The story of the fatherland card dates back
to
Venezuela’s first socialist visionary,
Hugo Chavez.
In 2007, voters rejected his bid
to remove presidential term limits.
And that’s when Chavez had the idea
for a national ID card to keep tabs on people.
You know, to make sure people get
all the government services they’re entitled
to.
Yeah.
And if anyone knows how to make sure people
get what’s coming to them,
it’s the Chinese Communist Party.
A few months after Chavez
failed to get term limits removed,
he sent a delegation to China to learn how
the Communist Party was using Big Data
to monitor its citizens.
Reuters spoke to one of the people
on that original delegation.
After being initially impressed,
he began to have fears that there might be
a teensy weensy chance the technology
could lead to government abuses of privacy.
I know, that sounds pretty unfounded.
And clearly it was.
Because when he brought up his concerns
with Venezuelan officials,
a few days later,
several armed men kidnapped him,
knocked several of his teeth out with their
guns,
accused him of treasonous behavior,
and extorted money from him.
You see?
Clearly the Venezuelan government
doesn’t need China’s help to abuse power.
In fact, the only reason it took about a decade
for China to build Venezuela’s national
ID card,
was because it was too expensive
and they first tried to get Cuba to build
it.
Yeah, you know you’ve got problems
when Made in China is too expensive.
But the Cuban built version never got off
the ground,
so China’s ZTE was brought on as part of
a 70 million dollar government effort
to boost national security.
Um, I mean, to oversee the distribution
of food and services, haha.
Fun fact, Reuters found out that ZTE
is using US-built data storage units
made by American hardware maker Dell.
Reuters reached out to Dell for comment.
Apparently ZTE is a client of Dell in China,
but totally not in Venezuela.
Ah the joys of US tech companies doing business
with shady Chinese companies.
You never know where your products may end
up.
Meanwhile, as Venezuelans starve,
they need to use their Chinese-made fatherland
card
to get food and medicine.
Assuming they can get past the police
armed with Chinese-made weapons.
So what do you think of the ZTE-made fatherland
ID card?
Leave your comments below.
And before we go,
now is the time when I answer questions from
you,
my loyal 50-cent army—
fans of the show who support what we do
through the crowd funding website Patreon.
Rodney Hall asks
“Chris, your recent piece about Chinese
food fraud
both revolted and nauseated me.”
You’re welcome.
“After taking some Pepto
and doing some deep breathing exercises,
it occurred to me to ask:
what about all the imported Chinese food
sold in the USA?
How likely is it that I could be
buying food at *redacted*-Mart
made with sewer grease?”
A stomach churning question, Rodney.
While I’ve never heard of a sewer grease
making its way into the US,
Chinese imports have been
cause for concern in the past.
“Between 2004 and 2007,
an estimated 100,000 homes in more than 20
states
were built with toxic drywall imported from
China.”
Made in China toys are also sometimes toxic.
As well as cheap jewelry.
What about stuff you’re actually
supposed to put in your mouth?
Well, China does export food like garlic,
tilapia,
and cooked chicken to the US.
And the FDA has halted Chinese shipments in
the past.
I would say it’s unlikely there is sewer
grease
in exported Chinese food products,
but China does have a lot of food safety issues.
And considering the degree of China’s environmental
pollution,
And water pollution
I wouldn’t trust anything from China
with an organic label.
Thanks for your question, Rodney.
If you’d like to hear your question answered
on the show,
sign up to support China Uncensored
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
It’s less than the cost of your daily cup
of coffee.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time!