On this episode of China Uncensored:
"A million dollars isn't cool. You know what's
cool?"
"A billion people."
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I'm your
host Chris Chappell.
You know, we've all had our embarrassing moments
on Facebook, right?
Like that time I got stuck on top of a troll
in Norway.
Or that Halloween I dressed like a future
robot version of Michael Jackson.
Wait. That was awesome.
Even the founder of Facebook, Mark Zuckerberg,
has had his public foibles.
Like this picture he posted last week.
Oh ho ho, Mark, did you not notice how dangerously
full of smog the air was that day?
"It's actually 15 times the level considered
safe by the World Health Organization."
Huh, come to think of it, how did Mark Zuckerberg
even post the photo,
since Facebook looks like this in China?
I wonder if anyone else noticed that?
Oh.
Well, like I said, we all have our embarrassing
moments on Facebook.
Just not everyone gets it photoshopped into
the most iconic image of oppression from the
Tiananmen Square Massacre.
Anyway, some people have taken offense to
Zuckerberg's photo.
But that was nothing.
Because the next day, he met with the head
of China's propaganda department.
This all created fevered debate on the Chinese
interwebs,
especially on China's largest mirco blog,
Sina Weibo.
One popular account asked users,
"Will Facebook this time successfully enter
the Chinese market?"
Now, one would think even this comment wouldn't
get past Chinese censors, since Facebook has
been blocked in China since 2009.
But it wasn't long before the censors cracked
down...
on people picking on poor Mark Zuckerberg!
China Digital Times leaked this,
a top-down instruction telling press to control
"malicious commentary on Facebook founder
[Mark] Zuckerberg's visit to China."
Yes, the ones responsible for censoring Facebook
are defending the founder of Facebook.
Even CCTV said...
wait, CCTV has 21 million Facebook fans?!
In fact, the state-run Global Times brags
that CCTV's Facebook presence is
“outshining many of its foreign counterparts.”
Now anyway, it's been no secret that Mark
Zuckerberg has gone pretty far in his attempts
to woo the Chinese Communist Party.
I mean, it's understandable that he'd try
to impress crowds with his Mandarin.
And you have to admit,
this family Lunar New Year greeting was kind
of adorable,
in an awkward way.
But Zuckerberg goes that extra mile.
Like when he so coincidentally happened to
be photographed with Chinese leader Xi Jinping's book.
That was just there.
On his desk.
Prominently.
Then there was the time, I kid you not,
he asked Xi Jinping to name his unborn daughter.
Xi Jinping declined.
So I think it's safe to say Mark Zuckerberg
will do whatever it takes to get China's 700
million internet users onto Facebook.
And can you blame him, really?
Yes. Yes you can!
And not just for his embarrassing sucking
up that is obvious to people on both sides
of the Great Firewall.
The Chinese regime ranks dead last in Internet
freedom, according to a survey last year by
Freedom House.
And yet this weekend, Zuckerberg praised the
progress China has made on the Internet.
"Zuckerberg said he appreciates China's achievement
in Internet development."
Seriously?
So you're saying you appreciate China's advanced
censorship technology?
That's like going to Agent Smith and saying,
"Oh yes, I really enjoy this Matrix you've
built up. Yes, mmm, very impressive. "
"I...hate this place."
That's understandable.
Because seriously,
how would you feel if Facebook censored your
posts according to Chinese law?
My Facebook page would look like this.
And that's why I'm somewhat concerned when
my favorite state-run propaganda media says
Zuckerberg, "sets a good example for foreign countries
hoping to enter China's market."
Because if Zuckerberg is successful at getting
Facebook into China,
then he will be setting an example:
that an acceptable price for doing business
in China
is not just complying with the government's
censorship controls,
but running full tilt toward them with open
arms.
And if Zuckerberg thinks the controls are
going to loosen up,
he'd better think again.
Just this month, Chinese censors put into
effect new restrictions on foreign online publishers,
saying the purpose of content must be to "promote
core socialist values."
Which Zuckerberg should know all about from
reading Xi Jinping's book.
So for Facebook to ever be unblocked in China,
Zuckerberg will have to deal with what the
Global Times calls
a "lax filter system in dealing with harmful
information."
In other words, anything the Party doesn't
like.
And here's the thing,
I believe that Mark Zuckerberg genuinely cares
about China and Chinese culture.
It's just that by trying to get Facebook into
China,
he's helping the people who are making it
worse, keep it that way.
So what do you think about Facebook's attempt
to get into the Chinese market?
Would Zuckerberg be setting a bad precedent,
or is it worth censoring content to get Facebook
into China?
Leave your comments below.
And remember to check out the China Uncensored...
Facebook page ! While it lasts.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell. See you next
time.