On this episode of China Uncensored,
could Xi Jinping’s big campaign
wreck China’s economy?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
We’ve all been there.
Maybe it’s the Secret Santa exchange at
your office holiday party.
Or the extended family Christmas celebration.
That awkward moment when someone gives you
a gift you just don’t know what to do with.
“Thanks Aunt Marge!
A picture of the Last Supper with cat heads,
that you painted yourself!
You shouldn’t have…”
And it’s an even bigger deal in modern China,
a place with a rich tradition of less handmade
gift giving.
For example,
business leaders love to give their local
officials
something to mark the Lunar New Year,
like,
oh I don’t know,
say,
solid gold mooncakes.
Which are only slightly less edible than the
traditional kind.
But gosh darn it,
you’re a hard working official.
And there’s a pile of solid gold mooncakes,
just sitting in your office, collecting dust.
What are you going to do with those?
Re-gifting?
Nope,
There's something even better.
You can just sell these pesky gifts for cash!
Stores have cropped up around China
catering specially to officials looking to
unload bribes,
er, I mean gifts,
for some nice spendable yuan.
And then the stores turn around and resell
those bribes,
I mean, gifts,
to business leaders looking to impress
other hardworking government officials.
Yes,
These intrepid Chinese entrepreneurs have
come up with a gift recycling industry.
In fact,
it’s a 115 billion-dollar-a-year business.
That’s according to
- and I’m not making this up -
China’s Gift Industry Research Institute,
which tracks gift purchases throughout the
country.
Because yes,
in China there’s a government organ
for literally every aspect of your private
life.
This has been going on since at least 2001,
when state-run Xinhua first published an article
about it.
In 2014,
CCTV made a half hour special about the industry.
In Hangzhou alone,
there were over one hundred gift-buying shops,
usually located near government buildings.
I’m sure that’s just a coincidence.
But if you’re looking forward to selling
off
a few of your own extravagences while in Hangzhou
for the G20,
you might be in for disappointment.
Because this robust industry is dying,
Another victim of Chinese leader Xi Jinping’s
anti-corruption campaign.
Since Xi came into power in 2012,
officials have been under close scrutiny.
Last year alone,
Xi’s campaign took down 300,000 officials.
Corruption is kind of a problem in China.
According to research publication YaleGlobal,
80% of government officials there are corrupt.
In a Charney Research survey
of more than 2,000 Chinese companies,
35% said they pay bribes or give these kind
of gifts
in order to operate.
It’s “an unspoken rule” according to
one CFO.
But I mean,
what’s the problem with a few billion dollars
in gifts between friends, right?
Well,
according to Switzerland’s Crema Research,
it just means less money for minor things.
Like education.
And public health.
One study estimated that corruption actually
costs China
about 3% of its GDP,
or 200 billion dollars every year.
China’s former head of state,
Hu Jintao,
said it could even tear the Communist Party
apart.
But like ripping off a Band-Aid,
getting rid of corruption is going to be painful.
Xi Jinping’s anti-corruption campaign
is actually contributing to China’s economic
slowdown,
at least in the short term.
Officials are terrified of being hit with
a corruption charge.
As a result, many officials aren’t approving
new projects,
so things just don’t get done.
And the extravagant banquet industry is hurting,
too.
But perhaps the greatest victim is luxury
goods.
Imports are down 55%.
Sadly,
this means that China’s gift recycling industry
is feeling the pain as well.
Just when I needed their help, too.
Uh,
could I interest anyone out there in a unique,
handpainted interpretation of the Last Supper?
So what do you think of China’s corruption
based economy?
Can it survive an anti-corruption drive?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time!