China is preparing for war
While Xi Jinping tells troops to fall in line.
And Taiwan and the US should be prepared.
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.\h
Chinese leader Xi Jinping is telling the\h
People’s Liberation Army to prepare for war.\h
Last week, Xi Jinping visited the PLA\h
Marine Base in Guangdong Province.
And he told the troops “to devote their “minds\h
and energy” to “preparing for war,” to “maintain\h\h
a state of high alert,” and to remain “absolutely\h
loyal, absolutely pure, and absolutely reliable.”
To be fair, Xi Jinping often\h
tells the PLA to prepare for war.\h
Like back in May this year.
And in January 2019.
And in October 2018.
And in August 2017.
You get the picture.\h
And it makes sense. Xi Jinping spent a lot of\h
time and effort reorganizing the PLA and purging\h\h
all his enemies there. He didn’t do all that\h
so the PLA could be *unprepared* to go to war.\h
So Xi Jinping just telling soldiers to be prepared\h
for war isn’t necessarily very alarming by itself.\h\h
But there are also other reasons that people are\h
getting worried about a possible PLA attack.\h
The same day as Xi’s speech,\h
in the nearby city of Shenzhen,
officials “ordered all residents to prepare\h
emergency supplies in 72 categories,\h\h
such as enough food and water\h
for 72 hours and a fire blanket.”
In fact, China’s Emergency Management Ministry\h\h
and several municipal governments, like Beijing\h
and Tianjin, issued similar orders last month.
So, is China gearing up for\h
war? And if so, against whom?
The most obvious target is Taiwan.\h\h
The Chinese Communist Party has been threatening\h
military action against Taiwan this entire year.
From flying warplanes over Taiwan airspace...
to releasing video of China’s military\h
launching a simulated invasion of Taiwan.
“In its annual work report this year, the\h
Chinese government removed the word ‘peaceful’\h\h
from long-standing references\h
to ‘reunification’ with Taiwan.”
Now if you’ve watched or listened to the\h
interview we did with Taiwan expert Ian Easton\h\h
on the China Unscripted podcast,\hyou’ll remember\h\h
that because of weather constraints,\h
there are really only two times a year\h\h
China could launch an invasion across the Taiwan\h
Strait—in the spring and in the early fall.
Both those windows have passed this year.\h\h
So we’re not going to get a Chinese invasion\h
of Taiwan on our 2020 disaster bingo. Oh darn.
The next window for invasion is in March\h
2021. Does Xi Jinping’s military rhetoric,\h\h
and the emergency rationing, mean\h
the PLA will invade next March?
Not necessarily. According to Taiwan’s defense\h
ministry, “China’s military still apparently lacks\h\h
the landing craft and logistical support needed\h
to carry out a full-scale sea and air invasion.”
And as much as the Chinese Communist\h
Party wants to conquer Taiwan,\h\h
losing a fight would be devastating to the image\h
of the Party within China and around the world.
More likely, this is an attempt\h
by the Party to demoralize Taiwan\h\h
into thinking a war would be too costly and\h
bloody, so it might as well just surrender now.\h
Well, I doubt Taiwan will surrender.\h\h
But there’s another target audience\h
for Xi’s speech: the United States.\h
And I’ll tell you why after this short break.
Welcome back. Chinese leader Xi Jinping\h
is trying to convince the United States\h\h
that it would be too much hassle to defend\h
Taiwan in the event of a Chinese invasion.
Xi Jinping has also been\h
making speeches recently about\h\h
the War to Resist U.S. Aggression and Aid Korea.
You probably know it as the Korean War.\h\h
It’s the only time that US and Chinese forces\h
have actually fought with troops on the ground.
And the fact that Xi is suddenly bringing this\h
up, isn’t just because of the Korean boy band BTS.
This year is the 70th anniversary of the Korean\h
War. And Xi Jinping and the other members of the\h\h
Politburo Standing Committee recently visited a\h
military museum where Xi talked about the war.
He said, “The victory in the War to Resist\h
U.S. Aggression and Aid Korea was a victory of\h\h
justice, a victory of peace and a victory\h
of the people.” And a victory for honey.
Wow, I’m amazed we can get all these\h
direct soundbites from Xi Jinping.
He called it a “historic decision” and an effort\h
to “safeguard peace and resist aggression”.
Yes, after Communist North Korea invaded the\h
South, and the UN, backed mostly by US troops,\h\h
stepped in, Chinese forces had to resist American\h
aggression against the North Korean heroes.
Now that isn’t exactly a new way\h
for China to frame the Korean War.\h\h
So why is Xi Jinping bringing\h
it up now, seven decades later?\h\h
It’s a not very subtle metaphor. See, today,\h
China is also resisting aggression from the US,\h\h
which is trying to interfere in\h
internal Chinese affairs, aka Taiwan.
So the message to the US is\h
clear—we’ve fought you before,\h\h
we’ll fight you again and it won’t\h
be pretty. So don’t back Taiwan.\h
Also, don’t read up on your Korean War\h
history, because then you’d learn how\h\h
US involvement actually succeeded in *saving*\h
South Korea from invasion by communist forces.
Anyway, China has been threatening\h
retaliation over US weapon deals with Taiwan.
And Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman\h\h
Zhao Lijian recently told Washington\h
to “Cut all ‘US-Taiwan military ties.’”
But there was another message hidden\h
in Xi’s recent speech to the PLA.\h\h
One that I bet he was hoping the rest of the\h
world wouldn’t pick up on. Did you catch it?
Here it is again: He told the troops “to devote\h
their “minds and energy” to “preparing for war,”\h\h
to “maintain a state of high alert,”\h
and to remain “absolutely loyal,\h\h
absolutely pure, and absolutely reliable.”
Sure, Xi Jinping wants you to focus on\h
the readiness and willingness of the\h\h
PLA to fight a war, so maybe you think twice\h
about whether it's even worth fighting China.\h\h
But he doesn’t want you to think too\h
much about the part where he says\h\h
the military needs to remain\h
absolutely loyal, pure and reliable.
Like I said earlier, Xi Jinping\h
spent years purging the PLA.\h\h
High ranking generals have been jailed for life,
and many have been “suicided,” as they say.
That is not good for morale. So it’s possible\h\h
Xi Jinping doesn’t quite feel as in\h
control of the military as he’d like.\h
But you know what would\h
boost morale? Another purge.
And now it’s time for me to\h
answer a question from one of you,\h\h
who supports China Uncensored through\h
the crowdfunding website Patreon.
Arnold Keen says, “If the economy in China\h
continues to go south don't be surprised\h\h
that the CCP decides they need to start\h
a war with Taiwan to distract the people\h\h
from their problems. It seems to work most of\h
the time. The fact they may be starting a war\h\h
with 4 or 5 other nations is probably the only\h
thing currently stopping them. But the saying\h\h
'desperate times leads to desperate\h
measures'\h is still meaningful today.
Arnold, what are you talking about?!\h
China’s economy is going south? No.\h\h
China’s economy is great! Just ask the media!
China’s economy is surging!
It’s the envy of the world!
Because it’s the world’s only major growth engine.
Which is why US investors are\h
all over China’s bond market!
Unless of course you for some reason question\h
the official numbers coming out of China.\h\h
Which the New York Times and Bloomberg\h
obviously don’t, so why should you?
But you're absolutely right the Chinese\h
Communist Party tries its best to distract\h\h
its citizens from economic woes. Usually\h
with things like anti-Japanese sentiment.
But the problem with using a war to\h
do that is that the Party could lose.\h\h
Plus there’s the economic cost of war itself,\h\h
and the risk of countries around the\h
world finally wising up to the Party.
But don’t you worry about\h
the Chinese Communist Party.\h\h
There’s a reason why it spends more on\h
internal security forces than on its military.\h\h
Because if people inside China get a\h
little too rowdy over economic woes—why\h\h
send the tanks to Taiwan? It’s much easier\h
to just use them to crush your own people.
Thanks for your comment Arnold.
And if you’d like to have me respond to\h
your question or comment on the show for\h\h
hundreds of thousands of people to hear, join\h
what I call the China Uncensored 50 Army...
and support us in the battle against the Chinese\h
Communist Party. You can join for as little as\h\h
a dollar per episode on the crowd funding\h
website Patreon. You’ll get some other cool\h\h
perks as well. Head over to Patreon.com/China\h
Uncensored to learn more. Link is below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell. See you next time.