On this episode of China Uncensored,
the Chinese Communist Party says they want
to
spread peace around the world.
But just in case,
they’re also filling the skies with terrifying
war machines.
Welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
We all know America has the world’s greatest
military.
But I’ve got some bad news for you.
Or good news,
depending on which country you’re living
in.
Because the Chinese military is catching up
fast.
So get ready to have your hopes for a peaceful
world dashed,
as we bring you 5 deadly Chinese military
aircraft.
Number 5: the Harbin Z-19 Chinese attack helicopter
With a top speed of 174 miles per hour,
it may not be fast, but it sure is furious.
The Z-19 started life as a French helicopter
for search and rescue and MEDIVAC.
It was built under license by China’s
Harbin Aircraft Manufacturing Corporation.
But then they added armor plating,
a bunch of guns,
a mean-looking paint-job and voila!
One terrifying Harbin Z-19 copter ready for
battle.
The base model includes air-to-ground guided
missiles
and rocket projectiles.
And it packs a special surprise.
“The crash-proof seats are equipped with
bulletproof armor.
The oil tank is also crash proof
and designed to seal itself off once attacked.”
Wait, so if you shoot at it, the gas tank
shuts off
and...what...the helicopter falls out of the
sky?
What do you do?
“These helicopters are designed to be exported
to other countries.”
Oh I get it!
Sell copters that fall out of the sky to rival
countries.
Now that’s a clever way to win a war!
Anyway, all I can say is,
before you buy,
get that fuel tank cutoff thing checked out.
Number 4: The J-15 Flying Shark
While the Z-19 is a licensed copy of a French
helicopter,
the Shenyang J-15 Flying Shark is a totally
unlicensed
knockoff of the Russian SU-33.
The Russians say China stole their design,
and were so upset that they broke off talks
to sell
dozens of the SU-33 aircraft to the Chinese
Air Force.
And you know your relationship is on the rocks
when
even the Russians refuse to sell weapons to
you.
Chinese designers of the Flying Shark say
any similarity is totally a coincidence.
And they’re quick to point out
the Flying Shark is way better—
it’s a lot faster,
has longer range,
and can fly higher.
The J-15 is what’s called an air superiority
fighter jet.
It’s designed for air-to-air combat.
Plus it’s great at taking off and landing
from an aircraft carrier.
And China is the proud owner of...
one single fully operational carrier—
called the Liaoning.
So now you know where to find the entire fleet
of two dozen Flying Sharks.
Yes, all in one convenient location.
Number 3: The Chengdu J-10
Now China might have only one working aircraft
carrier,
but you know what they’ve got lots of?
Vigorous Dragons!
Yup, that’s the code name for the Chengdu
J-10.
The Chinese military has about 240 of them
in service.
And while in this dragon looks more sleepy
than vigorous…
…don’t be fooled.
According to Military Today,
this is the first Chinese-developed combat
fighter
that approaches Western fighters in terms
of
performance and capability.
It’s got cannons, air-to-air missiles,
laser-guided bombs,
free-fall bombs and rockets.
But you wouldn’t get that
from any Chinese air show.
No, the whole project was so secret
that the first photos of the J-10 didn’t
come out
until 3 years after its maiden flight in 1998.
But there was not so much secrecy
with the J-10’s more recent successor,
which brings us to...
Number 2: The J-11 warplane
There are plenty selfies on Chinese social
media of pilots
in their knockoff Russian fighter planes.
And with each one,
China gets another black mark
in the books of Russian arms dealers.
According to the National Interest,
China started out by making a fully authorized
copy
of Russia’s top-shelf Sukhoi SU-27 multirole
fighter,
the plane that challenged the legendary twin-engine
F-15.
But then China ducked out of their contract
with Russia,
reverse-engineered the Sukhoi SU-27,
and made their own souped up version.
They call it the J-11.
Then a whole alphabet soup of J-11’s followed,
like the J-11B, the J-11D and the J-11BS.
I’m not making that last one up.
Anyway, the J-11-based aircraft
are the spearhead of the Chinese regime’s
efforts
to make long-range fighters
that can contest the seas around China.
And that brings us to...
Number 1: The J-20 stealth multipurpose fighter
The J-20 stealth, according to state-run media,
is China’s most advanced stealth fighter.
Well, technically, with its massive fuel tanks,
it’s more of a long-range interceptor.
So while it would probably lose
in a Top Gun-style dogfight
against a US F-22 or F-35 stealth fighter,
it’s perfect for attacking defenseless stratotankers—
the aerial fuelling stations that those smaller,
scrappier fighter jets are pretty much dependent
on.
China’s air force recently declared the
newest generation
of the J-20 to be combat-ready.
But designers admit there are
a few wrinkles left to iron out—
like engine reliability, control system,
stealth coat, hull materials and infrared
sensor…
Wait, those seem like...kind of big problems.
Um...let’s just take the state-run media’s
word for it.
The J-20 is really, really deadly.
Now all these dangerous Chinese planes in
the sky
can only mean one thing—
way more people believing in chemtrails.
And, if you believe experts like historian
Alfred McCoy,
who writes about challenges to US global power…
...thanks in part to high tech aircraft,
China could soon become the world’s
biggest military superpower.
And now it’s time for a fan question
from one of our supporters on Patreon.
Roberto Miglioli asks:
“Chris, how far is China willing to go
regarding the South China Sea standoff?
Do you think China will go to war to secure
that area?”
I think the better question is,
would any country go to war
to stop the Chinese Communist Party?
Because short of that,
nothing is stopping the Communist Party
in the South China Sea.
Despite neighboring countries
and even an international court
telling them not to,
the Communist Party built up fake islands
in disputed territorial waters.
And even though Chinese leader Xi Jinping
promised China wouldn’t militarize those
islands,
they’ve put missile launchers
and even recently landed a long range bomber,
in those disputed territorial waters.
That means China can now project military
power
anywhere in Southeast Asia,
and as far away as northern Australia.
So the Party has already all but secured the
area—
without going to war.
Thanks for your question, Roberto.
And everyone else:
Remember that as a bonus
for supporting China Uncensored
with a dollar or more per episode,
I’ll answer your questions, too.
Click the link below.
And what do you think about China’s efforts
to fill the skies with Flying Sharks,
Vigorous Dragons,
and other deadly aircraft?
Leave your comments below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Find out about China’s secret military plans
and what it means for the world.
Visit ChinaUncensored.tv.
We upload full half hour episodes
you won’t see on YouTube.
Learn about the shady practices of the Chinese
regime,
before even world leaders do!
ChinaUncensored.tv.