Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
You know, not everyone is so lucky to be present
for the exciting 19th Party Congress in Beijing—
where delegates get to listen to reports from
the Central Committee,
and pretend to elect the Party’s new leadership.
Fortunately, the CCP has developed
over 100 smartphone apps
to help Party members remain loyal.
But what kind of apps could you possible want,
in a country where the Communist Party
has already done so much to involve itself
in every aspect of your life?
Well, perhaps this commercial
will make it make it clearer.
What’s great about the iPhone in China,
Is that if you want to brush up on
your knowledge of Marxist-Leninist-Maoist
Thought,
There’s an app for that.
If you want to sing along
to your favorite childhood propaganda songs,
There’s an app for that.
If you want to hear dramatic retellings
of the communist revolution,
including the story of the first Chinese hero
to shoot down an American plane,
There’s an app for that.
And if you want to virtually sweep the tombs
of those communist martyrs,
There’s even an app for that.
If you want to visit every landmark along
the entire 6,000-mile-route
of Mao Zedong’s Long March,
where thousands of people died
for virtually no reason,
There’s an app for that.
And if you want to turn that tragic history
into a fun video game.
There’s also an app for that.
And if you want to help your local Party branch
monitor your ideological education,
force you to take Party knowledge exams,
hound you for Party membership fees,
and evaluate whether you’re learning your
lessons
in a timely and active manner,
Well, there’s a lot of apps for that.
Yep.
There’s a Communist app for just about anything.
Only on the iPhone in China.
So what communist apps—
or anti-communist apps—
would you like to see?
Leave your comments below.
And remember,
if you want to see full half-hour episode
of China Uncensored and other content,
go to ChinaUncensored.tv.