On this episode of China Uncensored,
China wants to build the world’s longest
underwater tunnel—
to a country that it doesn’t even recognize
as a country.
Hi, welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
Authoritarian regimes sure come up with the
craziest schemes.
Like China’s canal designed to transport
billions of gallons of water
all the way from the south of the country
to the north,
losing most of it to evaporation,
and wrecking ecosystems in the process.
That one was Chairman Mao’s idea.
Or China’s plans to build a giant city so
big,
it’s bigger than the entire population of
England and France combined.
Just kidding they’re not building “a”
megacity.
They’re building 19 of them.
And now Chinese engineers want to build
the world’s longest underwater train tunnel.
Kind of like the Channel Tunnel,
that connects England and France.
Only much longer.
And less of a mutually agreed-upon decision.
Because, according to the South China Morning
Post,
Chinese scientists are planning the world’s
longest train tunnel...
to connect mainland China to Taiwan.
Rumor has it, the Chinese Communist Party
absolutely adores the plan!
So much so, in fact,
they’re ready to start planning without
Taiwan’s cooperation.
Researchers told the South China Morning Post
that
“it’s possible Beijing would start work
on the project
in a unilateral and largely symbolic move.”
The 84-mile Taiwan Strait Tunnel
would link Pingtan in Mainland China...
...to Hsinchu in Taiwan.
And yes, Hsinchu happens to be where Taiwan
has an army base—
where forces train hard to prepare for an
aggressive,
unannounced visit by the People’s Liberation
Army.
Otherwise known as an invasion.
So there’s a good chance that Taiwan might
react negatively
if members of a Chinese tunnel drilling team
start to
pop up out of the ground unannounced.
But due to engineering constraints, a tunnel
this long
could probably never be completed without
digging from both ends.
And when Taiwan’s Minister Chen Min-tong,
who’s responsible for relations between
Taiwan and the mainland,
got wind that the plans for the tunnel were
ready and the CCP
was anxious to break ground,
he immediately denounced the project,
saying “The proposal is part of China's
consistent
united front propaganda and was made unilaterally.”
Chen also said there had not been any bilateral
communication between China and Taiwan on
the subject,
much less any kind of agreement.
But from the Communist Party’s perspective,
an agreement isn’t really necessary—
although it would make things go much smoother.
That’s because the Party considers Taiwan
a province of the People’s Republic of China,
and has vowed to seize control of it sooner
or later,
by force if necessary.
Actually Chinese president Xi Jinping has
ordered
the People’s Liberation Army to be ready
for an invasion of Taiwan by 2020.
No wonder Taiwan is a bit suspicious of this
underwater tunnel.
The Taiwanese minister also said that by proposing
the tunnel,
China was “attacking Taiwan’s potential
for international space
using militaristic intimidation and trying
to mislead the public
into thinking that this was a bilateral decision.”
But even if Taiwan okayed the tunnel,
the project could still be fraught with some
of the same problems
that have plagued China’s own rail system.
Like the massive corruption that caused the
Communist Party
to have to dissolve and restructure THE ENTIRE
RAILWAYS MINISTRY.
And also, give the railways minister a suspended
death sentence
for taking 10 million dollars in bribes.
But even if the tunnel is built without corruption,
it could still end up like some of
China’s other grand-scale planning ideas
that disregarded the realities of the natural
environment.
Like the Three-Gorges Dam—
the world’s largest hydro-powered project,
that displaced 1.3 million people,
and is causing landslides,
droughts,
oh, and earthquakes.
Did I mention earthquakes?
A Chinese scientist—
who asked not to be named because who in their
right mind
would put their name on this plan—
said the underwater tunnel would need to cross
not one,
but two earthquake fault lines.
The scientist called the tunnel one of the
“most challenging
civil engineering projects in the 21st century.”
And that’s because in addition to cutting
across
two earthquake fault lines,
the tunnel has to slice through complex layers
of rock,
including extremely hard granite sandwiched
between layers
of far less stable sandstone and shale.
But even if they got it to work
without an earthquake getting in the way,
there’s another engineering problem.
The tunnel is too long to pump air through.
So China would have to build not one but two
artificial islands
in the Taiwan Strait, to pump fresh air down
into the tunnel.
Fortunately, the Chinese regime
is good at building artificial islands.
Unfortunately, I think the Taiwan government
might
object to building islands off the coast of
Taiwan.
But even if Taiwan okays the artificial islands,
and the tunnel is built without massive corruption,
and it doesn’t cause earthquakes,
there’s another reason it might not be a
great idea.
Remember how China has threatened to invade
Taiwan,
if Taiwan ever declares independence?
Well, you know what’s a really easy way
to move tanks?
Trains!
Looks like there might be some wide loads
coming through.
And before you go, it’s time for me to answer
another question
from a fan who supports China Uncensored
on the crowdfunding website Patreon.
James McKay asks: “Hi, Shelly.”
Ugh, this one’s for Shelley?!
“When you travel together,
who is considered your "carry on":
Chris or Matt?
Will you elaborate on how you stretch the
team's
(likely very modest) travel and accommodation
budget?”
Shelley, do you want to answer this one?
Sure Chris.
James, if any of us was the carry on, it would
be me.
But I don’t really want to be stuck in
an overhead compartment at 35,000 feet,
so I usually buy my own plane ticket.
How do we stretch our travel budget?
We try to get sponsorship for everything.
Airlines, as you might guess,
don’t really want to sponsor anyone who
undermines the CCP.
But we had a hotel sponsor us in Taiwan.
Otherwise, we usually stay in an airBNB or
in someone’s home.
We also borrow our camera gear from our friends
whenever we can.
And if people take us out to dinner while
we’re on the road,
we don’t complain.
Especially if it’s hotpot.
Just saying.
Thanks Shelley.
Want to have your questions answered on the
show?
Of course you do!
Join the China Uncensored 50-Cent Army,
by supporting the show with a dollar or more
per episode
on the crowdfunding website Patreon.
And yes, you can ask Shelley questions, too.
The link is below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
Thanks for watching.
Did you know we also make
a half-hour version of this show every week?
It’s broadcast on the NTD network
in New York, LA, and San Francisco.
Plus you can it on our free app for Amazon
FireTV,
Apple TV, and Roku.
Or visit ChinaUncensored.tv.