On this episode of China Uncensored,
A foreign country has been interfering in
our elections.
Guess which one!
The CIA says China is undermining the US.
And if anyone knows about undermining a country,
it’s the CIA.
And finally, fingers crossed for a trip to
Tibet!
Sadly it probably won’t be free.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
A foreign government is interfering in US
elections.
And President Trump is tired of
letting Russia get all the credit.
This time, he’s talking about
a different country in particular:
China.
Speaking to the UN Security Council,
Trump said, “[China does] not want me or
us to win
because I am the first president ever
to challenge China on trade.
We are winning on trade.
We are winning at every level.
We don't want them to meddle
or interfere in our upcoming election."
And that had to be a bit awkward.
I mean, the UN Security Council is only five
countries.
And China is one of them.
Well, Russia is also one of them,
so I guess they were relieved.
Is the Chinese Communist Party interfering
in US elections?
Yes, but not like Russia.
Internet bots are for amateurs.
More on that in a future episode.
According to the new director of the CIA,
China is working to diminish US influence
around the world.
She specifically talked about how the Chinese
regime
promises loans to many developing countries,
which they can’t repay.
On paper,
China is investing almost a trillion dollars
as part of its Belt and Road Initiative—
an infrastructure plan where China
gives developing countries massive loans.
So far, the actual amount spent has been
less than the Chinese regime promised.
Which is actually a good thing,
because those loans have been
trapping those countries in debt,
while Chinese businesses extract resources
and often do very little for the local economies.
Yes, why would any country
ever want to do business with anyone else?
Now believe it or not, US-China relations
aren’t doing great.
I know, shocking, but there are some warning
signs.
Just two days before a planned meeting between
a top Chinese naval officer and his US counterpart,
the Chinese side called it off!
At the same time,
China denied a request from a US naval vessel
to enter port in Hong Kong.
This is not a first.
In 2016,
when everyone was freaking out about China
building military facilities
on artificial islands in the South China Sea,
the ones they said they would never militarize…
China also denied another US naval ship
from entering port in Hong Kong.
The ship denied entry this time, the USS Wasp,
responded,
“Roger That.
We’ll just buzzzz off.”
But that doesn’t mean there can’t be friendly
military exchange
between the US and another part of China.
Namely, Taiwan.
Which communist China believes is a province,
but most sane people believe is a country.
The US is selling 330 million dollars of weapons
to Taiwan.
Obviously, the Chinese Communist Party is
unhappy.
So they “urged” the US to cancel the deal,
or risk doing damage to US-China relations.
I believe that ship has already sailed.
That ship is the USS Wasp
and it’s somewhere off the coast of Hong
Kong by now.
Some good news for a change.
The Vatican and the Chinese Communist Party
are close to finalizing an agreement
that will change the lives of Catholics in
China.
No, it won’t stop the Party from tearing
down churches.
Or get the Party to stop forcing people
to replace pictures of Jesus with Xi Jinping.
Or stop Christians from being killed for their
organs.
But, so far the Pope will agree to recognize
7 Catholic bishops appointed by
the officially atheist Chinese Communist Party.
I don’t think the Pope understands how to
negotiate a deal.
Maybe he should get some advice.
And finally, planning a trip to Tibet just
got a little easier...
well, okay it’s not easy.
US citizens are still banned from travelling
there.
I think it’s because we just couldn’t
withstand the sheer joy
Tibetans feel about being liberated by the
Chinese Communist Party.
Yeah, that looks like joy...
the same way this looks like being liberated.
But the US House of Representatives has passed
a new bill that will deny US entry to Chinese
officials
who prohibit American citizens from traveling
to Tibet.
Will this force a change in Tibet?
Who knows?
I mean, if the Chinese regime didn’t change
for the Beastie Boys,
are they really going to change for a bunch
of congressmen?
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And before you go,
now is the time when I answer questions from
you!
The loyal members of the China Uncensored
50-cent army
who support the show on the crowd funding
website Patreon.
Charles Walter Brooke asks
“Chris, which High Ranking Member of the
Chinese Communist Party
would you most like to Interview, and Why?
And, What kind of uncomfortable questions
would you like to grill them with?”
Well, besides obviously Xi Jinping—
who has not yet responded to my repeated
requests for an interview, by the way—
I’d like to interview Wang Qishan.
Wang is Vice President of the People’s Republic,
and more importantly, he’s Xi Jinping’s
main guy
in charge of the anti-corruption campaign
being used to purge all the officials Xi Jinping
doesn’t like.
I’d ask Wang Qishan to give me the dirt
on
all the corrupt officials that are next on
the chopping block.
And I’d bring a wheelbarrow,
because there’s gonna be a lot of dirt.
Thanks for your question, Charles.
And if you have a burning question,
first, you should probably have a doctor check
that out.
And then, you should sign up to support China
Uncensored on Patreon.
Join our 50-cent army so you can send me those
questions
and so I can answer on the show!
So once again,
thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored
and be sure to subscribe if you aren’t.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Well, sorry to say,
that’s the end of another China Uncensored.
But this isn’t goodbye!
Hit that subscribe button
and turn the notification bell on
so you know when we have more episodes.
And more episodes we will have.
A new one comes out every Monday,
Wednesday, Friday and sometimes Saturday!