On this episode of China Uncensored,
5 Ways China Plans to Dominate SpaceHi,
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Space.
The final frontier...
for China’s enterprising space program.
Its continuing mission:
to explore places
where NASA probes have already gone,
to dominate other civilizations,
and to boldly steal US space technology.
China truly does have ambitious space plans.
And if you watched Valerian,
which you probably didn’t,
you’d know that the Chinese government
sees its own future in space.
And with NASA funding having leveled off in
recent years,
China hopes it can be the new space sheriff
in town.
So what, exactly,
are China’s plans to dominate space?
Here are five of them.
Number 5: Moon Rover
But not just any moon rover.
This one will land on the dark side of the
moon.
Presumably, to make contact with the Decepticons,
hoping to ally with them and dominate the
Earth.
What they don’t realize is that the Decepticons
would never team up with the Chinese Communist
Party.
Even Decepticons have standards.
China has a mission to land a rover
on the dark side of the moon
at end of 2018.
It’s a technical challenge because communications
are harder to handle with a probe on the dark
side.
The mission is called Chang’e-4,
named after the Chinese goddess
who lives on the moon.
The point of the Chinese rover mission
is to study the moon’s geology—
and to prove once and for all
that the moon has been part of China’s territory
since ancient times.
Number 4: Mars Rover
Not content with sending a rover just to the
moon,
China also wants to send a rover to Mars.
I mean, it’s called the Red Planet.
It’s just asking to be conquered by communists!
The mission is set to launch in 2020.
It will land a rover that will collect important
data
on temperature, atmosphere, and surface conditions.
I guess no one told them that NASA
has been landing rovers on Mars since 1997.
Wouldn’t it be easier for the Chinese military
to just hack that temperature data from the
US?
Actually, they can just Google it.
Oh, wait.
Google’s blocked in China.
Number 3: Asteroid Moonification
A Chinese space official said earlier this
year
that China plans to launch several
asteroid exploration spacecraft
starting in 2020.
The ultimate goal:
“to ‘capture’ an asteroid
and try to fire it into the moon’s orbit.”
The idea would be to land a spacecraft
on the asteroid’s surface, and then—
not kidding here—
use rockets to change its trajectory
and propel it into orbit around the moon,
creating a moon moon.
Also called moonception.
Sure, sending a spaceship to an asteroid
may sound like the plot of a bad 90s movie
starring Bruce Willis and Steven Tyler’s
screaming.
But as outlandish as this idea sounds,
the Chinese are giving it serious consideration.
And there’s a practical purpose here:
A single asteroid can contain
more than a trillion dollars in precious metals.
In addition,
China’s space officials suggest that an
asteroid
could even maybe become a base for a future
space station.
Low gravity,
and lots of metal for construction.
And speaking of space stations...
Number 2: Regular Space Station
This one is much more realistic
than capturing an asteroid.
China wants to have the dominant space station
in low earth orbit.
Right now,
the International Space Station is pretty
much
the go-to place for hanging out in space
and making brushing your teeth look fun.
China already has a couple of space stations:
Tiangong-2, which is in orbit
but currently floating around unmanned;
and Tiangong-1
which is done with its mission
and is about to crash land on Earth somewhere
and hopefully not kill anybody.
Now China wants to launch Tiangong-3 in 2022.
It will be a permanently manned modular space
station,
meaning it can be expanded.
The International Space Station is set to
be
decommissioned in 2024.
So if Tiangong-3 is successful,
it could become the world’s dominant
zero-gravity research facility
for astronauts brushing their teeth.
And number 1: Space Weapons
Because an authoritarian regime’s
ambitious space plans
couldn’t be complete without space weapons.
Researchers from China’s top laser research
institute
have proposed building a 5-ton spacecraft
that would orbit the Earth,
and could be used to shoot down other satellites
with chemical lasers.
They wrote that
“the space-based laser weapon system
will be one of the major [anti-satellite]
development projects.”
This is a big deal,
because such a weapon,
if it actually gets funded,
could destroy the communications
and monitoring equipment of an enemy.
For example,
Canada.
And that could also blind this country
to China’s launch of various missiles
or other combat satellites.
But don’t worry,
Chinese state media assures us
that China’s space program,
which is run by the Chinese military,
is all about peace.
The way China’s urban management police
are all about social harmony.
Hey, elderly people are a serious threat
and need to be harmonized.
And coming up after the break,
something smells rotten in Australia.
And, no,
it’s not a Vegemite sandwich.
Want to directly help me
make more great episodes for you?
Check out our crowdfunding site on Patreon.
You can support us with,
for example,
a dollar per episode.
So click the orange button here
and support us now.
Thank you!