When are you going to take it?
Sometimes I don't.
If I like a moment.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I'm your host Chris Chappell.
This is incredible.
Almost majestic.
What am I looking at?
Show 'em, Shelley.
No, no, no, not that.
This is something even rarer than a dumb old
cat.
Shhh.
Look!
The first ever meeting of a Chinese and a
Taiwanese leader.
But unlike all those unenlightened news photographers
with their flashes going off
I'm not going to take the photo
I have video from Reuters.
You know, this was a pretty historic moment
though.
On Saturday in Singapore,
Chinese leader Xi Jinping met with Ma Ying-jeou,
the president of Taiwan.
It's the first time this has happened since
the Chinese Civil War ended in 1949.
That's when the Communist Party seized control
of Mainland China and the Republic of China
government fled to Taiwan.
Now under what's known as the 1992 Consensus,
Taiwan and Mainland China agree that there
is only One China…
to rule them all, one China to find them,
one China to bring them all and in the darkness
bind them.
Uh, I mean, there is officially only one nation
called China,
and Taiwan is a part of that.
It's just both sides say they're the legitimate
government of the whole thing.
This has caused some tensions in the past.
Made worse by the Communist Party's threats
to invade,
if Taiwan ever tries to declare that it's
an independent country.
In fact, China's People's Liberation Army
reportedly has thousands of missiles pointed
at Taiwan.
And earlier this year,
the People's Liberation Army even staged a
mock invasion of the Taiwan presidential palace.
And that's why it's so incredible to see Xi
Jinping and Ma Ying-jeou shaking hands on
the same stage.
Even though they share the same language,
history, and culture
Taiwan and Mainland China couldn't be more
different.
Like they were from different planets.
Deep in space lies an imperfect duplicate
of earth known as the bizarro world.
On this topsy turvy world lies weird duplicates
of the citizens of metropolis,
including the city's most famous super hero.
Yes, it me.
Bizarro Number 1.
Taiwan and China are basically like Superman
and Bizarro Superman.
Taiwan has beautiful, clear waters.
Mainland China has filthy, toxic sludge.
Taiwan has freedom of the press.
Mainland China has the freedom to be oppressed.
Taiwan has a president, and, wait,
so does Mainland China!
Only the people didn't vote for this president.
Doesn't stop there either.
After the meeting, both Xi and Ma held press
conferences.
But one was not like the other.
Reporters asked Ma the tough questions,
and he responded the way a democratically
elected leader typically responds
with bold-faced lies.
Xi Jinping, however, didn't even show up at
the mainland China press conference.
Instead, China's minister of Taiwan Affairs
Office went up against,
softball questions from Chinese state-run
media.
Of course if you live in Mainland China,
you wouldn't have see how a democratically
elected Mandarin speaking president deals
with tough questions from a free press,
because state-run television didn't show it.
So what did this meeting accomplish?
Well, there were no joint statements given,
and no agreements made.
So you might be asking yourself,
why did it even happen?
That's a good question.
Since Ma Ying-jeou became president in 2008,
he's helped bring the two nations closer together
than ever before.
This has not been too popular inside of Taiwan,
where some view him as basically cozying up
with the enemy,
that, you know, has thousands of missiles
aimed at Taiwan…or at the general direction
of Taiwan.
But tourism, trade, and economic exchange
have risen dramatically.
The up side of this is that people from Mainland
China have a chance to see the non-Bizzaro
version of their country.
The down side is that some in Taiwan see the
economic ties as simply another form of invasion
by the Mainland, just without the bullets.
That's one of the reasons why it looks like
Taiwan's opposition party, the DPP,
is poised to defeat Ma Ying-jeou's KMT party
in the upcoming January elections.
The DPP has always taken a harder line with
Beijing.
Xi's meeting with Ma probably won't change
the likelihood of the DPP's candidate getting
elected.
But having good relations with the Taiwan
government will probably help the Chinese
Communist Party as it alienates basically
every other one of its other neighbors over
territorial disputes in the South China Sea.
Because, since there's only "One China,"
Mainland China and Taiwan by definition make
the same outlandish territorial claims.
As for Ma, well,
he's the first president of Taiwan to ever
meet with his bizarro counterpart.
Place in history books secured.
So what do you think of the meeting?
Leave your comments below and be sure too...
Who are you?!
Me Bizzaro Chris.
Bizarro Number 1.