On this episode of China Uncensored,
namaste or nama go now?
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Over the last few months,
I’ve been covering the military standoff
between Chinese and Indian troops
along their border.
Chinese state-run media had been threatening
war,
saying the conflict will get worse
if India doesn’t back off.
And that if not, war is inevitable.
Well, something terrible has just happened.
India’s new defense minister is wrecking
the inevitable war
by directly approaching Chinese troops at
the border—
with kindness and understanding.
Just look at this video!
Do you know what Namaste means?
What would you say in Chinese?
We just say Ni Hao.
So I say Namaste.
Ni Hao.
It’s as if she views Chinese soldiers
as fellow human beings
equally deserving of love and respect!
How are they going to kill each other now?
No one is more upset, I think,
than my favorite Chinese state-run media,
the Global Times.
It’s hard to say namaste to war.
Fortunately, damage was contained.
That video was posted on Twitter, after all.
And Twitter is banned in China.
What’s that, Shelley?
Chinese people saw it anyway?
And according to the Times of India,
they went “gaga” over it.
Which seems like maybe overstating it slightly.
Since they quoted all of two people on the
internet.
But the Global Times didn’t let this positive
reaction
trip them up for long!
They referred to the namaste incident,
as a an expression of her “goodwill.”
If you look at what the expert said, it’s
actually pretty positive.
But putting it in scare quotes sure makes
it seem sinister, doesn’t it?
Because let me tell you something about
Indian Defense Minister Nirmala Sitharaman.
She’d like you to think she’s all “namaste.”
But while she was on the border,
she also inspected a nearby airport.
Yeah!
Which was totally...
what was it again Global Times?
An “aggressive gesture,”
right, got it.
And how about an accusation of some kind?
Ah, perfect.
I mean, yeah India?
Why are you so paranoid?
Is it because a thousand Chinese troops
just returned to the site of that border dispute?
To continue working on the road
that could help the Chinese army invade India
someday?
The road that was the cause of the border
standoff
in the first place?
I mean, to be fair,
they’re only widening the existing road,
not making it longer.
Totally different.
Or are you paranoid because the Chinese regime
is withholding monsoon data that could be
critical
to saving the lives of Indian citizens?
Or, are you paranoid
because the Chinese regime is selling weapons
to your long-time rival Pakistan?
Or is it because they’re setting up ports
that could give the Chinese navy
easy access to the Indian Ocean?
Surely it’s none of those things.
Because you’ve got to trust the Global Times
when it says,
“India is not a major focus
for China’s strategic ambition.”
Yup.
Not at all.
Because it’s not like China and India
are in a competition or anything.
Even though they both are the most populous
economic powerhouses in Asia.
Okay, well...
the Chinese regime may be a bit jealous that
Chinese people seem to love Indian culture
so much.
Since “One of the most popular movies
in China over the summer,”
was the Bollywood hit Dangal.
And obviously there’s a little bit of competition
in the Indian Ocean.
India is looking to buy US drones
to counter all the Chinese navy activity there.
And President Trump does seem to favor
selling weapons to India.
And who could forget the competition
of which world leader would go first?
After you!
No, after you!
You know, maybe state-run Chinese media
don’t have much to worry about.
Namaste.
And coming up after the break,
China is ramping up its weapons sales,
but the result isn’t quite what you would
expect.
You know I hear Chinese leader Xi Jinping
is actually really into yoga.
He’s favorite pose?
The downward Pooh Bear.
If you want more great jokes like that one,
check out ChinaUncensored.tv.
It’s a laugh riot!