On this episode of China Uncensored,
Xi Jinping Thought gets added
to another constitution—
just when Chris Chappell Thought...
that he’d had enough.
Is a trade war between
the US and China brewing?
I hope it’s over tea.
And finally, Ice Boy is back in the news.
Just let it go.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Well I know it’s the moment you’ve all
been waiting for.
Yes, at the end of last week—finally—
we were treated to the second plenary session
of the 19th Party Central Committee.
It’s that special time of the year when
top officials
have another important meeting to discuss
the things they already decided on.
Like whether to add Xi Jinping Thought
to the Constitution of China.
The answer was...
yes!
Now wait, you say.
Wasn’t “Xi Jinping thought on Socialism
with Chinese characteristics for a new era”
already added to China’s constitution?
No, silly.
You’re thinking of 19th Party Congress
back in November!
That’s when “Xi Jinping thought”
was written into the Communist Party’s constitution.
This time,
they agreed to write Xi Jinping Thought
into the country’s constitution.
Yes, those are two different things.
The point is, Xi Jinping is ungodly powerful.
I say that because remember,
the Communist Party is officially atheist.
He can’t very well be godly powerful,
otherwise people wouldn’t be allowed
to believe in him.
But adding Xi Jinping Thought to China’s
constitution
wasn’t the only change.
They also added a line about the need
to have a nationwide surveillance system.
I just hope that doesn’t conflict with Article
40,
which says freedom and privacy are protected
by law.
So this Chinese New Year,
make a resolution to get in shape!
If you’re going to be watched,
you might as well look good.
The relationship between the US
and the Chinese regime
has been strained this week.
US trade authorities suggested
they may take concrete steps
to protect US intellectual property.
It comes right after the US imposed tariffs
on foreign solar panels,
a market China dominates.
“Trump’s move helps US solar-panel manufacturers,
such as FirstSolar, Tesla, Suniva, and SolarWorld.”
But according to Quartz,
the results may be mixed.
Suniva, for one,
is majority owned by a Chinese company.
Alongside the solar panel tariff
was one made on foreign washing machines.
But, will that help the US get to the bottom
of wherever that one missing sock disappears
to?
Let’s hope so because I’m running out.
The US has imposed more sanctions on North
Korea.
I frankly didn’t know there was anything
left to sanction.
They target “North Korea’s crude oil industry
and shipping companies as well as
individuals or entities in Russia and China.”
The Trump administration has long hoped
for the Chinese regime’s help in reining
in North Korea,
but China has been perhaps less than proactive.
Like the whole secretly selling oil thing.
Freedom House has released its 2018
Freedom in the World Report.
China earned a score of 14 out of 100,
one point less than last year.
If only it was a game of golf,
then China would be doing so well!
Except golf is frowned upon in China
for being too bougie.
And Chinese censors are cracking down
on China’s fledgling hip hop community.
According to the BBC,
at the second plenary session last week,
“A memo surface that said programmes could
no longer feature any hip-hop content or artists.”
State-run media have in particular targeted
PG One,
the winner of a Chinese reality show called
the Rap of China.
Some of his lyrics are demeaning towards women,
and others hint at drug use.
Too bad PG One didn’t keep it PG-13.
But instead of standing by his lyrics,
he apologized,
removed some of his songs from the internet,
and blamed them on the bad influence of “black
music.”
And remember “ice boy” from a few weeks
ago?
He was a symbol of rural poverty.
But now he’s become a great photo op
for the Chinese Communist Party.
Ice boy endured the hardship
of walking 3 miles to school every day
in the freezing weather
with only a thin coat.
Surely all of China can be so resilient.
He was invited, “to the capital over the
weekend
and celebrated as a patriotic hero.
He waved a Chinese flag in Tiananmen Square,
tried on riot gear at a public security bureau
and swore an oath to be loyal to China
and the ruling Communist Party.”
Of course he did.
And he said he wants to become a police officer.
Aww, isn’t he cute!
I bet no one told him about
the part of that job
that involves arresting dissidents.
What’s most interesting about Ice Boy
become a celebrity in Beijing,
is that the Communist Party has managed
to use him to bury the narrative about
how Ice Boy represents the crippling rural
poverty
that affects nearly half of China’s population.
Poverty?
No, Ice Boy is struggling against
the icy conditions of winter!
Just like the Communist Party struggles
on behalf of the people.
And coming up after the break,
we’ll take a look at how the Communist Party
helps get guns into the hands of ISIS.
Stay up to date with the latest in China news
over at our website ChinaUncensored.tv.
We have full length half hour episodes
served up free you won’t see on YouTube.
Once again that’s ChinaUncensored.tv.