On this episode of China Uncensored,
the Pope wants to give the CCP more authority
over Chinese bishops.
Underground Chinese Catholics
had better say their prayers...
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Pope Francis loves China.
Perhaps an odd statement considering
the Chinese Communist Party is officially
atheist.
And they have been blowing up Christian churches.
But don’t worry, those were Protestant churches.
Who needs those when you have
the Chinese Patriotic Catholic Association?
That’s the official Catholic church in China.
For decades, the Vatican and the Communist
Party
have had a schism—
where the Vatican oversees
all the Catholics outside China,
and the Communist Party oversees
all the Catholics inside China.
In China, the Holy Trinity
looks slightly different.
The main issue of contention
is who has the right to appoint
Catholic bishops in China.
China’s position has always been
that the Communist Party gets to appoint
Catholic bishops for state-approved churches—
so they can preach the Good Word
of Jesus Christ with Chinese Characteristics.
This has obviously been a point of contention.
In some individual cases,
the Vatican has given its stamp of approval
to bishops the CCP appoints.
But now Pope Francis is trying to bridge the
gap
through broader cooperation with the CCP.
Some Catholics, though,
think this betrays Christ.
A cardinal from Hong Kong explained that
“The official bishops [in China]
are not really preaching the gospel...
They are preaching obedience
to Communist authority.”
This week the story broke
that the Vatican was asking two bishops
in China to retire or be demoted,
to make way for two Chinese Communist Party
approved ones.
It’s especially odd considering
one of those state-approved bishops
“was excommunicated in 2011
after being consecrated
without Vatican approval.
He is also a member of the National People’s
Congress,
the Chinese parliament.”
And it’s also odd considering how the CCP
routinely persecutes underground Catholics
who remain loyal to the Vatican
instead of to the Patriotic Catholic Association.
If Pope Francis is willing to give the Communist
Party
what it wants on the issue of appointing bishops,
it may be only a matter of time before
he tries to change the Vatican’s stance
on another big issue:
The Vatican is one of the few countries in
the world
that still officially recognize Taiwan
to be the true China.
What do you think of the Pope’s decision?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Want to know more about Christianity in China?
Visit our website, ChinaUncensored.tv,
where we cover the Christian situation in
China,
plus many other stories that will have you
saying,
“Holy See.”