Hello Jordan, thank you for joining me today.
Thanks for having me.
This is Jordan Horowitz, the co-director and
producer of Angel of Nanjing.
It's a film about a guy who's dedicated the
past 10 years of his life
to preventing people from killing themselves
on the Yangtze river bridge in Nanjing.
We have a clip of that movie, so let's check
that out.
How come you're in such a bad mood, Big Sis?
I know your burden is too heavy,
and your mind is overwhelmed.
What difficulty can it be? Sufferings are
normal.
I really can't stand it anymore.
You think you can escape suffering by avoiding
the problem?
I think it's useless to wait for my husband
to change his mind.
Can I help you? What's the use having a brain
if you don't come up with ideas?
He met a foreign lady in Macao. That lady
is 4 years younger than I am.
He's got skills.
How can he be true to me when he's having
an affair?
How do you think he would treat your daughter
after you die?
Today you met me, your Big Brother.
Let me give you an idea or two.
If I can't resolve your issues, then you can
proceed with death, ok?
Ok, come with me.
What's wrong?
So, Chen really sounds more like a football
coach than anything else.
Yeah, I can see that.
He's got a big personality and he's very in
your face at times.
And that works?
It works for him, yeah.
You know, psychologists might tell you
that's not the proper method when dealing
with things like that,
but they're saying that from an office.
Yeah, they're not on the bridge talking people
down.
Exactly!
What he does, in my experience,
following for a year he's very effective and
he's kind of no nonsense,
he's kind of funny at times.
His methods are extremely effective.
About how many people has he been able to
talk down?
According to his records, he's saved over
300 people.
Wow!
And that was at the time of us making the
movie,
so I'd imagine that number's much higher now.
Yeah, and so why did you want to make this
movie?
I read about him online in a small article
a really good friend of mine had sent to me,
and I was just really inspired by what he
was doing,
I thought it was amazing.
As soon as I read it, I knew it was something
that I just had to jump on.
But I notice in the film, you don’t show
any of the stuff you're supposed to show
when you're shooting a movie in China;
there's no glistening skyscraper or high speed
rail.
China actually comes across as kind of a pretty
poor place.
I'm wondering was this the China you expected
or was it different from what you imagined.
I don’t really know what I expected going
there.
I do feel strongly that this was the China
that I encountered.
This was the daily life for me being there
and this is Chen's daily life, and Chen does
not live in an affluent area.
He's a very average, common man.
Which is what makes what he's doing-
it's what makes him so effective at what he's
doing
because most of the people going to the bridge
to kill themselves
are very poor people and that’s how he's
so relatable to them.
So one thing that I just want those of you
watching to understand
is that this bridge is very high,
so if you jump, there's no surviving that.
Yeah.
When you were with Chen, were there people
he couldn’t save?
There were definitely times where we would
arrive on the weekend
and Chen would point out, like a bloodstain
or something on the cement
and he's like somebody jumped last night
or something like that.
And how did that affect him?
It definitely affects him.
We talk about that at great length in the
film.
He says he's profoundly affected by what he's
done.
He does not think of himself as a hero. He
really struggles with-
He's saved over 300 people and he doesn’t
think of himself as a hero?
Yeah he really feels like a failure for the
people he hasn’t saved.
It really haunts him.
He drinks a lot, he smokes a lot, as you see
in the film, and those are the reasons.
A lot of drinking.
Yeah.
And I understand you had to join him?
Yeah Chen, you know Chen likes to drink.
He insists that we drink with him when we're
there
so there's some shaky footage in the film
and I think a big part of that-
part of that is because we're so far away
filming on very telephoto lenses
and another part is that we're probably drunk.
Well so that’s something I was wondering.
The first thing i was thinking when I saw
this film is,
how did two foreigners film this entire documentary
in China
and not get stopped by authorities?
We were definitely concerned about that when
we first went out there.
My partner and I would keep duplicate sets
of hard drives in separate places
just incase something happened.
Luckily nothing ever happened
but there was one instance with a translator
who for some reason
he thought the guards who patrolled the bridge
were trying to arrest us
and apparently he ran off the bridge and threw
his cellphone in the water
and it was a big deal,
fortunately the whole thing got calmed down.
But needless to say, he didn’t work out.
No, well I mean especially cause you don't
have a cellphone
to contact him with anymore.
That's probably the main thing.
He did send us some threatening emails for
a while but it all worked out.
Threatening you about what?
He got it in his head that the best thing
for us to do is alert the government
on what we're doing and Chen is the one who's
like, that’s a huge mistake.
He's like- "I've already got enough bad attention
on me,"
he's like, "you just need to just keep your
mouth shut."
There's bad attention on Chen?
I mean he's saving people from committing suicide.
So it's gotten better, it used to be-
Chen told me when he first started what he
was doing,
he would get threats from police saying "you're
bringing—"
because Chen gets a lot of attention from
the press,
they're like, "you're bringing bad attention
to China.
We're losing face. If you keep doing this,
you're going to get hurt."
So its more important that China looks good,
rather than actually saving people?
It's debatable.
He has gotten some humanitarian awards and
I do think times have changed.
They now realize that he's looked at in such
a positive way
that he's actually bringing good attention
to the area.
So they've stopped threatening him?
Yeah, as far as I know.
Wow. Well so, what- they threaten him- what
could the government be doing?
It seems to me that if you just built higher
fences, it would solve a lot of-
It's a very valid point.
For example, here in New York, the Williamsburg
Bridge has a fence
that is pretty high and it'd be really hard
to climb over it.
China doesn’t do that,
if you jump off of that bridge you land in
the water and you don’t disrupt anything.
And from what I've heard, they said it costs
too much money.
But as I understand it, on that bridge
there are high fences around the area where
somebody could jump
and land on the train tracks below.
That's right.
There's one small section of the fence where
it's overhanging a train track,
and if you were to jump, you would land in
the train tracks,
so they put a fence there and nobody jumps
there.
Cause you might delay traffic.
It's really sad.
I mean it's a very easily, fixable scenario
and it really sucks that they don’t do anything
about it.
So rather than building high fences,
they threaten the one guy who's trying to
actually help people.
Yeah, at first.
So what motivates him to potentially go up
against the government,
to spend over a decade of his life and his
own money to do this?
He learned form the media from the early new
reports that most of the people-
over 60% of the people that go to the bridge
to commit suicide
are outsiders to the city,
and Chen himself is an outsider so he knows
what that feeling is like
of having nowhere to go, no one to talk to,
and just really struggling.
Well, he sounds like an incredible individual.
Yeah, he's a great guy, and he's got a great
sense of humor,
that’s my favorite part about him.
Even in that clip you saw some of that come
out.
Yeah.
When he compliments the woman's husband who's
cheating on her.
Right right.
You know what's so great about Chen is that
he's just an ordinary guy
doing something really extraordinary with
his life
and it really made me think about how we all
could be doing that.
Yeah that’s incredible.
Well Jordan thank you for joining us.
Thanks for having me.
And if you want to know more you can go to
AngelOfNanjing.com;
check out the movie, it's really inspiring.
Thank you again Jordan.
Yeah, no problem.
Once again, I'm Chris Chappell, see you next
time.