On this episode of China Uncensored,
does this corruption make me look fat?
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
You know,
the Chinese Communist Party is a little like...
Smaug!
Sure, it seems big and scary.
But then it starts to show off…
My teeth swords.
My claws are spears.
My wings are a hurricane!
And reveals its greatest weakness.
Hmm,
does this mean I’m Bilbo?
No, I’m pretty sure I’m someone else.
Anyway, it’s a common problem:
The big scary bad guy has a glaring weakness.
In the Communist Party's case, it’s corruption.
In 2012, then-Chinese leader Hu Jintao passed
the torch to Xi Jinping.
But before he retired, Hu warned that failing
to defeat corruption
And so Xi has made rooting out corruption
kinda his thing.
Since Xi’s anti-corruption campaign began
in 2013,
he’s taken down more than one million officials.
(Show Headline
'One million' Chinese officials punished for
corruption
That’s according to official statistics
just released
by the Central Commission on Disciplinary
Inspection,
the government organ in charge
of Xi’s anti-corruption campaign,
and headed by China’s most woeful man,
Wang Qishan.
But why stop at a million?
Xi and Wang are just getting started.
The Central Commission on Disciplinary Inspection
also partnered with Party mouthpiece CCTV
to make this:
a reality show starring some of the biggest
officials
taken out.
It’s called “The Real Corrupt Officials
of Beijing.”
What’s that, Shelley?
Oh, it’s called “Always on the Road.”
Weird.
Fortunately,
my favorite state-run media,
Global Times, explains the unusual title:
“The [anti-corruption] campaign is ‘always
on the road’
and will never turn back.”
Ah, of course.
How silly of me for not immediately getting
it.
The show's featured confessions
include Bo Xilai and Zhou Yongkang,
two of Xi Jinping’s biggest rivals.
Also giving a totally uncoerced confession
is Zhou Benshun,
who confessed to the heinous crime
of giving his dead pet turtle Buddhist burial
rites.
Communist Party officials are suppose to be
atheists, you see.
Let’s hope he never met fellow “confessionaire”
Zhang Jianjin.
He’s a former Party secretary for a pharmaceutical
company
who was often treated to extravagant meals,
including a three-foot long crocodile tail.
Because anyone can have common food,
like a footlong hot dog.
Just go to the Yulin Dog Meat Festival.
Anyway,
there’s one thing all of these fallen officials
have in common:
They acted on their own,
and there is absolutely, definitely, for suresies
no systemic problem within the Communist Party
that led to this rampant corruption.
“The wrong lies with me.” says Li Chuncheng.
“How did a provincial party secretary nurtured
by the party for so many years change into
this?” said Bei Enpei.
He was sentenced to death for taking bribes
of nearly $38 million.
So are all officials featured in “Always
on the Road” corrupt?
No, of course not!
One official featured prominently is described
as spartan,
humble, and happy with a simple diet:
Xi Jinping!
Simple diet?
I guess he does eat a lot of vegetables.
According to the New York Times,
“In many areas,
[Party Members] have been ordered to watch
the show.”
I mean, it would be corrupt not to force people
to watch it!
Now on the one hand,
showing that Xi Jinping is tough on corruption
makes him,
and the Party,
seem powerful.
But on the other hand,
might people start to wonder,
“Hey, they’ve already punished a million
corrupt officials
and they’re still going at it.
Is there, maybe, a bigger problem with the
Communist Party?”
The correct answer is NO!
All these officials acted completely on their
own,
and there is absolutely no culture created
by the Communist Party that
condones corruption.
Nonetheless,
according to this recent poll by the Pew Center,
“Roughly half (49%) the Chinese public
says corrupt officials are a very big problem
in the country,
while another 34% believe they are a moderately
big issue.”
All this comes at a crucial time for the Communist
Party.
Because this week,
it held its annual plenum.
The Sixth Plenum, to be exact!
What’s a plenum?
Well, it’s when China’s top Communist
leaders come together,
don their ceremonial robes,
and seal themselves behind the vaulted doors
to discuss Party policy,
economic strategy,
and once again try to awaken the slumbering
cosmic horror,
Cthulhu.
Just kidding about that last one.
That's actually scheduled for next year's
plenum.
Each plenum has a different theme.
According to Party mouthpiece Xinhua,
this year the Plenum will focus on
“The norms of political life within the
Party
under the new situation,” and
“A revision to an intra-Party supervision
regulation.”
Which I think is the Party-speak equivalent
of Xi Jinping saying:
I’m watching you; don’t cross me.
Yes,
if anything has become clear
in the opaque dealings of the Party,
it’s that Xi has been consolidating power,
by purging political opponents in his so called
Anti-Corruption Campaign.
“We observe that 77% of local Party secretaries,
governors,
have been rotated,
the military has been fully restructured,
suggesting that President Xi is fully in power.”
And funny enough,
many of those provincial Party leaders
have recently been referring to Xi as the
“core leader.”
Two thirds of them in fact,
according to Reuters.
And the Communist Party just announced
that Xi is now officially the “core leader”
of the Party.
That means Xi ranks right up there
with Mao Zedong and Deng Xiaoping—
in other words,
it means he’s made big headway.
We’ll talk more about this in a later episode.
But Xi’s position is still uncertain.
Many of the 300 Central Committee members
that make up the Sixth Plenum
were appointed by former Chinese leader
and retired Mario villain Jiang Zemin,
Xi’s biggest political opponent.
And Xi Jinping has another problem.
The head of his anti-corruption campaign,
Wang Qishan,
is 68 years old.
Theoretically,
68 is the mandatory retirement age,
which means that he’s supposed to retire
at next year’s
Party Congress.
And who would be willing to replace this guy?
Xi Jinping will also be expected to name his
own successor
for when he steps down in 2022.
But that’s only if he follows precedent.
And let’s just say,
Xi is kind of unprecedented guy.
So what do you think?
Is Xi’s anti-corruption campaign saving
the Communist Party?
Or shooting itself in the foot
by exposing its dark underbelly?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Remember,
this show relies on support from viewers like you,
so if you can,
please considering supporting us on Patreon.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.