Protests in Hong Kong are heating up.
And in response to chief executive Carrie Lam,
a new group of angry citizens is getting involved.
Here in Hong Kong
demonstrators and police have been clashing.
After more than a million people took to the streets last Sunday,
in protest over a proposed extradition bill.
If passed,
it could allow the Hong Kong government to extradite people in Hong Kong
to mainland China.
Hong Kong chief executive Carrie Lam is calling the protests "organized riots."
And China's foreign ministry is telling the US to stop creating chaos in Hong Kong.
That's after the US already said it wasn't getting involved.
But that's not stopping China Uncensored from getting involved.
Walking into the protest, Shelley and I were ready for anything.
Well maybe not that...
For what Carrie Lam called an organized riot,
there sure were a lot of older women.
Shelley, I thought you said there were going to be some serious mothers here.
Yeah, I said there were going to be some serious mothers.
Suddenly this protest made much more sense.
But it still had an air of rebellion one might expect from... slightly younger older women.
Do you think tonight's protests will turn violent?
No, I don't think so.
Do  you think the protests tonight will turn violent?
No, not at all.
With a message of "don't shoot our kids,"
at least 6,000 people, mostly mothers, according to organizers,
staged a sit-in at a public park in the heart of Hong Kong's business district.
But Hong Kong police have shown in the past that they know how to handle rowdy older women.
Woah.
But that hasn't stopped mothers this time from getting involved.
Why did you attack those kids like this? It's enough for today.
Just leave!
So why are you here tonight?
We're a group of mothers. We're all caring parents.
We want our children to have a
to have a home where they can breathe freely and voice their opinion freely.
Many of the youngsters were being hurt.
They had been arrested without reasonable reasons
They just fight for their freedom and voicing their opinions.
But you know what? Carrie Lam is a mother, too.
And that's why she says she's pushing the extradition bill.
Because it's for the people's own good.
And you don't want to spoil your children, right?
And Carrie Lam certainly hasn't been spoiling these kids.
But these mothers have something to say about that.
When we heard from her speech like this,
we think as mothers, we all disagree with the way
of Carrie Lam.
What she did, we all disagree.
So we want to
to use our own way to express
our support to our kids in our own way.
We're actually very angry about that.
No mother would use such violence toward their children.
Not to use bullets, and they had.
And all mothers should have the responsibility to provide a good
and respectable environment for their children to grow.w
And more importantly, she is not our mother.
She is paid by us. We are the taxpayers who want her to remember it very clearly.
So tonight, we are the mothers of the children who went to protest
and we ant her to listen to it.
So if the authorities think they can walk all over Hong Kong's freedoms,
they're gonna have to get past some serious mothers.
But as the night wore on, their protests were getting clearly out of hand.
You can almost hear the kids screaming.
Aw, cut it out, Mom! You're embarrassing me!