On this episode of China Uncensored,
there’s gold in them thar...
Olympic Games...
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
It’s that time again
when countries around the world set aside
their differences
and come together...
to decide which country is the greatest through
gladiatorial combat.
Otherwise known as the Olympics.
Sadly they’ve done away with the nudity
and death matches
that made the ancient world so great.
But China wants you to know that it is the
greatest country on Earth.
China always gets pretty excited for the Olympic
Games.
China brought home only 5 gold medals at the
1988 Olympics.
But like that scrawny kid in high school,
they've been drinking milk.
And at the 30 year reunion,
they came back a beefcake,
winning 51 gold medals in 2008.
So understandably, Chinese people want some
respect.
Should the rest of the world hold China's
banner high?
Well they did.
And it looked like this.
Yeah, that's the Chinese flag.
But not quite.
Chinese media was furious about such an obvious
blunder
at medal ceremonies during the early days
of the Rio Olympics.
Subtle error?!
I don’t think so.
This is the actual Chinese flag.
And this is the flag hoisted at the Olympics.
See?
The stars are angled wrong!
I mean, what idiots approved this?!
Oh the Chinese Olympic Committee did.
Well, obviously they would have assumed Rio
could get the right Chinese flag.
I mean, where did they get that that knock
off anyway?!
Kind of ironic that the knockoff Chinese flag
was made in China.
But that was only the beginning of the humiliation
China had to endure.
Last Saturday, Australian swimmer Mack Horton
apparently called Chinese swim champ Sun Yang
a drug cheat.
Sun did test positive for a banned drug back
in 2014,
one that he said he was taking for a heart
condition.
But that drug is now no longer considered
a stimulant,
and is no longer banned.
So that was unfair.
If Sun deserves to be called out for anything,
it's apparently for acting like kind of an
arrogant jerk.
Swimmers: the Axe Body Spray of the Olympics.
Anyway, state-run media Global Times
did not like Horton's comments about Sun.
In fact, they took it as an opportunity to
slam the entire country of Australia.
Not only did the Global Times call Horton’s
win “immoral” and “disgraceful,”
it called Australian media “evil” and
suggested that Australia,
“a country at the fringes of civilization,”
and “Britain's offshore prison,”
might have, “a different moral standard.”
And if you think Global Times
is making a really, really big deal out of
something
that maybe isn’t that big of a deal,
“It's not a big deal to us.”
Right.
So why is China so obsessed with Olympic prestige?
For more on this
I’m joined by Senior Expert on the Feelings
of the Chinese People, Mia Chen.
Mia, ni hao?
Uhh, g’day Chris.
I like your headdress.
Is that one of those ancient Ming Dynasty
ones?
No, it's just to keep the flies away.
Wait, are you speaking with...
An Australian accent?
I was going to say an offshore British prison
accent, but yes.
Righteo
So why is Chinese media reacting so strongly
to,
what some might call, petty things?
Well, the Chinese media is a bit aggro, Chris.
But Olympic gold is one of the few things
China can say
it’s neck and neck at with the United States.
They've got heaps of medals, now.
That’s the kind of soft power you can only
get
by taking kids as young as five out of school
and training them all day every day in the
hopes
that one of them can be the best...
at trampoline.
“Only two men will be chosen to represent
China at trampoline in Rio...
I was selected for training when I was 7.
Or you can x-ray them to see if they're going
to grow really tall,
like they did to Sun Yang.
What?
Are you a criminal?
Oh, don’t you start that too!
Australia is very diverse, and only a few
parts of it were used as a prison colony,
and that was a really long time ago…
Oh, I’m sorry,
I think Mia had to go put some shrimp on the
barbie.
So what do you think of China’s Olympic
reaction?
Leave your comments below.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Um, you know we call them “prawns”.
And we don’t barbecue them.
So you've just met my friend Mia Chen from
Asian Beauty Secrets.
Hi!
If you're interested in Chinese medicine,
food, and ancient wisdom,
click here to check out my YouTube channel.
Seriously, it's pretty awesome.
Go check it out.
And where can I get one of those cool fly-swatter
hats?
Actually, those are only for tourists.
Like Foster's beer.
What?