On this episode of China Uncensored,
North Korea’s new missile has China going
ballistic.
The world’s oceans belong to all mankind.
Except for the ones that belong to China.
And multi-party democracy?
That’s evil.
Unless people’s votes don’t actually count;
then it’s fine.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
In our top story,
North Korea has successfully completed
another missile test.
According to the totally unbiased reporting
from state-run media,
it’s capable of striking
“anywhere in whole US mainland.”
Don’t worry,
because US President Donald Trump
still has a good bromance going on
with Chinese leader Xi Jinping.
After a phone call,
new sanctions are on the way!
But there’s one thing the Chinese regime
is still exporting to North Korea: refugees.
Like one mother and son who were recently
caught
attempting to flee North Korea.
They crossed the border into China,
ultimately on their way to South Korea.
That’s where the husband/father is waiting
after himself fleeing in 2015.
His name is Lee,
and he’s sent a message to Xi Jinping
begging him to save his family.
“When defectors are caught
trying to go to South Korea,
Lee tells me they’re sent to political camps,
and never leave.
From what I know, in 2–3 years,
maybe less, you’ll wither to death.”
The Chinese regime should know how wrong that
is!
They’ve been able to keep prisoners alive
in Chinese forced labor camps for over a decade...
before they wither to death.
But not wanting to be outdone by North Korea,
either in cruelty or missile technology,
the Chinese regime is close to rolling out
its own ballistic missile capable of striking
anywhere in the world.
They even broadcast a series of videos
on state-run TV about it.
But don’t worry.
The Chinese Communist Party
is committed to world peace.
They only kill innocent people inside China.
Speaking of people inside China,
a Chinese court this week sentenced
a Taiwanese activist to five years in prison.
We talked about Lee Ming-che back in September.
Well this week he was found guilty
of “subverting state power”
by promoting dangerous ideas
in group messaging chats.
Ideas like like multi-party democracy.
His sentence has the bonus effect
of striking fear into the hearts of Chinese
activists
and the people of Taiwan in general.
Instead of promoting multi-party democracy,
what Lee should have done,
is promote the system
they already have in mainland China,
which is...multi-party cooperation.
You see, while China has eight political parties
other than the Chinese Communist Party,
the CCP is “the sole party exercising political
leadership
in this system of multi-party cooperation.”
Cooperation means that all the parties are
equal.
The CCP is just more equal than everyone else.
And besides, everyone knows that Chinese people
aren’t ready for democracy!
Unless they live in Taiwan…
And apparently Chinese people aren’t ready
for violent video games, either.
That’s why hit South Korean multiplayer
shooter
PlayerUnknown’s Battlegrounds, or PUBG,
is coming to China...
with Chinese characteristics.
Chinese tech giant Tencent has bought the
rights
to bring PUBG to China.
And they’ve agreed to make some changes
to the original South Korean version.
Chinese censors had said the game was
“too violent and said it would likely be
blocked
because it ‘severely deviates from socialist
core values.’”
But what could be more in line with socialist
core values
than violence and senseless killing?
Maybe they can just slap some
Communist Party flags in the background,
and then it will be ok.
That's at least what another video game company in China did.
The blood just blends in.
And speaking of sticking to core values,
a Chinese scholar is criticizing India
for doing military drills in the Indian Ocean.
He says, “It should be stressed that
the Indian Ocean belongs to all mankind,
and India’s actions are an attempt to
turn the ocean into India’s territorial
waters,
which is a violation of International Law.”
All the world’s oceans froze over in irony.
And the Trump Administration is making another
move
against the Chinese regime for unfair trade
practices.
The Commerce Department has officially launched
a probe into China’s aluminum exports to
the US.
If China is found to be dumping at prices
that are artificially low,
the US could impose tariffs.
And it’s not just the US
that’s having trade trouble with China.
A group of German businesses is warning
that some German companies may pull out of
China.
Why?
Because of “a request from the ruling Communist
Party
to set up cells in their companies.”
Apparently, there are already more than 100,000
foreign-invested companies in China
that have a Party secretary embedded with
their staff.
It’s something the Communist Party requires.
But hey, who doesn’t want a Party in their
company?
Oh, wait.
The Germans don’t.
That actually makes sense.
So what do you think of this week’s news?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Wait!
There’s more episodes ready and waiting
for you!
Every Friday afternoon,
we upload the full half-hour show
to our website and our app on Apple TV,
Fire TV, and Roku.
Check it out now,
because some of those segments
won’t be on YouTube until next week.
Click here to visit our website,
ChinaUncensored.tv