bjbj,(,( On this episode of China Uncensored,
Guess what s washing up in Chinese Rivers
Now? Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I m
your host Chris Chappell. Okay, this is not
funny anymore. When 6000 dead pigs washed
up in Shanghai s drinking water, and the idiot
authorities said it was still fine to drink,
that was already a bad joke. When that number
shot up to 16,000, it just stopped being funny.
Then, then they had to find a thousand dead
ducks in another river, along with a few hundred
more pigs. And the water was still safe to
drink. I, I don t think these authorities
understand what it means for water to be safe
to drink. Maybe they just mean it s politically
safe to drink the water, like they won t get
arrested for it. But come on, seriously! Do
they have to start finding human corpses before
they say the water isn t safe to drink? Of
course that s ridiculous. If you ve been watching
China Uncensored, you d know, of course, of
course human corpses have been washing up
by the hundreds for decades. Recently, authorities
in Lanzhou City in Gansu Province said they
find about 100 bodies every year in their
part of the Yellow River. That s probably
a gross underestimation however. Though, really
the truth is even grosser. The Gansu Province
has become home to a booming business called
body fishing. A body fisher is someone who
combs the river looking for corpses. They
leave the bodies floating in the water to
preserve them and then charge the families
about 500 dollars to take a look at their
deceased loved ones. In this report from 2010,
just one body fisher said he finds about 100
corpses a year, so yeah, there s more than
100 corpses a year turning up. Of course,
according to Lanzhou s environmental official,
even though there s hundreds of decomposing
corpses, it s had no effect on the quality
of water. Okay, come on. If hundreds of dead
bodies doesn t affect water quality what does?!
Unless, maybe the water quality is already
so bad, what they re saying is it just can
t get any worse. And they say don drink the
water when you go to Mexico. Come to think
of it, how many of you have been to China
and had a glass of water or tea? Of course,
the other unpleasant question this whole thing
raises is, why are there hundreds of corpses
in China s rivers? You d think, you know,
police might want to fish out the bodies and
I don t know, investigate. Authorities say
most of the victims drowned or died in accidents,
but, well, I think we ve established how credible
Chinese authorities are. The body fishers
say most of the corpses look like suicides
or murders, but that obviously can t be. Why
just in February China s Ministry of Public
Security (LINK) reported that China s murder
rate was nearly the lowest in the world, and
what few homicide cases there were get solved,
so there s no way these hundreds of unidentified
dead bodies could be unsolved murder cases.
There s no way. So, what do you think will
be the next thing they find washing up in
China s rivers? Comment below and let me know
what you think. Thanks for watching this episode
of China Uncensored. Once again I m Chris
Chappell, see you next time. h`SK hUos gdim
[Content_Types].xml #!MB ;c=1 _rels/.rels
theme/theme/themeManager.xml sQ\}# theme/theme/theme1.xml
G$$DA : BR \{i5@R V*[_X ,l\Y Ssd+r] 5\|E Vky-
V4Ej 6NGU s?^V * 7;wP EBU` 5<V8
LStf+] C9P^ wB>VD GGHPXNT, /M,W m2iU [[v _Xtl
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.rels 6?$Q
K(M&$R(.1 [Content_Types].xmlPK _rels/.relsPK
theme/theme/themeManager.xmlPK theme/theme/theme1.xmlPK
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.relsPK
<a:clrMap xmlns:a="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/main"
bg1="lt1" tx1="dk1" bg2="lt2" tx2="dk2" accent1="accent1"
accent2="accent2" accent3="accent3" accent4="accent4"
accent5="accent5" accent6="accent6" hlink="hlink"
folHlink="folHlink"/> Chris Normal.dotm Chris
Microsoft Macintosh Word PICT+H kZo\{g9^ g9g9Z
kZo\{c g9kZZ o\{g9^ g9kZg9^ g9g9c o\{o\
g9kZo\{o\{kZ g9kZkZ\{ 6kZkZc g9g9^ g9g9kZg9g9c
kZg9c g9kZg9Z Nsg9c g9o\{kZg9g9^ o\{g9kZw o\{o\{w
"g9o\{kZkZo\{w kZo\{kZkZo\{kZs kZkZs o\{g9s kZg9o\{w
kZo\{^ o\{kZo\{kZs o\{kZkZ^ g9kZw g9kZc kZkZs
g9kZo\{ g9kZg9kZo\{kZ^ kZkZo\{s o\{o\{kZo\{s g9kZo\{o\{g9c
g9kZg9c kZg9w g9o\{kZg9o\{s o\{g9kZo\{ o\{kZw o\{o\{kZkZo\{w
kZo\{s o\{o\{g9c g9g9o\{^ o\{g9kZg9^ g9kZc o\{o\
g9kZZ g9g9o\{kZg9g9o\{w o\{kZ^ g9kZ^ kZkZg9Z
kZkZg9o\{c g9o\{ o\{kZw o\{o\{kZo\{kZo\{o\{s o\{o\{s
kZo\{s o\{o\{w kZo\{s o\{o\{w kZo\{^ o\{o\{s kZo\{c
kZkZw g9kZc o\{g9c kZg9kZc AkZkZo\{V o\{g9Z o\{g9R
kZg9Z g9kZZ g9g9kZkZZ g9kZkZc g9o\{Z kZkZo\
o\{o\
g9kZg9g9c g9g9s g9kZg9g9c g9kZs o\{kZs kZg9s
g9g9c o\{o\{ *kZZ kZo\{Z o\{kZg9c g9g9kZZ kZkZc
o\{g9^ g9o\{R g9kZg9c g9g9^ g9g9s g9g9kZZ g9g9c
o\{o\{w o\{8s o\{o\{kZo\{o\{kZo\{kZkZs o\{kZkZs o\{o\{kZo\{o\{kZs
o\{o\{s kZo\{s o\{kZo\{kZw o\{kZc o\{o\{c o\{kZo\{g9g9s
g9kZs o\{g9g9kZkZs o\{kZ^ kZkZo\{g9g9o\{kZs g9kZo\{s
g9kZg9g9^ kZg9^ g9g9w kZg9kZo\{o\{w kZg9^ kZg9V
kZg9R ;g9o\{kZ^ kZo\{kZg9w kZkZo\{s kZg9o\{s o\{kZkZs
kZg9kZc g9kZo\{c g9o\{kZs o\{g9kZ\{ kZg9c kZg9o\{o\
kZo\{s o\{kZkZs o\{g9g9w kZg9w kZo\{kZ\{ kZo\{ +g9V
kZg9V g9g9Z =g9s g9kZ^ o\{kZkZV o\{o\{ kZkZc
g9kZg9g9s kZo\{o\{g9c kZkZZ g9g9c o\{o\{g9kZg9c
kZkZg9kZZ g9kZ^ g9o\{s o\{kZ\{ o\{o\{kZ o\{g9s o\{s
o\{kZs g9o\{g9s o\{g9s o\{o\{g9s g9kZc kZkZs Do\{g9o\{c
g9o\{g9c g9g9c kZg9g9s g9kZo\{g9c g9o\{^ kZo\{c
o\{kZ^ g9o\{c g9o\{c g9kZc g9g9o\{c o\{o\{s )g9Z
kZkZV g9kZc 6o\{V g9g9V kZo\{V g9kZkZ o\{kZc
kZo\{g9kZc g9g9 g9g9c g9g9c o\{g9V o\{g9 o\{o\{c
o\{o\{ Co\{c o\{o\{c o\{kZs o\{o\{c o\{kZkZs kZo\{w
kZo\{s g9o\{w g9o\{s kZkZs g9kZs g9g9c g9g9o\{o\{kZs
o\{kZ^ g9g9o\{g9g9Z g9kZg9Z kZg9kZc kZo\{g9o\{g9kZg9kZs
kZg9o\{Z g9kZg9o\{kZ kZo\
g9kZ^ kZo\{ o\{o\{s o\{o\
o\{kZs g9o\{o\
kZg9^ g9g9Z g9o\{^ g9kZZ o\{g9Z g9g9kZg9o\{o\{c
g9kZg9g9kZZ o\{o\{ kZo\{w o\{g9 kZo\{o\{s kZo\{w
kZo\{s kZkZw $o\{c o\{kZg9^ g9g9kZc o\{o\{kZc g9kZs
o\{g9c g9kZg9 g9o\{g9^ g9g9c g9NsV g9kZR g9o\{V
kZg9Z g9g9Z g9kZc o\{g9Z kZkZg9V kZg9V kZkZc
g9kZw g9g9\{ kZg9c kZg9o\{^ g9o\{kZg9 o\{kZo\{s
o\{o\{s o\{o\{g9 o\{g9 o\{o\{s o\{o\{s o\{o\{kZo\{o\{s
o\{o\{kZs o\{g9^ o\{g9 kZg9o\{s g9g9kZo\{s o\{kZs
g9kZkZo\{c o\{g9g9kZ g9)c o\{g9c o\{g9g9s kZo\{kZc
g9g9kZkZs g9kZc o\{kZs Bg9g9V kZkZV kZg9Z (g9V
kZNs^ g9g9^ $kZZ kZo\{^ o\{g9c g9o\{g9c kZg9^
g9g9kZc g9g9kZZ g9kZ\{ g9kZkZ o\{o\{s o\{o\{s o\{o\{w
o\{o\{ o\{o\{ Title Microsoft Word 97-2004 Document
NB6W Word.Document.8