On this episode of China Uncensored,
5 countries that have faced the wrath
of the Chinese Communist Party.
Hi, welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
You don’t want to get on China’s bad side.
That’s the message to nations that dare
to cross the Chinese Communist Party’s red
lines.
Sometimes it’s over major policy stuff,
like challenging their territorial claims
in the South China Sea.
Other times it seems trivial,
like when Chinese tourists got
kicked out of a hotel for misbehaving.
“This is killing.
This is killing.”
But regardless of whether the problem is big
or small,
the Chinese Communist Party wants to make
sure
other countries feel the pain.
That way they’ll be less likely
to stand up against the Party in the future.
Here are 5 countries that have paid the price
for crossing the Chinese regime.
Number 5
Norway.
A country in northern Europe famous for vikings,
the midnight sun, and trolls.
And while I’ve always been a big fan of
Norwegian trolls,
no one likes to get trolled.
But that’s what happened in 2010,
after the Norwegian Nobel Committee gave
the Nobel Peace Prize to Chinese writer
and dissident Liu Xiaobo.
Then Norway experienced what it’s like to
get
trolled by the Chinese Communist Party.
China’s foreign ministry fumed about the
award,
and said that giving Liu the prize
“runs completely counter to the principle
of the prize
and is also a blasphemy to the peace prize.”
And to show Norway that nothing quite rankles
the CCP
like the suggestion that people should have
a say
about who gets to run China,
they pretty much froze diplomatic ties for
six years.
And even worse, they cancelled
a concert by a Norwegian Eurovision winner.
Look, I don’t understand Eurovision, but
I respect it.
Another one of the casualties?
Norway’s second biggest export after oil
and gas—fish.
Norway used to be the biggest exporter of
salmon to China.
But after Liu got the Nobel prize,
China took its revenge and cut salmon imports
by over 60%.
All of this is even more ridiculous
because the Nobel Prize Committee is completely
separate
from the Norwegian government.
So it’s not like the government had any
control
over who gets the Nobel Peace Prize.
That seems to be something that the Chinese
authorities
couldn’t quite grasp though,
as they apparently offered to unfreeze diplomatic
ties
if the Norwegian government promised that
the Nobel Peace Prize
would never go to a Chinese dissident ever
again.
But then Liu Xiaobo died of liver cancer last
year
while still in Chinese custody.
And just a few months later,
China moved to restore relations with Norway.
The Norwegian prime minister
visited the e-commerce giant Alibaba,
and soon after a seafood trade agreement
was signed to export $1.5 billion worth of
salmon to China by 2025.
Which led to uncomfortable headlines like
“Norway wants China to forget about the
human rights thing
and eat salmon instead”
Number 4
South Korea
Back in 2016, South Korea deployed an American-made
anti-missile defense system known as THAAD.
It’s officially designed to intercept missiles
from North Korea,
but it could also stop missiles from, really,
any aggressive communist neighbor.
And this was not lost on Chinese leaders,
who hated THAAD from the get-go.
Within a month of deployment,
tour groups from China to South Korea dropped
to nearly zero,
as this graph shows.
And individual tourism from China fell by
about half.
Cuts to tourism cost South Korea more than
15 billion dollars
and four hundred thousand jobs.
But to make things weirder,
China also took out its anger over the missile
defense system
on Korean pop culture.
I guess once the Chinese Communist Party decided
to target Eurovision, K-Pop is fair game.
Korean pop and drama stars started having
their appearances in China cancelled.
And remember K-pop star Psy and his video
Gangnam Style,
which got so many views it ‘broke’
YouTube’s view limit of 2,147,483,647?
Well China decided it wasn’t gonna help
bring Psy’s view count
any closer to YouTube’s new limit of 9.22
quintillion
and banned his music videos from streaming
into China.
It wasn’t until last year,
when the new Korean president Moon Jae-in
took a softer line on THAAD that we saw reports
about Psy’s sudden return to China’s charts,
which was touted as “the surest sign yet
of a thaw between Seoul and Beijing”
Oh, and make sure you share this China Uncensored
video…
9.22 quintillion views, here we come!
Number 3
The Philippines
Back in 2012, when Chinese and Filipino ships
first clashed over disputed waters in the
South China Sea,
Chinese authorities retaliated with the fury
of what’s been called the China-Philippine
Banana War.
First the Chinese regime drastically
reduced banana imports from the Philippines,
claiming they were infested by pests.
Later they put the squeeze on other fruits,
including papayas, mangoes, coconuts, and
pineapples.
I guess Chinese authorities don’t like Pina
Coladas,
or getting caught in the rain.
Especially if it’s Filipino rain.
Chinese authorities issued travel warnings
to discourage Chinese tourists from visiting
the Philippines.
And it had a huge impact in some parts of
the country.
But after Filipino President Rodrigo Duterte
decided to get all buddy-buddy with Chinese
leader Xi Jinping...
...the tourism floodgates have opened again.
And don’t worry, the Chinese regime lifted
the import ban on Philippine bananas, too.
Duterte has achieved this partly by backing
down
over claims in the South China Sea,
and making *hilarious* jokes like,
the Philippines ought to just be a province
of China.
Ha.
And presto!
Within a few months,
the number of Chinese tourists grew by
40 percent and China announced plans
to increase imports of mangoes, coconut and
dragonfruit.
But the Philippines isn’t the only country
with competing claims in the South China Sea.
For example, there’s Vietnam, Malaysia,
Taiwan, and Brunei.
There’s an old Chinese saying called
"kill the chicken to scare the monkeys",
which refers to making an example out of someone
in order to scare monkeys.
And with the Philippines,
China is sending a message...
if you don’t monkey around, we’ll buy
your bananas.
Number 2
Sweden
When a Swedish hotel refused to let a Chinese
family
spend the night in the lobby for free and
called the police,
the Chinese regime called bloody murder.
“This is killing.
This is killing.”
That was actually Mr. Zeng, the son,
accusing Swedish police,
who appear to gingerly place him on the sidewalk
outside the hotel,
of trying to murder his parents.
A passerby filmed the scene and told Sweden’s
biggest newspaper
that the police tried to calm the situation
while the Chinese family just ”shouted and
screamed”
and the son basically ”threw himself flat
on the ground.”
But the family complained to the Chinese ambassador,
who seemed pretty willing to elevate this
into a major diplomatic incident between Sweden
and China.
Ambassador Gui Congyou complained to Swedish
newspapers
that Chinese citizens were treated brutally
by a country that supposedly cares about human
rights.
“We find it shocking and hard to understand
that the three Chinese tourists
were treated in such a brutal manner
in a country that always talks about
human rights and justice.”
Chinese state-run media repeated the same
message
suggesting that Sweden was a human rights
hypocrite.
Now if you think the Chinese authorities
and state media are making a big deal about
nothing,
there’s just one more piece of the puzzle.
That’s right, the Dalai Lama visited Sweden
just one week before the Zeng family got kicked
out of their hotel.
Maybe the Chinese regime decided to channel
their usual outrage about the Dalai Lama
into outrage about these mistreated Chinese
tourists.
This whole story blew up in China where the
search term
“Chinese tourists mistreated by Swedish
police”
received more than 130 million views on Weibo.
But not everybody was sympathetic to the tourists.
In fact, some found them,
and the reaction from the Chinese authorities...embarrassing.
But just as the controversy was dying down,
a Swedish satire showed released this helpful
how-to video for Chinese tourists.
“For example, we do not poop outside historic
buildings.”
Now at first glance, this seems extremely
racist.
But when you watch the entire episode
hosted by the Swedish version of me,
it’s clear that the satire was actually
mocking Swedish people
for being ignorant and racist about Chinese
people.
As well as the Swedish government for hypocritically
caring
more about doing business with China than
human rights.
“But we allow this to continue because we
need the money.
And it will be so hard to get the money
if there is a lot of fighting
about Chinese authorities having Swedes imprisoned
and violating human rights and so on.
But that didn’t stop the Chinese Ministry
of Foreign Affairs
from calling the show “a gross insult to
and vicious attack on China
and the Chinese people.”
Satire is hard, I know.
Number 1
Taiwan
Finally, it’s everyone’s favorite China--Taiwan.
Also officially known as the Republic of China.
Also officially not known as a country, even
though it is.
Taiwan’s previous president Ma Ying-jeou
really focused on increasing Taiwan’s ties
with mainland China.
Which led to this beautiful meeting
between the two leaders of China..ish.
Under President Ma, Taiwan went from having
no Chinese tourists to having more than 4
million of them.
But that changed after Taiwan’s current
president,
Tsai Ing-wen took office.
Tourism from mainland China dropped 36 percent
within the first 7 months of her term,
as the Chinese Communist Party restricted
the number of Chinese tour groups.
But it turns out that tourism from China
could be the least of Taiwan’s worries.
Over the last two years,
the Chinese Communist Party has made a push
to isolate Taiwan internationally.
Five different countries have switched from
recognizing Taiwan
to recognizing mainland China instead.
And the Chinese regime even pressured international
airlines
to not list Taiwan as a country on their websites.
Because everyone knows,
if it’s not on the internet, it doesn’t
exist.
But there is some good news for Taiwan!
It looks like the Chinese Communist Party’s
attempts
to punish Taiwan economically through restricting
tourism is...
backfiring.
Although tourism from mainland China is down,
international tourism in Taiwan is way up,
thanks to more tourists from Japan, Korea,
India, and Southeast Asia.
And it’s actually better for Taiwan’s
economy,
since these tourists spend
more than mainland Chinese tour groups,
and the money goes to Taiwanese
and not mainland Chinese owned businesses.
It looks like the Chinese Communist Party
may have to
look for different ways to punish Taiwan in
the future.
So what do you think about the countries
that got punished for angering the Chinese
Communist Party?
Leave your comments below.
And now is the moment you’ve all been waiting
for!
When I answer questions from a member
of the China Uncensored 50 cent army—
the fans who make this show possible
by contributing through the crowd funding
website Patreon.
Brian Caylor asks,
What was the subject of your first episode?
I would like to watch it.
Oh Brian, you’ve opened Pandora’s box!
The very first episode of China Uncensored
was actually not even called China Uncensored.
It was called China Unscripted.
Here’s a quick clip.
Hi, welcome to China Unscripted.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Fun times.
I eventually realized since there was a script,
calling it China Unscripted made no sense.
Fortunately we ended up reusing that name
years later
for our new Podcast, China Unscripted.
By the way, subscribe on iTunes.
The biggest difference, besides the name,
was I covered three topics in a single episode.
The first was a Canadian journalist named
Mark Bourrie,
who was working for Chinese state-run media,
Xinhua.
He accused them of asking him to spy on the
Dalai Lama.
That lead into a story about state-run media
paying Western media companies, like the Washington
Post,
to publish Chinese propaganda.
And then, in a tradition apparently going
all the way back
to the beginning of the show,
I complain about my student loan debt
and ask Chinese state run media to make me
an offer as well.
Hey, I can relate to what it’s like to need
money.
I got my Master's at NYU, I have crippling student loan debt.
So what I’m saying is, Xinhua, make me an
offer.
Welcome, comrades.
You know, that was before Shelley joined on
the show,
and can I just say,
I think it had a little something to it.
What’s that Shelley?
Okay, no it didn’t.
Thanks for your question Brian.
And remember, China Uncensored is only possible
because of viewers like you who contribute
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
Even a dollar an episode makes a huge difference.
So head over to Patreon.com/chinauncensored
to learn more.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Unscripted.
I mean Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.