On this episode of China Uncensored,
it’s getting hot in here…
So put on that radiation suit.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Bad news folks!
Nuclear war with China is imminent.
The good news is that we all know what to do.
Duck and cover!
This is the Dongfeng-31.
It’s equipped with a nuclear warhead
and can fly almost 5000 miles,
far enough to hit the continental US.
Now, don’t worry,
I’m not going to tell you China just sent
several of these
to Heilongjiang Province,
which is along the border with Russia
and the closest point in China to the United
States.
Because allegedly China just sent several
Dongfeng-41’s
to Heilongjiang Province,
along the border with Russia
and the closest point in China to the United
States.
There have been reports for years
that China was testing these missiles,
but we haven't seen them until now.
Maybe.
According to always accurate state-run media,
the Global Times,
the Dongfeng-41 can carry not one,
but 10-12 nuclear warheads,
and can fly over 8500 miles,
to hit anywhere in the world.
Yes, even your backyard, little Jimmy.
So you know what to do, right?
Duck and cover!
That potato salad will never be the same.
Anyway, what was the Kremlin’s response
to China putting nukes on their border?
They don’t care!
Apparently,
images have been surfacing on Chinese social
media
of the Dongfeng 41 in Heilongjiang Province.
Remember,
we haven't seen confirmed images before.
And media have been eating it up,
like a barbeque on the fourth of July.
Some media are reporting it’s a response
to President Trump’s provocative remarks
on China.
At least, the Global Times said that
some media are saying that.
Hey, it makes sense, right?
Therefore it must be true.
Just listen to what Trump’s Press Secretary,
Sean Spicer said about the South China Sea.
I think the U.S. is going to make sure
that we protect our interests there….
yeah we're going to make sure that we defend
international territories
from being taken over by one country."
And Trump’s Secretary of State
is even talking about blockading China’s
access
to artificial islands they built in disputed
territorial waters.
We’re going to have to send China a clear
signal
that first the island-building stops
and second your access to those islands
is also not going to be allowed.”
Well China’s having none of it!
"China's position on the South China Sea issue
is clear and consistent.
China's resolve to protect its sovereignty
and maritime rights
in the South China Sea will not change.”
And now Global Times is saying
“China's nuclear capability should be so
strong
that no country would dare launch a military
showdown
with China under any circumstance,
and such that China can strike back
against those militarily provoking it.”
So if you’re freaking out, good.
Continue to watch China Uncensored.
Only China Uncensored can protect you.
So are you ready to see the footage
that has everyone up in arms?!
Yes, 7 seconds of...
something under a black tarp.
That is the only evidence that China
has put an experimental nuclear missile on
the border of Russia.
When asked about the reports,
China's Foreign Ministry called them
"speculation circulated on the Internet."
Hey, just because something's on the internet
doesn't mean it's not true!
Or, that it's true, either.
Even Global Times says,
“there has been no authoritative information
on whether China has a Dongfeng-41 strategic
missile brigade,
how many such brigades it has,
and where they are deployed.”
So really,
this is probably all smoke and mirrors.
So what’s actually going on?
Well, this all follows almost immediately
on the heels of Chinese leader Xi Jinping
calling for a world without nuclear weapons
in a speech in front of the United Nations.
So is Xi a hypocrite?
Well, maybe.
But going before the UN
and saying nuclear weapons should be completely
prohibited,
then immediately putting nuclear weapons
on the border of Russia,
in striking distance of the US?
That’s just stupid.
And you don’t get to make it to the top
of the Communist Party
by being stupid.
Psychopathic toad, yes.
Actually stupid, no.
Xi Jinping is,
as you know if you’ve been watching,
locked in a life or death struggle with a
political faction
within the Communist Party
tied to former Chinese leader Jiang Zemin.
And there’s been so many instances,
like this,
where Xi says one thing,
then the Party seems to do, immediately, the
exact opposite.
Which makes Xi look stupid.
And bad.
So when the Global Times,
the hawkish publication with ties to the Jiang
faction,
runs a story based off one really shaky video,
is the message really to tell Trump
to back off the South China Sea?
Or is it a message to the world that
“hey, this Xi Jinping guy is lying
and probably plotting something evil behind
his stoic facade.
Unlike his predecessors in office,
who were all goodness and light.”
But, just in case, you know what to do.
Duck and cover!
And try not to get run over by your tractor.
What do you think?
I’ll be delving more into the power struggle
inside China on an upcoming episode.
So stay tuned.
And don’t forget to support China Uncensored
on Patreon.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.