China is targeting Americans
in a new wave of Hostage Diplomacy.
What’s behind it?
Welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.\h
If you’re an American watching this video
from inside China—Get out!!!
Get out of China while you still can!
Okay, it’s maybe not quite that serious.
Maybe.
But tensions between the United States and
China are getting worse.
Yeah, they’ve been getting worse for a while.\h
Now we’ve reached the “China warns it
may detain Americans” stage.
As in, those are some nice American citizens
we’ve got here.
It’d be a shame if something bad happened
to them.\h
This makes a lot of sense.
Because the Chinese Communist Party is just
threatening to do what the US government is
doing.
You see, the US has been arresting Chinese
scholars for no reason at all, other than
the fact that they were Chinese... and didn’t
disclose their military ties on their visa
applications...and may have also been spying
for the Chinese military on US soil.
In fact, it seems diplomats in the Chinese
Consulate in Houston were working with these
scholars.
Which was a big reason why the US shut that
consulate down.
So obviously the only fair thing to do, is
for China to arrest random US citizens in
retaliation.
Yes, that’s what the Chinese regime is threatening
to do.
“The Chinese officials have issued the warnings
to U.S. government representatives repeatedly
and through multiple channels...including
through the U.S. Embassy in Beijing.”
Sources told the Wall Street Journal that
China’s message was clear: “The U.S. should
drop prosecutions of the Chinese scholars
in American courts, or Americans in China
might find themselves in violation of Chinese
law.”
What law?
We don’t know yet, but I’m sure they can
find something.
Because the Chinese Communist Party is working
on a little something called hostage diplomacy.
People started talking about China’s hostage
diplomacy back in 2018.
That’s when China detained two Canadian
citizens inside of China, Michael Kovrig and
Michael Spavor.
Their crime?
Being Canadian.
I get it.
It’s a crime to be so nice.
But in China, they were actually charged with
espionage.\h
Not right away, of course.
They had been detained for a year and a half
before they were formally charged.
China’s bureaucracy can be slow.
Sometimes it takes years for them to figure
out why they arrested someone.
At least on the surface.
Because in reality, the Chinese Communist
Party knew exactly what they were doing from
the get go.
They arrested the two Canadians because, well,
actually because they were Canadian—at the
wrong time.
They were Canadian, and the Canadian government
had just arrested the CFO of Chinese telecom
Huawei.
She has been accused of violating US sanctions
on Iran.
So the Communist Party was showing Canada:
If you arrest one of our citizens, we’ll
arrest two of yours.
And you Canadians won’t do anything about
it, because you’re too nice.
This is called hostage diplomacy.\h
But I don’t want to give you the impression
that the Chinese Communist Party are the only
ones who do this.\h
It’s also done by great countries like North
Korea.
Of course, the Chinese Communist Party does
not like the term hostage diplomacy one bit.
I know that from my favorite Chinese state-run
media, the Global Times.
This was from this past summer, after the
two Canadians were charged:
“Asked if China’s prosecution of two Canadians
was ‘hostage diplomacy,’ Chinese Foreign
Ministry spokesperson Zhao Lijian said...the
question was ‘full of evil intentions,’
and replied ‘it would be better to ask the
Canadian government about hostage diplomacy.’”
Wait, are you sure you want to ask the Canadian
government about hostage diplomacy?
Because the Canadian defense minister is going
to tell you exactly what he thinks.
\h
Hostage diplomacy—isn’t there a more...
diplomatic name for it?
How about: “captivating diplomacy”?
But the Chinese government is going even further
to play down the issue.
I’ll tell you how after this short break.
Welcome back.
Remember how I said earlier that China warned
it may detain Americans?
Well now, China is denying that it ever threatened
to detain Americans, haha.
The Americans probably just *misinterpreted*
all of those repeated warnings issued through
multiple channels including the US Embassy
in Beijing.
Of course, hostage diplomacy, I mean “captivating
diplomacy”, didn’t begin with the two
Canadians.
I did a whole episode about it back in 2018
called 5 Times China Detained Foreign Citizens
(for No Good Reason).\h
But basically China has been using hostage
diplomacy for many years against Americans
and Canadians, as well as Brits and Australians.
Even smaller countries like Sweden.\h
Here’s another example.
This month, Canada said it would begin accepting
Hong Kong activists as refugees.
The Chinese Communist Party did not like that.
So the Chinese ambassador to Canada threatened
that if Canada goes through with this, “That
could have consequences for the ‘health
and security’ for the 300,000 Canadians
living in [Hong Kong].”
In other words, if you’re a Canadian living
in Hong Kong—get out!
Get out now!!!
So yeah, Canadians, Americans, and pretty
much everyone else...now is not a good time
to be in China.
A US State department official has warned
that China can pretty much come up with whatever
reason it wants to detain a US citizen.
“We warn U.S. citizens that business disputes,
court orders to pay a settlement, or government
investigations into both criminal and civil
issues may result in an exit ban which will
prohibit your departure from China until the
issue is resolved.”
Exit bans are when they stop you from leaving
the country.
Which is one key reason why the US State Department
has issued a Level 3 travel advisory on China
that says you might want to reconsider travel.
“The PRC government uses arbitrary detention
and exit bans...to gain bargaining leverage
over foreign governments.”
What if you’re an American citizen who’s
already in China, though?
Well, over the summer, the US State Department
issued a security alert to American citizens
in China.
Warning them to “exercise increased caution”
due to the heightened detention risks in China
Most average Americans are probably still
safe.
We haven’t gotten to the point where Chinese
authorities are targeting all Americans in
the country.\h
But there are certain things that put Americans
more at risk of being detained or arrested
in China, especially now that the Chinese
regime has explicitly threatened Americans.\h
And I’ll tell you what those are after the
break.
Welcome back.
What kinds of things put Americans living
in China at risk of being arbitrarily detained
or arrested?
The most obvious thing is doing anything illegal.
But that’s not as straightforward as in
some other countries.
Definitely do not do drugs in China.
But things that once seemed more minor, like
working in China on a non-work visa, or doing
business in China without the right paperwork,
can get you arrested.\h
For example, there’s been a surge in arrests
of foreign teachers in China.
Many of them arrested for visa issues.
Of course, doing illegal things in China also
includes things like protesting the government,
or helping dissidents, or making jokes about
Xi Jinping on WeChat.
But only Chinese people are being detained
for that.
For now.\h
If you have past connections to the US government,
or if you have worked for a non-governmental
organization, or NGO, you’re also more at
risk.
The Chinese Communist Party does not like
NGOs.
They think NGOs are actually being controlled
by foreign governments.
And that is because all Chinese NGOs are controlled
by the Chinese Communist Party.\h\h
One of the two Canadian Michaels, Michael
Kovrig, was a former diplomat and was working
for an NGO when he was detained.
On our China Unscripted podcast, we interviewed
Peter Dahlin, a Swedish citizen who was also
working for an NGO in China when he was detained,
forced to confess, and deported.\h
Working in the media also puts you more at
risk.
Two Australian journalists were evacuated
from China last month after Chinese authorities
tried to put exit bans on them.
And that includes working for Chinese state-run
media.
An Australian CGTN anchor was also detained
last month.
Working in media can even include making YouTube
videos.
Even if your videos aren’t political or
negative about China.
As our friends at ADV China found out.
We talked to them on our podcast about their
experience in China and the threats that forced
them to leave.
Being involved in sensitive business deals
can put you at risk.
Like with Australian Stern Hu for the mining
company Rio Tinto, who spent 8 years in prison.
You are definitely more at risk if the Chinese
Communist Party can use you for leverage.
That happened to Americans Victor and Cynthia
Liu, who were banned from leaving China.
Their mother, also an American citizen, was
detained.\h
Why?
Victor and Cynthia’s estranged father is
a fugitive official, a former executive for
a state-owned bank that’s wanted for fraud
charges.
And the Chinese Communist Party thinks that
holding his children hostage will force him
to return.\h
And that brings me to the last thing that
puts you more at risk: being ethnically Chinese.
The sad truth is that the Chinese Communist
Party is more likely to target American citizens
who are ethnically Chinese than those who
are not Chinese.
We’ve seen this happen over and over again.
Chinese authorities treat Chinese people the
way they treat pandas.
No matter where you are in the world, no matter
where you were born, you belong to China.
That extends to Chinese minorities like the
Uyghurs as well.\h
So why is China making these threats now?
I mean, the trade war has been going on a
while; and the US has been targeting Chinese
companies like Huawei for a long time; and
the US military has been challenging China’s
claims in the South China Sea for years.
“But former U.S. national security officials
say the Justice Department’s cases against
the military-affiliated researchers, who were
arrested as they had prepared to leave the
country, represented a major, public embarrassment
for China in a way that other U.S. actions
targeting China haven’t.”
Basically in the past, the US did what China
wanted—by handling these kinds of incidents
behind closed doors.
That’s changed over the past several years.
FBI Director Christopher Wray has now said
the whole of Chinese society is a threat to
the US—and that it requires a whole of American
society response.
The US government is more willing to make
these kinds of cases public now so the American
people learn about it.
Joke’s on them, though.
Because most Americans aren’t interested
in learning about it.
I mean, let’s be honest: Would you rather
go on YouTube to watch China Uncensored—or
to watch a Minecraft Let’s Play video!
Oh my gosh, 11.6 million views?!
Why am I wasting my time making videos about
China?!
Oh right, it’s because of you, my amazing
fans.\h
Speaking of amazing fans, now it’s time
for me to answer a question from one of you
who supports us with a dollar or more per
episode.
William E Williams asks, “Do you think if
the NBA takes a knee - it will be easier for
them to suck on China's money?
Oh - if you can illustrate this on a t-shirt
I'll buy 2!
Oh William, I’d say it’s already working.
The NBA broadcast had been banned after Houston
Rockets General Manager Daryl Morey tweeted
his support of protests in Hong Kong.
“The losses from that one tweet could amount
to as much as $400 million, NBA commissioner
Adam Silver has said.”
China demanded the NBA fire Morey, which would
have looked really bad.
So now, a year later, he decided to quietly
step down.
Totally not because of the whole Hong Kong
thing.
“Daryl Morey cited personal reasons for
this being the ‘right time’ to step down.”
And owner of the Dallas Mavricks, Mark Cuban
has said, despite the genocide, China’s
a customer and is okay doing business with
them.
So I’d say the NBA has worked hard to get
back into the China market at any cost.\h
As for the t-shirt, we are working on getting
a merchandise store back up, so, stay tuned
for that.
Thanks for your question William.
Be like William and support China Uncensored
through the crowdfunding website Patreon.
Thank you for watching.
And did you know, 60% of you who watch China
Uncensored are not subscribed to our channel?
How could you not be subscribed?
This show is so great!
Way better than a Minecraft Let’s Play.
I think.
So please, hit the subscribe button.
It’s a huge help to the show.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.