Here you go.
Where's Matt?
Oh he's coming, with the bags.
What's wrong?
Nothing.
I don't really like Christmas.
What?!
I love Christmas.
Don't you like the presents, the lights, the music…
It's too commercialized.
It's all run by brands and corporations
who only care about making money.
And Christmas means presents.
And presents mean shopping.
I hate shopping.
Don't you at least like the decorations?
No, they're too polished nowadays.
Everything has to be perfect.
What happened to fun, wacky Christmas decorations?
Oh, don't know, but I'm going to go see what Matt is doing.
I'll be right back.
I wish I still believed in Christmas.
Aggggh!
Who are you?!
I'm here to grant your wish!
My wish?
You wished to believe in Christmas again.
So I'm here to show you the true meaning of Christmas!
Are you an angel?
No.
The ghost of Christmas Past?
Uh, she's kind of busy right now.
Then who--WHOA!
Where are we?
We're at the Mall of Asia, one of the biggest
malls in Asia!
The Mall of Asia?
In the Philippines?
I know Christmas is a big deal here,
but shouldn't we be at a church or something?
Well, that’s not really my thing…
Wait, who are you.
I’m the fairy of Christmas...Consumerism.
Christmas Consumerism?
Look, a fairy’s got to survive, ok?
If people stop believing in you, that’s
it!
Wow, I had no idea.
I can still show you the true meaning of Christmas.
Okay...lead the way!
Do you like Christmas carols?
I mean, yeah, sure, I guess.
Why?
Well because the Philippines has the longest Christmas
season in the world.
Four months of Christmas carols!
Wow, they really grab you by the jingle bells
here.
So are you in the Christmas spirit now?
Does it look like I am?
Ok...I've got another idea.
Wait, what?
What happened! Where am I?!
Christmasland in New Taipei City!
Argghh, what did you spray me with?
Uhh, the Christmas Spirit.
Ugh, my head really hurts!
Is my nose bleeding?!
No, no, that's just the joy of Christmas.
Ahh, what’s happening?!
So Christmas was brought to Earth by space
bears?
I don’t remember that part of the Bible.
Well, that kind of looks like a church.
Look traditions change.
The important thing is how Christmas brings
people together.
Let's take a look!
Couldn't you have brought me here when it's
not raining?
Look, I'm not the weather fairy.
Hey, you know, I've noticed a lot of people
on dates.
Oh yeah, that's because Christmas in Taiwan
is all about romance.
That's a weird way to celebrate the landing
of the space bears.
Well, the family togetherness holiday here
is Chinese New Year.
So Christmas is more like Valentine's Day.
Oh, what if you don't have a Valentine?
Er, Christmastine?
Then you go out with your friends.
Well, that's kind of nice, actually.
Sure beats Valentine's.
But seriously, can we get out of the rain?
OK!
Wait!
No!
I’m going to be sick!
Oh no! Do you get seasick?!
No, it’s that stuff you keep hitting me with.
Uh, welcome to Hong Kong!
No!
I am serious.
I am concerned about the long term health
consequences of this.
You'll be fine.
Probably.
Anyway, just look around!
Is that a laser?
It's a symphony of lights!
Huge corporations like HSBC, Bank of China,
Bank of America,
all wishing you a Merry Christmas.
Wow, large multinational corporations care
about me?
Of course!
Without you, who would buy their products?
Huh, I never thought about it like that before...
Come on, there’s one more thing I want to
show you.
Is it just me, or are these snowmen a little
menacing?
No they're totally fine.
The paranoia will wear off in a couple of
hours.
I knew it!
I knew there were side effects!
I didn't say that.
Uh, let's go.
So if Christmas in Taiwan is brought by the
space bears,
Christmas in Hong Kong is about asking for
the blessings of our snowmen overlords?
Not exactly.
Ok so the decorations are kind of weird.
But isn't it wonderful seeing all of these
friends and families taking pictures together?
Yeah, it is kind of nice.
So have you learned the true meaning of Christmas?
You know?
I think I have.
It’s about American cultural hegemony dominating
the world.
Uugggggh, ok, close enough.
Nooo!!!
Chris? Chris, wake up!
Noooooooo!!!
Are you ok?
Do you need to go to the hospital?
It was just a dream.
What happened?
I...had the weirdest dream.
You were there
and you were not there...
You sure you're ok?
Yeah, yeah, I'm fine.
Are we going shopping?
Let's go shopping.
But you hate shopping.
What's that on your hair?
What are you doing?
I'm going to get this analyzed in a lab.
What?
Merry Christmas!
You know, it's true,
wherever you find love, it feels like Christmas.
Wait, have you been watching The Muppet Christmas
Carol again?