On this episode of China Uncensored,
between China and India,
who won the border dispute?
Welcome back to China Uncensored,
I'm Chris Chappell
and I've got some bad news.
I won't be able to make a name for myself
as a reporter covering the war
between China and India.
I had it all planned out, too!
After the war was over,
I'd sell the rights to my story
and see it turned into a Bollywood sensation.
Or a nationalistic Chinese thriller.
Which movie I'd do
would depend on who won the war, obviously.
But unfortunately for my movie
peace has won the day.
On Monday, India's Ministry of External Affairs
posted this notice,
saying both sides have been talking to each
other,
and there would be an
"expeditious disengagement of border
at the face-off site at Doklam."
And now you'll never get to see
my sick dance moves/fighting skills.
Anyway, for those of you somehow new to the
issue,
Indian and Chinese troops have been facing
off
for the past two
It's in an area called the Doklam Plateau,
on the awkward three-way border
between India, China, and Bhutan.
Chinese soldiers were building a road
in their own territory.
Except Bhutan was like,
"Excuse me, that's OUR
not China's."
And so Indian troops came to Bhutan's aid
to help enforce that border.
Not so much out of friendship;
more because a Chinese road
would be a security threat to India.
So the conflict got pretty heated.
Like when Indian and Chinese troops
chest-butted each other like drunk frat boys.
And when Chinese state-run media
was one step short of inciting war.
And who could forget the time Chinese leader
Xi Jinping and Indian Prime Minister Modi
faced off on a dragon and a tiger,
and it looked like Xi was going to win,
until Modi, who, by the power of Grayskull,
was able to overpower Xi Jinping and his dragon,
which it turns out wasn't all that great
because it was made in China.
I just want to say:
India's TV news is way more entertaining
than America's.
Anyway, as that animation
India was the clear winner in the border dispute.
"Big diplomatic victory for the Indian government..."
"India and China have agreed to begin disengagement
of troops at Doklam."
Yeah, hashtag #ModiTamesDragon!
The most popular hashtag since...
Oh.
Hang on a second.
What's that, Shelley?
Ok, this just in from Chinese state-run media:
"China said Monday it had made on-site checks
of India's withdrawal of personnel and equipment
from Donglang, also known as Doklam,
after over two months of military standoff."
Wait a second.
That Chinese host makes it sound like
Indian troops withdrew first.
So...both sides are claiming victory now?
C'mon!
They can't both be winners!
This isn't kindergarten tee-ball.
Maybe it was a mutual withdrawal,
but both sides' media just reported it
in a biased way to play to their audiences.
I've never heard of any media
doing that before,
but I suppose it's possible.
I mean, the wording used
by India's Ministry of External Affairs,
"expeditious disengagement," seems to be intentionally
vague.
As one expert told the Washington Post,
"Clarity is the enemy of face-saving."
So anyway,
India can claim it got China
to back off from construction,
and China can can talk about how
it's a responsible big country.
But I would say overall,
India handled it masterfully
by refusing to give in until China backed
down,
while not being provoked by the rhetoric
from the CCP.
And this is a good lesson
for other countries dealing with
an aggressive Chinese regime.
The Chinese regime was pushing its claims
further than it should have.
China kept claiming it had historical rights
to the area,
as per an agreement from the year 1890
between the UK and China's Qing Dynasty.
Now there's nothing necessarily wrong
with following an old treaty--
except in this case,
it's disputed,
and China knew that Bhutan
didn't recognize China's claim.
And more importantly,
the Chinese regime conveniently "forgot"
that as recently as 1998
they'd agreed to "maintain peace and tranquility
until a final settlement is reached
on the boundary"--
which they didn't follow.
So when the People's Liberation Army
started building a road,
India came to Bhutan's aid
and refused to back down.
Then the CCP brought up the 1890 treaty,
and India brought up the 1998 treaty--
and refused to back down.
Then the CCP directed its state-run media
to threaten war with India.
The idea, according to this article,
was for the CCP to use
"ambiguity, risk manipulation
and controlling the narrative
to win without fighting."
But India still refused to back down.
And that was was a brave and risky move--
considering that if even a single soldier
from either side had accidentally fired a
shot,
it could have instantly triggered
a very serious conflict.
But India understood the political game.
leader Xi Jinping didn't really want a war.
That's because if if the PLA didn't immediately
win a decisive victory,
it would hurt Xi Jinping's reputation
ahead of the 19th Party Congress later this
year.
And also, the Indian Prime Minister
did something smart.
He met with Xi Jinping on the sidelines
of the G20 Summit in July.
They didn't agree on the border dispute,
but they agreed to at least have their people
call their people and talk about it.
So for the last month or so,
they've had backchannel discussions aimed
at resolving the conflict--
even as the media kept blowing the story up.
So how did it get resolved?
Indian troops withdrew from the region
on August 25th,
and Chinese troops announced
they'd stopped building that road,
at least for now--
claiming that "weather was a factor."
It's the international relations version of,
"I would have kicked his butt,
but I didn't want to get his blood all over
my new shirt."
So even though there's no clear winner or
loser,
both sides get to save face.
And in the end,
isn't that the important thing?
Besides avoiding war, I mean.
So is this the end to border disputes
between India and China?
Let's see what India's army chief has to say.
"The recent standoff in the Doklam plateau
by the Chinese side attempting to change
the status quo are issues which we need to
be wary about,
and I think such kind of incidents are likely
to increase in the future."
Wait, such kind of incidents are
"likely to increase in the future"?
That's terrible!
Or is it?
And coming up after the break,
the most dangerous job in China.
And it's not what you think.
Click bait!
Well, you might have to wait for my Bollywood
adventure,
but you don't have to wait for China Uncensored.
Every Friday, we upload full half hour episodes
of China Uncensored for free
to our website ChinaUncensored.tv!
You could have seen this segment
and much more if you had visited ChinaUncensored.tv.
But history doesn't have to repeat itself.
Check out ChinaUncensored.tv now.