there are philosophers and sociologists who even\h
before covet the kobe crisis and the pandemics\h\h
they pointed at the china model as the uh solution\h
for for for the future in terms of policy and\h\h
politics uh the the the solution to the the\h
the the great big question on sustainability of\h\h
modern states and all the problems with democratic\h
society and this and this and that and they kindly\h\h
kind of envision a technocratic model uh based\h
on the chinese regime where they say you know the\h\h
ideology marxist ideology is not per se very\h
strong in china anymore they use the name they use\h\h
the framework but but it's not real communism it's\h
a it's a kind of social democrat uh technocratic\h\h
model in which everyone has been he is being\h
taken care of by the state so they don't need to\h\h
to to worry about anything and they\h
even can get rich when the state\h\h
says you can get rich if you don't put too\h
many question if you do what i want if you\h\h
if you enjoy the liberty i give you it's not the\h
god-given liberty but it's a ccp given liberty so\h\h
there are western philosophers sociologists even\h
politicians who think that this chinese model\h\h
could be the solution to the uh modern\h
democratic problem kobe came into the\h\h
into the scenario and added to that uh in the way\h
you you were saying uh you know look at china uh\h\h
china was so good and so able to resolve quick\h
the the covet problem and this is by the way what\h\h
they say they tell us we don't have um we don't\h
have um any means to verify the the what what the\h\h
regime says but but many many western corners\h
took that at face value and say yes okay yeah\h\h
uh beijing was was was was um very practical\h
they they solved the problem so let's adopt that\h\h
that model and of course as you were uh correctly\h
pointing out uh the big enemy of this techno new\h\h
technocratic chinese uh model again is his\h
religion organized religious uh churches\h\h
movements uh whatever because they do just the\h
opposite first of all they don't obey the to these\h\h
atheistic god ultimately they\h
have another god they had another\h\h
another superior being to to to whom they\h
they looked so they they okay they cope\h\h
with with the load of the state but if the\h
state gives them liberty so there is some\h\h
tension here that becomes a threat in the\h
eyes of these technocratic chinese apologies
and plus big groups churches uh movements\h
of course they are the one who uh\h\h
nurture the virus because we know that you\h
know social distancing in a lot of that and\h\h
repressing uh uh liberty of movements like they\h
did in china is the key to defeat the virus and\h\h
churches and groups and religious groups just do\h
the opposite uh we have seen examples of these\h\h
outside of china when huge large religious groups\h
were accused of being nurturing the virus because\h\h
they had big evidence there is no proof that\h
that is true but it's very suitable to the to the\h\h
ideological language of these people\h
who say you know big governance\h\h
equal to religious groups equal to\h
spreading the the virus it's very useful\h\h
for for people who who see religion as an enemy\h
yeah and again i'm not i'm not trying to sound\h\h
conspiratorial we we there are facts who can\h
document these uh it happened in korea it\h\h
happened at some extent in taiwan and the whole\h
idea even in the west to shut down churches just\h\h
before uh supermarkets goes back to the idea\h
churches groups religious movements are the\h\h
other problems uh as to the kobe so let's get\h
dream read of them first and then we can discuss\h\h
the the kobe problem it it it originates in\h
the ideology of the of the materialistic regime\h\h
like the communist regime in in in china but\h
it it easily goes beyond china been taken\h\h
by some technocratic ideologues and applied to\h
some western society with with some differences\h\h
but you know this is what we are facing now in\h
countries like like mine or or in the west where\h\h
you know the problem is shut down churches before\h
doing anything else because covet is lies in in\h\h
churches this is becoming um a common mentality\h
which is very dangerous dangerous i think uh you\h\h
could even not be a religious person but when\h
you start thinking that religion is the problem\h\h
you mean that the most intimate of the human soul\h
is the problem so you need to to repress that\h\h
in order supposedly a democratic society\h
i don't believe that this is democracy
you