A secret coronavirus experiment
At the Wuhan Institute of Virology
Has been scrubbed from the internet
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
The coronavirus pandemic has been a disaster.
I don’t even think we fully grasp how much
damage it’s caused yet.
But we’ve only just begun to uncover the
crazy story of the Wuhan Institute of Virology,
the biolab some think leaked the virus that
sparked the pandemic.
And now, new information has come out about
a secret experiment that began at the lab,
at the start of 2019, just a few months before
the first reported cases of Covid in China.
Joining us today is Jack Posobiec, senior
editor of Human Events.
Thanks for joining us.
Hey, really excited to finally be on, man.
Yeah.
So Human Events recently covered the story
that the Wuhan Institute of Virology was doing
experiments with transgenic mice.
That is mice that for instance, have been
genetically altered to have human DNA.
Scientists have been doing that since the
'80s, but you discovered something new that
is a little bit disturbing.
What is it?
Right?
Right.
And so this is something where the Wuhan Institute
themselves who have come under so much scrutiny
and the United States side, which has been
partnered with the Wuhan Institute has also
been completely non forthcoming about where.
We know there have been instances in the past
of research and experiments that were going
on, where the study were being conducted of
gain of function experiments.
What we're now seeing that we've uncovered
is that there was a project that had received
approval and funding all the way back in 2018.
We found this on archive document from the
Chinese academic, The Medical Journal of Science,
where they stated that in January of 2019,
a new study was going to begin.
And I want to be very clear about that timeline.
It was supposed to run January of '19 through
December of 2021.
That is the timeline that we're given on this
approval document for the pathogenicity.
So that is essentially how pathogenic, how
transferable, how transmissible, how infectious
are these new bat coronaviruses in transgenic
mice.
These are mice that have been humanized with
human ACE2 receptors in their lungs.
So essentially they have the same type of
ACE2 receptors in their lungs of these mice
that humans have as well.
And whether or not spike proteins from these
bad Corona viruses can infect these mice.
This is the same type of stuff that people
were talking about in the past that could
lead to the risk of an outbreak of a pandemic
because we knew, and they knew that the pathogenicity
of this was very high, the transmissibility
of this was very high and that you were directly
essentially creating, enhancing these viruses
through gain of function experiments so that
they would be infectious to humans because
in the past it wasn't working because they
couldn't find ones that would infect the mice,
they couldn't find ones where the spike proteins
fit.
That's why they humanized the mice in the
first place.
And so the fact that this study was scheduled
to begin January, 2019.
And again, the information on it is very sketchy
because it has been completely scrubbed from
the Wuhan Institute's website, the database
is completely down.
There's no information in terms of where these
people are now, whether that researcher is
still involved.
Though the one thing that we've been able
to find that I was going to kind of looking
at it through another way, I was following
the mice.
I said, I wonder if the mice are still around.
It looks like they were actually also conducting
experiments later on in 2020 of the Wuhan
Corona virus so that SARS COVID-2 virus on
the very same humanized mice that they had
there at the lab.
So the question is that we don't really know
for sure how many of these live animals are
still at the lab or we're at the lab throughout
2020.
But what we do know is that this was scheduled
to run through 2021.
We have no more information about it, we don't
know if it's still going on, we don't know
if it was going on at beginning, but we do
know is that they don't want anyone talking
about it.
It's a very interesting timeline.
So what do you think of the lab leak hypothesis?
Well, so I think the lab leak hypothesis is
likely for a variety of reasons.
Number one, because we now know that they
were conducting these enhancement experiments
at the Wuhan Institute.
And that's just it.
It's not only a lab leak, it is an enhancement
through gain of function of many of these
viruses by parading them through these different
species, whether it be the civets, whether
it be farotts or other mammals or these mice,
these humanized mice.
So they are the ones who are creating these
chimeric viruses.
And we've seen in the past that they have
created chimeric virus strains with the insertion
of these spike proteins and then combine them
with the humanized mice to see what would
happen.
We can see that going as far back as 2015,
we can see it in 2016, 2017, even as far back
as 2007 at this lab.
These risky experiments were going on in the
Wuhan Institute.
People like Dr. Fauci knew, Francis Collins,
the head of NIH knew, Peter Daszak, who was
their cutout at EcoHealth Alliance, knew about
this.
And all of the researchers in the Wuhan Institute,
they should have told us from the very start
what was going on.
And they use as a sort of endorsement and
a justification for this, this line that,
well, if we're conducting these experiments,
the risk outweighs the benefit.
And why does the risk outweigh the benefit?
Because we will have the tools to prevent
the next pandemic from happening.
Well, here's the problem-
What do you mean, the benefit outweighs the
risk?
Right.
Exactly.
Yeah.
The benefit outweighs the risk because we
can prevent the next pandemic.
But that didn't happen.
The next pandemic is what happened and nobody
prevented it.
The tools weren't there, the playbook wasn't
there.
And in fact, it was the Wuhan Institute that
was at the heart of so many.
And now we're learning through the intelligence,
through information that we're getting out,
that these outbreaks are happening and it
wasn't going on in the wet market because
those early data points that we were getting,
yes, some people had been to the wet market,
it was a popular place to buy food, but not
everybody in those early infections had any
tie whatsoever to the wet market.
And that is why that story fell apart and
we later learned that that was a propaganda
narrative spread by the Chinese government.
Why did they spread that propaganda in the
first place?
So it doesn't make sense to me that the CCP
would purposefully release the virus they
can't control.
But it does seem like they took full advantage
of the situation.
What do you think?
That's pretty much where my thinking is on
this as well, is that once this came out,
the CCP, the Politburo there, Xi Jinping,
and the rest, Li Keqiang, they're looking
at the whole situation and saying, you know
what, if we can spin this in such a way where
it is not a China problem, but it becomes
a world problem, then we can position the
CCP, we can position China as not the bad
guy, not villain in the story.
We can position ourselves as the savior.
We can be the ones that save the world from
the virus, regardless of what it does to the
economic structures, the weakening it's going
to conduct to Western Europe and the United
States, the military issues that are going
to happen, not only throughout the west, but
also throughout Asia in terms of this pandemic
and this illness spreading throughout so many
of China's rivals.
They realize that they don't want to be the
ones to have to bear the full cost of this
thing and the full brunt of this thing.
And so they say, we can use this to our advantage
and Xi Jinping when he gave his speech at
the Tiananmen Square Gate, right at the same
place where Chairman Mao stood and so many
other leaders stood, he specifically said
that China did the best to rid the world of
the virus.
And now after 100 years of the CCP, he's saying
that China is leading the world and not any
other country.
Well, the coronavirus pandemic certainly raises
a whole lot of questions, but one of them
that comes to my mind is about what kind of
scientific experiments are being done behind
closed doors in an authoritarian regime that
does not value transparency?
What else do you think could be happening
behind the scenes?
Look, we've also done reporting at Human Events
where not only is this a question that's being
raised on podcasts and publications like our
own, but also from WikiLeaks.
We have a state department cable that was
written by Hillary Clinton in her office when
she was secretary of state, going back to
the founding of the Wuhan Institute of virology
as a BSL, Biosafety Level Four facility in
Wuhan, that was set up in partnership with
the French government.
So it's Hilary going to the French and saying,
what are you doing to make sure that this
is not part of a bioweapons program with the
PLA, the Chinese military?
Because we know that everything that they
have set up in that laboratory is the exact
same types of functions, the exact same types
of capabilities that they would need to produce
bio weapons.
So this is not a question by the way.
And they try to say that, oh, you bring it
up now, you’re tinfoil, that's a crazy thing,
who would ever suggest such a thing, couldn't
possibly be what was going on.
No.
State department, Hillary Clinton, their own
cable says they were worried that this could
be tied to a bioweapons program.
We also know of course that the Wuhan Institute
and the Chinese Academy of Science have ties
to the PLA, they've got multiple military
researchers, military scientists that are
working hand in hand there, they're stationed
there.
We know that a general was sent to the Wuhan
Institute of Virology pretty early on after
China came clean about the fact that there
was a pandemic whatsoever.
So we can see these ties between the military
and the Institute as well.
And so when you're asking about what type
of classified programs could be going in there,
I would simply have to refer you back to Hillary
Clinton.
So obviously the big shocker in all of this
is how much the US may have been involved
in the coronavirus pandemic, origin, research,
whatever you want to call it.
Do you think this pandemic has taught us anything?
Do you think this will change how the US elites
work with China?
So I have an op-ed coming out pretty soon
here at humanevents.com, talking about how
the history of the relationship between the
US and the west and China is written, has
to be taken on through a new lens.
Because when we first started our engagement
with China in the 1970s and through the cold
war, and then started the economic relationship
that really ramped up in the aftermath of
Tiananmen Square, going back to 1992, when
this new trade agreement was signed.
There was this idea that exposure to the west
and exposure to foreign direct investment
would liberalize China and seek to speed up
the rise of political reforms and human rights
in China.
What we've seen though has been the exact
opposite.
The CCP is the 1% of China.
They're the elite of China.
The 1% in the West, they haven't been the
ones teaching to CCP about human rights and
civil liberties.
No, no, no, it's been the other way around.
The CCP has taught our 1% authoritarianism
and the power, the intoxicating power that
you are given when you have total control
over a population, when you can make them
pliable consumers for your goods and for your
products, you could become richer, you become
more powerful, you can attain this God complex
over the people that you rule and then you're
instituting a type of neo-feudalism rather
than becoming this type of opening up and
liberalization the way that we were told in
the past from Deng Xiaoping and the way that
we were told in the West.
Now, this has been a marriage, where the CCP
is influencing the 1% in the west and they
become more authoritarian, they become more
controlling, and that is what they want.
They want total ownership, total control of
society.
That's where it's all coming from.
Well, definitely put a link to that op-ed
in the description below.
Jack, thanks for joining us today.
It was great to hear about this story.
Really appreciate it.
And thanks so much for having me on, I love
all the work that you guys do on China Censored.
Thanks Jack, I appreciate that.
And thank you for watching.
We also interviewed Jack Posobiec this week
on the China Unscripted Podcast.
On the hour long podcast, we covered everything
from the coronavirus to how US elite love
the Chinese Communist Party.
It’s fascinating, be sure to check it out.
Link is below.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, thanks for
watching China Uncensored.