The Chinese regime is using the Coronavirus
Outbreak
as a form of propaganda warfare.
And the backlash is huge.
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
As more information comes out about the deadly
coronavirus,
we are finally getting answers.
There’s been a lot of questions about where
the blame
for the virus’ spread should lay.
Chinese people eating bat soup?
A leak from a Chinese biolab?
A cover up at high levels of the Chinese Communist
Party?
No!
Turns out, America’s to blame!
Chinese social media sites,
“are pushing the idea that the virus
really originated in the United States.
Clips from Taiwanese TV and mistranslated
captions
from American reporting
are used to back up the case.”
Like this one, where the Chinese caption says
that the CDC
confirms the first case of the Coronavirus
originated in the US.
It’s not clear whether that translation
was state backed...
or if it’s just a reading comprehension
issue
by whoever made the Chinese caption.
But the Chinese Communist Party is turning
the coronavirus outbreak into a big propaganda
push.
They published this huge, glossy book called
“A Battle Against Epidemic: China Combatting
in 2020.”
It basically complies all official state media
reporting about the coronavirus.
And guess what the message is?
“The Chinese Communist Party,
despite all evidence to the contrary,
and despite the broad undercurrent of popular
anger
on Chinese social media,
has faced the epidemic with great wisdom
and effectiveness from the start.”
I get it.
We all believe we’re the hero of our own
story.
Even if we’re an authoritarian dictatorship
that routinely kills our own citizens.
To be clear, I’m not using the “royal
we” here.
Anyway, the book
“has gotten rave reviews in Chinese media,
not least because it was published by their
ultimate boss—
the Central Committee Publicity Department,
formerly known as the Propaganda Department.”
The Chinese regime is also taking the propaganda
battle
to American social media banned in China.
Like this poll by state-run Xinhua News.
In China's fight against the coronavirus outbreak,
which part impresses you most?
Gosh, there are so many choices!
It also doesn’t help that the World Health
Organization
is lavishing praise on how the Chinese Communist
Party
has responded to the outbreak.
One W.H.O. official even said this.
“If I had COVID-19, I’d want to be treated
in China.”
Yes, will it be the “box” treatment for
you, sir?
Or the “welded into your home to starve”
treatment?
Or perhaps the more plebeian “thrown into
a hastily built,
overcrowded quarantine center” treatment?
Meanwhile, the popular WeChat messaging app
has been censoring coronavirus content for
months.
And many citizen journalists and whistleblowers
who have spoken out about the coronavirus
have been jailed or simply disappeared.
But Chinese coronavirus propaganda doesn’t
always go as planned.
State run media released this video of female
medical workers
getting their heads shaved.
It was supposed to be a,
“wow, look at how dedicated these women
are!
Shaving their heads so they can fit into their
medical gear better.”
But it came off more as a group of men
humiliating a bunch of women in tears.
Chinese internet users were furious.
One person wrote on WeChat,
“Stop using women’s bodies as propaganda
tools.”
Don’t worry, that person won’t be
posting comments like that for long!
The Chinese Communist Party
is also using coronavirus misinformation
to attack Shen Yun.
Shen Yun is a New York-based performing arts
company.
According to its website,
it’s mission is to revive traditional Chinese
culture
through the arts.
It was also started by Falun Gong practitioners.
So the Chinese Communist Party really hates
Shen Yun.
But since it's based in the US, they can’t
touch it.
So they’ve started spreading rumors that
the dancers
are infected with the coronavirus.
Even though Shen Yun performers
are the least likely Chinese people to be
infected—
because they’re literally banned from traveling
to China.
The Communist Party’s propaganda got so
bad,
that in one city where Shen Yun was performing,
the health department had to step in, and
be like:
Guys, the dancers are not infected.
The Salt Lake County Health Department made
it clear that,
“Shen Yun is based in NYC, not China.”
This kind of propaganda attack isn't just
happening in the US.
In South Korea, where the coronavirus outbreak
really is severe,
a, “theater manager received a phone call
from a TV reporter
who said that the Chinese Consulate
had told the reporter that Shen Yun performers
were from Wuhan,”—
that’s where the outbreak began.
But all of the Commuinst Party’s attempts
to spread propaganda and lies about the coronavirus
are only damaging its reputation.
Abroad and even inside China.
What the Party calls “rumors,”
are now being taken as truths.
“‘Rumor is just a prophecy far ahead of
our times,’
says a quote widely shared online in China
in recent weeks.”
Taiwan is also accusing the Chinese regime
of spreading disinformation, calling it cyber
war.
“This week Taiwan’s government reported
an increase in fake online reports about the
virus on the island,
and blamed China’s “internet army”
for being behind the misinformation.”
I mean, just because there’s an outbreak
of a deadly disease,
doesn’t mean you have to stop being petty.
So what do you think about how the Chinese
regime
has turned the coronavirus outbreak into propaganda
warfare?
Tell me in the comments below.
Take a moment to subscribe to China Uncensored
if you haven’t already.
And even if you have,
because many viewers are telling me YouTube
has been unsubscribing them with no notification.
And as always,
support this show on the crowdfunding website
Patreon.
YouTube demonetizes most of these video
and would have run us out of business,
if it weren’t for the support of what I
call
the China Uncensored 50 cent army—
the fans who support us on Patreon.
As a thank you to them,
I answer their questions at the end of some
of my episodes.
Today’s question comes from William Adderholdt,
“The W.H.O.'s name for the coronavirus "COVID-19"
hasn't caught on.
Any idea why?
And what would be a good replacement name?”
Good question.
Coronavirus is actually the name of a family
of diseases.
For example, SARS is another type of coronavirus.
So in mid-February,
the World Health Organization dubbed this
new coronavirus disease
COVID-19.
This was their reasoning behind the name.
“We had to find a name that did not refer
to a geographical location,
an animal, an individual or group of people
and which is also pronounceable and related
to the disease.
Having a name matters to prevent the use of
other names
that can be inaccurate or stigmatising.”
And obviously the W.H.O. wouldn’t want to
do anything
that would hurt the feelings of the Chinese
Communist Party.
But this was already weeks after they declared
the coronavirus outbreak
a global health emergency and months after
the virus
first began to spread in China.
That was a long time for the public
to only have “coronavirus” as a name.
People got used to it.
And it sounds better than COVID-19.
What would be a better name for a deadly disease
spreading around the world and killing people?
Well, sounds like Communism to me.
But I think calling it that might just be
confusing.
Thanks for your question, William.
And thank you for watching.
If you’d like to hear your question answered
on the show,
join the China Uncensored 50-cent army
by going to patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.