On this episode of China Uncensored,
does the CCP support ethnic cleansing in Myanmar?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I'm your host Chris Chappell.
Myanmar:
The country formerly-and-sometimes-still known
as Burma.
It's one of the 14 countries that share a
border with China.
It's also one of dozens of countries that
share
economic development projects with China.
Myanmar is part of China's One Belt, One Road
Initiative--
which has nothing to do with how high Xi Jinping's
pants are.
The One Belt, One Road Initiative
is actually Xi Jinping's multi-trillion dollar
plan
to build giant infrastructure projects in
countries around the world,
mostly docks, airports, train lines--that
sort of thing.
The countries pay for it using money that
is often
borrowed from Chinese banks,
and then they will either pay it back if the
project is a success,
or be in debt to China forever.
You know, win-win.
Just like my student loans.
The Chinese state-owned conglomerate CITIC
is behind a huge set of infrastructure projects
in Myanmar.
They've recently completed a deep water port
in the Bay of Bengal,
plus oil and gas pipelines connecting that
port with China.
All this development has cost Myanmar
more than 10 billion dollars.
Most of the construction has taken place in
Myanmar's Rakhine State.
Which is the poorest state in Myanmar.
And it's full of ethnic minorities known as
the Rohingyas.
But there've been some problems.
Since August,
more than 480,000 Rohingyas have fled the
region.
Most of them to neighboring Bangladesh.
So why are they fleeing?
Well, it's complicated.
But recently Rohingyas have been facing persecution
from a group of violent religious extremists:
Buddhist monks!
It turns out,
regardless of race, religion, or creed,
all people have the capacity to be huge jerks.
It's what binds us all together.
Myanmar is a predominantly Buddhist country,
and it has seen a rise of extremism following
the end
of 50 years of authoritarian rule by a military
junta in 2011.
And radical Buddhist monks have incited killings
of Myanmar's Muslim minority--the Rohingyas.
Yes, you heard that right.
Sword-wielding Buddhist extremists
are killing impoverished Muslim minorities,
including women and children.
According to the International Crisis Group,
"Myanmar has been troubled by an upsurge
in extreme Buddhist nationalism,
anti-Muslim hate speech
and deadly communal violence."
This tension between Buddhists and Muslims
in Myanmar
goes back decades.
Only 4 percent of the country is Muslim,
and the Rohingyas were heavily persecuted
by the ruling military junta, too,
back when it was in power.
But even after Myanmar's transition to sort
of democracy,
the issues continued.
Two years ago,
President Obama condemned the discrimination
against the Rohingyas,
even as he praised Myanmar's budding democracy.
But there's an ongoing cycle of violence that
leaves no one blameless.
For example, last October,
Islamic extremists killed 9 police.
That led to a military crackdown on the entire
Rakhine state
that ended only in February.
The United Nations said the military
may have committed crimes against humanity
and ethnic cleansing.
Then in August,
a group of Rohingya Muslims again attacked
police,
and the army cracked down on Rohingyas again
in a big way.
And so did the Buddhists.
More than 1,000 Rohingyas have been killed
in recent months,
and as I mentioned,
more than 480,000 have fled to Bangladesh--
which, by the way, doesn't really want them
either,
but they are letting them in.
More than 60 percent of the refugees are children.
And once again, the United Nations
is calling the violence in Myanmar "ethnic
cleansing."
"The situation remains, or seems, a textbook
example of ethnic cleansing."
Which, if you think about it, "ethnic cleansing"
is a pretty weird euphemism.
The US Trump administration has also condemned
the violence against Rohingya Muslims.
"President Trump and I also call on the Security
Council
and the United Nations to take strong and
swift action
to bring this crisis to an end.
And give hope and help to the Rohingya people
in their hour of need."
So just a quick recap,
violent extremist Buddhists and the Myanmar
army
have been attacking Muslims.
And now the Trump administration is defending
the persecuted Muslims.
I'm not sure I know what's going on anymore.
Is there any firm reality I can grab onto?
What's that, Shelley?
Ah good,
the Chinese regime endorses the crackdown.
And they're saying the rest of the world
should just butt out of Myanmar's internal
affairs.
Good old predictable Chinese Communist Party.
You are my rock in this turbulent world.
Once again the Chinese regime is blocking
international efforts
to butt into the affairs of another country,
like it did with the violence in Sudan,
or the nuclear weapons development in North
Korea for years,
or any of a dozen other countries.
And it's a pretty common strategy of the Chinese
regime.
Because while the rest of the world wags its
collective finger,
the Chinese Communist Party is there to be
like,
don't worry,
what you do behind closed doors is your own
business.
And when it comes time to make large-scale
infrastructure deals,
just remember who's got your back in the UN.
As The American Interest puts it,
"Unencumbered by considerations of values,
Beijing can make friends with all kinds of
unsavory regimes
that the United States or the European Union
prefers to scold or sanction."
And China has big political interests in Myanmar.
For one,
China is battling the United States over influence
there.
Following the end of the military junta in
2011,
the US eased up on sanctions
that had been in place for two decades.
Obama became the first US president
to visit Myanmar while in office.
And the first US president to hug Myanmar's
new leader while in office.
That was a bit worrisome to Beijing.
Especially the hugging part.
Xi Jinping only got a handshake.
The last thing the Chinese regime wants
is another US ally right on its border.
The solution?
Drive a wedge between the US and Myanmar.
China has worked to build ties with Myanmar
for economic reasons, too.
Like easy access to the Indian Ocean,
without the trouble of going around the Malaysian
peninsula.
That's not to say the Chinese regime
is unconcerned about violence in Myanmar.
I mean, it might interfere with that oil pipeline.
Now China did back a UN Security Council resolution
"expressing concern" about the violence.
Oh yes, so much concern.
But China then blocked harsher language from
being added to it.
To the West, the CCP acts like it's playing
along,
while assuring Myanmar that it won't really
put the screws on them.
And let's not forget,
if China really were to criticize Myanmar
for its treatment of the Muslim minority,
it would sound a bit hypocritical,
considering the CCP's treatment of its own
Muslim minority,
the Uighurs.
And gosh, the CCP would hate to sound hypocritical
on something.
But the Trump administration doesn't really
want
to be too harsh on the Myanmar government,
either,
and supports the no-sanctions policy started
by Obama.
That's because the US has supported
the democratic developments in Myanmar
under its new leader.
And the US's overriding concern
is to keep Myanmar as a US ally,
and not alienate them--
because that might push them closer to the
Chinese regime.
So to sum up:
In Myanmar,
violent Buddhists extremists are persecuting
Muslims
and forcing them to flee the country.
Trump actually agrees with Obama
that persecuting these Muslims is wrong
and should stop.
But the US government also doesn't want to
push too hard
and alienate Myanmar's government.
And finally, the Chinese regime agrees
that the US shouldn't interfere,
since that would be against China's interests,
and also no country should interfere
with another country's internal affairs.
Unless we're talking about China trying to
interfere
in the internal affairs of New Zealand.
But that's a whole 'nother episode.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I'm your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
If you love learning about persecution - and who doesn't? -
You should check out our website, ChinaUncensored.tv.
We cover so many groups getting persecuted, you'll love it. I know you will
ChinaUncensored.tv.