On this episode of China Uncensored,
Hoooly See!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
The Vatican.
Known for priceless works of art,
top secret archives,
and Jude Law's pet kangaroo.
At least one of those things is not real.
Probably.
Anyway, last week,
the Vatican held a summit on organ trafficking
and transplant tourism.
And the real-life, not young pope has called
these things
a new form of slavery
and a crime against humanity.
So everyone was a little surprised
when the Vatican invited this man to speak,
China’s transplant chief,
Dr. Huang Jiefu.
Why?
Well, it’s kind of like holding a summit
on how to stop people from stealing food,
and inviting the Hamburglar
as your keynote speaker.
Dr. Huang Jiefu has been accused of being
a part of,
and covering up,
the Chinese regime's prolific organ trafficking
and transplant tourism.
Holy See?
More like Holy NOT See.
No, not Nazi!
Not See, like, they're not seeing the obvious!
Uh, moving on.
The Catholic Church approves of organ donation
and transplantation,
a tradition dating back to this guy.
But I’m pretty sure there’s some kind
of prohibition
against a government killing people for their
organs.
I think might be covered by one of the commandments.
I mean, it’s been a long time since I went
to Bible school,
but that makes sense, right?
Except that’s exactly what the Chinese regime
has been doing.
There is a mountain of evidence
that China has a large and complex system
to kill prisoners of conscience and harvest
their organs
for transplant.
A single organ can fetch 6 figures,
so a lot of people in China are profiting
from this.
This report released last year
estimates that between 60,000 and 100,000 organs
are taken from innocent people in China every
year.
Now for years,
the Communist Party was able to hide what
they were doing,
but it's not as easy now as it used to be.
People are wising up.
For instance,
this declaration last year by the European
Parliament
condemned China's organ harvesting.
Then there’s this one from the US House
of Representatives.
A major liver transplant journal,
Liver International,
just retracted a study by Chinese liver surgeons
because it seemed like the donors weren’t
so voluntary.
And mainstream media are actually reporting
on it as well.
Without using words like "allegedly."
Dr. Huang Jiefu,
despite trying to paint himself as a reformer,
has personally been involved in some sketchy
things.
In 2005,
he performed a high profile public demonstration
of a liver transplant.
Just to be on the safe side,
he ordered two extra matching livers as back
ups.
They were never used.
For those of you who aren’t transplant surgeons,
let me explain the problem with that.
As the Guardian puts it,
“Livers are extremely sensitive and need
to be removed quickly,
and are often unsuitable for transplantation
by the time the patient dies.”
So to be able to order two extra livers
means Chinese hospitals must have had a pool
of people
already set aside,
with all their blood work done
so they could match the organs,
and still alive,
so their livers could be harvested.
So where do China’s 60,000 to 100,000 organs
every year come from?
According to the report I mentioned,
they come from Falun Gong adherents,
the Uyghur ethnic group,
Tibetans,
and House Christians.
So the Chinese regime is killing Christians
for their organs,
and then sending their representative to a
conference in the Vatican
on how to stop organ trafficking and transplant
tourism.
For the past few years,
Dr. Huang has been traveling around the world,
trying to convince everyone that China's organ
transplant system
is fine now and made up of voluntary donors.
No one said that prisoners couldn't volunteer,
right?
As you can see in that quote,
there's another sneaky thing Dr. Huang does.
He's trying to make it sound like the Communist
Party
only uses death-row criminals for organs.
When it really is mostly using prisoners of
conscience--
people who the Party is persecuting for their
beliefs.
You can understand why so many people people
were mad.
The Chinese regime wanted to use its presence
at this summit
to show that hey,
our organ transplant system is totally legit
and accepted by the rest of the world.
You might argue maybe the Vatican
made an innocent mistake by inviting Dr. Huang.
They didn’t know.
But when the international outcry went out
about this,
their official response left something to
be desired.
They said the summit was meant to be an
“academic exercise,
and not a reprise of contentious political
assertions.”
Yeah, the Vatican.
They never get involved in politics.
But seriously,
why would the Vatican invite the guy not only
involved in,
but trying to cover up the same crimes against
humanity
the Pope has called out?
The guy who’s also very likely indirectly
involved
in killing Christians inside of China?
Well it could be a coincidence.
But the Vatican is trying to work out a deal
with the Chinese Communist Party
over the appointment of bishops.
Around the world,
the Roman Catholic Church is responsible
for appointing its bishops.
But in the 1950s,
the Chinese Communist Party set up its own
organization
to do that.
It’s called the Chinese Patriotic Catholic
Association.
Because you can believe in God,
after you believe in the Party.
I'm being serious.
The Chinese Patriotic Catholic Association
is under the jurisdiction of the Communist
Party.
So if you want to be Catholic in China,
you have two choices:
One: Belong to the “patriotic” church,
where your highest authority is not Father,
the Son, and the Holy Spirit,
but the officially atheist Communist Party.
Or Two: belong to an underground church,
and risk being arrested or having your organs
harvested.
Neither of these are great options.
And when the Catholic Church has tried
to appoint their own bishops or priests in
China,
they tend to get kidnapped and arrested.
So that's a problem.
But recently the Cardinal of Hong Kong
said that the Holy See and China have reached
“a preliminary consensus...
that will lead to an agreement over the appointment
of bishops [in China].”
So basically the Catholic church is considering
making a deal with the Communist Party.
The agreement is ostensibly over the appointment
of bishops,
but ultimately involves the entire issue
of religious freedom in China, because,
as China’s leader puts it,
religious groups must adhere to the leadership
of the Communist Party.
The same Party that’s harvesting Christians’
organs,
selling them for profit,
and then sending their top doctor to the Vatican
to lie about it.
That Communist Party.
So there’s concern that the Church
might be sacrificing human rights and religious
freedom
in order to establish diplomatic ties
and get more control over bishops in China.
Well, as Cardinal Tong put it,
“The moral principle of the Church teaches
us
to choose the lesser of two evils.”
So what do you think?
I’d especially love to hear from our Catholic
viewers.
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.