On this episode of China Uncensored,
I sat down with the most beautiful woman in
Canada—
and so can you.
If you sit down while watching this.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Brave.
Heroic.
A peerless beauty.
These are just a few of the things people
have said
about me.
Which is why I was so happy to speak with
Anastasia Lin,
someone I consider even braver and heroicker.
Not an equally peerless beauty of course,
since the whole point of being peerless
is you don’t have peers.
You might know Anastasia Lin as the 2015 Miss
World Canada.
She caused an international uproar
when she actually tried to uphold Miss World’s
mission statement:
“Beauty with a Purpose.”
“She’s spoken out about religious persecution
in China
and acted in films that highlight human rights
issues.”
C’mon Anastasia!
“Beauty with a Purpose” is supposed be
a thing you say,
not a thing you do!
But, no, she actually did stuff.
Like testify before US Congress on religious
persecution in China.
So when the finals for last year’s Miss
World were held in China,
obviously Anastasia had to “accept consequences
of [her] political action.”
In other words, the Chinese regime denied
her a visa,
making it impossible for her to compete in
the finals.
Also, they threatened her father, who lives
in China.
Also, they launched a state-run media blitz
to smear her name.
Did it work?
Did it silence this beauty with a purpose?
I took time out of my busy hero schedule last
week to talk with her and find out.
These are the sacrifices I make for you, my
audience—
talking to beauty queens.
So, Anastasia, I really admire you
because my favorite Chinese state-run media
The Global Times
has written several articles about you.
They have not written anything about me yet.
Well, I feel quite honored that they did that.
It is the highest honor, isn't it?
Well anyway, they’ve written about you that
you will
“pay a cost for being tangled with hostile
forces against China.”
Have you paid that cost?
I think what they meant is that I wouldn’t
get into the mainland market.
Who knows? Maybe I'm already on the underground
market.
They just don't know about it.
So tell us about some of the things you’ve
been doing
since this whole Miss World thing went down.
Well, on the Miss World final day,
I went to the National Press Club in Washington,
DC.
They invited me for a luncheon.
That’s sort of a response to the Miss World
Final in China.
They’re kind of a big deal right?
Yeah. There were a lot of cameras there.
I felt quite honored to have the platform
to talk to the world.
And then there’s the Oxford Union debates.
So you really are syncing up with hostile
foreign forces against China.
The first thing you do is you go to Washington,
DC.
Why not go to
North Korea
an ally of China?
North Korea?
I think they’d probably detain me if I go
there.
Well you are a beauty queen.
I mean, who wouldn’t want to detain you?
Oh my goodness.
I wasn’t ready for that joke.
But ok, Washington, DC of course…
You mean CNN doesn’t do things like that?
No, not really. They’re…
Professional?
Um, what was I saying again?
Yes, Washington, DC.
Washington, DC is the capital of the United
States,
the core of the free world.
So I feel, to be able to speak there…
Actually, on the day I was presenting there,
Barrack was hosting a press conference.
You are on a first-name basis with
the president of the United States?
Well, we’re competitors
because he was hosting a press conference
across the street from me.
It’s kind of hard to compete for attention
with
the president of the US, but
I think I held up well.
And then I went to testify in the UK Parliament,
and I went to meet the Dalai Lama last week.
The Dalai Lama?
So clearly, you have been totally shunned
by
the rest of the world for speaking out against
China.
At times. When my dress sponsor pulled out
from sponsoring me
because he had family members who are still
in China,
I did feel a little bit like the carpet under
me was pulled away, but
I did receive tremendous support from
all over the world.
Well about that, I know you have family in
China.
I’m wondering how they’re doing?
But also, like, the difference between…
Your family was threatened,
but you still did what you thought was right.
How do you feel about your dress sponsor,
as an example,
having their family be used against them in
that way?
I feel quite terrible for that guy,
because it must be very scary to suddenly
get
an email from the Chinese Consulate.
No one wants to put their family at risk.
I’m the same.
But at the beginning I felt that if I don’t
use the chance to speak up,
I may not ever get the chance again.
And if they know that this will work on me,
then they might keep doing things like that
to me,
to my family.
It’s just, I felt like that was the only
solution:
speaking up.
It seems like speaking up really did cause
quite
an uproar in the world.
Since that, has everything been ok with your
father in China?
Or has there been more pressure?
I know that his business partner backed out
from a deal,
and that’s probably just one partner that
he’s told me about.
In China, since the state media was not very
friendly with me…
What are you talking about?
The Global Times wrote several articles all
about you.
Yeah, um
questioning why I was “entangled with anti-China
forces.”
Yeah, my father did receive tremendous pressure,
and nowadays he doesn’t even tell me about
it,
because he knows that his phone is being listened
to.
If he says something,
it might not be good for his family.
He has a very young family in China.
I have a half brother who’s eight this year.
That’s very, very serious heavy stuff.
I’m curious:
So you’ve been such a heartfelt and dedicated
person
promoting human rights in China,
and you know, when I see that kind of passion,
I can’t help but be suspicious.
What’s really behind what you’re up to?
Or do you have any dark secrets from your
past?
Like what kind?
Well, I mean I heard…
Now you’re talking, you’re speaking up
against the Communist Party in China,
but I remember hearing that you used to be
a student council leader.
A Young Pioneer?
A Young Pioneer.
Yeah, I did that for a few years.
It was an intriguing experience,
because at the time I really didn’t know
what I was doing.
I mean, I felt like I did,
and it felt pretty awesome at the time,
because you’re the elite group.
But then only after I went to Canada did I
realize that
all I was doing was kind of brainwashing other
students.
And there’s nothing glorious about it.
I think that kind of partly motivated me to
try to let the rest of the Chinese people
know
what they’re going through.
So now you’re trying to brainwash people
with the truth?
I hope that I’m just presenting another
side of facts,
information that I wasn’t able to get
to make it available to them
and they can make their own choice.
And do you feel that message has gotten into
China,
with all the state-run media?
I think it has.
Actually, there are a lot of Chinese people
who climb over
the Great Firewall to see information outside.
And I remember last time when I went to Taiwan
for a conference about religious freedom,
I met a Chinese tourist group in the airport,
and they all wanted to take pictures with
me.
And I felt quite surprised that they were
able to read about it.
And they told me that although the national
media
would write one side of the story,
they can pretty much get what it was about.
This girl must have said something that the
commies didn’t like.
Wow, I’m very encouraged to see that
angering the Chinese Communist Party can
give someone so many opportunities.
I hope you’ll give me a few tips after
the interview.
I’m sure you have gotten a lot of
opportunities because of it.
Oh,
yes.
People love me, it’s true, it’s true.
I’m thinking I could do pretty well in a
beauty pageant myself.
Yeah.
Yeah. Thank you, thank you.
Thanks for that support.
I’ll use that in my pamphlets that I…
[when] Miss World Canada promotes me as a
beauty pageant [contestant].
So I understand you’re an actress,
and that you have a new film coming out later
this year.
Yeah, it’s called The Bleeding Edge.
Well, we have a clip of that, so why don’t
we play that.
Well, that certainly looked exciting.
It gave me all kinds of feels.
Why do you think this is an important movie,
an important topic?
Well, it talks about one of the most sensitive
topics
in regards to the Chinese Communist Party
now:
It's the organ harvesting of prisoners of
conscience.
After talking to victims, I realized that
this is something that
you know, perhaps I will have to work up my
courage to do.
Well it sounds like it’s a good thing you
did,
because as I understand, you were nominated
for the
Best Actress Award in the upcoming Leo Awards.
That’s one of Canada’s biggest screen
awards, correct?
Yes, I feel quite honored.
So, actress, beauty pageant, what is next
for you?
Well I have two documentaries coming out about my experience in Hong Kong.
It does address the bigger issue of
suppression of freedom of conscience in China,
which is something I think urgently needs
to be addressed.
And I’m going to continue to act in more
films.
Great. And…
And I’m running for Miss World this year.
Ah, so, what is this going to be?
So because of last year’s visa denial,
Miss World offered me the spot for Canada
in the 2016 Miss World.
And they have confirmed it recently.
So Miss World, the larger organization, not
just Miss World Canada?
Yes.
They had offered it to me last year.
I didn’t know if I was going to take it
at that time,
but I think since I continued on this platform,
I initiated it,
I should continue.
And it’s a great platform.
It’s called “Beauty with a Purpose,”
right?
So Miss World Canada confirmed my spot.
It’s a great sacrifice for them.
So they just gave you the Miss World Canada
position,
almost like you’ve been elected
Beauty Queen for Life.
I wish. Well, I…
I mean, I just,
you talk about democracy, and yet
you’re a queen, a beauty queen.
Some media called me the “badass beauty
queen.”
I feel quite honored to be crowned that.
I’m not comfortable with that kind of language
on this show.
This is a family show.
Oh, I’m sorry.
They were quite strong, but I think it’s
an accurate description.
Wow, I hope somebody writes that about me
someday soon.
Just say you agree.
We can Photoshop that in, I’m sure.
So, how do you think this coming year
will be different from the previous year?
We don’t know where it’s going to be held
yet.
Ah.
Yes. I hope it’s going to be in a country
where
freedom of speech is encouraged.
Oh, so China, right?
I mean, it’s in the constitution, they have freedom of speech.
Well, anyway, I hope it’s not going to be
in China,
but anything can happen.
In history, there were three times—
the final three years in a row that it was
held in China before.
So it could happen this year.
I hope not. I don’t want to be denied twice.
I’m actually a little surprised.
I would have thought they would’ve wanted to sweep this thing under the table
since it caused such an uproar for the pageant,
but…
Well, I think it’s great for them to offer
this opportunity,
and I hope this year they will make the right
choice,
since they know that repressive regimes
fundamentally don’t agree with us, in our
values.
So I don’t think they’re going to choose
China again.
We’ll see.
Well, I guess you are the representation of
“Beauty with a Purpose.”
Thank you.
Well thank you for joining us, Anastasia.
The film is called The Bleeding Edge.
It’s coming out later this year.
If you want to be notified when you can watch
it,
go to www.TheBleedingEdgeMovie.com
and Subscribe,
then enter your email address.
So, what do you think I can do to be
more like Anastasia Lin?
Leave your comments below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.