On this episode of China Uncensored,
Would China fight for North Korea in a war?
I hope we’ll never find out.
In China, coffee-lovers actually like Starbucks.
What?!
And finally, it’s getting cold in here.
So put on all your clothes.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
If the US goes to war with North Korea,
which nation would China back?
Well, it’s not so clear.
The United States and South Korea
held annual air force drills
over the Korean Peninsula this week.
More than 200 planes were involved.
North Korea did not take that so well.
State media accused the US of
“reckless nuclear war mania.”
Right, the US.
Not the country whose leader
poses in front of nuclear warheads.
And meanwhile,
China’s People’s Liberation Army
held its own air force drills
in new areas near the Korean Peninsula.
And according to a Beijing-based military
expert, Li Jie,
the PLA’s goal was to send a message to
the United States.
“The timing of this high-profile announcement
by the PLA
is also a warning to Washington and Seoul
not to provoke Pyongyang any further.”
So does this mean that China is warning the
US
that in the event of war with North Korea,
China will back North Korea?
Ok, they’re probably just posturing.
Let’s hope we never find out for sure.
But in the event of nuclear war,
the Chinese regime wants people in Northern
China
to be prepared.
In a Chinese province bordering North Korea,
state-run media ran a helpful cartoon
educating people on what to expect,
when you’re expecting...a nuclear holocaust.
For no reason in particular, really.
Just general knowledge that everyone should
know.
See, it’s called “General Knowledge
about Nuclear Weapons and Protection.”
For instance,
did you know that in the event of a nuclear
attack,
you should close your doors and windows
and hide under a table?
Be sure to scrub yourself thoroughly
to wash off that radiation!
And don’t forget to clean your ears.
You never want to forget to clean your ears.
It reminds me of the good old days of duck
and cover in the US.
Though you may laugh at some of the suggestions,
this is the first time ever the Chinese regime
has ever acknowledged that people in China
might actually be affected by nuclear conflict
on the Korean Peninsula.
Moving on to another region prone to conflict,
the Chinese regime has responded to US President
Trump
acknowledging Jerusalem as the capital of
Israel.
“We are concerned that the move
could sharpen regional conflicts.
The status of Jerusalem
is complicated and sensitive.”
Jerusalem is a bit of a thorny issue.
But China has made no secret of its ambitions
to be the one to solve the Israel-Palestine
issue.
Or at least to continue to play
both sides against the other
so it can do more business with Israel
while still supporting its old comrade in
arms,
the Palestinian Authority.
But depending on your point of view,
President Trump has just taken
one giant step to solving it,
or making it unsolvable.
Either way,
that’s the US showing it’s the global
power—
not China.
Speaking of things boiling over,
Starbucks has opened its first international
coffee roaster
and largest store in the world,
right here in Shanghai.
It’s 30,000 square feet big!
You know I never realized how creepy
the original Starbucks logo is.
Even Jack Ma showed up for the grand opening!
"I don’t like coffee,
but I like Starbucks."
Wow, Jack Ma and I have
the exact opposite opinion.
I have to say,
if ever there were a reason not to be jealous
of China’s rise,
it would be having the world’s biggest Starbucks.
In fact, I’d rather drink shredded jellyfish.
Which is actually the latest project
of China’s People’s Liberation Army.
The waters off China’s coast
are home to a lot of jellyfish.
Thanks to massive pollution.
And that’s a problem for the PLA Navy.
The jellyfish, not the pollution.
Swarms of jellyfish get sucked into ships
engines
and can bring them to a halt.
So PLA has developed a high tech new weapon
in the war against Poseidon,
called the jellyfish shredder.
It’s basically a big net with a bunch of
knives.
The only problem is...
it kind of shreds anything else that might
be in the water.
I think I know where China ripped off this
idea from...
I call it the Burns Omni Net!
It sweeps the seafloor clean.
It’s wintertime in China,
so stay warm.
Unless you need to burn coal to stay warm,
in which case,
see you in the detention center.
No, I mean literally.
This propaganda slogan
has been popping up around China.
It says “If you burn coal,
see you in the detention center.”
Chinese authorities are clamping down
on coal burning,
hoping it will stop the annual airpocalypse
that plagues the country.
What that means, though,
is that millions of people
will have to face sub-zero temperatures
with nothing more than a coat.
Now that is cold.
Students are being forced to hold classes
outside in the winter sun
because the schools are too cold inside.
Local authorities were supposed to transition
everyone in the rural areas
over to natural gas before
the deadly cold winter hit.
But there were setbacks laying pipes,
and the sudden demand for natural gas
created huge shortages.
So it would sure be a shame if I don’t know,
a large number of people were suddenly forced
out onto the streets.
And we’ll have more on that after the break.
We may not have coal,
but we’re leaving a light on for you
over at ChinaUncensored.tv.
It’s our website,
where every Friday you can watch full half
hour episodes
you can’t see anywhere else.
It’s a laugh riot.
So bring the tear gas.