The Second Trump-Kim Summit
Ended with no deal!
And that could be bad news...
for China.
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Subscribe to our YouTube channel for the latest
China news,
and click the notification bell
so you get an alert each time
we publish a new, amazing episode.
So, it’s the most anticipated blockbuster
sequel of the year!
No.
I’m talking about The Trump-Kim Summit Part
Two.
Perfectly balanced.
And like any good sequel,
it’s been left wide open for a part three.
Because Trump left the summit early,
with no deal on North Korean denuclearization.
Now is that a bad thing?
Did Mr. Art of the Deal fail?
Well it turns out
there were much bigger things on the line.
And President Trump quite likely had
another target in mind as well.
“CHINA!”
First, let’s talk about what actually happened
at the summit.
Then we’ll get to how China factors in.
Why wasn’t there a deal?
Trump said it was because North Korea
wanted all the sanctions lifted.
“Basically they wanted the sanctions lifted
in their entirety,
and we couldn't do that.
They were willing to denuke a large portion
of the areas that we wanted,
but we couldn't give up all of the sanctions
for that,
so we'll continue to work and we'll see.
But we had to walk away from that particular
suggestion.
We had to walk away from that.”
So basically, President Trump felt
he couldn’t get a good deal and walked away.
That’s important and I’ll get back to
that point in a moment.
But after Trump’s remarks,
North Korean officials said that they only
asked
for a partial relief of the sanctions.
Yes, partial relief...
of all of the sanctions.
Now North Korean officials could be telling
the truth,
or they could just be trying to save face.
You know, “She didn’t break up with me,
I broke up with HER!”
But you might be wondering,
is Kim Jong-Un even willing to denuclearize?
According to Kim, yes.
“Chairman Kim, are you ready to denuclearize?”
“If I'm not willing to do that, I won't
be here right now.”
“That's a good answer.
That might be the best answer you've ever
heard.”
Yeah, and how could you not trust a face like
this.
Trump, at least, says he does trust Kim.
“And one of the things importantly
that chairman Kim promised me last night
is regardless he's not going to do testing
of rockets and nuclear—
not going to do testing.
So, you know, I trust him,
and I take him at his word.
I hope that's true.”
But even if Kim agrees to stop testing nuclear
weapons,
there are fundamental disagreements
between the US and North Korea
on what “denuclearization” means.
North Korea would prefer it to mean
that they stop nuclear testing
and destroy *some* nuclear facilities,
but they get to keep all of their existing
nuclear weapons.
Sort of like a partial denuclearization.
Now, since Kim Jong-un came to power in 2011,
he conducted at least 4 nuclear tests and
86 missile tests overall.
And those tests were setting the world on
edge.
But after Trump took office,
he started a yelling match with Kim.
And everyone was pretty sure this was going
to cause nuclear war.
But it turned out to be a war...of words.
Ahead of Trump’s first meeting with Kim
last summer,
“North Korea blew up tunnels at a nuclear
test site
and destroyed missile-testing facilities.
After the summit, Kim stopped all missile
and nuclear tests,
honored the promise to return the remains
of U.S. troops,
and demolished frontline guard posts near
South Korea.”
So what happened?
What changed?
It wasn’t just Trump’s tough talk.
His administration put super serious economic
sanctions on North Korea,
and made China enforce them too.
These are the sanctions Kim now wants removed,
but Trump said, “Nah.”—
and walked away from this week’s summit
without a deal.
And this is where China comes in.
China is North Korea’s biggest ally.
And for a long time, China was the middleman—
so if the US or anyone else
wanted some kind of dialogue with North Korea,
they needed China.
For example, the Six-Party Talks from 2003
to 2013.
It was a series of meetings
aimed at getting North Korea to denuclearize.
China insisted on hosting the talks in Beijing.
And I can’t say the Chinese Communist Party
was the best middle man,
since the Six-Party Talks completely failed
to stop North Korea from building nukes.
But then Trump tried a different approach.
He forced the Chinese regime to enforce stiff
sanctions on North Korea.
How?
From early in Trump’s campaign,
he began threatening a trade war with China.
This headline is from 2016.
But he also indicated that he might be willing
to not start a trade war,
if China helped the US with North Korea.
It’s kind of like Trump was playing good
cop, bad cop...by himself.
So, he’s...both the good cop and the bad
cop.
Which confused the heck out of Chinese officials.
So Chinese leader Xi Jinping
went out of his way to treat Trump real nice.
He invited Trump to be the first American
leader
to dine in the Forbidden City.
And he treated Trump to a Peking Opera.
Trump was probably very happy...when that
was over.
But most importantly,
Xi Jinping agreed to Trump’s demand
that China put harsh sanctions on North Korea.
“In 2017, China’s strict implementation
of sanctions
has pushed North Korea back to the negotiation
table.”
And since Xi Jinping was so nice to Trump,
*surely* Trump would abandon his plans for
a trade war!
Fast forward to the first Trump-Kim summit
last June.
Trump gets Kim to back down,
solving the most immediate North Korean threat.
And since now there’s direct US-North Korea
dialogue,
it also cuts China out from being the middleman.
And then a few weeks later,
Trump launches trade tariffs on China.
Which, once again,
confused the heck out of Chinese officials.
What happened to good cop?
So, Trump used *threats* of a trade war
to get China to help bring North Korea to
the table.
And then once Trump no longer needed China’s
help with that,
he was free to launch the trade war that he’d
been threatening.
But that made Xi Jinping angry.
He really wears his emotions on his sleeve.
Anyway, Xi began meeting with Kim Jong-un
himself.
Kim has visited China four times since then.
He had never visited China before.
And when Kim traveled to the first US summit
in Singapore,
he had accepted Xi’s hospitality by flying
there
“on an Air China plane previously used by
Chinese senior leaders”.
And for *this* US summit,
Kim took his personal armored train through
China.
There’s two reasons for that.
One, according to a North Korean expert,
it’s because it makes Kim look slightly
less dependent on China.
But the other reason?
The Chinese regime allowed it
because it would take Kim on a ride near some
of China’s biggest cities,
to see the economic possibilities of sticking
with China.
You see, what Kim really wants is to make
North Korea the new China.
Yes, he wants North Korea to go from an isolated
hermit state
that persecutes its own people
and is shunned by the rest of the world,
to a prosperous modern state
that persecutes its own people
and is *celebrated* by the rest of the world.
Just like China.
Which could explain why Trump is also trying
to tempt North Korea with economic development.
“...we are all going to have a fantastic
success
with respect to Chairman Kim and North Korea.
They are going to have an economic powerhouse.
I have been writing about it,
I have been talking about it,
I think it is going to be an economic powerhouse,
and something I very much look forward to
helping with.”
But here’s where things get interesting.
The sanctions have crippled North Korea.
Kim clearly wants those removed.
But Trump isn’t going to give that to him—
unless Kim makes bigger concessions on denuclearization.
So, according to the New York Times,
“Kim wants Beijing to urge the United Nations
to ease sanctions against North Korea.”
But it’s not very likely Beijing will help
with that.
Why?
Because now, the US is in the middle
of another a tough trade negotiation with
China.
This time, instead of threatening a trade
war,
there’s already a trade war.
And just before the Kim summit,
Trump extended the deadline to work out a
deal—
which actually leaves China not knowing what’s
going to happen.
Which yet again,
confuses the heck out of Chinese officials.
As one analyst put it,
“I don’t think China wants to cross Trump
at this point—
the price is too high considering the trade
deal.”
So this means China won’t fight the US
on North Korea sanctions right now.
The only option for the leaders of both countries
is to make a deal with the US.
And remember, Trump just walked away
from the North Korea summit
when he didn’t like what he was offered.
So China knows he’d be willing to walk away
from US-China trade talks too.
Sometimes bad cop gets things done.
So what do you think of the second Trump Kim
Summit?
Let me know in the comments below.
And before you go,
now is the time when I answer a question
from a member of my loyal 50-Cent Army—
fans who support the show through the crowd
funding website Patreon.
David Schwimmer asks,
“[Was] Putin... bribed to undermine the
west and democracy at China's behest?
Good question, David.
China and Russia do sometimes work together.
They even hold joint military drills.
And who could forget the time
that Xi Jinping gave Vladimir Putin
that fancy gold best friends forever necklace?
They look so...almost happy.
But as far as I know,
there’s no evidence that Russia
is undermining the west specifically at China’s
request.
Don’t get me wrong:
Russia *is* undermining the west.
Like when they tried to interfere
in the 2016 presidential elections.
But Russia has its own reasons.
It doesn’t need to be told what to do by
China.
For instance, Russia is facing a slow economic
and political decline.
And what better way to make yourself feel
better
than by making sure everyone else suffers
as well!
That, plus being seen with your shirt off.
Plus, as one Russian journalist told the Atlantic,
“The Kremlin was ‘very upset about the
Panama Papers,’
which cast light on Putin’s wealth.”
And of course the Chinese Communist Party—separately—
is doing plenty of its own things to undermine
the West.
We’ve done like 500 episodes on that,
so you can just binge-watch China Uncensored
to learn more.
Thanks for your question, David.
Do you have a question you’d like answered
on the show?
Then sign up to support China Uncensored
on the crowd funding website Patreon
and contribute a dollar or more per episode.
We rely on your support to keep China Uncensored
going.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next
time!