On this episode of China Uncensored,
A Hong Kong student leader-
slash-dangerous criminal has been sentenced
to prison.
Plus, war may be brewing on three fronts.
Good thing China’s a nation of peace.
And finally, have you ever felt like
you were being watched?
You are.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
I’m afraid I have some bad news.
In Hong Kong, democracy activist,
friend of the show,
and apparent criminal mastermind Joshua Wong
was sentenced to 6 months in prison
for “unlawful assembly”
during the 2014 Umbrella Movement protests.
Fellow activists Nathan Law and Alex Chow
were sentenced to similar prison terms.
If this feels like déjà vu,
it’s because last November,
all three activists were already sentenced
for the same thing...
but they were given hours of community service
instead of prison time.
But apparently that wasn’t enough for
the Hong Kong government,
which is increasingly controlled
by mainland China—
the very thing the three of them
were protesting against.
They prosecutors filed an appeal
of the original sentences,
and earlier this week
a judge decided that, yes,
the punishment ought to be harsher
to deter other young people
from possibly unlawfully assembling
in the future.
According to the judge,
“the defendants’ banners of peace and
rationality
were empty words.”
And the court needed to
“impose sentences with an even greater deterrent
effect
in order to defend the dignity of the rule
of law.”
And nothing says
“the dignity of the rule of law”
like giving harsh sentences
to political activists.
But was it really a political decision, you
ask?
Well since they were sentenced to prison,
the activists can’t run for office
for the next 5 years.
Nathan Law had already been elected last year
to Hong Kong’s legislature...
until he was kicked out last month
for quoting Gandhi during his oath of office.
So yeah,
probably not political at all.
Now on to North Korea.
Earlier this week,
China implemented UN sanctions
against the rogue regime.
But in case you thought things
were getting too cooperative
on the North Korea issue,
Chinese state-run media the Global Times,
wrote last week,
“that if North Korea launches missiles
hat threaten US soil first
and the US retaliates,
China will stay neutral.”
In other words,
you’re on your own, America.
On the plus side,
it won’t be a repeat of the Korean War.
After all, China has bigger fish to fry.
Particularly fish from the South China Sea.
Another US Navy patrol conducted
a freedom of navigation operation
in the South China Sea on August 10th.
They cruised past Mischief Reef,
where China is building an artificial island
with military installations.
It prompted state-run media
to ask whether the US is making trouble
or keeping peace.
Obviously, making trouble.
If the United States wanted peace,
they’d just let the Chinese army
keep building military bases there...
in peace.
But one country that apparently does want
peace with China is Vietnam.
This week we learned Vietnam
pulled its oil drilling ship out of disputed
waters.
And China wants peace with the Philippines.
At least, according to the Philippines’
defense minister,
who said that Chinese officials
had promised not to claim
more territory in the South China Sea,
or build anything on the Scarborough Shoal.
They’d better not,
since I claimed that as China Uncensored’s
sacred territory
9 months ago.
And over to India.
You know the saying sticks and stones
may break my bones,
but words will never hurt me?
Chinese and Indian troops
must have been listening.
They threw stones at each other.
That was not the best idea
because in another disputed border territory,
China and India have already
been in conflict for weeks.
Chinese media have been particularly aggressive
in their response.
So this latest bout
of elementary school-style rock throwing
could lead to something more serious.
And finally,
big brother is watching.
So could you please be a little more entertaining?
In China,
everyone is being filmed all the time.
Cameras are everywhere.
They even have special police buses for it.
C’mon, people!
What ever happened to subtlety?
But what’s even weirder
is that in China,
your average citizen can get in on
the surveillance fun.
“China’s 751 million internet users
can binge on real-time video streams of
yoga studios, swimming lessons,
alpaca ranches and thousands of other scenes
captured by surveillance cameras.”
Some of those other scenes
include people shopping for lingerie.
That article even mentions
a popular feed of a slim
attractive receptionist in Beijing,
who, according to comments,
is a chronic nose picker.
There is so much constant surveillance footage,
one Chinese film director
complied 7,000 hours of it
to make a full length movie.
It includes footage
of people actually dying.
It’s ironic.
In a society where so much is censored,
a person’s private moments
can be seen by all.
It’s the real life version
of the Truman Show.
So if you’d like to see more,
stay tuned tuned after the break.
You might be freaked out
if someone was watching you,
but I love it.
And you could see more of me
if you go to ChinaUncensored.tv.
We have full length half hour episodes
available every Friday for free.
Check it out at ChinaUncensored.tv.