On this episode of China Uncensored,
it seems the Chinese military is building
missile silos
in the South China Sea -
for peaceful purposes…
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
The Chinese regime is just putting the finishing
touches
on some of its artificial islands in the South
China Sea,
in an attempt to break the Guinness World
Record
for the largest ever live-action game of Minecraft.
Watch out for the Creepers.
Maybe that's why they’re allegedly also
building
missile silos on those islands.
Two US officials exclusively tell Reuters
Beijing is almost finished building two dozen
structures
on their artificial islands.
And they’re built to house weapons,
likely long range surface-to-air missiles.
Yes, it appears China is building real missile
silos
on fake islands in disputed territorial waters
in the South China Sea.
But how do we know these are missile silos?
Well, according to Reuters’ sources,
they have “retractable roofs,”
and they “resemble others that house SAM
batteries.”
Well, hey, come on.
That’s not exactly a smoking...missile.
I mean, the retractable roofs could just be for,
I don’t know,
elaborate vampire killing devices?
Or indoor-outdoor swimming pools.
Or very small football stadiums.
What was China’s response?
Well, they admit it,
but with Chinese characteristics.
I want to repeat here
that China carrying out normal construction activities
on its own territory,
including deploying necessary and appropriate
territorial defense facilities,
is a normal right under international law
for sovereign nations.
So yeah, China is arming the islands they built.
Demonstrating, once again,
China "highly values" peace and stability
in the South China Sea.
Now this is causing huge waves internationally.
Even more so
than when they finished building that lighthouse.
Hey, that was kind of scary.
Fortunately, a US intelligence official told
Reuters
that these silos aren’t actually a significant
military threat.
They’re highly visible and vulnerable.
Just like me.
But why are they building these silos?
Well according to the anonymous officials:
They say instead it appears to be a
political test of the waters
to see how far Trump will go.
That’s it!
China began planning and building these missile silos
to test Donald Trump…
a year ago,
before he’d even won the presidential primary.
Proving that the Chinese military
has already invented time travel.
Or was that a Netflix show?
But there could be another reason.
By building these missile silos,
the Chinese regime can establish
an Aircraft Defense Identification Zone.
Basically, they could claim rights
to control all aircraft movement
within a certain area of the South China Sea.
And that could hinder the normal movement
of aircraft
from a number of countries.
Will the Trump administration push back,
now that this has landed in its lap?
Well, over the past several years,
the US government hasn’t been very effective
at actually stopping the Chinese regime
from militarizing those disputed islands.
Sure, the US Navy has sent in ships
to conduct freedom of navigation operations.
But those didn’t stop the construction.
As Rex Tillerson put it
during his senate confirmation hearing,
China’s activity in this area
is extremely worrisome.
And I think again the failure of a response
has allowed them just to keep pushing the
envelope on this.”
So perhaps the Trump administration
wants to push back.
But how could they do it effectively—
and without starting a war?
Perhaps they’ll attempt to use what General
Douglas MacArthur
called America’s “unsinkable aircraft carrier.”
No, not the floating plastic thing
from my favorite childhood board game.
I’m talking about Taiwan.
In December,
when Donald Trump took a phone call
from Taiwan’s president,
he proved he was open to use Taiwan
as a negotiating tool with the Chinese Communist
Party.
Trump could use weapons deals
and diplomatic relationships with Taiwan
as leverage to pressure the CCP
to chill out on its militarization
of those piles of sand.
But hopefully, whatever happens,
it can be executed in a skillful way.
Because World War III doesn’t sound fun.
Especially when China is developing
giant spider tanks,
and, of course,
missile silos in the middle of the ocean.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And to commemorate the completion of the missile silos,
I’m adding yet another new level of support
to our Patreon page!
Help us raise the funds to build our own…
bomb shelter.
And one lucky patron will get to spend the
apocalypse
with me and Shelley.
What’s that, Matt?
Oh, sorry,
there’s no more room.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.