On this episode of China Uncensored,
what happens when a Chinese jet and a US spy
plane stop being polite,
and start getting real.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I'm your
host Chris Chappell.
You know, many of the truths we cling to
depend greatly on our own point of view.
And nowhere is that more evident than in the
South China Sea.
“At least two Chinese J-11 tactical aircraft
—those are fighter jets—
they carried out what's called an unsafe intercept
of a US reconnaissance plane over the South China Sea.”
That's according to a US Pentagon Official.
But according to Chinese Foreign Ministry
spokesman Hong Lei,
the US statement was, "Not true."
Well how can that be? Is one side lying?
Haha, lying is such a strong term.
You see, the US spy plane was flying in international
airspace.
Unless you consider China’s point of view,
which is that pretty much the entire South
China Sea belongs to China.
In which case it’s like Hong Lei says:
“It must be pointed out that U.S. military
planes frequently carry out reconnaissance
in Chinese coastal waters,
seriously endangering Chinese maritime and
air security.”
You see it was the US acting dangerously in
Chinese airspace.
“At one point these jets, according to this
official, came within 50 feet of the American aircraft."
Whoa! 50 feet?!
Do you realize how dangerous that is?!
It's like that jerk in the Porche who
tailgates you on the highway.
But at airplane speeds.
But you can’t say the Chinese jets flew
within 50 feet of the American plane,
without also accurately saying the US plane
flew within 50 feet of the Chinese ones.
Here's China Uncensored’s Force Ghost for
more!
So what I told you was true, from a certain
point of view.
This is not a first either.
Pretty much the same thing happened back in
September 2015.
Though that unsafe interception was 500 feet.
Which, while being dangerously unsafe,
is still ten times less unsafe than 50 feet.
There was also that spy plane incident in
which shows you just how risky flying close
can be.
Because that time, unfortunately, the Chinese
jet actually collided with the US spy plane,
and the Chinese pilot was killed.
And the US plane was forced to make an emergency
landing in Hainan.
Whose fault was that?
Well, China forced the US to apologize before
they’d release the 24 American air crew members.
That took 11 days.
Don't think that’s how it should have gone?
Well, I guess it’s a matter of your point
of view.
And the point of view of my favorite Chinese
state-run media, the Global Times,
is that if the US keeps sending in more planes,
“the odds of another collision will go up.”
It’s the foreign policy equivalent of a
windmill attack.
I’m just going to keep swinging my arms,
and if you get hit it's your own fault.
And it will be the Pentagon's fault.
Now, last week’s dangerous spy plane encounter
happened just a few days ahead
of US President Barack Obama making his first
trip to Vietnam
where he lifted the US’s long-standing embargo
on sales of lethal weapons to the communist country.
“The United States and Vietnam are united
in our support for a regional order including
in the South China Sea.”
So China had better watch out! Unless you
instead believe this other thing he said.
"The decision to lift the ban was not based
on China or any other considerations.”
Yes, I believe that as much as I believe this.
“We would gladly see Vietnam develop
a normal, friendly and cooperative relationship
with all countries, including the United States.”
Anyway, last week’s spy plane intercept
also occurred just ahead of an international
tribunal in The Hague.
The Philippines filed a legal challenge over
China’s claims to the South China Sea.
And there’s no better way to solve a legal
dispute based on international law
than international arbitration.
Unless, from your point of view, arbitration
is illegitimate and you ignore its decision.
Now we don’t know for certain where last
week’s encounter actually happened.
But the Chinese Foreign Ministry says it was
near China’s southernmost Island province Hainan.
That’s where the Chinese regime bases its
growing fleet of nuclear submarines.
Those are a big concern for India,
and at the beginning of May,
the US began talks with India about submarine
warfare.
I’m sure against no one in particular.
Just like selling weapons to Vietnam is about
no one in particular.
So what’s your point of view about last
week’s incident?
Be sure to express it with full vigor in the
comment section below.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell. Thanks for
watching this episode of China Uncensored