On this episode of China Uncensored, people
who walk on glass bridges shouldn't throw
stones... or mugs.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I'm your
host Chris Chappell. You know, many great
feats of man have been brought low by the
simplest of things.
The mighty walls of Helms Deep—destroyed
by a single orc.
The proud Death Star—annihilated by a single
space wizard.
And the mighty Samuel L Jackson…
Now, everyone knows that 'made in China' and
'quality' go hand in hand, in the same way
that 'one more drink' and 'good decisions'
do. That's why tourists felt confident in
the safety of this glass walk way, built thirty-five
hundred feet in the air along China's Yuntai
Mountain Scenic Spot.
I mean, wouldn't you walk on it? It even got
the approval of Chinese officials, known for
their trustworthiness, who told people it
was exceptionally safe. It was after all three
quarters of an inch thick and treated to resist
not just bending, but shattering as well.
So what could go wrong?!
Well, apparently it shattered.
But only a little bit according to park officials
who admitted to finding "a small amount of
cracks." Or a terrifying amount, according
to a female tourist who said on social media
that there was a loud bang and everybody was
screaming. The social media post has been
removed. So really, who knows?
But one thing's clear: She posted this photo
of it on Weibo...which is really unclear.
So no one is quite sure exactly how much this
very, very high up glass bridge cracked after
less than a month of being open to the public.
But how could engineers have foreseen the
cataclysmic event that would humble their
efforts? According to the People's Daily Online,
one of the tourists dropped a stainless steel
mug on it. How can you plan for that?! Next
you'll be telling me the Titanic should have
had more lifeboats on deck "just in case."
As if you could predict the sinking of an
unsinkable ship.
And anyway this kind of thing happens all
the time, the Chinese park management reassured
people. Back in 2014, a glass beer bottle
shattered one layer of glass on the walkway
at London's Tower Bridge... Which to be fair,
I wouldn't be walking on in the first place,
given the notorious reputation for London
bridges falling down, falling down.
The bridge in Yuntai Mountain has been closed
for now. But soon they'll open it back up
to the public again. Do you think you'll be
visiting? It's a great view! Let me know in
the comments below. Once again I'm Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Ah! Great shoot, guys! Well done! (Boom)
If after watching that, you still want to
walk on the Yuntai Mountain glass bridge,
then you might be the kind of person who would
also participate in the most dangerous boat
race in the world. Check it out on Seeker
Daily.
You see this? That’s China building its
first homemade aircraft carrier,
called the Type 001A.