bjbj,(,( On this episode of China Uncensored,
America Up For Sale Now for years, people
have been saying China isn t ready for democracy,
but if the US keeps supporting China s brutal
Communist Party with our business, jobs, and
money, China will end up with more freedom.
That makes total sense! But it turns out all
we ve really been doing is supporting China
s brutal Communist Party. And they doesn t
seem too fond of the idea of democracy. The
US owes China one point one seven trillion
dollars, pays about 100 million dollars a
day in interest on that, and according to
the US Census bureau, in 2012 the US had a
300 billion dollar trade deficit with China,
the largest trade deficit any country ever
has had ever in history. Now, while this might
scare some people, the US has a few tricks
up its sleeve. The US has allowed its economy
to tank so hard that now the value of the
dollar is plummeting, so who cares how many
trillions of dollars of debt China owns. Looks
like the US has pulled the wool over the Communist
Party s eyes. But even as the American economy
suffers, there s still some who want to buy
American. China! All across the country, the
Chinese governments, or Chinese companies,
which for the most part are owned or linked
to the Chinese government, have been buying
up bits and pieces of America. Real estate,
infrastructure, businesses, homes, farmland,
natural resources, cough oil. According to
the Rhodium Group, an investment monitoring
company that focuses on China, in 2012, Chinese
investment in the US was $6.5 billion, whereas
in 2009 it was only 1.9 billion and before
that it wasn t even a billion. So where exactly
is this money going? Well, some people are
concerned that Sinomach, which the Chinese
government owns most of, is trying to establish
special economic zone, just like they have
in China, right in the middle of America.
Shenzhen was just a tiny finishing village
in the 70 s before it was designated a special
economic zone. And look at the workers paradise
it s become now! I mean, America s very own
Shenzhen, who wouldn t want that?! Here s
another one. In May of 2012, Sino-Michigan
Properties LLC bought up 200 acres of land
near the town of Milan, Michigan. But come
on, it s not like they re going to build a
Chinese city in the middle of America, right?
Actually, that s exactly what the plan was.
They had plans to build an entire city, complete
with lakes and a cultural center, catered
to Chinese businessmen who want to start companies
in the US, just 40 minutes away from Detroit.
It hit a little snag when they found it wasn
t legally possible to bring in that many Chinese
immigrants and still be profitable with current
immigration laws. Then there s the China Ocean
Shipping Company that owns vital ports on
both coasts. Which, you d think if US citizens
can now be sentenced to indefinite dentition
without trial under the National Defense Authorization
Act, the US government would at least give
equal weight to a possible conflict of interest
created by a communist country that flouts
the rule of law OWNING VITAL PORTS. The problem
is very little reporting is done about these
topics so it s really hard to know what the
latest developments are but is there a real
threat? Well, the US Congress apparently think
Chinese companies could present a huge threat.
In October 2012, A US House Intelligence Committee
found that Chinese telecommunications companies
Huawei and ZTE operations in the US were a
quote threat to national security interests.
Of course that didn t stop China s largest
auto parts maker from buying US A123 Systems
in January. They make electronic car batteries
and had a couple of big military contracts.
So sure that might transfer sensitive technology
used by the US military developed with US
taxpayer money into the hands of the Chinese
government, but I mean, they re our allies,
right? Since former US President Bill Clinton
signed a trade deal with ex-Chinese leader
Jiang Zemin, who by the way at the time was
orchestrating a genocide against 100 million
Falun Gong practitioners in China, the US
has found itself with a 2.5 trillion dollar
trade deficit. Maybe that wasn t such a good
idea. s funny, in a way, because the US has
pumped so much money into the Chinese Communist
Party directly or through its subsidiaries,
it s almost like the US is funding all this,
and all the horrible things the Chinese regime
does to the Chinese people. But remember,
China absolutely is not ready for democracy.
Whew, this was a depressing episode. I think
we should all take our minds off of it for
a little while with a nice, relaxing trip
to the movies. hCH' hy.t hi>X h_EG h6/M ha-@
ha-@ h6/M [Content_Types].xml #!MB ;c=1 _rels/.rels
theme/theme/themeManager.xml sQ\}# theme/theme/theme1.xml
G$$DA : BR \{i5@R V*[_X ,l\Y Ssd+r] 5\|E Vky-
V4Ej 6NGU s?^V * 7;wP EBU` 5<V8
LStf+] C9P^ wB>VD GGHPXNT, /M,W m2iU [[v _Xtl
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.rels 6?$Q
K(M&$R(.1 [Content_Types].xmlPK _rels/.relsPK
theme/theme/themeManager.xmlPK theme/theme/theme1.xmlPK
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.relsPK
<a:clrMap xmlns:a="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/main"
bg1="lt1" tx1="dk1" bg2="lt2" tx2="dk2" accent1="accent1"
accent2="accent2" accent3="accent3" accent4="accent4"
accent5="accent5" accent6="accent6" hlink="hlink"
folHlink="folHlink"/> Chris Normal.dotm Chris
Microsoft Macintosh Word PICT(J kZo\{g9^ g9g9Z
kZg9c kZg9Z kZo\{R g9g9^ (kZZ g9g9^ NskZZ kZNsZ
NskZg9NsV g9o\{g9c g9o\{c kZkZZ kZg9w o\{kZo\{kZkZo\{o\{g9kZkZo\{s
o\{kZkZc kZkZc kZkZc kZkZo\{w kZkZw g9o\{c kZkZo\{kZkZc
kZg9s o\{g9o\{kZkZ\{ g9o\{kZkZg9w kZkZo\{c g9kZs
o\{kZg9w o\{kZkZo\{o\{kZo\{kZ\{ kZo\{o\{ o\{kZg9w g9kZkZs
kZkZc kZkZ\{ o\{kZkZs kZg9s o\{kZ\{ %kZ^ o\{kZg9^
o\{g9 kZkZc g9o\{g9 *g9R g9kZR g9NsZ kZNsZ g9NsZ
g9g9w kZg9o\{s o\{o\{ g9o\{c o\{o\{kZ^ g9kZs o\{kZc
g9kZkZ o\{kZkZ^ g9kZkZo\{kZ kZkZg9g9c kZkZc
kZo\{c g9g9c g9g9s g9g9kZ g9g9c ,kZV g9g9Z
kZkZc g9g9c o\{g9kZg9^ o\{o\{s kZo\{w BkZZ o\{g9^
/kZZ !o\{Z kZg9Z g9o\{o\{g9^ g9o\{^ o\{o\{Z g9o\{g9^
o\{o\{g9o\{o\{kZc o\{g9g9o\{kZ^ kZo\{o\{g9w o\{o\{kZo\{c
o\{o\{kZ o\{g9w o\{kZs g9kZkZg9g9kZs g9kZs kZkZo\{w
kZg9s kZg9kZkZ kZg9s g9o\{kZo\{s o\{kZ\{ Nsg9
8kZR g9JRV g9NsZ kZNsZ g9g9^ g9kZV g9kZc (g9V
g9g9Z /g9c g9g9kZc kZg9s g9g9c kZkZg9^ kZg9^
kZg9o\{^ g9kZw g9g9c kZg9^ g9g9kZ kZo\{s g9o\{o\{
o\{o\{s o\{o\{s kZo\{o\{s o\{o\{s o\{o\{w kZo\{s o\{kZw
o\{o\{s o\{kZw o\{kZo\{kZo\{ o\{g9w kZo\
o\{kZo\{s &o\{^ kZg9g9c kZg9g9o\{kZc g9o\{c kZo\{g9g9kZc
o\{g9s g9o\{g9 g9o\{o\{g9g9c o\{o\{s o\{kZ kZg9V
kZkZZ g9kZkZR o\{g9V kZg9g9c o\{g9g9^ g9g9^
o\{g9^ Nso\{Z kZNsc kZkZc kZg9g9 "g9w g9o\{c
g9kZc kZg9\{ o\{o\{s o\{o\
kZg9s g9kZkZo\{o\{g9kZs g9g9kZkZg9V kZg9c kZg9\
7g9g9^ g9o\{c g9kZV o\{o\{g9kZZ o\{o\{ g9kZZ Nsg9R
o\{kZ g9o\{s kZkZo\{g9s kZkZs kZo\{ g9kZ\{ kZg9g9\{
?o\{^ g9kZs kZo\{c g9o\{g9g9 g9kZkZg9c kZkZs
g9kZkZg9g9\{ g9g9V g9kZc ?g9^ o\{g9^ g9kZc kZo\{w
g9kZ g9)kZg9^ o\{kZg9c kZg9s o\{g9c kZo\{g9^
g9kZs o\{o\
g9o\{s o\{o\{s kZo\{o\{s o\{o\{s g9o\{o\{ 'kZs o\{o\{s
kZo\{o\{w o\{o\{s o\{o\{s ;o\{c g9kZg9c kZg9c g9o\{kZkZg9^
g9g9s g9g9s g9o\{kZc o\{g9c g9g9V o\{Ns^ g9g9c
NskZ o\{g9kZc g9kZg9kZc Title Microsoft Word
97-2004 Document NB6W Word.Document.8