On this episode of China Uncensored,
well, we’re finally getting towards the
final round
of Civilization.
What?
Thermonuclear warfare?
Shoot, I wanted to get to Alpha Centauri…
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Kim Jong-un,
the rotund God emperor of North Korea.
What can you say about a man that,
when you type his name into Google,
it auto completes Kim Jong-un
flamethrower execution.
Apparently he executed an official by flamethrower.
Also, mortar…
And anti-aircraft gun.
Unless you're an actual hermit,
you’ve probably heard that the hermit kingdom
is on the warpath.
Last year marked North Korea’s
5th nuclear test.
They also released this nice video
where they blow up the US Capitol.
And threatened to nuke Manhattan:
“all the people there would be killed immediately
and the city would burn to ashes.”
Which is an odd threat to make since,
you know,
the United Nations is there.
And probably a lot of countries
would be mad at Kim
if he blew it up.
Also there are North Korean diplomats there.
And me, too.
So blowing up Manhattan
is in no one’s best interests.
To top it all off,
North Korea has been conducting
a series of ballistic missile tests.
Now all this posturing might have worked
on the United State’s last president,
who failed to put the bomb in O-bomb-a.
But things have changed under President Trump,
who puts the bomb in bombastic.
Not only has he launched a Twitter war on
North Korea...
He’s shown he may be willing
to go for an actual war.
In the course of a week,
Trump ordered a retaliatory missile strike
on Syria
for Assad’s use of sarin nerve gas.
Then dropped the “mother of all bombs”
on ISIS.
And over the weekend,
a US carrier strike group headed to North
Korea...
...as they prepared to celebrate the 105th
birthday
of founder Kim Il Sung.
And how did North Korea plan to celebrate?
“Satellite intelligence suggests that a
nuclear test
could be in the works.”
I mean fireworks are nice
but that is going a bit too far.
So it was a bit of a tense weekend.
Since we are not now scrounging through the
wasteland
looking for slightly radioactive
roach meat and Rad-X,
you might have correctly guessed
we did not have a nuclear war.
So if North Korea didn’t launch a nuke,
how did they celebrate their holiday?
With a military parade showcasing
their latest intercontinental ballistic missile
technology...
...and a big old dance party!
Because nothing says there’s no famine in
North Korea,
like lots of people dancing.
You can’t dance if you’re starving.
And then the next day,
they did have a totally awesome ballistic
missile test!
U.S. Pacific Command says it, quote,
"blew up almost immediately"
off the Korean peninsula's east coast.
Most people in North Korea weren’t too troubled
by the news of the failure.
Mainly because they didn’t hear
any news of the failure.
And when some Reuters reporters
spilled the beans,
citizens responded with all the correct answers.
If the news is true,
failure is the mother of success.
We will make more efforts to make
even more powerful weapons in the future.
That's a lie...
Scientists like me don't believe that.
And you've got to believe
the scientists of North Korea.
The good news is that President Trump
has worked out a close friendship
with someone powerful enough to have
an impact on North Korea.
The Easter Bunny.
It’s part of the new US-fairy tale alliance
that will also include Jack Frost,
Santa Claus,
and the Tooth Fairy.
Yes, things are looking very...
Grimm for North Korea.
What's that, Shelley?
Yes, I know that's just a movie.
But can North Korea
actually start a nuclear war?
Well, technically they haven’t even finished
the Korean War.
Right now it’s just in an awkward
decades-long ceasefire.
But if it starts up again,
this time, China's not on their side anymore.
It's on America's.
At least on this issue.
At first it might not seem like the US and
China
could be allies against North Korea.
After all, hundreds of thousands of Chinese
soldiers
died fighting against US troops
in the Korean War.
But the last Chinese leader
to really support North Korea
was the four-eyed toad Jiang Zemin.
And he’s Xi Jinping’s big political rival.
So it’s not a coincidence that,
as Xi Jinping takes down his political enemies
tied to Jiang Zemin,
he is also dismantling China’s old friendly
relationship
with North Korea.
In February,
China said it was cutting off coal imports
from North Korea
in compliance with UN Security Council sanctions.
And after the meeting between Xi and Trump,
even my favorite state-run media,
the super nationalist Global Times,
came out in favor of stricter UN sanctions
and warned Pyongyang that it should
"avoid making mistakes."
The Global Times, by the way,
has long been considered part of Jiang's faction.
So if even they are criticizing North Korea,
it doesn't look good for Kim Jong-un.
Now there are signs the the US and China
are working together on dealing with the situation…
...and the Chinese military has been put on
alert.
So China will not be joining North Korea
if they decide to provoke the United States.
But Chinese authorities also don't want
a sudden collapse of the Kim regime
to send millions of refugees across the border.
Could North Korea actually launch a nuke?
It's not clear whether they've been
able to make a nuclear warhead small enough
to mount it on a missile.
But South Korea or Japan
could definitely be in harm’s way
from a North Korean missile attack,
even if it's not a nuclear one.
For now, I guess all we can do is take comfort
in Vice President Pence’s presence
at the Demilitarized Zone between North and
South Korea.
Because dressing like you’re in Top Gun
says to me,
everything is going to be all right.
So how do you feel standing
on the brink of nuclear annihilation?
Leave your comments below.
And since YouTube has a real penchant
for demonetizing episodes about North Korea,
consider supporting China Uncensored
on the website Patreon,
link is below.
For just a dollar an episode,
you can help us keep the show going.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored,
once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.