It was called fringe, foolish, and debunked
But now people are finally admitting
The coronavirus could have come from a lab
Welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
This episode is sponsored by CuriosityStream.
It’s great for people like you who love
watching videos and learning cool stuff.
Curiosity Stream has a huge selection of documentaries
and non-fiction TV shows.
And I’ll show you more at the end.
So, have you ever talked about something that’s
kind of controversial, and people call you
crazy, and then it turns out you were right
all along?
Sorry Galileo, I guess the Earth does go around
the sun.
A year and a half after the initial virus
outbreak in Wuhan in December 2019, almost
3 million people around the world have died
of Covid-19.
I’ve been calling it the CCP Virus because
the Chinese Communist Party’s coverup allowed
it to spread.
In response to the CCP Virus, government lockdowns
have crippled economies around the world.
And now, the media would like you to know
that the Wuhan lab-leak theory is suddenly
credible.
The theory is that the CCP Virus may have
come from an accidental lab leak from the
Wuhan Institute of Virology.
That theory has been discussed since the beginning
of the outbreak.
But it was for the most part dismissed as
a conspiracy theory.
If you talked about the idea of a lab leak,
you were lumped in with Qanon supporters who
thought that Bill Gates created the coronavirus.
Which is obviously ridiculous.
Bill Gates didn’t create the coronavirus.
He was too busy hanging out with Jeffrey Epstein.
Last February, the predominant theory about
the coronavirus was that it came from bats
or possibly pangolins before jumping to humans.
And this seemed to make sense, because that’s
how other coronaviruses like SARS and MERS
first spread to humans.
At first, the spread of the CCP Virus was
supposed to have happened here, at the Huanan
Seafood Market.
It’s a wet market in Wuhan where exotic
animals were sold.
Many of the early cases were traced back to
the market.
Again, it seemed to make sense, because a
wet market is how SARS was first spread in
China back in 2002.
But there were problems with this theory.
One, “some early cases [of Covid-19] occurred
in people with no known link” to the wet
market.
Another problem: the wet market didn’t sell
bats or pangolins.
And even a year and a half after the initial
outbreak, scientists have not found a bat
or pangolin, or any other host species, infected
with the CCP virus.
That’s unusual.
The host species of the original SARS virus
was identified within four months of the SARS
outbreak, and the host of MERS within nine
months.
So while the zoonotic theory, that it jumped
from bats to humans naturally, makes sense,
there’s not really any evidence for it so
far.
But who needs evidence when you can just leap
to conclusions?
Follow the science!
Then there’s the lab leak theory.
Again, the theory is not that the CCP virus
was created as a bioweapon and unleashed on
the world.
The lab leak theory is that scientists were
experimenting on a bat coronavirus at a lab
in Wuhan, and it *accidentally* leaked.
To their credit, a handful of scientists and
journalists have been pushing all along for
an investigation into the lab leak theory.
But for the most part, if you talked about
the lab leak theory, the media basically treated
you like you were this guy.
Later in this episode, I’ll talk more about
how the US mainstream media’s dismissive
reports basically wrote the Chinese Communist
Party’s propaganda for them.
But first, there’s been growing evidence
over the past year that makes a lab leak look
much more likely.
We’ve been talking about this on China Uncensored
for more than a year.
And some of the Chinese Communist Party’s
actions are a bit suspicious.
Well, okay, I need to narrow that down.
How the Party treated this specific lab in
Wuhan was suspicious.
In January, the Chinese military posted its
top epidemiologist to the Wuhan lab.
In February, Chinese leader Xi Jinping began
talking about biosafety reform in labs.
That’s an odd response to a coronavirus
that supposedly came from a wet market.
And as the US began to investigate the origin
of the coronavirus, the Communist Party began
to heavily censor academic research about
the origin of the virus.
I mean, science and public health are always
best served when Communist officials are looking
over scientists’ work.
By the way, YouTube demonetized that episode
for portraying “harmful or dangerous acts.”
I can only assume it means that the Communist
Party covering up the origin of a global pandemic
is a harmful or dangerous act.
Right, YouTube?
More after the break.
Welcome back.
Did you actually see an ad?
Last year, the lab leak theory was largely
dismissed based on two letters.
Not research papers, but letters.
Essentially opinion articles from scientists.
The first was published in the Lancet on February
19, 2020 and signed by virologists and other
scientists.
It says: “We stand together to strongly
condemn conspiracy theories suggesting that
COVID-19 does not have a natural origin.”
The letter also called for the scientific
community to support and stand with the scientists
of China.
It turns out that letter was written by Dr.
Peter Daszak.
I’ve talked about Daszak before because
he was also on the World Health Organization
team that went to China to investigate the
origin of the coronavirus.
Of course the Party didn’t actually let
them investigate, and Daszak didn’t complain,
but that’s another story.
Daszak is the president of EcoHealth Alliance,
a non-profit group that among other things,
studies viruses in the wild.
In emails, Daszak told other scientists that
he wanted this letter to “avoid the appearance
of a political statement” and that it was
just about supporting Chinese scientists who
were under serious pressure.
Maybe that’s what he wanted to do, but by
calling the lab leak theory a conspiracy theory,
Daszak was making a political statement.
Also, Daszak and the EcoHealth Alliance had
a massive conflict of interest here.
They were funding research at the Wuhan Institute
of Virology through US government grants.
So if a lab leak did happen there, they’d
be in a lot of trouble.
But you’d never know that from this Lancet
letter, because the authors, including Daszak,
declared they had “no competing interests.”
Remember this, it’s important later.
The second letter was published in Nature
Medicine.
It said that the authors’ analyses “clearly
show that [the coronavirus] is not a laboratory
construct of a purposefully manipulated virus.”
But it turns out that letter did not clearly
show that at all.
One of the letter’s main arguments was that
the CCP virus genome did not show any signs
of cutting and pasting.
But there are newer methods of manipulating
a virus that don’t leave any marks.
Including the “no-see-um” or “seamless
approaches” and something called “serial
passage.”
Despite the problems with these two letters,
the media used them as the basis for article
after article “debunking” the lab leak
theory.
But there’s actually a lot more evidence
now for the lab leak theory than the zoonotic
theory.
Specifically, evidence shows it’s very possible
the Wuhan Institute of Virology was manipulating
this virus to make it more infectious to humans.
Here’s evolutionary biologist Bret Weinstein
.
“But the fact that there is no evidence,
that it shows up in Wuhan and immediately
spreads, tells us that this virus was well-adapted
to our cells, and well-adapted to transmit
between individuals, and that is conspicuous.
One way you could get there is if somebody
A) had added components to a virus in order
to make it transmissible to humans, so the
research in question would be research that
was interested in discovering what a pandemic
in humans of a bat-borne coronavirus would
be like, so that we could do something about
it, maybe we could prevent it, maybe we could
create a vaccine ahead of time.”
If you think it sounds insane to take a virus
and make it more infectious to humans, don’t
worry!
Virologists do this all the time.
They’re called “gain of function” experiments.
“[Virologists] have recreated the 1918 flu
virus, shown how the almost extinct polio
virus can be synthesized from its published
DNA sequence, and introduced a smallpox gene
into a related virus.”
So virologists are using DNA to recreate deadly
extinct viruses!
It’s just like Jurassic Park, except you
can’t run away from the velociraptors, because
the velociraptors are *inside* you.
But was the Wuhan Institute of Virology creating
Coronavirus Park?
Well, yes.
This gain-of-function research, making viruses
more infectious to humans, was being done
at the institute by Dr. Shi Zhengli.
She’s been called Batwoman for her work
on bat coronaviruses.
Dr. Shi learned to do this research on bat
coronaviruses with Dr. Ralph Baric at the
University of North Carolina.
They published this paper back in 2015 on
combining parts of a bat coronavirus and a
mouse coronavirus.
Baric was one of the inventors of the “no-see-um”
approach I mentioned earlier.
It lets scientists manipulate viruses without
leaving a mark.
So Dr. Shi likely learned how to do this.
Baric is also one of the scientists who published
a letter in Science magazine this month calling
for a complete investigation into the origin
of Covid-19, including the lab leak theory.
I guess we should follow the science.
And here’s where Peter Daszak comes in.
He’s the guy who wrote the letter calling
the lab leak a conspiracy theory.
As part of EcoHealth Alliance, Daszak applied
for research grants from the US government
to study bat coronaviruses.
Specifically, those grants came from the National
Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases.
And Daszak sub-contracted those grants to
Dr. Shi at the Wuhan Institute of Virology.
The descriptions of the research grants show
that “Dr. Shi set out to create novel coronaviruses
with the highest possible infectivity for
human cells.”
Here’s Peter Daszak talking about the work
they were doing with bat coronaviruses back
in December 2019.
This was before the CCP virus outbreak became
public knowledge.
“And we have now found, you know, after
6 or 7 years of doing this, over 100 new sars-related
coronaviruses, very close to SARS”
“Well I think…coronaviruses — you can
manipulate them in the lab pretty easily.
Spike protein drives a lot of what happen
with coronavirus, in zoonotic risk.
So you can get the sequence, you can build
the protein, and we work a lot with Ralph
Baric at UNC to do this.
Insert into the backbone of another virus
and do some work in the lab.”
So that’s pretty conclusive evidence that
the Wuhan Institute of Virology was doing
experiments on bat coronaviruses, the kind
that could have led to the CCP virus.
It doesn’t prove that the CCP virus is engineered.
But there are several things about the CCP
virus’s genetic code that are unusual or
almost non-existent in natural bat coronaviruses.
But these things would make sense for a virus
that was spliced together in a lab.
I’m not going to talk in detail about spike
proteins and furin cleavage sites because
this isn’t Viruses Uninfected.
But suffice it to say, one of these was so
unusual that an eminent virologist called
it a smoking gun for the non-natural origin
of the virus.
So the Wuhan lab was essentially creating
a Coronavirus Park, and the CCP virus could
have been one of their velociraptors.
But could those velociraptors escape the lab?
It actually wouldn’t have been that hard.
The Wuhan Institute of Virology is a BSL 4
lab.
That’s Biosafety Level 4.
It’s the highest level.
It turns out that the Wuhan lab had had safety
issues before.
“American embassy officials in Beijing made
several visits to the research facility and
sent two official warnings back to Washington
in early 2018 about the lab’s inadequate
safety measures.”
)
And even more concerning, it turns out that
a lot of the bat coronavirus research was
not being done in the BSL 4 labs, but in the
much less strict BSL 2 and 3 level labs.
Biosafety Level 4 looks like this.
Basically, a full body space suit.
Biosafety Level 2 looks like this.
It just requires you to wear a lab coat and
gloves, and possibly a face shield or goggles
if liquids might splash.
Last March, Americans were practically sterilizing
their groceries at biosafety level 2.
For a lab, that doesn’t seem like enough
protection.
And it might not have been.
The Wall Street Journal is reporting that
“Three researchers from China’s Wuhan
Institute of Virology became sick enough in
November 2019 that they sought hospital care.”
That was based on a US intelligence report.
That’s not completely new information.
It’s partly based on this fact sheet the
Trump administration released back in January.
But as more information gets reported, it’s
clear there needs to be an investigation into
the lab leak theory.
So why has it taken a year and a half for
most mainstream media to take the lab leak
theory seriously?
I’ll tell you after the break.
Welcome back.
Ever since people started talking about the
lab leak theory in January 2020, the mainstream
media has treated it like a conspiracy theory.
Like I said earlier, one reason was that they
believed the flawed Lancet and Nature letters
from scientists, without looking into them
further.
Another reason was the media kept conflating
the lab leak theory with the accusation that
the CCP Virus was created to be a bioweapon.
And a third big reason the media treated the
lab leak theory as a conspiracy theory was
because of who was saying it: Republicans.
Back in February 2020, Senator Tom Cotton
said that there needed to be an investigation
into the lab leak theory.
The New York Times accused him of repeating
a fringe theory.
The Washington Post called it a conspiracy
theory that was already debunked.
As time went on, most mainstream media just
ignored this story, unless they were trying
to further debunk it.
Especially after President Trump said this.
Reporter: Have you seen anything at this point
that gives you a high degree of confidence
that the Wuhan Institute of Virology was the
origin of this virus?
Trump: Yes I have, Yes I have.
And I think that the world health organization
should be ashamed of themselves.
Because they’re like the public relations
agency for China.
Well, he’s not wrong about the World Health
Organization.
But to the media, suddenly the lab leak theory
became President Trump’s theory.
And they *had* to debunk it.
They claimed experts called it foolish.
They said Fauci crushed Trump’s theory.
(
Dr. Fauci, by the way, is the director of
the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious
Diseases, the government organization that
gave Peter Daszak the grants that he then
gave to the Wuhan Institute of Virology.
But the point is, the lab leak theory became
a victim of the mainstream media’s culture
war against Trump.
A former New York Times science writer says
he thought the lab leak theory was far right
and equated it to Pizzagate and QAnon.
That same New York Times writer now grudgingly
admits it could be true.
But for well over a year, people who talked
about the lab leak theory were discredited.
In some cases they were banned from social
media.
It couldn’t have worked out better for the
Chinese Communist Party.
Chinese state-run media didn’t even have
to spend much energy denying the lab leak
theory.
The Western media did it for them.
And much more effectively, too.
All the Global Times had to do was show a
screenshot of the New York Times.
It’s quite disturbing that the mainstream
media, because of their own biases, ended
up handing the Chinese regime a propaganda
coup for so long.
Something that let the Party cover up its
own responsibility for the CCP virus and continue
to lie to the rest of the world.
But that might be over soon.
Because the media have discovered that hey,
this lab leak theory suddenly became credible.
Yes.
Suddenly.
And the media is now in full backpedaling
mode.
They might even start doing some actual reporting
on the lab leak theory.
You know, investigate something.
So what happens now that the lab leak theory
is no longer a conspiracy theory?
Everyone is calling for an investigation.
Some scientists say that even without China’s
cooperation, Congress could start an investigation
in the US.
And, hey, if this global pandemic did start
with a lab leak in Wuhan, maybe the US government
shouldn’t fund gain-of-function research
in China!
Just a thought.
But now, this issue is a lot more dangerous
for the Chinese Communist Party.
They can’t rely on Western media to be their
propaganda arm anymore, on this topic at least.
So I wouldn’t be surprised if some Chinese
scientists suddenly find the missing animal
host for a natural zoonotic transmission of
the coronavirus.
Like, maybe it’s mink.
Mink sounds good.
Thanks, state-run media.
When the Chinese propaganda machine ramps
into gear to counter the lab leak theory,
the real question is, will the Western media
fall for it?
Or have they learned their lesson?
And this episode has been sponsored by CuriosityStream.
CuriosityStream is a streaming platform with
dozens of collections of fascinating TV shows,
including award-winning and original programming.
For example, “Ancient Engineering”.
There’s an episode on how China’s most
brutal and possibly most insane emperor built
the Great Wall of China.
And to find workers, he had a brilliant idea:
He made more than 200 crimes punishable by
forced labor.
And if you died building the wall, no problem.
A family member would have to take your place.
With galaxy brain policies like that, no wonder
Mao Zedong idolized him!
With CuriosityStream, you can watch that and
thousands of other streamable documentaries
and non-fiction shows on topics like History,
Nature, Science, Food, Technology, and Travel.
So click the link below and use the code UNCENSORED
to get our special deal—just $14.99 for
the entire year.
You can watch CuriosityStream from your phone,
tablet, or computer anywhere, anytime.
So click the link below and check it out.
I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.