Chinese citizens are boycotting Xinjiang cotton
But not for the reasons you think
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
Over the last couple of years, the world has
finally started speaking out against the Chinese
Communist Party’s treatment of the Uyghurs.
Including the concentration camps, the forced
labor, and oh yeah, the genocide.\h
Two weeks ago, both the US and the EU imposed
sanctions on China over the treatment of Uyghur
Muslims.\h
And now that Uyghur forced labor in Xinjiang
is in the spotlight, international companies
are also responding.
Especially the world’s apparel brands.\h
That’s because “The region [of Xinjiang]
accounts for 85% of China’s and 20% of the
world’s cotton...and it is ‘very likely’
that any cotton from Xinjiang may involve
coerced labour.”
Fashion companies don’t want to be caught
selling slave-labor cotton.
That look is so 1860s.
That’s why organizations like the Better
Cotton Initiative started pulling out of Xinjiang
last year.
And companies like Under Armour implemented
controls to guard against cotton from Xinjiang
being used in their products.\h
Last September, H&M announced it was cutting
ties with their Chinese supplier because of
accusations of forced labor in Xinjiang.\h
And in January, one of the Trump administration’s
last China-related policies was a total ban
on cotton produced in Xinjiang.\h
As a result, “a multibillion-dollar supply
chain splintered almost overnight over a human
rights issue.”
Which is a good thing.
Unless you’re the Chinese Communist Party.
Because the whole genociding the Uyghurs thing
is starting to become a problem for the Party.
I mean, they’re not going to stop the genocide.
But what they really want is to be able to
commit genocide quietly, while the rest of
the world ignores what’s happening.\h
That worked for them so well before with Falun
Gong!
But now with the Uyghurs, foreign governments
and companies are starting to acknowledge
what’s happening and even worse, take action
against it.
The Chinese regime can’t let itself become
a pariah state, like Iran or North Korea.\h
So if you’re an authoritarian regime looking
to punish foreign companies for making you
look bad, what do you do?
I’ll tell you after the break.
Welcome back.
So the Chinese Communist Party had an image
problem.
But they found the solution: nationalism!\h
Yes, Chinese state-run media has managed to
turn this Xinjiang cotton ban to their advantage,
by using Chinese nationalism.
They did this by portraying the rejection
of Xinjiang cotton as an insult to the Chinese
people.
It started with this Weibo post from the official
account of the Communist Youth League.
It says “Trying to make money in China while
spreading rumors and boycotting Xinjiang cotton,
wishful thinking!”\h
Separately, the Communist Youth League posted
a picture of black slaves working on a US
cotton plantation.\h
This would become the two prongs of the Chinese
propaganda attack: foreign brands are lying
and hurting the feelings of the Chinese people,
and America is the country with slaves.\h
And this message spread through both the propaganda
apparatus and directly through the Chinese
government.
Here’s state-run Xinhua News Agency, publishing
a cartoon about the Better Cotton Initiative
being a puppet of the US.
And Foreign Ministry spokesperson Hua Chunying
even brought a picture of black slaves picking
cotton to show at her daily press conference.
Within hours of the first Communist Youth
League post, it became a full nationalistic
blowout online.
Because it wouldn’t be a mass campaign if
the masses didn’t get involved.\h
Chinese fashion designers talked about how
much they loved Xinjiang cotton.
More than 30 Chinese stars rushed to cut ties
with brands that had stopped using Xinjiang
cotton.\h
The celebrities shared this post that reads
“I support Xinjiang Cotton.”
Mian Hua is Cotton in Chinese.
Notice how the M and H are the M and H in
H&M.
I guess saying you support Xinjiang cotton
sounds a lot better than saying you support
Xinjiang genocide.\h
Anyway, Television shows that were set to
air had to be changed at the last minute,
with several episodes showing actors with
blurred out shoes!\h
This screenshot is from the trailer of a TV
episode set to release last week
And this is a screenshot from when the episode
aired.
Yup.
No Prada here!
Yeah, they actually pulled a Stalin on fashion
brands—airbrushing out the undesirables.
These brands practically stopped existing
in China.\h
You can’t even find an H&M store, because
they no longer appear on China’s map apps.
H&M has even been removed from Apple Maps
in China.
So H&M is just gone.
Cancelled.
Memory-holed.
Like it never even existed.\h
And it didn’t end there.
Rappers even released diss tracks against
these fashion brands.
“Nike Fxxk\h
Adidas Shit
China So Dope”
Pure poetry.\h
But the point is, hating Nike is hip!
I say Nike, you say Stupid, Nike, Stupid,
Nike, Stupid!)
Remember, if you don’t hate foreign brands
with all your guts, then you’re not really
Chinese!
Videos of people burning their Nike shoes
became a trend...
because their love burns for China.
Ripping up shirts has also gone viral.
“You’re Tshirt so sexy a”
Hold on, aren’t these products they’re
ripping up and burning Made in China?
But there are also concerns that all of this
performative patriotism could go too far.\h
Here’s a video of customers storming and
trashing Nike store inventory.
And this video shows a woman taking her voice
to the streets with a sign that reads “I
support Xinjiang cotton, Boycott H&M”.
And the security officers had a hard time
diffusing the public disturbance.
In the end they just grabbed her and took
her away.
“Everyone should join me and support Xinjiang
cotton!”
“Ok, ok, Support support!”
People have also been harassing people who
work for these stores.
Like this person who told an H&M worker to
quit their job because they’re selling out
China.\h
￼
And people also harassed store staff on live
streams.
Flooding the live chat with comments like\h
“Cut The Stream”, “Quit”, “Get Out
of China”.\h
The good news is it hasn’t gotten as bad
as the anti-Japan protests back in 2012, that
caused 100 million dollars in damage.
But I wouldn’t want you to think that all
Chinese people are joining in the anger.
Some actually said things like, “don’t
just support Xinjiang cotton, support Xinjiang
people.”
Those people had their accounts banned.
Which is yet another reminder of how the Chinese
Communist Party is always watching.
“According to tests conducted by China Digital
Times, internet platforms have been diligently
controlling search results and comments related
to Xinjiang and H&M since last week.”
As I mentioned earlier, brands like H&M announced
they were not using Xinjiang cotton last fall.
So why is the Chinese regime encouraging this
outraged behavior now?\h
Well, it probably has something to do with
how the US, Canada, the EU, and UK are sanctioning
Chinese officials over Xinjiang.
In addition to directly retaliating against
these countries, the Chinese Communist Party
is trying to punish foreign companies economically.
Because that’s always worked before.\h
And don’t forget, while there might be genuine
patriotic rage going on, it’s being orchestrated
by the Party.\h
“After the Communist Youth League ignited
the outrage on Wednesday, other government-backed
groups and state news outlets fanned the flames.”
They’re literally triggering people in order
to foment this kind of anger.
And they’re really good at it.\h
And now it’s time for me to answer a question
from a member of the China Uncensored 50 Cent
Army, fans who support the show on Patreon.
Hungry Hunter asks, “Question: What is holding
back the USA and others to also build bases
on these islands?
If I were the Philippines, I would ask other
nations for a 10 year plan to build tons of
bases there just to piss China off.
What they gonna do?
Complain in the UN that will have to punish
them too?
Wow, Hungry Hunter, you might have just come
up with an amazing solution to the South China
Sea dispute.
Or possibly the beginning of World War 3.\h
If you don’t know, China claims the entire
South China Sea as Chinese territory, with
their Nine Dash Line.
And to bolster that claim, they’ve been
building artificial islands and establishing
settlements on them, including these 7 reefs
in the Spratlys.
Some of those islands now have missile launchers
on them.
And even though the UN has told China to stop,
they just ignore that.\h
So what if all the other countries in the
region just got together and agreed to do
the same?
Or in the case of the Philippines, lease it
out to the US to build missiles on?
Beat the Chinese Communist Party at its own
game.\h
Thanks for your question Hungry Hunter.
And if you’d like me to answer your question
on the show, join the China Uncensored 50
cent army for as little as a dollar per episode.
Visit pateron.com/ChinaUncensored to learn
more.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next
time.