A Cover Up of the Deadly Coronavirus
Was only the beginning of the cruelty
China’s response to the Coronavirus
Can only be described as “vile”
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Now this may shock you, but it turns out,
an authoritarian regime that’s killed
millions of its own people over the years
doesn’t really care if people die from an
epidemic.
Not if the bigger threat is to its own rule.
The Chinese Communist Party
spent the first crucial weeks of the Wuhan
coronavirus outbreak
trying to cover it up,
which meant more people got sick.
And that’s bad because it makes the Party
look bad.
Like that international media are calling
it
“China’s governance failure.”
Even more humiliating, Chinese people
are actually praising Japan’s response to
the virus
and the help they’ve given China.
And that is impressive,
given the Communist Party’s decades of propaganda
about how terrible the Japanese are.
But don’t worry,
there’s still something the Chinese Communist
Party
can hate even more than Japan.
And that is America.
China’s Foreign Ministry is accusing the
US
of not helping with the coronavirus
and spreading fear and chaos by…
...evacuating its citizens from Wuhan.
And instituting a travel ban on foreign nationals
coming in from China.
Just like many other countries.
Including Japan.
And while Chinese state-run media accused
the US of not offering help,
that’s...a lie.
The US had offered to send CDC experts to
help in Wuhan.
That was back in early January,
when officials were still trying to pretend
things were fine.
China rejected the US’s offer.
Now US experts will be joining a W.H.O. delegation
to help with the coronavirus.
Meanwhile, the Chinese central government
is demanding that local Wuhan officials
round up everyone who may be infected,
and force them to go to quarantine centers.
A Beijing official has demanded that
“City investigators should go to each home
to check the temperatures of every resident.”
And that “During these wartime conditions,
there must be no deserters,
or they will be nailed to the pillar of historical
shame forever.”
It should be noted that the quarantine centers
don’t actually have nearly enough beds for
everyone.
And many of them don’t have enough doctors
or supplies
or even basic conditions to prevent the spread
of infection.
Although mentioning that might also get you
nailed to that pillar of historical shame.
Here’s a photo from inside a Wuhan gymnasium
that’s being converted into a quarantine
center.
That does not look like a good isolation ward
to me.
And anyone trying to get real news out from
Wuhan is being targeted.
One citizen journalist named Fang Bin spent
days
traveling to hospitals,
documenting overcrowded conditions
and a lot of dead bodies.
Then the police showed up at his door.
Well, technically they were just a group of
men in hazmat suits s
aying they had to see if he was infected.
Obviously, to test if he had the coronavirus,
these men had to break into his home,
and take away his laptop, desktop computer,
and cellphone.
And then they took him to a police station.
As is common procedure for well trained medical
staff.
The police “accused him of taking money
from ‘foreign forces,’
and threatened to quarantine him for ‘creating
fear.’”
Yeah, somehow I don’t think that’s a quarantine
you’d ever come back from.
Luckily, others quickly spread word of Fang
Bin’s detention online,
and he was released.
But beyond citizen journalists,
there are also doctors who’ve spoken out.
Dr. Li Wenliang
was one of eight doctors detained by Wuhan
police
after he warned other colleagues about the
coronavirus.
His mistake?
Speaking the truth while the Communist Party
was trying to cover it up.
Police let him go after he signed a statement
hat he would no longer commit “unlawful
acts.”
Unfortunately, none of that matters now,
because he died this week—
after contracting the coronavirus he tried
to expose.
He leaves behind his pregnant wife and a 5-year-old
child.
But the tragedy doesn’t end there.
After initial reports from state-run media
that Dr. Li had died,
there was a furious backlash on Chinese social
media.
And Dr. Li was suddenly no longer dead.
Instead, the hospital said he was in critical
condition
and on life support.
There were reports that Dr. Li had been put
on life support
hours after he had already passed due to the
backlash.
Hours later, after the hospital finally officially
announced his death,
the online anger continued.
People posted images like this one,
with Dr. Li’s mask replaced by barbed wire.
They used references to Les Mis and Chernobyl
to mourn Dr. Li.
And hashtags like I want freedom of speech.
And after that was censored,
we *demand* freedom of speech.
They even posted protest videos on TikTok.
But don’t worry,
the Chinese Communist Party knows how to handle
this.
First, “control” the online reaction.
And then, send officials to “investigate”
Dr. Li’s death.
The only question is, who will the scapegoat
be?
And it’s not just doctors and citizen journalists
the Party is going after.
They’ve turned anyone from Wuhan into pariahs,
turning neighbors against neighbors.
In one case,
authorities used metal poles to barricade
a family
that had been to Wuhan.
If you’re wondering how that family gets
food,
they rely on neighbors to lower something
down to their rear balcony window.
And some local officials are offering bounties
to people
who turn in Wuhan residents who are hiding
in other cities.
As the New York Times says,
“Across the country,
the response from local authorities often
resembles
the mass mobilizations of the Mao era.”
And I wish I could say that was the worst
of it.
But I’ve found with the Chinese Communist
Party,
the worst can always get worse.
Check out this story.
Authorities quarantined the father of a boy
who had cerebral palsy.
So the father “posted on Chinese social
media platform Weibo
appealing for help and explaining that his
son
had been left alone without food or water.”
Well, that didn’t go so well.
Without adequate care, the boy died.
Two local officials were fired in connection
to this case,
but this is always what happens.
Systemic corruption leads to tragedy,
and the Commuinst Party tries to push the
blame on local officials,
while the ultimate source of the problem remains
untouched.
Meanwhile, the Communist Party for more than
a week
denied Taiwan’s requests to evacuate its
citizens from mainland China...
since, you know, they don’t allow Taiwan
to have their own citizens,
because they consider Taiwan to be part of
China.
But finally, on February 3,
a charter flight was arranged,
but not through the Taiwanese government,
because the Communist Party can’t admit
there’s a separate Taiwanese government.
Instead, the flight was arranged through a
Taiwanese businessman.
It was supposed to get the most vulnerable
people out first—
frail and elderly Taiwan citizens.
At least, that’s who was on the flight manifest.
But it turns out,
dozens of the passengers who actually boarded
the plane
were not people with urgent needs,
but instead the spouses and children
of wealthy Taiwanese business people.
There are also reports that one person added
to the flight
was already confirmed to have the coronavirus.
As you can imagine, people in Taiwan are a
little upset about this.
Speaking of Taiwan, the Chinese Communist
Party
is using its position in the United Nations
to turn the deadly outbreak into a political
weapon against Taiwan.
The World Health Organization is a UN Body.
“At Beijing’s behest, the WHO has given
Taiwan the pariah treatment...
The WHO has held two emergency meetings since
the coronavirus outbreak.
Taiwan wasn’t permitted to attend.”
Yes, the Chinese Communist Party
is using the coronavirus to play politics.
So it really undermines the credibility of
the WHO
when its director praised
“the seriousness with which China is taking
this outbreak,
especially the commitment from top leadership,
and the transparency they have demonstrated.”
I think Taiwan’s Foreign Ministry Spokeswoman
explained it a little better.
“We have seen the Chinese government rudely
and unreasonably pressuring Taiwan on the
international stage
and putting political considerations above
human health.
We have seen that the disease has no national
boundaries
and epidemic prevention around the world should
have no loopholes,
so that they are putting political considerations
over people's health and safety,
this, basically, is extremely vile.”
“Extremely vile” sounds about right.
So what do you think about how the Chinese
Communist Party
has responded to the coronavirus?
Tell me what you think in the comments below.
And as you may have heard me mention,
YouTube has refused to run ads
on most of our episodes about the coronavirus.
Which means we can’t afford to keep covering
it.
Except for one thing:
We have the support of viewers like you,
whom I call the China Uncensored 50 cent army.
Through your contributions on the crowdfunding
website Patreon,
China Uncensored can keep paying our staff
and our expenses,
so we can keep letting you know about important
China issues,
like a deadly global pandemic.
So as a thank you to supporters,
I answer a question from them at the end of
some of my episodes.
Today’s question comes from Logan.
“Is there any truth to the drones with disinfectant
story
I have been hearing about?”
Wow, you know what?
It’s true.
According to Chinese state-run media,
they are using drones to spray disinfectant.
I guess in China, chemtrails are real.
Drones are actually being used in a lot of
ways
to combat the coronavirus.
In some cases,
drones are delivering groceries to people
in quarantined villages.
And my favorite state-run media the Global
Times
reposted online videos of drones yelling at
people to go home.
Some of the drones were used by local traffic
police.
Others, like this one, were from a local social
media influencer
working with his village Communist Party committee.
Yes, auntie, this is the drone speaking to
you.
You shouldn’t walk about without wearing
a mask.
Yes, you’d better go back home and don’t
forget to wash your hands.
You see we’ve been telling people to stay
at home
but you still wander outside.
Now a drone is watching you.
I mean, that’s only marginally less scary
than actually getting sick from the coronavirus.
Thanks for your question, Logan.
And if you’d like to join the China Uncensored
50-cent army,
head over to patreon.com/chinauncensored to
learn more.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.