On this episode of China Uncensored,
Gap draws a map of China on a T-shirt—
but it’s missing all the fun parts.
China stops importing trash from Europe.
Well, other than its fashion trends.
And a Chinese family raises a cute, cuddly
dog.
Except instead of a dog,
it was a bear.
This is China Uncensored.
Welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
US fashion retailer Gap is apologizing profusely
for this t-shirt.
Yes, they are “extremely sorry”
for the shirt’s “erroneous” design.
What’s that?
You don’t see what’s so offensive about
this shirt?
It’s because it doesn’t “respect the
sovereignty
and territorial integrity of China”!
Which means the t-shirt doesn’t include
Taiwan!
Or the 9-Dash Line that surrounds the entire
South China Sea!
Gap is just the latest foreign company
that has stumbled onto the Chinese
sovereignty and territorial integrity landmine.
Recently, the Chinese Communist Party sent
this letter
to 36 foreign airlines demanding they stop
listing Taiwan
as a separate country.
Although if Gap is apologizing for anything,
it should really be for trying to make both
khakis
and swing dancing cool.
In other news,
realizing just how sensitive
territorial claims on t-shirts can be,
a group of Chinese tourists showed up in Vietnam
wearing this—
the kind of shirt Gap really ought to make
if they want to stay in China.
It has both Taiwan
and the ridiculous looking 9-Dash Line.
Needless to say,
since Vietnam disputes China’s 9-Dash Line,
people in Vietnam were not too happy
with their new guests’ attire.
In fact, these Chinese tourists were stopped
at the airport by security
and told to remove their shirts.
Still, the photo went viral in Vietnam,
with a lot of internet users there
calling for the tourists to be immediately
deported.
I’m starting to think that the next world
war
is going to be fought over a t-shirt.
According to Deutsche Welle,
China sent Iran a shipment of over
a thousand tons of sunflower seeds.
Maybe it’s in preparation for the first
annual
Sino-Iranian Sunflower Seed spitting contest!
China and Iran have pledged to grow trade
to 600 billion dollars a year.
Iran could be an important part of Xi Jinping’s
Belt and Road Initiative,
as a physical bridge that could link China
and Europe.
And since sunflower seed shipment this happened
two days after President Trump announced
he was putting sanctions back on Iran,
this is probably China’s way of telling
Iran,
“Hey buddy, we’ve got your back.”
Also, your sunflower seeds.
Here’s a quick update
on the story of the former CIA agent
who is accused of selling out to China.
Court documents say Chinese intelligence officers
gave him 100,000 dollars
and promised to take care of him for life.
Well, his alleged selling out
got a bunch of CIA agents killed.
So now it looks the US
will take care of him for life, too.
China used to take
almost half of Europe’s plastic trash.
But no longer.
“But an environmental crackdown
China began last January
has led to a whopping 96 percent drop
in how much it takes.
And now there's a messy problem for Europe:
What to do with all this leftover garbage!”
Maybe they can ship it here to New York.
No one will be able to tell.
This footage from Hong Kong Free Press
shows a journalist getting roughed up
by police in Beijing.
The Hong Kong journalist was in Beijing covering
the trial of a right’s activist Xie Yanyi.
Don’t worry,
police let him go to the hospital.
As soon as he signed an apology letter.
And finally, this video from state-run CGTN
shows a black bear that was supposedly
raised as a pet by a Chinese family.
They thought it was a dog.
“Honey, something’s wrong with Fido.
He won’t play fetch.”
Funny story,
the same thing happened to me.
The family was so disappointed when they found
out
I wasn’t a puppy.
Sorry mom.
Thanks for watching the headlines from China
this week.
Once again, I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
And time for another question from you,
our loyal supporters on Patreon!
Mark Mathews asks: “Have you read the book
Nine Commentaries on the Communist Party?
Do you recommend it to others?”
Yes, I’ve read it.
And I definitely recommend it to anyone
who wants to really understand
the nature of the communism
and how it’s affected modern China.
It gives insight into how the Communist Party
seized and maintains power.
And let’s just say,
the body count is high.
On that cheery note,
I’ll put a link to the book in the description
below.
Thank you Mark for your question.
And just a reminder to the fans
who support China Uncensored on Patreon,
leave your questions on our Patreon website
and maybe I’ll answer yours next time.