On this episode of China Uncensored,
Olympic Gold.
When she shines she really shows you all she
can.
Oh Rio, Rio dashing China’s Olympic Plan.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your...
host whose pop music references come from
1982, Chris Chappell.
Chinese athletes have flopped at the Rio Olympics!
Oh, I’m sorry, does that sound harsh?
Well, yeah, it actually kind of does.
And it wasn’t me who said that.
It was China’s state-run Xinhua news.
And that picture is Chinese gymnast You Hao
“flopping” at the men’s parallel bars
final on Tuesday night.
I haven’t seen a worse display on parallel
bars since Gymkata,
a movie that combined the skill of gymnastics,
the kill of karate,
and former Olympic gymnast Kurt Thomas
fighting for his life in the fictional country
of...Parmistan.
Yes, all of my movie references are also from
the 80s.
Now this is not what China had planned.
The Chinese Communist Party recruits thousands
of children
to train for their entire lives to win Olympic
Gold.
“Picked at a young age,
Gao Lei is a product of the world's largest
mass recruitment and sports training program.
51,000 athletes are currently training
at elite national and regional Institutes
like this one this one.”
But the important thing about this massive
sports system
is that...it works!
In the 2008 Beijing Summer Olympics,
China won 51 gold medals.
So it didn’t seem like a stretch
that party mouthpiece Global Times
ran this spread before the Rio Olympics.
Except now it’s pretty clear that isn’t
going to happen.
Here’s another Xinhua sports tweet,
that they later deleted, for some reason.
They’re...not too happy the Brits have outdone
them.
“Burn me.”
As of this morning,
Chinese athletes have only won 20 gold medals.
That’s a far cry from expectations.
And, coincidentally, Chinese media have suddenly
shifted their tone
away from valuing Olympic gold above all else.
China Central Television ran a story called
“When we are no longer obsessed with gold
medals.”
It said, “we will be able to openly applaud
our rivals
to reflect our great country's confidence
and tolerance.”
I...actually kind of agree with that?
A Global Times piece talked about
how the burden of Olympic medals was "unfair"
to athletes.
I...also agree with that.
And another Global Times piece says the public
doesn’t really care about gold medals because
fitness is more important.
I mean, it's hard to disagree with that.
What's going on here?!
One expert interviewed said that
“As China grown from a backward country
to become the world’s second largest economy,
its people no longer need to use sporting
prowess
as a means to boost national confidence.”
Oh, ok.
Well, as an American,
representing the world’s largest economy,
all I have to say is...
BOOYAH!!!
Ohh, mmm, sporting prowess is boosting my
national confidence!
In all seriousness,
it’s great that Chinese media isn’t going
all
Tiger Mom on their Olympic athletes anymore.
I mean, that’s the kind of attitude that
leads to this.
“I feel terribly guilty for disappointing
my country,
the Chinese weightlifting team
and all the people who supported me.
I really wanted to be the best but I didn’t
make it.
I am sorry!”
Yeah, what a national disappointment!
He got silver.
Compare that four years ago
to one of the breakout stars of Rio
Chinese swimmer Fu Yuanhui.
Here's her reaction to placing third in the
100-meter backstroke semifinals.
Did you not expect that you...
I thought it was 59 seconds!
I was so fast!
In the end, she tied for the bronze medal
and won the hearts of the Internet forever.
At least when it comes to Internet memes,
she won gold.
There are 206 countries or regions competing
in the Rio Olympics.
And Chinese athletes have:
The third most gold medals.
Chinese athletes have done incredibly well.
That is something to celebrate.
And I'm happy to say that
as a reflection of my great show’s confidence
and tolerance.
So what do you think of how China’s state-run
media are treating the Olympics?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.