bjbj,(,( China s First Lady: Upbeat, Presentable,
Great Closing Act for Student Massacre Hello,
soon-to-be news-knowers; this is China Uncensored,
I m your host Chris Chappell. Well, the United
States has them, France and Britain occasionally
produce them, and they re the envy of less
fortunate states around the world though North
Korea has recently astonished everyone by
obtaining its own. No, not nuclear weapons
glamorous first ladies. Now China has recently
joined the elite of countries whose first
spouse makes her own headlines. New Communist
Party head Xi Jinping recently went abroad
with his wife, Peng Liyuan, and she was the
one turning heads. No, not Xi; she. Uh, that
is, she (pointing exasperatedly at picture)
Ms. Peng! Mr. Xi may have too many years of
dumplings and mind-numbing bureaucracy under
his belt to look dashing and it s probably
been years since he dashed anywhere. But Peng
Liyuan has for years been one of China s biggest
celebrity singers, and a general in the People
s Liberation Army, to boot. And her predecessors
as first lady were, uh, well. She adds something
to the role. s also famous enough that, when
Xi Jinping was chosen as China s new Communist
Party leader, many people just referred to
him as Peng Liyuan s husband. You see, she
s more famous than Xi, and she and Xi combine
their fame to that Xi s even more famous and
uh, moving on Anyway, it was all going according
to plan a bright, upbeat first lady was finally
making China look a little more friendly and
dynamic on the world stage, and instead of
searching online for censored things like
Tiananmen massacre, tons of impressionable
Chinese youth were looking for things like
Peng Liyuan s blouse. Then that got censored
too. No joke. Anyway, the bright and shiny,
Kennedy-esque image that Xi and Peng project
has now been overshadowed for some people,
by a recently-revealed photo of Peng in full
army gear, singing to armed troops, in Tiananmen
Square. Oh yeah, it s also in 1989. Shortly
after that massacre that never happened. Apparently,
Peng was dispatched by the PLA to sing reassuring,
patriotic songs to the young soldiers who
had recently been forced to gun down thousands
of protesting students. Needless to say, she
doesn t put this one on her resume. It s worth
noting that she might herself have been targeted
if she d turned down the assignment even the
official Communist Party leader of the time
was thrown out for supporting the students
too much. But anyway, while her husband talks
about achieving the Chinese Dream and Peng
smiles and promotes vegetable eating, like
all good first ladies, it might be worth remembering
that China is still a bit different from other
countries in some important regards. On the
outside, it may start looking like Kennedy
s Camelot inside, it s still more like Stalin
s Kremlin. hKw$ h"qZ h"qZ h"qZ [Content_Types].xml
#!MB ;c=1 _rels/.rels theme/theme/themeManager.xml
sQ\}# theme/theme/theme1.xml G$$DA : BR \{i5@R
V*[_X ,l\Y Ssd+r] 5\|E Vky- V4Ej 6NGU s?^V
* 7;wP EBU` 5VD
GGHPXNT, /M,W m2iU [[v _Xtl theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.rels
6?$Q K(M&$R(.1 [Content_Types].xmlPK _rels/.relsPK
theme/theme/themeManager.xmlPK theme/theme/theme1.xmlPK
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.relsPK
<a:clrMap xmlns:a="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/main"
bg1="lt1" tx1="dk1" bg2="lt2" tx2="dk2" accent1="accent1"
accent2="accent2" accent3="accent3" accent4="accent4"
accent5="accent5" accent6="accent6" hlink="hlink"
folHlink="folHlink"/> Chris Normal.dotm Chris
Microsoft Macintosh Word `hIa5 PICT&P g9/c
g9g9kZc kZg9c g9o\{Z o\{kZZ kZJRg9kZc kZg9\
o\{o\{w kZo\{ o\{kZ\{ kZkZc g9o\{^ g9g9o\{^ o\{c g9kZZ
g9g9Z >g9R g9NsR NskZNsV o\{g9kZc kZo\{g9c kZkZ^
g9g9c g9g9kZkZ^ NskZ g9g9kZg9o\{kZ^ kZg9o\{g9g9kZc
kZg9kZs o\{o\{s kZo\{s kZo\{o\{s kZo\{o\{kZg9o\{o\{w
o\{o\{w o\{o\{s kZo\{o\{s kZkZs g9g9kZg9c g9kZ g9g9
JRg9c .kZkZg9Z g9g9c kZg9g9V kZkZc g9kZkZg9c
g9kZkZg9g9c kZo\{g9s kZkZw o\{o\{w o\{g9o\{o\{w
o\{kZs kZg9o\{w kZkZo\{o\{kZo\{s o\{g9\{ kZo\{g9\{
o\{o\{g9s g9o\{ o\{g9kZc g9g9^ kZg9c kZo\{g9c g9kZc
o\{o\{^ kZg9o\{o\{ o\{g9g9c g9g9w kZg9g9s o\{g9o\{o\{c
g9g9 o\{o\
kZ+s kZo\{g9o\{g9w g9o\{g9w kZg9o\{g9kZkZo\{s kZg9o\{kZo\{w
kZo\{c g9o\{g9kZo\{kZw kZo\{w g9o\{c o\{g9w o\{kZg9c
g9kZs g9o\{s g9kZg9s g9g9o\{s kZkZg9s kZo\{g9kZkZo\{g9kZg9kZs
kZkZg9w g9kZs g9g9kZg9kZ\{ g9o\{c kZg9c kZkZ
o\{g9 o\{o\{c o\{g9^ kZNsc g9kZ /g9s g9g9^ kZkZZ
g9g9Z o\{kZR NskZZ o\{o\{R kZg9 g9g9Z g9g9c kZg9Z
g9g9 kZg9o\{g9g9 g9kZo\{c g9g9kZs o\{kZZ g9g9kZ^
g9o\{g9kZg9Z g9g9s o\{kZo\{kZo\{o\{w o\{kZw kZo\{s
o\{o\{s kZo\{o\
kZg9c g9g9c o\{g9Z kZg9c o\{g9g9^ g9g9 o\{o\{w
o\{o\{g9\{ o\{o\{w o\{o\{w o\{g9s g9kZo\{w o\{o\{ o\{o\{kZkZg9kZ
o\{o\{s o\{g9c g9g9o\{g9g9Z o\{kZg9kZg9kZg9o\{kZg9kZV
g9kZ g9g9kZs kZg9^ o\{g9^ g9g9R kZNsZ NskZZ
o\{+s g9o\{kZo\{g9o\{c g9kZkZo\{ o\{kZkZo\{c o\{o\{s
kZo\{o\{kZs kZkZw o\{o\{ kZo\{s o\{kZkZo\{o\{s o\{o\{c
kZo\{V g9)w g9kZg9g9kZg9g9o\{o\{g9^ kZg9^ kZg9g9w
kZo\{c kZkZs o\{o\{V kZkZc kZo\{s o\{kZw g9g9Z
g9kZg9c kZkZ^ Nsg9c kZkZV %g9kZR g9kZc kZg9g9
g9kZ g9kZs kZNsR NskZV Nso\{NsV 2g9V g9-c kZo\{kZ^
Nsg9g9Z g9g9kZo\{o\{kZg9w g9g9kZc g9kZo\{V g9g9s
g9kZ #kZs o\{o\{kZkZs kZo\{o\{s o\{o\
o\{o\{ kZkZw kZo\{s o\{o\
kZg9g9V kZkZg9c kZo\{g9c g9o\{c g9kZc g9kZZ
kZkZR o\{o\
NB6W Word.Document.8