China’s got a new economic plan.
Designed to counter\h
the threat of decoupling from the US.
What does it mean for the rest of the world?\h
Welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.\h
We’ve just been through an historic event
that will set the direction of one of the
world's biggest economies for years to come.\h
And that historic event is... the Fifth Plenum
of the 19th Central Committee of the Chinese
Communist Party!
Why, what did you think I was going to say?\h\h
China's top leaders have wrapped up a four-day
gathering unveiling the country's critical
blueprint for the next five years.
The communist party of china today released
the 14th five-year plan.
You know what they say about Communists.
They always have a 5-year plan.\h
Unfortunately, this year the Communist Party
did not commission a catchy theme song to
explain their 14th five-year plan to foreigners.
So we’re just going to have to play the
one from five years ago about the 13th 5-year
plan, the shi san wu.
If you know what’s coming, sing along.\h\h
If you wanna know what China’s gonna do,
best pay attention to the shi san wu.
The shi san wu.
The shi san what?
The shi san wu.\h
Look, back in 2015, Chinese propaganda was
going through an...experimentation...phase.\h
The point is, every five years, the Chinese
Communist Party unveils a new economic plan.
This time, the five-year plan focuses a lot
on what’s being called China’s “dual
circulation” economy.
I’ll let Chinese state-run media explain.\h
But what exactly is a dual circulation economy?
The concept has two equally strong components:
"internal circulation," which refers to domestic
economic activities, and "external circulation,"
which relates to China's economic links with
the outside world.
It signals that China wants to reduce the
role of international trade in its economy,
and strengthen its domestic economy.\h
You know, Chinese propaganda was more fun
when they were experimenting.\h
So why is the Chinese Communist Party trying
to strengthen China’s domestic economy?
Because of the coronavirus that was totally
not the Communist Party’s fault, and also
because America is a big fat meanie.
As the COVID-19 pandemic sends shudders across
the world, the economic outlook outside China
does not look particularly optimistic at the
moment.
Worsening China-U.S. relations have also loomed
large in China's consideration, as the U.S.
contemplates decoupling and seems bent on
crippling China's economic and technological
development.
Right.
That’s what’s happening.
The US is targeting Chinese companies to cripple
China’s development.
It’s totally not because companies like
Huawei, WeChat, and TikTok pose national security
threats to the US.\h
Just remember, everyone: China is the victim
here.\h
But it’s true that there’s been a lot
of talk in the last year or so about the US
decoupling from China economically.\h
That includes reducing America’s reliance
on Chinese manufacturing, moving supply chains
out of China, and moving financial dealings
out of Hong Kong.
And the coronavirus is speeding up the process
of decoupling.
It was a shock to many countries when they
couldn’t get medical supplies because they
were all made in China.
And when they finally were able to get medical
supplies from China, there were concerns that
some of those medical supplies were poor quality.\h
Or made with forced labor.
Here’s a crazy idea: Maybe other countries
can make medical supplies that aren’t poor
quality or made from slave labor.\h
Now despite that wake-up call, the idea of
the US decoupling from China has been controversial.\h
While some people think decoupling can happen...
Others say it will backfire.
But one thing’s for sure: the Chinese Communist
Party is terrified of decoupling.
And I’ll show you why after the break.
Welcome back.
The Chinese Communist Party is terrified of
the US decoupling from China.
That’s why Chinese state-run media have
run dozens of articles about why decoupling
is bad.
The US decoupling with China is a misjudgment.\h
Decoupling is not feasible.\h
It’s unrealistic and harmful.\h
But it will only harm the US.\h
And anyway, it’s doomed to fail.\h
You get the idea.\h
So Chinese officials are a tad bit concerned
about the US decoupling from China.
Which is why in this new 14th five-year plan,
they are seeking complete economic self-reliance.
According to my favorite state-run media,
the Global Times, China will “focus on boosting
the domestic supply chain and homegrown innovation
to become completely self-reliant in economy
and core technologies.”
Now you might think, hold on, doesn’t complete
economic self-reliance sound like China is
decoupling from other countries?\h
Well that’s where you’re wrong!\h
It’s totally not decoupling.
Economic self-reliance through this “dual
circulation” strategy is one that the Chinese
Communist Party has been talking about since
May.
“This model entails engaging international
capital, financial, and technological markets
when advantages can be gained while simultaneously
bolstering indigenous capabilities to avoid
over-reliance on the global economy.”
So don’t worry, foreign investors.
The Chinese Communist Party still wants your
money.
Over the weekend, the Party published a speech
from Chinese leader Xi Jinping in their official
policy journal, Qiushi.
Which in English means “Seeking Truth”.
It makes sense because the Communist Party
needs to seek the truth in order to find it..
and then hide it better.\h\h
Xi Jinping actually gave this speech back
in April, but the fact that Qiushi published
it now means it’s directly related to the
Communist Party’s new 5-year plan.\h
So what did Xi talk about?
A lot of it was about everybody’s favorite
topic: supply chains.
Wait!
Don’t change the channel.
This is important.\h
“Xi Jinping called for setting up independent
and controllable supply chains to ensure industrial
and national security.”
You know, this is one of those rare occasions
when I say, maybe we could learn something
from the Chinese Communist Party here.
I mean, sure they’re great at starting personality
cults and purging their enemies, but they
definitely know their supply chains, too.
So when Xi Jinping calls for supply chains
that are “independent, controllable, safe,
and reliable,” that’s not a bad idea.
After all, a large part of the US decoupling
from China is also about having supply chains
in the US that are “independent, controllable,
safe and reliable.”
Which from America’s perspective means supply
chains that are not controlled by China.
In Xi Jinping’s speech, he also said that
the Communist Party must “tighten the dependence
of the international industrial supply chain
on China, and form a strong counter-measure
and deterrent ability for foreign parties
to artificially cut off supply.”
Basically, Xi wants China to be able to
counter any attempts to cut off China’s
imports of necessary goods through sanctions.\h
Here’s an example of what he’s afraid
of: Last year the US tightened sanctions on
Chinese telecom company Huawei.
Those sanctions prevented companies from selling
Huawei US technology.
Or selling Huawei things that were made with
US technology, even if those things were not
made in the US.
Like semiconductor chips.
Those sanctions slowed Huawei’s sales growth.
But even worse for Huawei, they started running
out of smartphone chips because of the sanctions.\h
So now Huawei is trying to set up a chip plant
in China that would not use any US technology.
So that’s one reason why Chinese officials
are afraid of US decoupling.
They don’t want the US to be able to cut
off goods to China.\h
But the other part of Xi Jinping’s statement
is also illuminating.
In addition to preventing other countries
from cutting off China’s supply, Xi said
that the Communist Party must “tighten the
dependence of the international industrial
supply chain on China.”
So while China is becoming less dependent
on the rest of the world, they also want to
make the rest of the world *more* dependent
on China.
I’ll explain how after the break.
Welcome back.
China wants to be less dependent on other
countries, while making other countries more
dependent on China.
By doing things like dominating medical supplies.
Or becoming the biggest trading partner for
countries and making them dependent on buying
stuff from China, and selling stuff to China.\h
Even if other countries are not completely
dependent on China, it’s enough to make
them believe that it would be too painful
and costly to lose China as a trade partner.
A good example is Australia, which exports
a lot of goods to China.
China and Australia are in the middle of a
diplomatic and trade dispute.
It picked up steam back in April after Australia
called for an independent investigation into
the origins of the coronavirus.
Since then, Chinese officials have placed
import bans on a bunch of Australian goods.\h
Those bans could stop 6 billion Australian
dollars worth of goods.
This week, tons of live Australian lobsters
were left stranded at an airport in China.
Won’t somebody think of the lobsters?!
Meanwhile, Chinese state-run media have directly
said that China is importing less from Australia
because of Australia’s political stance.
So with the Chinese Communist Party essentially
trying to use trade to bully Australia, maybe
Australia should think of ways to diversify
its exports to other countries.\h
Doesn’t anyone else want Australian lobsters?
But according to a former Australian ambassador
to China, Australia’s economic dependency
on China will not change.
He said that Australia needs to find a way
to reset the relationship with China.\h
Because “talk about Australia significantly
diversifying its economic relationship with
China by turning to other markets is ‘nothing
other than wishful thinking.’”
So the former ambassador’s message is that
Australia is always going to be dependent
on China and there’s nothing Australia can
do about it except be nicer to China.
At this point you might be thinking, is this
guy working for China?
Close.
He runs a China business advisory firm.
And he’s on the board of a Chinese-owned
coal mining company in Australia.\h
With former ambassadors like these, who needs
enemies?
But the point is that the Chinese Communist
Party’s strategy in the five year plan,
as directly stated by Xi Jinping, is to make
China a self-reliant economy while keeping
the rest of the world’s economy dependent
on China.
You know, sometimes, when Party leaders tell
us what they’re going to do, we should believe
them.
Especially since it looks like Chinese officials
are already doing it to Australia.
And the US will be next.\h
Because remember, America is the real bully.
And now, it’s time for me to answer another
question from one of you, a fan who supports
China Uncensored on the crowd funding website
Patreon.
Jason says, “Chris, Matt, and Shelly should
build the Zhongnanhai in minecraft, fill it
with commies, and then they drop millions
upon millions of tons of TnT on it.
That's the quality content i pay monthly to
see
Well that’s good to know Jason.
So in a recent episode called China Is Targeting
Americans about how China is threatening to
kidnap Americans, I lament that people seem
more interested in watching Minecraft lets
plays than China Uncensored.\h
That’s a video from Mumbo Jumbo, one of
my favorite Minecrafters.
And so many of you have been suggesting Matt,
Shelley and I start our own Minecraft lets
play.
That is something we *could* do.
But is that something you *want* us to do?
Let me know in the comments.
And Jason, if enough people agree with you,
maybe you will be seeing us build Zhongnanhai
in Minecraft.
I have no idea how long that would take.
Probably way too long.\h
Thanks for the suggestion Jason.
And if you like the show, be like Jason and
support China Uncensored through the crowdfunding
website Patreon.
And I might answer your question at the end
of an episode.
Or build your face in Minecraft.
Thank you for watching.
And did you know, 60% of you who watch China
Uncensored are not subscribed to our channel?
If you’re watching, please, hit the subscribe
button.
It’s a huge help to the show.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.