On this episode of China Uncensored,
five Hollywood movies infiltrated by China.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Hollywood seems to have a
difficult time dealing with Asia.
Mickey Rooney as a Japanese man!
Who could have imagined that
taping your eyelids and wearing buck toothed
dentures
to play a living stereotype
would be in poor taste?
But we've moved way beyond that now.
These days,
whenever a story calls for an Asian character,
Hollywood just casts a white actor
and tells everyone that they're Celtic.
It’s called whitewashing -
taking ethnic characters and making them white.
And who cares what anyone thinks?
You can see more on that here.
But at the same time,
Hollywood cares very much about what China
thinks.
And that’s because China is poised to become
the world’s largest movie market soon.
At a predicted 8.3 billion dollars for this
year,
China’s box office is already number two,
just a few billion away from catching up with
the US.
But the Communist Party of China
only allows 34 foreign films a year.
And they’re subject to strict censorship
requirements.
So that means,
before the next Hollywood blockbuster goes
into production,
studios go to great lengths to ensure their
movies
won’t hurt the feelings of the Chinese censors.
Yeah! Now that a more bettah!
Like when Angelina Jolie
was promoting Maleficent in Shanghai.
A reporter asked who’s her favorite Chinese
director.
She named Ang Lee,
and then said,
“I am not sure if you consider Ang Lee Chinese;
he’s Taiwanese!”
Well that made everyone pretty ang-ry
because that seemed to imply
that Taiwan was somehow a separate entity
from Mainland China,
just because it has its own government,
currency,
and Olympic team.
One Weibo user even called Jolie
a “deranged Taiwan independence supporter.”
Disney was concerned
this could affect their movies chances in
China.
So they made Jolie go on a publicity tour
in Shanghai.
Moral of the story,
Maleficent made 48 million dollars in China.
Money is a moral, right?
But it’s not just celebrities that need
to be careful.
Everyone watching an American movie now needs
to be careful, too.
Because there’s a pretty good chance that
the next blockbuster you watch
will have been changed to appease the Chinese
Communist Party.
And here are 5 Hollywood movies that already
happened to.
Number 5
Great Wall
The biggest production in China’s film making
history!
It’s set 1000 years in the past,
and Matt Damon helps save China from monsters.
Matt Damon.
Something like that.
But there’s more to the story than whitewashing.
The movie is produced mainly
by Legendary Entertainment,
the people who brought you Jurassic World
and Interstellar.
Legendary is an American company,
but it was bought earlier this year by the
Dalian Wanda Group,
the same Chinese company that owns
the biggest theater chain the world.
Will the Great Wall finally give the Chinese
government
the soft power movie they crave?
I just hope they give us Matt Damon back.
Number 4
Iron Man 3
So when the main villain
—or is he?—
is based on an offensive Chinese stereotype,
you can understand why that would be changed.
But Iron Man 3 takes it a step further.
For the Chinese release, they added a four minute new scene
featuring two famous Chinese actors
saving Tony Stark's life.
And don’t forget the product placement!
Enjoy Yili Milk today!
Remember that one.
Disney also partnered with
Beijing-based DMG Entertainment.
Not only did that help Iron Man 3
break past the 34 foreign film limit,
it also meant Disney got a bigger share of
the profits—
40% of the profits instead of just 25%.
Yeah,
the Chinese regime normally only lets foreign
movies
keep 25% of the box office revenue.
Robert Downey Jr,
the actor who plays Iron Man,
also went to Beijing for a press conference.
“I'm interested in all things Chinese,”
he said,
“and I live a very Chinese life in America.”
By which I can only assume
he means working for 5 dollars a day,
dealing with corrupt local officials,
and staying away from political issues
to avoid having his organs harvested.
Number 3
Independence Day: Resurgence
How do you make the sequel
to the highest grossing movie of 1996 a hit
in a country it was never shown in?
Well, for one,
get rid of that whole “America saves the
world” theme.
Instead,
why not have China and the US work together
as part of the Earth Space Defense
to defeat the aliens?
Be sure to throw in Hong Kong pop star Angelababy.
And let’s not forget \hMoon Milk,
a competitor to the Yili Milk
from Iron Man 3.
In fact,
Independence Day Resurgence features so much Chinese product placement
that even my favorite state-run media,
the Global Times,
makes fun of it.
On the plus side,
this level of teamwork did help get the movie
a same-day release in China and the US.
Pretty rare,
since usually there’s a long censorship
process involved.
Fortunately,
they just made censorship part of the script
writing.
Number 2
World War Z
The great thing about this movie is,
even if you read the book,
it will still seem fresh!
Because it’s an entirely different story.
Spoilers for the book:
The zombie virus that sweeps the world
begins in China.
It’s spread through the Chinese military’s
black market organ trade.
The Chinese regime covers it up
by launching a war on Taiwan.
Civil war breaks out as top officials
mobilize the army to protect their own skin,
leaving the rest of the country to burn.
That only ends
when a rogue Chinese nuclear submarine
nukes the Politburo Standing Committee.
Now, spoilers for the movie…
there are none.
It’s already been spoiled
because literally nothing in the book is in
the film.
This was all done
in the hopes of getting a China release—
which they did not get.
I mean, nuke the Politburo!
Plus, the Chinese regime has had problems
with Brad Pitt
ever since he was in that movie
about that separatist leader,
the wolf in monk’s robes,
the Dalai Lama.
So yeah,
that movie was never going to get a piece
of the Chinese market.
And finally, Number 1
Transformers: Age of Extinction
Not just the toys are made in China.
was a co-production between Paramount pictures,
a Chinese company, Jiaflix Enterprises,
and, get this,
state-run newscaster and Communist Party mouthpiece, CCTV!
That means the Chinese Communist Party was
directly involved.
And you might just be able
to make out their fingerprints on the film.
For instance,
the villains of the film are the American
government,
specifically the CIA.
That hurts.
One US authority puts a gun to the hero’s
daughter’s head
to get him to reveal information.
The main villain is manipulating the US government.
His appeal to “national security”
is really just a cover for a secret project
he’s got with a big corporation that will
make him rich.
And he’s willing to kill for it.
As popular entertainment magazine Variety
wrote,
“My first reaction to “Age of Extinction”
was
that it was an astonishingly unpatriotic film.
But I was wrong.
‘Transformers: Age of Extinction’ is a
very patriotic film.
It’s just Chinese patriotism on the screen,
not American.”
Because how do Chinese authorities come off?
Well,
when aliens attack Hong Kong,
who you gonna call? The Chinese central government!
And then the Chinese defense minister comes along
and vows to protect Hong Kong.
Just a few months after the movie came out,
tens of thousands of Hong Kong protesters
spoke out
against that very same Chinese “central
government”
for destroying their freedoms and way of life.
Then there’s this scene.
Even when running from CIA assassins,
there’s always time to stop for Shuhua milk,
made by our old friends at Yili!
And here you have Mark Wahlberg
stopping to use the ATM at his favorite bank—
China Construction Bank—
in Texas.
And what did they get for teaming up
with the Chinese government
to make anti-American propaganda?
300 million dollars,
surpassing China’s previous top grossing
movie,
Avatar.
Moral of the story is—
money!
In fact,
Paramount must really have enjoyed the experience
working with the Chinese regime.
That might be why the Dalian Wanda Group
is trying to buy a 1 billion dollar stake
to 49% of Paramount.
But this all is just the tip of the iceberg.
Check out our upcoming episode
where we dig deeper into how China’s cultural
takeover
of Hollywood is part of the Communist Party’s
larger plans
to influence and surpass the US.
So what do you think of the silver screen
turning red?
Leave your comments below.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time!
This episode of China Uncensored is sponsored by Yili Milk!