China Tries to Throw Its Weight Around
By Demanding G20 Countries
Don’t talk about Hong Kong
Will they stay silent?
Welcome to China Uncensored. I’m Chris Chappell.
China has demanded countries around the world
not bring up Hong Kong at the G20 Summit.
But the Hong Kong people have something to
say about that.
The situation in Hong Kong has become
an international embarrassment for the Chinese
Communist Party.
In early June, 1 million Hong Kongers
took to the streets to protest an extradition
bill
that could allow Hong Kong authorities to
send people
to mainland China for trial.
They saw the bill as a threat to their way
of life.
Then after continued protests were
met with police firing tear gas and rubber
bullets into the crowd,
the Hong Kong government announced it would
postpone the bill,
but not officially withdraw it.
So *2 million* Hong Kongers took to the streets
to protest.
People in Hong Kong really don’t trust the
Chinese Communist Party.
So Beijing made some mistakes
in how they handled the situation in Hong
Kong.
And like most of us, they absolutely don’t
want
anyone else to bring up their mistakes.
Especially not at the upcoming G20 summit
in Osaka, Japan.
“What I can tell you for sure is that G20
will not discuss the Hong Kong issue.
We will also not allow G20 to discuss the
Hong Kong issue.”
The G20 is an annual meeting of the leaders
from some of the biggest economies in the
world.
And these other countries might not be too
happy
about being told what they can talk about.
I mean, no one’s ever gotten President Trump
to not talk about something he wants to talk
about.
Especially on Twitter.
And according to US Secretary of State Mike
Pompeo,
Trump is going to discuss Hong Kong with Chinese
leader
Xi Jinping when they meet during the summit.
Ahead of the G20, about 1500 Hong Kongers
spent the day in a marathon march to the consulates
of all 20 countries...except, well, China.
And while China says Hong Kong is purely an
internal affair…
“Hong Kong matters are purely an internal
affair for China.”
Hong Kongers are actually asking for some
foreign interference.
Hong Kong is too small for China.
We need international powers to help.
We need foreign forces to help.
It’s America!
Outside of the US Consulate,
protest organizers called on the US to use
its influence.
In desperation, we seek your engagement and
assistance t
o fight back this authoritarian regime with
us.
The US state department expressed grave concern
about our situation and we cannot be more
appreciative of the care...
We humbly ask that you could further extend
our plea to the other heads of state in particularly
President Xi during the G20 talks, and stand
behind Hong Kong’s autonomy.
Representatives from 16 of the G20 countries
came out
to accept letters from the protesters.
Protesters were looking to remind these countries
that Hong Kong’s situation is an international
issue.
And they had some thoughts about the Chinese
regime’s demands.
So what do you think about China telling other
countries
not to bring up Hong Kong during the G20?
It's not up to him.
It's not up to China because it's a international
conference.
Of course, China cannot dictate the voices
or the discussion in the international society.
I feel like the way that they are doing
it is actually showing their authoritarian
style
I don't know how they can do that.
If any of the leader try to raise a question,
I don't know how they can refuse to answer
or just try to ignore it.
The more you say you should not bring it up,
the more you try to conceal what's happening,
it brings even more international notice.
That’s a good point.
Maybe the Chinese Communist Party
should try some reverse psychology.
The could tell everyone they will *totally
allow* the G20 to discuss Hong Kong.
Regardless, the Chinese Communist Party
won’t be too happy about Hongkongers going
around
asking other countries to help “liberate”
Hong Kong.
Unless they’re referring to the People’s
Liberation Army.
But protesters didn’t stop with just a marathon
petition protest.
They also held an online fundraising campaign
to buy full-page ads in major international
newspapers during the G20.
They asked for 3 million Hong Kong dollars.
They raised more than 6.7 million. In less
than 12 hours.
So far, they’ve confirmed ads with
the New York Times and the Globe and Mail,
among others.
Hey, China never said newspapers couldn’t
talk about Hong Kong, right?
Now is not a great time for the Chinese Communist
Party.
It’s not just the massive public displays
of civil disobedience in Hong Kong.
It’s also increased international attention
on the persecution of the Uighurs,
And organ harvesting of Falun Gong practitioners.
If this continues, the Chinese regime
may have to change its strategy from demanding
other countries don’t bring up its human
rights abuses,
to sticking fingers in its ears and going
la la la, I can’t hear you.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell coming to
you from Hong Kong.
See you next time.