Trump calls Xi Jinping The King of China
Taiwan scrambles as Chinese jets invade their
airspace.
And China gets personal on Grindr.
That and more on this week’s China news
headlines.
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
This week’s China news headlines.
On Tuesday, President Trump spoke at
the National Republican Congressional Committee
spring dinner.
You know, dinner and a show.
What more could you want.
His speech hit the usual fan favorites—
China has been ruining the country,
but it’s not really China’s fault,
it’s bad US leadership.
Bad previous US leadership that is.
But then he dropped this very unusual anecdote.
“I was in China, making a speech,
President Xi, who is a strong man,
I call him king.
He says, 'but I am not king,
I am president.'
I said no, you're president for life,
and therefore, you're king.
He said, ‘Huh.
Huh, I like that.’”
I believe we actually have footage of Xi’s
response.
“Oh ho ho thank you!”
Last year,
Xi Jinping got term limits removed from the
presidency,
making him effectively president for life.
So he’s more than a president,
but also not quite a dictator.
Which is why I call him the presitator.
But Trump’s story about calling Xi
a king shows Trump’s unique ability
to sound like he might be complimenting you
while also possibly trashing you.
Does calling him king help or hurt Xi?
Hard to say.
Xi Jinping is locked in a battle for control
of China
with a rival political faction tied to former
Chinese leader
and toad king Jiang Zemin.
One of the weapons Jiang’s faction uses
against Xi
is portraying him like he’s trying to become
a new emperor.
Having the president of the United States
call him king and saying that he liked it,
could put Xi in an awkward position.
Does that mean Xi Jinping could be less willing
to make a deal with Trump on trade?
I have no idea.
Former Pentagon leaders released this statement,
warning of the risks of Chinese 5G.
5G is the future of wireless communication.
None of us really know how it works,
but we do know: It’s the future!
But if Chinese companies like Huawei
are building these networks,
that could be a problem.
That letter bluntly lays out the risk to national
security.
It says “As military leaders who have commanded
U.S.
and allied troops around the world,
we have grave concerns about a future
where a Chinese-developed 5G network
is widely adopted among our allies and partners.”
Current defense leaders are also warning about
Chinese 5G.
Ellen Lord, the Under Secretary of Defense
for Acquisition and Sustainment,
recently said Chinese 5G is such a serious
issue,
it could change US alliances on a fundamental
level.
She said at a conference last week,
“If our allies and partners go with a Huawei
solution,
we need to reconsider how we share
critical information with them.”
Specifically, the US is part of
what’s called the “Five Eyes”—
an intelligence network that also includes
Australia, Canada, New Zealand, and the UK.
But don’t worry,
it’s not like any of them would consider
using Huawei.
Ugh, guys!
Of course, you can’t totally blame
New Zealand and the UK.
Well, actually you can.
But the problem is,
the US hasn’t developed its own
end-to-end 5G service provider.
Major US telecom companies have said t
hey won’t use Chinese 5G providers
like Huawei or ZTE.
But they still need to rely on
European telecom companies.
So the lack of options definitely gives
Chinese competitors an advantage.
Fortunately, I’ve come up with
an unhackable system of telecommunication.
And for email,
I have an equally unhackable system.
You know how I’ve been talking about
how China plans to invade Taiwan?
Well, Chinese fighter jets
just flew over the maritime border
between the two countries, slash regions.
And so Taiwan scrambled its own jets
to confront the Chinese fighters.
That’s according to this statement
from Taiwan’s Ministry of Foreign Affairs.
This is how the world ends, people!
Not with a bang,
but with a tweet.
Now it hasn’t yet been confirmed
if the Chinese jets did it intentionally.
It’s been almost 20 years since
the last time that happened.
But it does come just a few days after
a similar incident near Japan.
Japan had to send out its fighters
after 4 Chinese bombers flew near,
but not quite through,
Japanese airspace.
But again, it could be unintentional.
Maybe Chinese pilots just got lost...
because they were using the new
made-in-China GPS navigation.
A Chinese woman was arrested after entering
Donald Trump’s Florida resort Mar-a-Lago.
She was, “carrying four cellphones
and a thumb drive infected with malware,”
into Mar-a-Lago while Trump was visiting
over the weekend.
That’s according to federal court records.
The woman had said she was there to use the
pool.
But then security wondered why
she didn’t bring a swimsuit.
I mean, I think the four cell phones is more
suspicious.
But maybe they were just curious
what she planned to do without a swimsuit.
Anyway, when she was questioned by Secret
Service,
she said she was there for a United Nations
friendship event that evening.
Turns out, that event that did not exist.
Which is so weird,
because she had been told about it by her
friend Charles.
You know, Charles!
I mean, she only ever spoke to him by text,
so there was no way Secret Service
could actually learn anything about this Charles
guy,
but I don’t know.
Something about the name suggests to me
that this Charles guy is in charge.
Now I’m not saying that this woman was a
spy.
Because that seems like a truly incompetent
level of spycraft.
She might just be a huge Trump groupie
who wanted to get close to that beautiful
mane of hair.
At any rate, she wasn’t charged with espionage.
Just lying to a federal agent
and gaining access to a restricted area.
And frankly,
it’s unlikely that the woman ever would
have
been able to get the malware
to an area used by the President, since,
according to the Secret Service,
“Entering the resort does not permit access
to areas used by the president,
which require additional security screening.”
It was almost the perfect plan.
Except for all the ways it failed.
The Trump administration is interested in
Grindr.
For national security concerns, obviously.
Grindr is a popular gay dating app.
And it was mysteriously bought by a Chinese
company
two years ago.
That’s why, the Committee on Foreign Investment
in the U.S
“began investigating Grindr as early as
July 2018
because of concerns about the security
of sensitive user data collected by the app,
which included the HIV status
of millions of gay people around the world.”
For example, the Chinese government could
use
the HIV status of someone in the US military
as blackmail.
But how would this information
get from Grindr to the Chinese government?
Well, once Grindr was taken over by a Chinese
company,
they got a new chief technology officer.
And he was really keen on working with
a Chinese state-backed HIV research group.
But in an email sent to employees,
obtained by NBC news,
he wanted to make sure people wouldn’t say
it was about sharing HIV data
with the Chinese government.
Not that they didn’t share data with the
government.
He just didn’t want people to say that.
And finally,
the US has a drug problem.
Drug overdoses are the leading cause
of unintentional death in the United States.
In fact, it’s more than gun homicides
and car accidents combined.
And guess where a lot of these
deadly synthetic drugs are being made?
China!
According to this report by the U.S.-China
Economic and Security Review Commission,
China is \h"the largest source of illicit
fentanyl
and fentanyl-like substances" in the US.
Trump has been pushing Chinese regulators
to go after the source—
laboratories inside China.
And now it seems like that might happen.
“China has announced that all variants of
fentanyl
will be treated as controlled substances.”
The problem in the past was that drug makers
could get around fentanyl bans by just alternating
the chemical structure of the drug slightly,
and then their new drug would technically
not be banned.
But now, Chinese law will consider all fentanyl-related
drugs
to be controlled substances.
That sounds good,
But a drug policy researcher told NPR
that the regulations may not be easy to enforce.
He said, “law enforcement would have to
‘take a sample’ from a facility and eventually
‘analyze whether it's a fentanyl-related
structure.’”
Boy, that sounds like a lot of work.
Instead of taking a sample,
wouldn’t it just be easier to just...
take a bribe?
Besides, Chinese police
are not exactly known for good enforcement.
Well, except when arresting dissidents.
Then they’re great at it.
And before you go,
now is the time I answer a question
from a member of the China Uncensored 50-Cent
Army—
fans who support the show
with a dollar or more per episode
through the crowd funding website Patreon.
Tyler Fausnaught asks
“Would zoos be obligated to pay the panda
fee
if American scientists were to clone a panda?
If so, what international law binds us
to obey China's global panda hegemony?
Perhaps we could donate the cloned panda
to a zoo in Taiwan.
Wouldn't it be worth it
just to see the CCP pitch a fit?”
Tyler, you are perhaps a mad genius!
But technically, wouldn’t the clone,
being genetically identical to its “parent”,
still belong to China?
I don’t know,
science is making things weird and complicated.
But anyway,
I can’t see any American scientist
trying to clone a panda
without getting China’s permission,
and I can’t imagine that permission
being given without any further obligations.
Panda diplomacy is just too valuable a tool
for the Chinese Communist Party.
The ultimate in soft, cuddly power.
Not that I’d want to cuddle a panda.
What am I,
the prime minister of Canada?
But would I personally encourage a scientist
to violate the laws of nature,
and play God just to troll the CCP?
I’ll have to think about that one.
Thanks for you question, Tyler.
If you’d like to hear your question answered
on the show,
sign up to support China Uncensored
through the crowd funding website Patreon.
It’s less than the cost of your daily cup
of coffee.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.