A once beautiful relationship
broken by the coronavirus!
Is there any future for US-China relations?
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Tensions between the US and China
are at an all-time high
because of the coronavirus,
which a lot of people are now calling the
“CCP Virus.”
Everyone’s doing it! Even a columnist for
the Washington Post.
That’s because the Chinese Communist Party,
the CCP,
spent the first crucial months of the outbreak
covering it up.
That allowed the coronavirus to spread around
the world.
And that’s why we’re in the situation
we’re in today...
where the world has to postpone the next Wonder
Woman movie.
And if that doesn’t affect you, maybe this
will—
the Final Fantasy 7 remake may be delayed.
And thus, World War 3 began:
China vs the Weebs.
The US-China relationship was already strained,
ever since the US decided to stop rolling
over
for the Chinese regime’s intellectual property
theft,
espionage, unfair trade practices, currency
manipulation,
and well...it’s a long list.
But the coronavirus may have pushed
the relationship to the breaking point.
“As the world declares war on the coronavirus,
another battle has erupted between two of
its great powers—
China and the United States.”
President Trump has responded with fire and
fury.
“But I'm a little upset with China. I’ll
be honest with you.”
Ok, that was less fury and more mild displeasure.
So far, Trump is not backing down on trade
tariffs.
But that could change.
The Trump Administration is seeking comments
from the American public
on whether to temporarily lift
some of the tariffs because of the coronavirus.
My public comment is: Don’t do it.
It’ll just make us more dependent on China
again.
Meanwhile, the Chinese Communist Party
is expelling American journalists from China.
And it’s going on a propaganda offensive,
including trying to blame the whole coronavirus
thing
on the US military.
So President Trump decided to make it clear
the epidemic started in China
by calling it the “Chinese Virus.”
“The Chinese virus.”
Chinese state-run media called him racist.
And then Western media started calling him
racist.
Well, they called him racist again, but because
of this.
"Why do you keep calling this 'the Chinese
virus'?
Why do you keep using this?"
"Because it comes from China."
"A lot of people say it's racist."
"It's not racist at all, no.
Not at all.
It comes from China.
That's why.
I want to be accurate."
But now Trump has said he’ll stop using
the term “Chinese Virus.”
Prompting a victory lap from Chinese state-run
media.
Maybe that means Trump will adopt the term
that all the cool kids are using:
CCP Virus.
He might as well,
since things aren’t getting any smoother
between the two countries.
Secretary of State Mike Pompeo says China
is still withholding information about the
coronavirus.
“My concern is that this cover-up,
this disinformation that the Chinese Communist
Party is engaged in,
is still denying the world the information
it needs so that we can prevent further cases
or something like this from recurring again.”
And Texas Congressman and Republican member
of the House Foreign Affairs Committee\hMichael
McCaul
took to Fox News to say this.
“In my view this was one of the worst coverups
in history.”
It’s even worse than how NASA covered up
the flat earth!
By building a round earth.
But the anger with the Chinese regime
is not just from Republicans.
This is a bipartisan effort.
I love how China brings us together.
But perhaps what terrifies the Chinese Communist
Party the most
is a growing sentiment for moving US companies
out of China.
The Chinese regime loves to act tough,
but it knows it needs US money to fuel its
own economy,
especially after the coronavirus hit.
Even Western universities,
which for years have depended on Chinese students
as a source of income,
are getting a little wary.
But the Chinese Communist Party has one ace
up its hole.
Wait, how does that saying go?
Anyway, they’ve found an American performer
who is able
to articulate the superiority of China’s
coronavirus fight.
As Chinese state-run media puts it,
“American rapper Cardi B shows support
for China's coronavirus fight.”
“When they put Wuhan China in quarantine
the coronavirus cases is going lower,
that's because they spray s--- over the street...
While we quarantine in our home,
what is the government doing,
like spraying s— in the streets,
y'all gonna start taking our temperatures,
you're all going to like one by one
take our temperatures and what not,
see if we got it or not.
Cause like, how am I supposed to know if i
got the coronavirus.”
Wait, I’m sorry. Is that showing support
for China?
I mean, I guess the US government could be
spraying
more s--- in the streets.
Frankly, I liked it better when Chinese state
media
were blaming the coronavirus on the US military.
So what do you think of
what’s become of the US-China relationship?
Leave your comments below.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
thanks for watching China Uncensored.