The Central Threat of our Times
is the Chinese Communist Party.
And a coverup of the Wuhan Coronavirus.
That and more today’s China News Headlines.
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
This week’s China news headlines!
First up, the Wuhan coronavirus.
We’re not going to tell you what the latest
numbers are,
because the situation is moving so quickly,
by the time you watch this video,
they will be different.
But we can tell you more about the coverup.
Remember those eight people who were detained
by police
for “spreading rumors” about the coronavirus
back in December?
It turns out, they were all doctors!
The Beijing Youth Daily interviewed the original
doctor
who spread the so-called rumor.
It turns out, the doctor
“had warned a WeChat group of former medical
school classmates
about seven patients from a local wet market”
who were exhibiting symptoms that he initially
thought was SARS.
After screenshots from the private group leaked
on social media,
“The doctor was summoned to a police station
and forced to confess his error
and pledge not to repeat it.”
So were the other doctors in the group chat,
apparently.
According to the Beijing Youth Daily,
the doctor is now himself in an isolation
ward
after he fell ill while treating patients.
As you can imagine,
this news has contributed to the ongoing backlash
against Chinese officials for covering up
news about the virus.
People are so unhappy,
that even the Supreme People’s Court has
published an article
about how that the police were wrong for detaining
the doctor.
The good news is, the Chinese Communist Party
has obviously learned their lesson about the
need
for greater openness in this time of crisis.
Which is why the Party has ordered the article
about the doctor
be deleted from the internet.
Nothing to see here, folks.
Ok, so maybe propaganda can’t defeat the
new coronavirus.
But you know what can?
Drones.
Specifically, drones that yell at you.
Yes, auntie, this is the drone speaking to
you.
You shouldn’t walk about without wearing
a mask.
Yes, you’d better go back home and don’t
forget to wash your hands.
You see we’ve been telling people to stay
at home but you still wander outside.
Now a drone is watching you.
My favorite state-run media, The Global Times,
published this compilation of drones in China
policing people
and telling them to wear masks,
or go back home.
Clearly, the best way to keep people healthy
is to scare the bejeezus out of them,
and then post that footage on China’s version
of TikTok.
Hey kid! We are in unusual times!
Don’t stroll around outside!
You don’t even wear a mask.
Hurry up and go back home!
The coronavirus is very serious...
Run!! Don’t come outside.
Staying home is contributing to society.
That little girl just got yelled at by a drone.
She’s never leaving her house again.
In non coronavirus news,
US Secretary of State Mike Pompeo
had some pretty harsh words for China.
“The Chinese Communist Party presents the
central threat of our times.”
Central threat?
Personally, I feel like it’s that second
helping of pancakes.
Sure, it tastes great.
But don’t expect your day to be productive
anymore.
And too much of it will probably give you
a heart attack.
But Pompeo has reason for singling out the
Chinese Communist Party.
The chairman of Harvard’s Chemistry Department
Charles Lieber
was arrested on charges of lying about
getting millions of dollars in Chinese funding.
He’s a pioneer in the field of nanotechnology.
That’s something the Chinese Communist Party
is extremely interested in.
And I know about mostly through Metal Gear.
The nanomachines inside soldiers bodies adapt
to different conditions,
promoting the release of neurotransmitters,
hormones, and stimulants,
giving them an edge in battle.
The US was funding Lieber’s research with
$15 million dollars.
At the same time,
he was part of China’s Thousand Talents
Plan.
As part of that,
a Chinese tech university gave him $1.5 million
dollars
to set up a research lab in China.
“The school also agreed to pay him a $50,000
monthly salary
and offered about $150,000 in annual living
expenses
for “significant periods” from 2012 to
2017.”
As a side note, that Chinese tech university
was located in Wuhan.
So lucky for him, now that he’s been arrested
in the US,
he won’t have to go back to Wuhan—
where the coronavirus has been spreading.
There were two other people charged
along with professor Charles Lieber:
One is Yanqing Ye,
a Chinese robotics researcher at Boston University.
She had concealed that she was also in the
Chinese army.
The other is Zaosong Zheng.
He’s a cancer researcher who was caught
traveling to China
with 21 vials of biological samples.
There’s also been a string of Chinese “students”
getting caught spying at the Key West Navy
Base.
Pretty freaky stuff.
There’s also been an increase in trademark
theft
committed by Chinese factories.
According to China Law Blog,
Chinese factories are stealing intellectual
property
much faster than even a year ago.
It comes as they fear US companies
will move their manufacturing out of China
because the trade war has made China production
more expensive.
Despite warnings from the US,
the UK has given the go ahead Chinese telecom
giant Huawei
to build part of its 5G network.
I believe we have footage of the UK’s prime
minister on this issue:
Tell me why.
Ain't nothin' but a heartache.
Ain’t nothing but a mistake.
I never want to hear you say...
But I want it Huawei.
Huawei has connections to the Chinese military.
This makes the entire UK telecom system vulnerable.
And that also puts the US system at risk by
proxy,
as well as jeopardizing the entire Five Eyes.
That’s a security alliance between the US,
UK,
Canada, Australia, and New Zealand.
So the UK’s decision is very, very stupid.
Do they not get China Uncensored in the UK?
And the European Union is also rather stupid
about this whole thing.
The European Commission has set new guidelines
that basically leave the decision to use or
ban Huawei
up to individual countries.
Letting countries make their own decisions
is not a problem per se.
But it’s a concern in this case because\hthe
Chinese regime
has been working to pick apart the EU country
by country.
Through investment deals, which often include
Huawei deals,
China is able to buy off European countries.
Greece is a great example.
After heavy Chinese investment in its struggling
economy,
Greece blocked the EU from criticizing China’s
human rights record.
Now, China is using Huawei as a wedge issue
across Europe.
Germany is especially at risk.
German Chancellor Angela Merkel has favored
a Huawei deal.
It’s nice to know that despite Brexit,
Boris and Angela still have one thing in common.
Merkel is pushing for Huawei
even against the recommendations of her own
intelligence agencies.
In other words…
“The Chinese Communist Party presents the
central threat of our times.”
And that does it for this week’s China News
headlines.
What do you think?
Let me know in the comments below.
Be sure to subscribe and hit that bell icon
so you’ll get notified when new episodes
come out.
And as I’ve mentioned before,
YouTube often demonetizes episodes like this,
because they’re too controversial.
We would have been run out of business years
ago,
if it weren’t for fan support
through the crowd funding website Patreon.
So as a thank you to these fans,
I answer their questions at the end of some
of my episodes.
This question comes from Kevin Oberdick.
“How did the KMT Party morph into a pro-unification
party?
Is Chiang Kai-shek rolling over in his grave?
Or, what am I missing?”
Very interesting question.
So the KMT party was the party of the Republic
of China.
They were the government of China
before the Chinese Communist Party won the
Chinese Civil War,
and the KMT retreated to Taiwan.
Today Taiwan is a multi-party democracy,
so the KMT is just one of many parties.
But it is known as generally a more Beijing-friendly
party.
So how did the mortal enemy of the CCP have
such a drastic turn around?
Well, that’s a pretty clear example of just
how successful
the Chinese Communist Party is at infiltrating
groups and subverting them.
Money is a big part of it.
The KMT argues that Taiwan needs closer economic
ties to China
for the economy.
And maybe KMT politicians get some money for
that view along the way.
There are claims that China spent 200 million
dollars in the last election
to support the KMT candidate.
But also, keep in mind there’s a spectrum
to the current KMT.
No prominent KMT politician is arguing
for a one country two systems arrangement
like Hong Kong.
At least not any more.
Some, as I said,
genuinely believe the Taiwanese economy
requires close dealing with the Communist
Party.
I mean, the best way to make money is to work
with Communists,
we all know that.
Others still have this sort of old timey nationalistic
feeling
that Taiwan and China should unify in some
way.
So it would be a little unfair to say
that every KMT member is pro-Communist.
Is the former head of the KMT, Chiang Kai-shek,
who fought Mao,
rolling over in his grave?
Well, I can’t say for sure.
Grave robbery is a crime.
And I don’t encourage people to commit crimes.
Well, except thought crimes.
Thanks for your question.
And thank you everyone for watching,
and for supporting China Uncensored.
If you’re not a patron yet,
join our 50-Cent Army!
Go to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored and contribute.
The link is below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.