On this episode of China Uncensored,
Look! Up in the sky!
It’s a bird!
It’s a plane!
It’s the Chinese Dream!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
Bad news everyone.
Superman is dead.
Yes, the Man of Steel, and of Tomorrow,
the Last Son of Krypton
Clark Kent
died tragically of a lingering illness
after once again saving the world.
By his side were Wonder Woman,
Supergirl,
the guy whose mother was also named Martha,
whoever these people are,
and of course, Lois Lane.
Also present at his death
was a bearded version of himself from an alternate
dimension.
I don’t know, it's the comics.
How will DC comics fill this hole in our hearts?
After all, they've only killed Superman nine
or ten times before.
Once when He-Man stabbed him in the chest.
Well, it turns out there's no need to worry,
because DC Comics has a little something up
their sleeve.
This guy!
The New Super-Man.
You know, something looks a little different.
Something that more traditional Superman purists
may take issue with.
Yes, I'm of course talking about
this dash in the middle.
The copy editors are going to be upset over
this one.
Oh, and I don’t think this Superman
will be fighting for Truth, Justice, and the
American way.
Although, does the alignment of the stars
on that Chinese flag look a little off to
anyone else?
Anyway, the fictional Ministry of
Self-Reliance
is able to transfer part of the dying Superman’s
powers to Kenan Kong
Like I said, comics.
Oh there’s also a Chinese batman and wonder
woman.
They’re part of the Justice League of China.
Yeah.
New Super-man is written by Taiwanese-American
Gene Luen Yang,
who is actually pretty awesome.
He’s a former computer science teacher
who started writing comic books.
Kind of important ones like “American Born
Chinese,”
one that I highly recommend.
The Library of Congress has named him
the national ambassador for young people’s
literature.
The point is this guy’s got talent.
And with New Super-Man,
he’s trying some interesting things
to bridge an iconic American property with
traditional Chinese culture.
For one, the traditional triangular chest
emblem
has been replaced with an octagon.
Here’s what he said about that in an interview
with KPCC:
“The octagon is actually a reference to
'bagua,'
which is a Taoist concept,
and it's fundamental to a Chinese view of
the universe.
And that'll play, like Taoism,
Taoist concepts at least, will play a vital role in
this character's journey."
He’s also taking a page from one of the
Four Classics of Chinese literature
Journey to the West.
You see, Kenan Kong starts off as kind of
a bully.
You know who else starts off as a bully?
Sun Wukong, the Monkey King.
“The Monkey King also has a similar story
arc.
He starts off as a bully
and he has this process of enlightenment
where he arrives at a more selfless character.
So by doing this with Kenan Kong,
we are referencing both an American story
— the story of Clark Kent —
and a very Chinese story—the story of the Monkey King."
So that’s all very cool.
And DC Comics has been looking for ways
to add more cultural and ethnic diversity.
One thing that's not clear though,
is whether the New Super-Man will ever be
released in China.
That could be difficult,
unless the comics completely ignore
the political and human rights situation in
China.
And for the people who are concerned that
Super-Man
will end up being a stooge of a communist
government,
well, they already did that one.
The Great American Icon...
Reimagined as a Soviet Hero!
Comics!
But supposedly Kenan Kong’s father was a
social activist
so there could be an interesting story arc
there.
Here he is talking about the importance of
truth, justice, and democracy.
Uh oh.
I hope Super-Man's dad doesn't get invited
to drink tea
with the Ministry of Self Reliance.
I for one am interested in seeing where this
story goes.
Since the Chinese regime doesn’t even like
individual groups amassing power,
somehow I don’t think they’ll be too happy
about a possibly independent-minded super
man.
What do you think about the New Super-Man?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next
time.