On this episode of China Uncensored,
Trade War tit for tat,
Who says re-education is a bad thing?
And finally, everyone sells out Taiwan!
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
There was an explosion on Thursday afternoon
outside the US Embassy in Beijing. According
to the Embassy,
it was set off by one guy with a bomb,
and he only injured himself.
There’s no word yet on what motive
the 26-year-old bomber might have had,
but one thing’s clear:
He’d didn’t do a very good job of getting
his point across.
Beijing police are calling it an “isolated
security incident,”
which means you definitely should not try
to look into it any further.
But you know who the real threat is?
Chinese citizens who attempt to share information
with journalists.
For example, this woman who’s sharing photos
and video of the incident with journalists
on We Chat.
And now here she is being gently
dragged away by plainclothes police,
in\hthis video posted by AFP journalist Becky
Davis.
But don’t worry. Within a few hours,
Chinese censors removed nearly all mentions
of
the explosion from Chinese social media.
And that solves that.
Anything you might have heard about some kind
of a
vaccine scandal going on right now in China—
ignore it!
It’s being totally overblown,
according to Chinese state-run media.
That’s obviously why Chinese censors have
purged
the word “vaccine” from the entire Chinese
Internet.
Because again, there’s no story here.
The editor-in-chief of my favorite Chinese
state-run media,
the Global Times, criticized the small number
of people
who aren’t focusing on how well the government
is doing
in the face of the scandal.
I mean, “incident”.
Yeah, like these lame Chinese parents calling
vaccine-makers devils.
A quarter of a million defective vaccines
were given to children
in China’s Shandong province.
I mean, mistakes happen, right?
The trade war between the US and China is
in full swing.
And the Chinese Communist Party is going tit
for tat.
President Trump announces 34 billion dollars
in tariffs.
The Chinese Communist Party announces 34 billion
dollars in tariffs.
Trump hits back with an additional 200 billion
And the Chinese Communist Party hits back
with...
well, ok, 200 billion dollars is more than
China buys from the US,
so they can’t really match that.
But they still want to hit the US back.
That’s why China’s current 34 billion
in tariffs
aims to specifically punish American farmers.
Not because the Communist Party hates farmers—
but because US farmers tend to be Trump voters.
The Communist Party may not have democracy,
but they sure understand how it works.
So to counteract the effects of Chinese tariffs,
Trump has announced 12 billion dollars worth
of subsidies.
“The size of the aid package is in line
with the estimated
$11 billion cost of the tariffs to American
farmers.”
And guess what? The Communist Party has its
own aid packages
for Chinese companies hurt by US tariffs.
That would be in addition to all the illegal
subsidies
the communist Party already gives to Chinese
companies.
What this all means is,
both sides are hunkering down for a long trade
war.
In other trade war news,
the US and EU are working on a trade deal.
If the US and the EU do strike a deal,
that would give them both more leverage
to focus on trade disputes with China.
As you can imagine, the Chinese regime is
thrilled.
Especially after all the effort they made
to get the EU on their side.
Eat your heart out, Xi Jinping.
Speaking of long, protracted battles,
Mark Zuckerberg has been trying to get Facebook
into China for years.
And frankly, it’s gotten embarrassing.
Whether it’s his casual jog through the
Beijing smog,
or casually leaving a copy of Xi Jinping’s
book
prominently on his desk when a Chinese official
comes to visit,
or casually asking Xi Jinping to name his
first-born child...
well, it finally paid off!
Facebook was given permission to open a subsidiary
in China.
It marks a huge breakthrough for the tech
company.
Wait, what’s that Shelley?
It got shut down after one day?!
It turns out that Facebook had gotten permission
from the local provincial government,
but not from the Cyberspace Administration
of China,
which was like...no.
It might be time for Mark Zuckerberg
to realize that Xi Jinping is just not that
into him.
Wow, Xi Jinping and I actually agree on something.
Um... and be sure to follow China Uncensored
on Facebook!
Hey, that’s not hypocritical.
Hypocritical is Chinese state-run media
running their own Facebook pages,
even while Facebook is banned in China.
Speaking of state-run media,
The Global Times has finally confirmed something
we’ve already known for a long time.
The Communist Party has opened re-education
camps in Xinjiang.
But according to the Global Times,
those camps are a good thing!
You see, Xinjiang in western China is home
to the mostly Muslim Uighur ethnic minority.
And anytime the Chinese Communist Party, say,
collects biometric data from millions of people
there,
or forces people to install software on their
phones
that monitors their text messages,
...and people complain about it,
it’s because they’re Muslim extremists!
And definitely not because they have
legitimate privacy concerns.
I mean, if you’re not a terrorist,
why would you care about privacy?
That’s why, if you complain, they put you
in prison.
As the Global Times puts it,
“Extremists in prison need to transform
their thoughts.
We have invited experts on religion
to rectify their extremist thinking.”
These “extremists” are told to repeat
phrases like,
“My soul is infected with serious diseases.
There is no God. I don’t believe in God.
I believe in the Communist Party.”
Now you might think,
with Chinese Muslims being forced to
abandon Allah for Xi Jinping Thought,
the Islamic leaders of the world
would have something to say about it.
Except, they don’t.
Perhaps it’s because “Many Muslim governments
have strengthened their relationship with
China
or even gone out of their way to support China’s
persecution.”
The Chinese Communist Party gave a July 25
deadline
to foreign airlines to stop listing Taiwan
as a separate country-slash-region on their
websites,
or else.
But do you think airlines bowed down to that
Orwellian Nonsense?
Yes. Yes they did.
But apparently, they didn’t bow deeply enough.
According to the Civil Aviation Administration
of China,
40 out of 44 airlines have successfully complied
with their wishes.
The four airlines who didn’t get 100% on
their geography test?
They were all American.
You see, instead of listing Taipei as part
of China,
these airlines just took off the country designation,
listing Taipei by itself.
Well, Taipei comma...nothing.
There was never anything else there, ok?
But that’s just not A-plus work,
according to the Chinese Communist Party.
You see these US airlines have started to
rectify the issue,
but their “rectification is still incomplete.”
Which does not sound creepy and authoritarian
at all.
What will happen next?
Well, the airlines get a two-week extension,
but China’s Civil Aviation Administration
will be paying close attention.
After all, these US airlines wouldn’t want
to be grounded, would they?
Not only has the Chinese regime’s pressure
affected airlines,
it’s also pushed Taiwan out of hosting the
kids version of the Olympics,
the East Asian Youth Games.
That’s so childish.
Reportedly, it’s because Taiwan wanted to
change the banner
of its official sports teams from “Chinese
Taipei” to “Taiwan”.
Unfortunately this could set a dangerous precedent
for Taiwan—
and democracy in general.
It could make it very hard for Taiwan
to ever host an international sporting event
again.
So don’t hold out for the Taipei Olympics
in 2036.
Unless Taipei is controlled by the Communist
Party by then.
Well, that’s it for this week’s uplifting
headlines.
What do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And before you go, now is the time when we
answer
a question from fans who support China Uncensored
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
Joe Knox asks,
“Jiang Zemin, Toad master,
will he ever be brought to justice?
and what form or retribution would be appropriate?”
Good question Joe.
On the one hand,
Jiang Zemin is a very old man—
almost 92 and he’s not in great health.
As you can see,
he can barely stand.
And I can barely stand him.
But I hope he lives long enough to see the
day justice comes.
But it’s not just about bringing Jiang Zemin
to justice.
The entire faction tied to him is guilty of
crimes against humanity.
Like the system he oversaw where Falun Gong
practitioners,
house Christians, Tibetans, and Uighurs
are killed for their organs in state-run hospitals.
So justice demands more than just his head.
The problem is, putting Jiang Zemin on trial
will expose corruption so massive
and deep within the Chinese Communist Party,
that it could bring the entire system down.
Obviously, that’s not going to be a popular
move
as long as the Communist Party stays in power.
The Party has never admitted wrongdoing for
pretty much anything.
Ok, they admitted that Chairman Mao was 30
percent wrong.
But hey, he was still 70 percent right!
I hope that what eventually happens
is some communist equivalent of the Nuremberg
Trials.
Those were the Nazi trials after World War
2.
Basically, the entire history of Communism
will need to be put on trial,
with the world collectively deciding,
you know what:
100 million dead people later,
communism is probably not a good idea.
Thanks for your question, Joe.
And to everyone watching, remember,
China Uncensored is made possible by support
from viewers like you.
So I’d like to ask you, if you can,
contribute a dollar or more per episode on
our Patreon website,
so we can keep uncensoring China.
The link is below.
Thanks for watching this episode,
once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Hey, if you haven’t heard,
we have a new podcast, China Unscripted.
Myself, Shelley, and Matt the producer,
go into way more detail than we ever could
on the show,
which means more jokes too.
So subscribe to us on iTunes.
Once again that’s China Unscripted.