On this episode of China Uncensored,
ISIS.
They’ve got lots and lots of guns.
And where did those guns come from?
You guessed it:
A lot of them came from China.
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
It turns out ISIS—
the so-called Islamic State—
has been getting a lot of its weapons from
China.
Almost half.
The good news is,
ISIS has taken a real licking in Iraq.
“This is liberation day for Iraq”
ISIS has been nearly completely driven from
Iraq
and politicians say that victory
is close in the entire region.
“The Islamic State’s military organization
in the Levant
is nearly totally defeated.
I am confident that in the coming weeks,
we can reach this military victory
on the ground.”
But not so fast, says Conflict Armament Research—
or CAR.
They’re an organization that uncovers
how terrorist groups like ISIS
get their weapons.
They say that ISIS terrorists still
“pose a grave threat to regional
and international security.”
One reason is that ISIS forces
“are in possession of advanced weapon systems,
which will pose a threat to
regional and international forces
in the years to come.”
And thanks to that,
ISIS still has the “capacity
to conduct insurgency and terrorism
well beyond the region” of the Middle East.
CAR has been investigating how weapons
are falling into the hands of terrorists,
because that helps identify weak links
in supply chains—
ideally, so that weak links can be fixed,
and guns kept away from the bad guys.
This guy with the baseball hat
is Damian Spleeters.
He may look more like
Freddie Mercury than Sherlock Holmes––
but he’s 100% weapons detective.
He looks for clues to find out
where weapons come from.
Nearly all military munitions—
from bullets to missiles—
are marked in some way.
Illegal suppliers often try to destroy
engravings or codes stamped into steel,
but you can still usually identify
where they came from.
And—according to the CAR report—
nearly half of the weapons in the hands
of ISIS fighters come from China.
Yes, 43.5 percent of munitions
documented in Iraq and Syria
were made in China.
They may not be the highest quality,
but far more than from any other country.
These are just some of the lethal toys
ISIS supposedly had its hands on.
“T-55 tanks”
“...122mm BM-21...
these systems can fire
multiple rockets per second
at a range of about 13 miles”
“Chinese HJ-8...
HJ-8s highly effective against armor,
bunkers, and fortifications.”
Now, it’s true that the country of origin—
where weapons are made—
is only half the story.
It’s also important as
how they get into the hands of terrorists.
And according to CAR,
the ones to blame for illegal weapons
getting into the hands of terrorists
aren’t always the ones that make them,
but often the ones that buy them legally
and then illegally supply them
to unauthorized users.
So, what’s crucial is not who makes it,
but how it gets spread around.
Take the US, for example.
Even though only 1.8 per cent of the weapons
in ISIS hands are US-made,
the United States has played a larger role.
According to the report,
the US bought weapons,
mostly from Eastern Europe,
and diverted them to Syrian rebels,
who were fighting against the dictator of
Syria.
And then ISIS got them from the Syrian rebels.
Our battlefield sleuths know this
because they ran a trace on these weapons.
Ok, this is how it works.
When Spleeters or another Sherlock
finds a gun used by ISIS fighters,
he checks the serial number
or other identifying features.
It’s like running the plates.
Say it was made in the US.
He sends the US government a trace request.
If the trace request gets approved—
bang—you can map out the supply chain
and find out where things went wrong.
Thanks to traces approved by governments
that are serious about keeping guns
out of the hands of terrorists,
we know that the United States
bought a bunch of weapons
and then diverted them to Syrian rebels.
It’s not always pretty,
because you sometimes get egg on your face.
But knowing the truth helps the US military
keep weapons out of terrorist hands.
Which is their goal.
But things look a little different
when it comes to a few other countries—
like China.
You see, even though China
made about half of the arms in ISIS hands,
CAR investigators only know how about
7% of these got there.
The Iraqi and Sudanese governments
bought them from China.
Then ISIS stole them.
But how the other 93% or so of Chinese guns
fell into ISIS hands...
that’s a mystery not even our
tattooed Sherlock could solve.
At least not until the Chinese government
agrees to run a trace.
And so far, according to CAR,
that just hasn’t happened.
I’m not saying the Chinese regime
is covering something up.
They would never do that!
I’m just saying the Chinese regime
has refused to cooperate.
So it’s nearly impossible to find out
how ISIS got most of its Chinese weapons.
Ah, the Chinese Communist Party:
Helping to make the world a safer place
by dodging the bullet when it comes to accountability.
And refuse to say where the bullet came from.
Of course, China’s not the only one.
Russia has also refused trace requests
and the United States has refused a few as
well.
But at the end of the day,
it’s guns made in China
far more than anywhere else
that are ending up in the hands of terrorists.
And coming up after the break,
if you think the Chinese regime loves guns,
well, wait till you see their new hypersonic
missiles.
So what do you think about China
refusing to provide critical information
about how ISIS got its guns?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Don’t be in the dark about how CCP weapons
get in to conflict zones.
Visit ChinaUncensored.tv.
We upload full half hour episodes
you won’t see on YouTube.
Learn about the shady practices
of the Chinese regime,
before even world leaders do!
ChinaUncensored.tv.