China loves Socialism with Chinese Characteristics
But Socialism with Venezuelan Characteristics...
not so much
Trouble brews for China as Venezuela crumbles
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Be sure to subscribe to our YouTube channel
for the latest China news,
and click the notification bell so you get
an alert
when we publish a new episode.
Venezuela!
The Socialist Paradise where,
for the low low price of just 15 million bolívars,
you can buy a chicken!
Yes, that’s right.
Venezuela’s socialist economy
has not worked out all that well.
The economy crumbled and according to the
IMF,
inflation hit a million percent.
“The currency is so devalued,
some shopkeepers weigh the money,
rather than waste time counting.”
Tomatoes for five million, anyone?
Or just 3 million for a roll of toilet paper?
Needless to say,
that doesn’t make a country very stable.
And just last week,
this happened.
“As hundreds of thousands of protesters,
fed up with the government of Nicolas Maduro,
flooded the streets of Caracas, Wednesday.
Venezuela's opposition leader Juan Guaido
declared himself the country's interim president.”
I am so jealous.
I’ve often tried to declare myself president,
and yet it has never stuck.
The Trump Administration was quick
to support this new interim president.
“Nicolas Maduro is a dictator
with no legitimate claim to power.
The National Assembly is the duly-elected
representative of the people
and through their constitutional system
and now the interim president, Juan Guaido;
it represents the will of the people.”
Needless to say,
that didn’t go over very well with Maduro’s
people.
“Because Mr. Pence doesn't have a job,
now he wants to come and run Venezuela...
I will say it like the Venezuelan people would
say it to you,
‘Yankee, go home.’”
Go home?
Mike Pence *is* home.
He lives in Washington DC.
Anyway, Maduro himself officially broke ties
with the US.
“I have decided to break diplomatic and
political relations
with the imperialist government of the United
States.”
I mean, that’s a little ridiculous.
It’s not like the US would ever be involved
in a coup in South America!
Anyway, Maduro is finding his government increasingly
isolated.
Nearly every other Latin American country
has sided with the new interim president.
But you know who still has Maduro’s back?
China.
Chinese Foreign Ministry Spokeswoman Hua Chunying
said,
“China supports efforts made by the Venezuelan
government
to protect the country’s sovereignty,
independence and stability.
I want to emphasize that outside sanctions
or interference usually make the situation
more complicated
and are not helpful to resolving the actual
problems.”
And China should know.
Because China’s outside interference
is part of the reason Venezuela is in this
mess.
And it goes beyond the moral support China
gives other socialist nations and dictatorships
to counter the democratic West.
First of all, you might be wondering—
since the protests in Venezuela have been,
well, pretty hot—
how has Maduro managed to stay in power this
long?
Well, it’s partly thanks to around $350
million dollars
of weapons from China and Russia.
And China has consistently pumped money into
Maduro’s government.
At the end of last year, Maduro even made
a state visit to China.
And somehow convinced Xi Jinping to wear a
beauty queen sash.
And Xi doesn’t do that for just any socialist
dictator.
Chinese premier Li Keqiang reportedly promised
that China was
“willing to provide whatever help it can
offer.”
I bet Maduro really hopes that offer is still
on the table.
So why would China continue to support a guy
who’s probably on his way down?
Well, China has invested heavily in Venezuela.
Venezuela was a key part of the Belt and Road
Initiative.
That’s the Chinese regime’s trade
and infrastructure investment strategy,
whereby they give a developing country infrastructure
loans
they maybe can’t pay back,
and when they don’t pay them back,
China takes over the infrastructure.
It’s worked great around the world.
Like in Sri Lanka.
And Pakistan.
And Djibouti.
And for a while,
it looked like things were going great in
Venezuela as well.
Over the past 10 years,
China invested about 70 billion dollars in
Venezuela.
That’s about half of all China’s lending
in Latin America.
But there was a catch.
According to the Foreign Policy,
“To guarantee repayment,
Beijing insisted on being repaid in oil.”
Like how I used to collect all my debts in
pogs.
Which was a mistake.
Just like oil.
Because oil prices tanked in 2014.
And that caused a huge problem,
compounded by the fact that the socialist
government
relied too much on redistribution of state
oil profits,
instead of encouraging the people
to build a robust economy in other sectors.
Oil made up about half of Venezuela’s GDP.
So when prices collapsed,
not only did the country go broke,
but the amount of oil they had to give to
China skyrocketed.
And they began falling behind on their payments.
Of course, China has a plan for that.
When other countries fail to pay back their
loans to China,
China just takes over a port,
or builds a military base or something.
And it looked like there was a similar plan
in Venezuela.
Venezuela has the world’s largest oil reserves.
Last year,
Venezuela sold about 10% of shares in an oil
joint venture
to a Chinese state-owned enterprise.
Combined with the shares already owned by
China National Petroleum Corporation,
that meant China owned 49% of the oil venture.
But now it’s turning out that the brilliant
plan
of destabilizing a country with unpayable
debts
might not be a good long-term strategy.
Nearly every Latin American country, and Canada,
is siding with Trump’s support of the new
opposition leader,
Juan Guaido.
And what happens if Guiado does replace Maduro?
Would he then rethink some of those Chinese
loans?
That’s what happened in Malaysia
when the long time Prime Minister was ousted.
But besides potentially losing
all that investment money and oil,
there’s another big loss China would have
to swallow—
a loss of influence.
At the turn of the 21st century,
China had very little presence in Latin America.
But Venezuela helped with that.
Now, China’s trade with Latin America
is 22 times what it was back in 2000.
And a lot of Latin countries that used to
have
diplomatic relations with Taiwan,
now have switched to the People’s Republic
of China.
Of course, a change in leadership in Venezuela
doesn’t guarantee that they would cool ties
with the China,
but that’s a risk.
And if Venezuela has a new leader,
and the Chinese regime loses its foothold
there,
lots of things could change.
And that’s why it’s basically only friendly
dictatorships
like China, Russia, Syria, and Turkey
that are saying Maduro should stick around.
I mean, obviously Turkey is on the list.
After all, Maduro dined at the restaurant
of Turkish heartthrob chef Salt Bae.
Soft power has nothing on red meat power.
Especially when you’re the president of
a starving country.
“We're hungry.
There's hunger.
I stand in line all day long,
but I don't get anything.”
“I haven't bought milk for months.
Meat and chicken are extremely expensive,
if you can even find them.”
One’s that’s basically turned into
a real life version of the Purge.
So what do you think China will do if Maduro
is ousted?
And if you want to know how the situation
in Venezuela
relates to America,
head over to our sister channel America Uncovered.
The link to that episode is below.
And before we go, now is the time
when I answer questions from you,
my loyal 50-cent army—
fans of the show who support what we do
through the crowd funding website Patreon.
Jacky Yang asks,
“Do you think the CCP will try to attack
you or your crew,
if they found you a danger to their national
stability?”
A lovely thought.
Well, I don’t know to what extent the CCP
is monitoring me or the show.
I mean, I’m still waiting to be directly
criticized
by my favorite state-run media, The Global
Times.
But no matter how much of a thorn
in their side China Uncensored is,
there’s a limit to what the Communist Party
would be willing to do to an American in America.
However, if I decided for some insane reason
that I wanted to go to Mainland China,
things might be different.
Maybe Chinese police would “discover”
I was actually trying to, I don’t know,
plan on smuggling 500 pounds of drugs,
and then I’d wind up like this Canadian.
So I think I’ll keep making the show here
in New York City.
Thanks for your question, Jacky.
If you’d like to hear your question answered
on the show,
sign up to support China Uncensored
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
It’s basically the price of your daily cup
of coffee.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time!