On this episode of China Uncensored:
China ends its one-child policy!
Sort of.
Hello and welcome to China Uncensored, I'm
your host, Chris Chappell.
Big news out of China last week—as explained
in this video by British state-run media BBC.
(cheers)
Wow. I guess they're putting all their investigative
resources into Sherlock.
Well, ending an unpopular and draconian population
control policy is certainly cause for celebration.
"Now we have the introduction of a new policy:
One couple, two children."
Wait. So they're ending the one-child policy...by
making it a two-child policy instead?
You know, the one-child policy was never supposed
to be a permanent thing.
It was established in 1979 after a huge population
boom in China.
After the Communist Party began its rule in
1949,
the population of China almost doubled in
30 years.
And this wasn't a coincidence.
Mao Zedong encouraged people to have lots
of kids.
That's partially because he was concerned
about nuclear war.
He said in a 1957 speech that it didn't matter
if half of China's population was killed,
because there were so many people, they could
just repopulate.
At the time, the Communist Party even banned
birth control.
But eventually, officials started worrying
about overpopulation.
So they created the one-child policy.
It was a massive social engineering project
designed to counter
the previous social engineering project that
got out of hand.
It's also not precisely a one-child policy.
There are so many exceptions that two thirds
of Chinese people are already allowed to have
a second child,
for example, farmers whose first child is
a girl.
So what's the big deal about changing the
one-child policy now?
For more on this, we go to former one-child
and copy editor Shelley Zhang.
Chris.
Shelley, most people outside China have a
negative view of the one child policy,
but some people also think it was a "necessary
evil"
to stop overpopulation in China.
Was the policy a success?
The Chinese government says that the policy
prevented 400 million births,
but demographers are pretty skeptical.
In fact, it's looking more and more like the
one child policy was completely unnecessary.
Really. Completely unnecessary?
Well, the biggest drop in China's birth rate
happened before the one-child policy.
In 1970, the government started running a
propaganda campaign to encourage people to
get married later and have fewer children.
Family size dropped by half in just 10 years.
Researchers now think that the birth rate
would have continued to drop naturally as
China's economy improved.
That was even confirmed by a secret government
experiment.
So are officials changing the one-child policy
now because it's clear it's not necessary?
Well, they're changing it because the one-child
policy caused a demographic disaster.
China is now dealing with not having enough
young workers to support the elderly.
This sounds like a huge amount of pressure
on the next generation.
Yeah, and because of the preference for boys
over girls,
there are now 30 million more men than women.
So how is the one-child policy enforced, anyway?
It's unevenly implemented through a massive
bureaucracy.
Quotas are set by the central government,
and enforced by local family planning commissions.
Wow. So what happens to people who violate
the policy?
So it varies pretty widely.
You can be fined anywhere from a few thousand
dollars to 6 to 8 times your annual income.
In some cases, if you can't pay, officials
will force you to have an abortion, or sterilize
you.
Remember Feng Jianmei?
In 2012, she was seven months pregnant with
her second child, and couldn't pay the fine.
Officials captured her and forced her to have
an abortion.
A photo of Feng with her stillborn baby went
viral on social media,
causing an outcry against family planning
enforcement.
From what I remember, Feng lived in a rural
area,
so she should have been able to have a second
child.
Oh, yeah, she was eligible.
But she hadn't applied for a birth permit
before getting pregnant.
So because she didn't have a birth permit,
she was fined,
and because she couldn't pay the fine, she
had a forced abortion?
Yes.
Under the one-child policy there have been
more than 330 million abortions and almost
200 million sterilizations.
And if Feng's daughter had been born, she
wouldn't be able to get a residence permit.
That means she couldn't go to school, couldn't
get a job, couldn't even go to the doctor.
There are 6.5 million "undocumented" Chinese
in that exact situation.
You know, I think about this sometimes because
after I was born in China, my mother got a
government-mandated IUD (intrauterine device).
Even though IUDs are supposed to have a 99%
effectiveness rate, she got pregnant.
So if we hadn't already moved to America by
then,
my sister probably wouldn't be alive today.
That's really heavy.
So it sounds like changing the one-child policy
will be a good thing?
Right now, it looks like family planning commissions
will still exist to enforce the two-child
policy.
And a big reason is money.
A lot of local governments make a substantial
part of their revenue from family planning
fines, especially in poorer areas.
There's even a saying that, for money,
"Big cities depend on land, small towns depend
on birth planning."
Some estimate that fines have made more than
300 billion dollars since the one-child policy
started.
Will the new two-child policy help the demographic
crisis the one-child policy caused?
It will take decades,
because the birth rate probably won't increase
fast enough.
When the two-child policy was piloted back
in 2013,
only 1 in 20 eligible couples applied to have
a second child.
You know, in the end, stopping the one-child
policy is good PR.
Most people outside China will probably think that
it's a great thing.
But what they won't realize is that the underlying
system isn't changing.
Chris?
Thanks, Shelley.
So the Communist Party is swapping the one-child
policy for a two-child policy.
But that's not going to change the fact that
the Party is still telling people how many
children they are allowed to have.
So will this new social engineering project
designed to counter the previous social engineering
project
created to fix the first social engineering
project work?
What do you think? Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China Uncensored
and check out our Facebook page.
I'm Chris Chappell. See you next time.
Ai Weiwei is well known for criticizing Chinese
censorship through his art.
And now he is accusing LEGO of censoring him
because of alleged pressure from the Chinese
regime.
So Ai Weiwei handled the rejection in the mature, adult manner that one would expect from the eccentric artist.
The US guided missile destroyer, the USS Lassen,
sailed within 12 nautical miles of Chinese
territory
—as long as you consider artificial islands
built on submerged reefs part of China's territory,
which no besides China does.