On this episode of China Uncensored,
China Wants to Tell You About the South China
Sea.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
An international United Nations Tribunal
may have ruled against China's claims to the
South China Sea,
but the Chinese Communist Party has something
the UN doesn't have
billions of dollars to spend on propaganda.
The Chinese regime has invested
8.9 billion dollars in what they call “external
publicity work.”
That is, spreading its propaganda message
to the West.
They've bought newspapers, television networks,
they even created an English language version
of state-run CCTV
and put its headquarters seven blocks from
the White House.
And hey, newspapers around the world are struggling
financially.
Why not just pay them to put propaganda side
by side with actual journalism?
They call it China Watch.
Here it is in the Wall Street Journal,
The Daily Telegraph,
and the New York Times.
And then there's this.
If you haven't noticed the giant ad
for Communist Party mouthpiece Xinhua in the
center of Times Square,
you're probably playing too much Pokémon
Go.
Oh, but it's been there.
Broadcasting Chinese propaganda 24/7, 365
days a year since 2011.
Yes, for five years.
At that time,
this prime piece of ad space
was estimated to cost at least three hundred
thousand dollars
a month.
And the Communist Party is putting it to good
use now.
Check this out!
Okay, so you can't actually hear the sound
in Times Square.
But it’s a video explaining why the South
China Sea
clearly belongs to the Communist Party
and why the Hague ruling is illegitimate.
The newest one has been playing 120 times
a day since July 23.
And its last day is August 3,
so hurry to Times Square before it's too late!
I'm kidding of course.
As a New Yorker,
I recommend you avoid Times Square like the
plague.
Fortunately, the video can also be seen online.
It’s one among many propaganda videos on
the South China Sea
you can enjoy from China’s state-run media.
Here’s a fun animation of a grandpa telling
his granddaughter
about why the South China Sea belongs to China.
Well, I think those countries should really
take a look at history.
Then they'll see that China was the first
to settle there,
the first to trade there, and the first to
make the area secure.
You can believe it,
because Grandpa has a British accent.
Then there’s this one from China Daily.
It shows foreigners trashing the tribunal.
"China has a position
a long standing position,
and it's not budging."
That’s weird.
No, not that those quotes sound like they
could be
merely describing China’s position not supporting
it
but that China Daily used the same hip hop
baseline
as this song about about tricking people and
then stabbing them to death.
Just saying.
Anyway, are you shocked that the Chinese Communist
Party’s propaganda
can be played in New York's Times Square?
Well, I'll tell you who was shocked.
Catherine West.
She's a member of the UK Parliament.
Here's what she said in the video about the
South China Sea.
That's why we have to be careful,
that yes, we need to resolve something very locally,
and have a grown up approach to dialogue."
Well that's just what China is always saying
about the South China Sea!
She gave that interview at the 5th China-Europe
High-level Political Parties Forum in Beijing
held in May 2016.
Except when Quartz reached out to her for
comment,
it turned out grown-up dialogue is still lacking.
Not only did nobody tell her they were going
to use her interview for this,
they completely quoted her out of context.
What she was actually saying is that China
has been militarizing the region
and it needs to stop doing that
and start using dialogue, like grown-ups.
Not exactly the same message,
but you wouldn't know that if you're watching
in Times Square.
So how do you feel about the Chinese regime
broadcasting its message in Times Square?
Want to support an alternative?
Join my China Uncensored 50-Cent Army!
Sure, China has billions of dollars,
but I have you!
Go to patreon.com/ChinaUncensored and Become
a Patron.
For 50 cents an episode, or whatever you can afford,
you can support me and my team
exposing the Chinese regime’s billions of
dollars of propaganda.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.