We can’t afford to show you this
Or this
Because YouTube doesn’t want us to.
Welcome to China...Censored.
Because censorship seems to be what YouTube
wants.
If you’re watching this show, I assume you’re
interested in what’s happening in China—the
kind of stuff the Chinese regime wants to
cover up.
The analysis you won’t get from any other
media.
The jokes you find mildly amusing.
But YouTube, which is owned by Google, does
not want us to talk about certain “sensitive”
China topics.
In fact, they punish us when we do.
Most of the time, YouTube is not outright
censoring China Uncensored.
Instead, they demonetize content that violates
their vague “community guidelines.”
A demonetized video means it gets no ads or
so-called “limited ads”, which is pretty
close to no ads.
And after a video has been demonetized, generally
YouTube won’t recommend it as much, so the
number of people who see it is limited.
For example, a few days ago we put out an
episode about how Chinese police are stealing
ordinary people’s motorcycles, right out
from under them.
Demonetized.
Can’t have people seeing how Chinese police
abuse people.
You see, over the years I’ve found a distinct
pattern to what gets demonetized—any footage
from China that makes the Communist Party
look bad.
Take for instance the coronavirus.
The Communist Party’s initial response to
the coronavirus was a coverup followed by
brutal suppression of Chinese people.
We showed you what the Party was doing in
this episode, the Coronavirus Cure isn’t
Authoritarianism.
So let’s take a look at what the People’s
Republic of China did to deal with the Coronavirus.
Starting with how Chinese officials rounded
people up and threw them into mass quarantine
camps.
And if people went outside without a mask,
they did this.
And this.
And this.This guy didn’t wear a mask, so
they tied him to a pillar.
Still without a mask.
These ethnic Uyghurs weren’t supposed to
go outside.
So officials hung signs from their necks calling
them dogs.”
The Chinese Communist Party’s coronavirus
response was horrific.
But at the time, people were praising the
Communist Party’s response.
Some Western media even suggested you might
be better off sheltering in China.
The New York Times suggested that open societies
were a problem.
So we figured it was important to show you
how bad it really was in China.
And when we did that, YouTube hit us hard.
First this episode was demonetized...
...then YouTube flat out deleted the video
without explanation.
Completely censored.
We made a huge stink about it on social media,
so they put it back up, again without explanation,
but now it was ineligible for monetization.
Plus, it was now age restricted.
You had to be over 18 to see the video, and
you’d see this message before you could
watch it.
Oh, our video was “inappropriate or offensive”?!
I think YouTube’s censorship was “inappropriate
and offensive”.
And this was far from an isolated incident.
Most of our coronavirus coverage in the early
days of the pandemic got demonetized.
YouTube wasn’t giving any explanation.
But by that point I had noticed a pattern.
It seemed like any time we showed Chinese
authorities using violence, we would get demonetized.
Back in 2019, almost all our coverage of the
Hong Kong protests were getting demonetized
too.
Here’s a clip from our episode Hong Kong
Police Lay Siege to University Students.
Over the weekend, Hong Kong police once again
surrounded Polytechnic University of Hong
Kong, known as PolyU.
They began arresting students, and...stomping
on their heads?!
Jeez.
Overnight clashes began at PolyU on Sunday
evening.
Police fired volleys of tear gas and blocked
the exits after protesters set fires on a
bridge.
More than a thousand people were trapped inside
the university, including reporters, medics,
and high school and university students.
It’s important for people to see that kind
of footage—to know what’s really happening
in Hong Kong.
It was demonetized.
Here’s another Hong Kong episode that YouTube
age restricted and labeled ineligible for
monetization.
Clashes between protesters and police in Kong
Kong over the weekend turned parts of the
city into a bona fide battlefield.
Complete with plenty of police violence, rubber
bullets, and enough tear gas to make Chuck
Norris cry.
Good one 2019 Chris.
But demonetized.
And it wasn’t just the coronavirus and Hong
Kong stories getting demonetized.
If we showed footage of Uyghurs shackled and
blindfolded, YouTube would demonetize us.
When we covered anti-China protests in Vietnam,
YouTube would demonetize us.
Here’s footage of police cracking down on
protesters inside China.
Including beating up an old woman.
YouTube demonetized AND age-restricted it.
The crazy thing is, all this was being done
without any explanation from YouTube.
Eventually, under pressure, YouTube began
to tell creators why something was demonetized
after human review by someone at YouTube.
We’d get notifications like this.
It says our video contains “situations showing
hurt, damage, or injury.”
In other words, it exposes what a brutal authoritarian
regime is doing—and we can’t have that!
Even though YouTube’s policies supposedly
allow you to show this footage when there’s
educational or documentary context.
You know, like the fact that we’re reporting
the news.
But even when we didn’t show that kind of
footage, we’d still often get demonetized.
This episode, Coronavirus: 2nd Wave Hits Chinawas
demonetized for “harmful or dangerous acts”
such as “accidents, pranks or stunts”.
A human reviewer made that claim.
There were no stunts or pranks in that video.
That makes no sense.
Unless you consider China’s coverup of coronavirus
infections a stunt.
But I don’t think that’s what YouTube
meant.
This episode, Hunter Biden’s China Deals
Under Investigation was demonetized for Adult
content such exposed breasts, full nudity
or animal mating.
Look, I know there are the Hunter Biden sex
tapes floating around out there, but our episode
only talked about Biden’s China deals.
It didn’t show any of the stuff YouTube
claims it did.
By the way, that was also one of our weekly
news roundup episodes.
So we also talked about alleged Chinese spy
Fang Fang targeting US politicians, how China
is using big tech to arrest Uyghurs, and the
US sanctioning Chinese officials for the crackdown
on Hong Kong.
Which one of those was “sexual behavior,
language, or expressions?”
And in case there’s still any confusion
about what YouTube is really doing here, this
episode, China Must Have a Chernobyl Moment
() was demonetized for “situations that
may endanger participants”.
That episode—is a 35 minute interview over
skype.
It’s just me and the guest talking.
I don’t see how that could possibly be a
situation that “endangers participants”...wait,
unless YouTube is making a subtle threat to
stop interviewing Chinese dissidents.
OK, I don’t think it was.
But I still can’t imagine the reason it
was demonetized.
Especially since that demonetization was confirmed
by a human reviewer.
So clearly, people at YouTube don’t want
you to know what’s really going on in China.
I’m not sure why, since YouTube is so vague
about it.
And since they’re so vague, I’m left to
my imagination.
Which goes to places like, I wonder if YouTube
is being influenced by Google.
Since Google is working with the Communist
Party on Artificial Intelligence Research.
Which might benefit China’s military.
And of course, Google had once tried to launch
a censored search app for the China market.
But if Google and YouTube are trying to get
us to tone down our message, we’re not going
to do it.
No matter how much they take away our ads,
or even delete our videos, we won’t stop
uncensoring China.
But to do this, we need your help.
YouTube ad revenue is unreliable.
It’s up and down and sometimes gone—depending
on what topics we cover.
Even in the best of times, it’s never been
enough to pay our staff—including writers,
video editors, sound editors, and of course
rent on our studio here in New York.
Our main source of support is viewer contributions.
That’s right, you—my amazing viewers...
...fans I call the “50-Cent Army”—the
people who help us fight the Chinese Communist
Party’s so-called 50-Cent Army of paid trolls
who spread propaganda.
You are the reason we can afford to cover
the most sensitive topics—because no matter
what YouTube does, you have our backs.
If you want to help us...
go to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
Each membership level has rewards.
For just a dollar per episode, you can leave
questions for me to answer at the end of my
YouTube episodes.
Other rewards include our monthly letter,
behind the scenes footage, the music we use
in the show, live Google hangouts with me,
and a lot more.
If you don’t have a Patreon account, it’s
easy to sign up with just your name and email.
Choose what you want to pledge per video.
We publish about 18 episodes per month.
And you can pledge that amount for “every
creation”...or set a monthly limit.
For example, if you only want to pledge 10
dollars a month, you can pledge 1 dollar per
creation, with a monthly limit of 10.
But the more you pledge, the more episodes
we can afford to make.
Pay with Apple Pay, credit card, or PayPal—and
boom!
You’re now a member of the China Uncensored
50-Cent Army!
If you don’t want a recurring payment through
Patreon, you can visit ChinaUncensored.tv/support—and
make a one-time contribution through PayPal,
Bitcoin, or old-fashioned mail.
But for us, we prefer to have your ongoing
support through Patreon.
No matter what, your contribution goes directly
to supporting China Uncensored.
Shelley, Matt, and I produce this show through
our own production company.
Our only obligation is to you, our viewers.
So please, support China Uncensored so we
can continue to cover the topics YouTube,
Google, and the Chinese Communist Party don’t
want you to know about.
The links are in the description below.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Thank you.
You’re awesome.