On this episode of China Uncensored,
ever wonder how China’s Internet became
so censored?
You can thank this guy.
Welcome back, I’m Chris Chappell.
The Internet’s got a new loser!
Just look at him!
No, not Facebook’s Mark Zuckerberg.
I mean the happy guy in the chair.
That’s Lu Wei,
China’s Internet Czar.
Former Internet Czar.
That photo’s from 2014.
He’s not so happy anymore.
Because Lu Wei is the latest high-ranking
official
Chinese leader Xi Jinping has taken down
in his ongoing purge of political opponents—
what he calls the “anti-corruption campaign.”
According to this announcement,
Lu Wei has been accused of
“seriously violating Party discipline.”
Which basically means,
he’s as good as convicted,
expelled from the Communist Party,
and destined for prison.
Sorry Mark Zuckerberg!
If you were trying to get Facebook into China,
you chose the wrong guy to Zuck up to.
Once upon a time,
Lu Wei was basically the ruler of China’s
Internet—
the guy responsible for earning China
the coveted title of Freedom House’s
“worst abuser of internet freedom,”
for three years in a row!
That’s a way less controversial title, by
the way,
than People’s Sexiest Man Alive.
I’m with the Houston Chronicle on this one.
Kim Jong Un is still waiting for your call,
People Magazine.
Anyway, yes,
China is officially the three-time consecutive
champion
of worst internet freedom.
Take that, Syria!
Wait, Syria still has Internet?
Back to Lu Wei.
The Guardian describes him as the
“powerful and flamboyant former head
of China’s Cyberspace Administration.”
That was the administration
that oversaw Internet censorship.
Lu was certainly powerful.
But flamboyant?
I mean, he loved to get photo ops
with Western tech giants kissing up to him—
like Facebook’s Mark Zuckerberg,
Apple’s Tim Cook,
and Amazon’s Jeff Bezos.
I think it’s more like,
he’s kind of crazy.
He said “Freedom and order are twin sisters.”
Which would make sense
if he was trying to argue that free countries
are more stable—
which is usually true.
But I think he was using that to justify
China’s heavy-handed Internet censorship.
But you know what?
That makes sense, because—
get this—
there’s no censorship on the Chinese Internet!
Yes, China’s top Internet censor says
there’s no Internet censorship.
He claims the Internet is simply “managed.”
Which is like selling cruelty-free beef,
and saying the cows weren’t slaughtered.
They were just massaged.
To death.
So it should be no surprise
that Lu Wei is same guy once hired
a famous songwriter to write the song
“Cyberspace Spirit.”
Powerful Internet country!
The Web is where glorious dreams are!
From the distant cosmos to the home we long
for!
Powerful Internet country!
Tell the world that the China Dream
is lifting Greater China to prominence!
Wow, that’s pretty catchy...
in a creepy Soviet way.
Hope I don’t get that stuck in my head.
And if that song’s not crazy enough,
Lu Wei also allegedly went to parties
serving human breast milk.
Lu Wei also did some practical things.
Like spearheading China’s plan to eliminate
VPNs,
the special software that allows Chinese netizens
to get through the Great Firewall of China
and access the real Internet.
And when Lu Wei was in charge of
the Cyberspace Administration of China,
he oversaw the early drafts
of the now infamous Cybersecurity Law
that requires foreign companies store
their user data inside China—
and give the Chinese Communist Party
full access to that Chinese user data.
Under Lu Wei,
the Chinese regime’s grip on social media
tightened.
Internet users had to register with their
real names.
And that means no fake Twitter accounts.
We know who you are,
Anakin Skywalker.
Also, Lu Wei banned
all of Twitter.
Of course, if you’re on the Chinese internet,
you won’t hear much about the fall of Lu
Wei
because the Chinese Internet is
of course, massively censored.
I mean massaged.
I mean, managed.
China Digital Times discovered this
Propaganda Department directive
that orders media to censor-slash-manage
all comments about Lu Wei.
It’s almost poetic,
how his downfall is being censored
by the very apparatus that he built.
What’s that, Shelley?
We have video of the propaganda directive?
Go ahead.
Ok, ok, you got me.
Man, that song is catchy.
Where was I?
Oh right, as I mentioned earlier,
the fall of Lu Wei is tied into Chinese leader
Xi Jinping’s battle against his political
opponents,
a loosely tied faction under former Chinese
leader Jiang Zemin.
Sorry, wrong toad.
The resemblance is really uncanny.
So Lu Wei was deeply enmeshed in the propaganda
wing
of the Communist Party—
the guys responsible for making the Party
look good.
In other words,
miracle workers.
Somewhat inept miracle workers.
For two decades Lu Wei
“served as party secretary
of the state-run Xinhua news agency,
and Beijing’s propaganda chief,
eventually making it up to deputy head
of the CCP’s central propaganda department.”
That means he worked under
the head of Party propaganda,
Liu Yunshan.
Liu was one of the highest ranking members
of Jiang Zemin’s faction,
and used his clout to undermine Xi.
If you want to learn more about Liu Yunshan,
watch my previous episode online,
“Who Controls China’s Propaganda.”
Xi Jinping has been trying to wrestle
control of the Party’s propaganda
from the Jiang Zemin faction.
Especially when it comes to the Internet.
That’s why Xi Jinping gave himself
so many fancy new titles,
like head of the Central Leading Group
for Internet Security and Information.
A year ago,
Lu Wei was mysteriously fired
from the Cyberspace Administration of China.
And Xi Jinping appointed his own guy to replace
him.
Now, Lu Wei has been detained,
and “Several of Lu’s associates and officials
in charge of regulating online services
have also been taken into custody.”
What’s that, Shelley?
We have video of Lu Wei’s confession?!
Wow.
Yes, I want to see it.
Hey.
Fool me once, shame on you.
Fool me twice,
shame on...you, twice.
Back to Lu Wei.
State-run media isn’t being kind to him.
The Global Times wrote,
“Lu was a typical ‘two-faced person,’
as he severely deviated from Party principle
and ruined the image of the cyberspace administration
team
and harmed the development of cyberspace.”
Which really doesn’t make much sense
if you think about it.
Lu Wei did exactly the Communist Party wanted
as far as censoring the Internet.
And even though he was fired a year ago,
there hasn’t exactly been a big push
to undo all the controls he put in place.
The internet will continue to be “managed”
to benefit the Communist Party.
But undoing Lu Wei’s work
is not what the investigation of him is about.
If previous purges of high ranking officials
are any indication,
I wouldn’t be surprised if Xi Jinping
is ultimately making his way for Liu Yunshan.
Because even as Lu’s former Xinhua News
Agency
turns on him...
...one thing is clear:
Xi Jinping’s anti-corruption campaign
is not winding down.
And neither is Internet censorship,
just so we’re clear on that.
And Lu Wei’s downfall offers yet another
example
of why doing business in China is risky business.
Remember that photo of Lu and Mark Zuckerberg?
All that hard work spent developing a relationship
with someone who ended up on the wrong side
of a political purge.
Now he’ll have to start all over again
with the new Internet czar.
What a waste.
Kind of like when former Canadian Prime Minister
Stephen Harper met with disgraced Chinese
official
and proud Jiang faction member Bo Xilai
right at the beginning of Bo’s downfall
back in 2012.
Which was dumb.
But maybe things will work out better
for Mark Zuckerberg.
After all,
according to Chinese state-run media,
he did spend his time with Lu Wei
praising Xi Jinping’s book
that was conveniently and prominently
placed on a desk.
He even told Lu that he bought the book
for his coworkers, too.
What a boss.
Yes, Shelley?
We have video of Lu talking to Zuckerberg.
Nice try.
I’m not falling for that again.
What?
You promise that it’s not that
Cyberspace Spirit song?
Ok, fine, roll it.
That is the first time I’ve been happy
about being Rickrolled.
Thanks, Shelley.
What do you think of the fall of Lu Wei?
And do you have Cyberspace Spirit?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Aren’t you happy you have access
to an uncensored Internet?
Well, depending on what happens
with Net Neutrality at least.
But why not celebrate your uncensored Internet
by visiting ChinaUncensored.tv?
There you can see full half hour episode
that you won’t see on YouTube.
And definitely not in China.
Once again that’s ChinaUncensored.tv.