Huawei maaaaybe can’t be trusted.
China sets its sights on Mars
And Microwaves!
They can do more than just heat your food
That and more on this week’s China news
headlines.
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Subscribe to our YouTube channel for the latest
China news,
and click the notification bell icon.
That way, you get an alert each time we publish
a new episode.
This week’s China news headlines!
Huawei.
The Chinese telecom company
that wants you to know that it’s a totally
private company
that absolutely does not coordinate
with the Chinese Communist Party.
Have you ever given any information
to the Chinese government
in any way, shape, or form?
For the past 30 years,
we have never done that,
and in the next 30 years to come,
we will never do that.
Ok, of that reporter’s not going to say
it, I will.
Ren Zhengfei is lying.
There.
I said it.
He’s a bald-face lying liar.
Of course Huawei shares information
with the Chinese government!
In fact, experts told CNBC that
“Huawei would have no choice
but to hand over network data to the Chinese
government
if Beijing asked for it,
because of espionage and national security
laws in the country.”
They’re talking about the 2014 Counter-Espionage
Law
and the 2017 National Intelligence Law.
Article 7 of the National Intelligence Law
says,
“Any organization or citizen shall support,
assist and cooperate with the state intelligence
work
in accordance with the law.”
Basically what that means is that if the Chinese
state
asks you for *anything*,
you need to comply.
The 2014 Counter-Espionage Law says,
“When the state security organ investigates
and understands the situation of espionage
and collects relevant evidence,
the relevant organizations and individuals
shall provide it truthfully and may not refuse.”
That basically says the same thing—
using the excuse of national security.
So Huawei would obviously need to give up
any information the Communist Party wants.
And even if there weren’t already laws that
said that,
the Party is perfectly capable of making them
do it anyway,
since there is no meaningful rule of law in
China.
I mean honestly,
do you think these guys would take no for
an answer?
According to Council on Foreign Relations
adjunct senior fellow Jerome Cohen,
“Not only is this mandated by existing legislation
but,
more important, also by political reality...
The Party is embedded in Huawei and controls
it.”
Which is why Congress passed a bill
that bans the US government from using Huawei
technology.
And that’s why Huawei has sued the US government.
They say it violates their constitutional
rights
for congress to punish them without a fair
trial.
To which I say...
I can’t wait to see what turns up during
that fair trial.
So Huawei might not be at the top of the list
to build America’s 5G network.
But that doesn’t mean China
won’t be bombarding us with something!
According to my favorite Chinese state run
media,
the Global Times,
China has developed a weapons system
based on microwaves.
It’s non-lethal.
It just stimulates nerves to cause excruciating
pain.
The weapon can be focused on an individual
or a group.
It can even be mounted on cars.
Huh, if I didn’t know better,
I’d say maybe this was the weapon
used to make those US Embassy workers in Cuba
and China
experience severe pain.
But I can’t imagine there’s a connection.
Anyway, I wouldn’t want you to be think
that
the Chinese Communist Party is gearing up
to attack foreign countries.
Honestly, they don’t have time.
They’re too busy creating a harmonious Chinese
society
through systems of mass control.
Chinese authorities have made great progress
building their social credit system.
And last year,
they successfully stopped millions of citizens
from traveling because of a low social credit
score.
According to the National Public Credit Information
Center
Chinese courts banned people from 17.5 million
flights
and 5.5 million train rides in 2018.
I just hope they found out *before* they got
to the airport.
But there’s one trip everyone in China is
waiting for:
The trip to Mars.
“Next year, China will launch its Mars probe,
which is expect to encircle,
land on and explore the Mars.”
It’s not just any Mars.
It’s “The Mars”.
This probe will be unmanned.
But it could bring China one step closer to
being
the first country to land a man on mars…
that a bunch of people on the Internet
will say was faked in a film studio.
Speaking of impossible trips,
the United Nations investigator on religious
freedom
would sure like to make a trip to China’s
Xinjiang region—
to look into those re-education camps.
I mean there’s a rumor going around that
instead of them being about re-education
to learn job skills,
the camps are more about re-education to be
loyal to the Party.
Because nothing makes you more loyal than
getting tortured.
More than a million ethnic Uighur Muslims
are in the camps,
so I think it’s best figure out what’s
really going on there.
The UN investigator made his visitation request
in February,
but Chinese authorities still haven’t responded.
I’m sure they’ll get on that soon.
Of course, China sits on the UN Human Rights
Council,
so maybe China can just send its own representative
instead.
And finally,
last year we told you that some local officials
in China
had told Christians to replace pictures of
Jesus
with pictures of Xi Jinping.
And I’m sure you were wondering,
“How could they possibly do this?...
only to Christians and not to *all* religious
believers?”
Well don’t worry,
it was just an oversight,
and the Communist Party is working on it.
In round two,
Tibetans are being told to put their Buddha
statues aside
and replace them with Xi Jinping.
Photos of Xi Jinping.
Not statues of Xi Jinping meditating.
Too creepy.
And before you go, it’s time when I answer
a question
from a fan of the show who supports China
Uncensored
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
Coralline Algae asks,
“Does China have any adversaries
in South or Central America?”
Adversaires?!
What?!
No!
The Chinese Communist Party makes friends
wherever it goes.
Especially in poor authoritarian dictatorships.
China’s presence in Latin America began
in 2001,
when Venezuela became the first Latin American
country
to enter a “strategic development partnership,”
with China.
And look how well that turned out!
Since 2001,
trade between China and most Latin American
countries
has skyrocketed.
So really, things are just getting better
and better for everyone.
Probably.
Maybe.
Of course, considering the Chinese regime’s
playbook—
where they get a country in debt,
take their resources,
and help brutal dictators control their own
people—
there could come a day when some of these
“strategic partners” in Latin America
become adversaries.
Thanks for your question, Coralline.
So why am I answering questions on the show?
It’s because companies that are “strategic
partners” of China
don’t dare to work with a show
that criticizes the Chinese Communist Party.
So we rely on support from viewers like you
on the crowdfunding website Patreon.
Answering your questions on the show
is one of my ways of saying thank you.
So head over to patreon.com/chinaucnensored
to find out how you can keep China, uncensored.
Thanks for watching.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.