On this episode of China Uncensored,
if you're invited to participate in a Chinese
marathon...
RUN!!!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I'm your host Chris Chappell.
As the Financial Times put it,
“Running is the new religion of the Chinese
middle class.”
I guess because the old religion was wiped
out by the Red Guards.
And as anyone who’s a runner knows,
this religion requires blood sacrifice!
Aches and pains, swelling and inflammation,
cuts and bruises from having to dodge chainsaw
wielding motorcyclists...
But seriously, running can be dangerous.
Especially in China.
“More and more events are unfolding from
the Guangdong Marathon Fiasco.
There were close to 20,000 participants,
including 12,208 incidents of injury and sickness.”
Now don’t worry,
it’s not that over half the participants
were injured.
Some people just had multiple injuries.
The Guangdong Marathon Fiasco, as it’s being
called,
was, well, kind of a fiasco.
And if you think that's a crazy amount of
injuries and illness, get this.
Some of the incidents were completely preventable—were it not
for this.
Orchard Fruity Soap.
Now with extra moisturizer.
Those are the kind of things that probably
should have been written in Chinese,
so that when they were handed out to people
who just finished running a marathon,
they wouldn’t mistake them for energy bars
which they did.
Clearly, there were some major organizational
fails at this particular marathon.
Like, not having wide enough roads for the
20,000 participants
Or a serious lack of trash cans.
Just look all those banana peels!
No wonder so many people got injured!
But as state-run China daily puts it,
“Running is in, and the latest fashion is
sweeping China.”
And who do we have to thank?
Why the Communist Party, of course!
Now the Chinese have always been a health-conscious
people.
In parks throughout China you’ll see people
doing all kinds of exercise
Taichi, Qigong, Square Dancing.
Oh man, you do not want to get on the bad
side of China’s Square Dancing Grannies.
But running is a relatively new thing.
And not just among billionaire social media
moguls.
As the economy has developed,
China’s growing middle class is dealing
with a growing middle class problem. Namely…
office butt.
So running is the new thing.
There are even themed running groups.
Like the Beijing-based Mama Running, for new
mothers.
It has nearly more than 800 members.
People also use running as a way to celebrate
important occasions.
Like Mao’s 122 birthday
People got sick from the smog.
There’s even a “Half Naked Marathon”.
And the "Beijing Undie Run".
Which does not look healthy.
Anyway, according to the Chinese Athletics
Association,
there were 134 marathons held in 2015,
more than double the previous year.
And if Party Mouthpiece Xinhua News is right,
which it ALWAYS IS,
this year will see more than 200 marathons
in China.
Marathons have become so popular that in many
big cities,
runners have to win lotteries to enter.
All this running has Western sportswear companies
running for the Chinese market.
In 2014, Adidas made more than 270 million
dollars in China,
and has sponsored the Beijing marathon and
Shanghai Half Marathon.
Adidas is so successful,
they’ve inspired not just one,
but at least two knockoffs!
And of course,
it’s a great market for fruity soap.
So what do you think about the Guangdong marathon
fiasco?
And what’s your best, or worst marathon
experience.
My answer to both is North Korea’s Pyongyang
Marathon.
Leave your comments below and subscribe for
more episodes of China Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell. See you next
time.