Chinese Netizens Are Tortured And Punished
For Leaking Information On Xi Jinping’s Daughter
Daddy Xi Is Not Happy
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
In China, netizens can be\h
arrested for simply browsing\h\h
China’s Dirty Web—basically,\h
the Dark Web for doxing sites.
Like many young internet users, netizens in China\h
have formed subcultures on certain websites.\h\h
Some of these websites are hosted\h
on foreign servers outside of China,\h\h
so authorities can’t shut them down as easily.
Some of these websites function\h
as wiki database sites—that is,\h\h
users can contribute information on the site.
The Chinese Communist Party calls these\h
wikis the “Esu Circle”. Esu means Vulgar.\h
One of the Esu Circle websites is Zhina Wiki. And\h
just look at this homepage. Now that’s vulgar.
It started as a place where young netizens could\h
share memes and throw shade at public figures like\h\h
celebrities and athletes. But in 2019, users\h
on Zhina Wiki shared personal information\h\h
about Xi Jinping’s relatives: his brother-in-law\h
Deng Jiagui, and his daughter Xi Mingze.
That leaked information included Date\h
of Birth, Household Registration number,\h\h
and for Xi Mingze, her new name.\h\h
She allegedly had her name changed after getting\h
her Bachelor’s Degree from Harvard University.
The only official photo of Xi Mingze is\h
this Xinhua propaganda photo from the 90s.\h\h
And it’s not really a photo of her. It’s\h
a photo of how great her dad is. Daddy Xi!
But that little girl\h\h
is now 28. And very few people actually\h
know what she looks like as an adult.
Occasionally, alleged photos\h
of her have been leaked.
This Daily Mail article from\h
8 years ago shows this photo,\h\h
but without citing a source.\h
It’s most likely not her.\h
There’s also this photo, from\h
thefamouspeople.com—also not a reliable source.\h
There’s also this photo from Getty\h
Images, labeled as Xi Mingze, but\h\h
not confirmed that it’s the same Xi\h
Mingze who’s the daughter of Xi Jinping.
And obviously none of these\h
photos are the same person.\h
And this latest leak from the Zhina Wiki\h
website is yet another unconfirmed photo.
Whether accurate or not, Daddy Xi is not pleased.\h
And in the typical communist style, the\h
response to the leaked photo is pretty extra.\h\h
The Ministry of Public Security established\h
a special task force. In the end they jailed\h\h
24 netizens for the information leak.
Which is crazy. When can you get\h
24 people to cooperate on anything?
The most severe sentence was given\h
to 21-year-old computer prodigy\h\h
Niu Tengyu, who had made around 200 entries\h
online. He was deemed the primary offender.
Niu Tengyu was sentenced to 8 years in prison for\h
“picking quarrels and provoking disturbances,”\h\h
5 years in prison for “infringing on citizens’\h
personal information,” and 2 years for “illegal\h\h
business operation.” His combined sentence is\h
15 years in prison, and the court decided to\h\h
implement a 14-year sentence with a 130,000\h
RMB fine—which is about 20,000 US dollars.
14 years in prison seems excessive for\h
leaking a photo and some information—and\h\h
it wasn’t even embarrassing information.
Just imagine someone leaking information\h
about the US president’s embarrassing child.
Twitter might freeze your account.
But you won’t go to prison.
Even Donald Trump eventually stopped\h
hiding his embarrassing daughter.
And Xi Mingze is by all accounts well behaved\h
and low key. So what’s such a big deal that\h\h
the people who allegedly leaked her\h
information are going to prison?\h
Well, it’s hard to say. But the prison\h
sentence isn’t even the worst part.\h\h
I’ll explain after the break.
Welcome back.
Niu Tengyu is the Chinese netizen who\h
was sentenced to 14 years in prison\h\h
for allegedly leaking this photo and information\h
about Xi Jinping’s daughter, Xi Mingze.
Visiting “Esu Circle” websites has not been\h
punished by the judicial system before.\h\h
But this case is different because\h
it involves Xi Jinping’s family.\h\h
And that’s also why Chinese lawyers\h
are reluctant to represent Niu Tengyu.
This handwritten letter from Niu Tengyu was\h
released by an anonymous friend or colleague. It’s\h\h
about how the authorities tortured him to confess.
￼\h
It says: “Around January 2020, I was forced to\h
write ‘confessions’ on a few hundred pages of\h\h
A4 paper. I wrote tens of thousands of words. All\h
of the content I wrote was required by the police,\h\h
and I was forced to make up and fabricate things\h
that are non-existent, deliberate fabrications\h\h
according to their demands. I had to write enough\h
pages within a given timeframe following the\h\h
titles and outlines they demanded. When failing\h
to do so, I was allowed to eat nothing but rice,\h\h
I was deprived of sleep, and I was hung up and\h
beaten. Between December 10, 2019, and January 20,\h\h
2020, I slept less than 30 hours in\h
total, and I was crippled by beating.\h\h
I’m hereby stating that all these\h
documents were fabrications under duress,\h\h
and they do not represent my own\h
opinion, and much of them are not true.”
According to Niu’s mother, the police tortured him\h\h
to get him to confess to being\h
the ringleader behind the leak.
She also said that one of Niu’s\h
arms has been permanently injured\h\h
and he was beaten until he was\h
unconscious several times.\h\h
I know what you’re thinking: That’s\h
an excessive amount of torture.\h\h
But remember, he’s a dangerous terrorist. He\h
posted a photo on the internet. Allegedly.
And I say allegedly because it might\h
not have been Niu Tengyu at all.
The founder of one of the Esu Circle websites\h
has testified that Niu Tengyu wasn’t actually\h\h
involved in the information\h
leak, but is just a scapegoat.
After all, there’s no way to verify\h
that Niu Tengyu was the one who found\h\h
Xi Mingze’s information in the first place.\h
According to Xiao Yanrui, who started several\h\h
of the Esu Circle websites, the data may have\h
been shared online by...corrupt police officers.
Xiao says the administrators of the Zhina\h
Wiki website, where the information was\h\h
actually leaked, are based overseas. So the\h
authorities chose to blame Niu Tengyu instead.\h\h
Even though Niu was not posting on Zhina Wiki.\h
He was posting on a different website, Esu Wiki.\h
And according to Xiao, the information about\h\h
Xi Jinping’s relatives was\h
not even posted on Esu Wiki.
Xiao also said that Niu had traveled with him\h
to Hong Kong to see the protests back in 2019.\h
So...this could have been about punishing\h
him for visiting the Hong Kong protests,\h\h
while at the same time covering\h
up police behavior? Hmmm.
And now it’s time for me to answer a question from\h
a viewer who supports China Uncensored on Patreon.
Bruce Johnson asks:
Chris, what's your general impression of the\h\h
post Trump/mid pandemic world as it relates\h
to China's future? It seems between Trump\h\h
and the CCP's handling of the Coronavirus, the\h
cat is out of the bag.\h How much will all this\h\h
impact China's trajectory of becoming a\h
true super power and rival of the US?\h
Well, Bruce: The good news is that through the\h
pandemic, a lot of people are waking up to the\h\h
problems with the Chinese Communist Party—from\h
their initial cover up that caused the spread,\h\h
to the hostile mask diplomacy, to\h
the ineffective Chinese vaccines.\h\h
Even some governments are getting tougher\h
on the CCP, like the UK and Australia.
In terms of post-Trump, it’s hard to say. We’ve\h
only had a few weeks of post-Trump, and it’s not\h\h
yet clear what the Biden administration is going\h
to do on China. They’ve said some tough things,\h\h
they’ve said some cooperative things. But\h
ultimately it’ll be actions that count.
But the best way to prevent the\h
CCP from being a true super power\h\h
is simple: Stop giving them money. That’s it.\h
Stop investing in their bonds. Stop buying their\h\h
products. Stop watching their stupid panda videos.\h
And if we all do that, the CCP will not survive.
Thanks for your question, Bruce.
Be like Bruce and join us on Patreon. Go to\h
Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored to learn more.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.\h
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.