On this episode of China Uncensored,
it's that time of year again...
time to walk the dog!
Not like that!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Every year, there’s a dog-eating festival
in southern China.
You may have heard of it:
The Yulin Dog Meat Festival.
But back in May,
Chinese animal rights activists announced
that after many years of protests,
local officials had finally told them
that this year,
they were banning dog meat sales
ahead of the festival.
Victory!
And that’s it!
Thanks for watching this episode of...
just kidding.
It turns out
there’s been a bit of a misunderstanding.
What officials actually meant was that t
he festival would continue as normal,
dog meat sales unbanned.
But don't worry.
officials and the dog meat vendors
reached a satisfactory agreement
that should satisfy the millions of people
around the world
who object to the festival.
“Vendors and officials reached a compromise
setting a limit of two dogs
displayed per stall.”
See, a two-dog limit
is almost as good as a ban, right?
Only two dogs per…
Okay, so that limit was ignored.
But at least some vendors
changed their signs,
so instead of dog meat,
it said tasty meat.
Much better.
Calling something tasty
definitely makes people think it's tasty.
About ten thousand dogs are killed
every year for the Yulin Dog Meat festival.
And every year,
it causes a huge international outcry,
because, well, puppies are only cute
when they're dressed as food.
But perhaps you’re like
my favorite state-run media,
and ask what’s the big deal
with eating dog?
I mean, Americans slaughter almost
10 million pigs per month!
This is a case of us American Imperialists,
“demanding non-Westerners change their eating
habits,
because they think their cultures and feelings
deserve more respect than others.
Such a condescending attitude
is not comfortable.”
Well, Global Times,
it’s not so much the fact
that they’re eating dog meat
that bothers most people.
It’s that the dogs are tortured and boiled
alive,
because “there is a belief that the adrenaline
released through the pain
makes the meat more tender
and provides health benefits.”
Right.
But even if you believe in
the supposed health benefits
of eating tortured animals,
you still might want to stay away.
Because most of these dogs are slaughtered
in disgustingly unsanitary conditions,
and a lot of them are extremely sick.
So yes,
we American imperialists, with our humane...
What's that shelley?
Do I know how factory farmed chickens are
killed?
Electrified water?
Throat-cutting machines?
I'm...never eating drumsticks again.
Well, point taken about factory farming,
but at least animals in factory farms
aren’t tortured for the specific purpose
of making them tastier.
But more importantly,
there’s this one other fact—
and I don’t think this happens in America.
“About 90 percent of the dogs
are stolen on the streets
and stolen from people's yards
so a lot of the dogs that we rescue
have actual collars on."
Can’t we all agree
that stealing other people’s pets
and eating them is deeply uncool?
But before you start accusing Chinese people
of being dog-eating barbarians,
I have to tell you:
Dog-eating is really not mainstream Chinese
culture.
In fact, Chinese people
are some of the loudest voices
calling for an end to
the Yulin Dog Meat festival.
In fact,
throughout most of Chinese history,
eating dog was considered distasteful
and not at all common practice.
A lot of Chinese people
really love dogs,
and in China today,
pet ownership is on the rise.
So it’s little wonder
people are kind of upset
about their pets being stolen,
boiled alive,
and then eaten.
Now you’d think the local government ought
to do something about this.
Well, remember:
local officials are the ones
who came up with the compromise
that vendors could display, at most,
two dogs—
a regulation that wasn’t even being adhered
to.
And what about all the protests?
The government’s response to protests
has been to either crackdown on activists
or simply ignore the problem.
“What has the Yulin city government done?
They covered it up.
Firstly they don't mention
this extremely sensitive word anymore,
and secondly, they haven’t prevented
the killing of dogs or selling their meat.
They just require that businesses
selling dog meat in the market
cover up the words,
‘dog meat’ on their signs.”
Ah yes, if it doesn't say “dog meat”
on the signs,
then no one will know that the meat
at the “dog meat,”
excuse me,
“tasty meat” festival
is actually dog.
It’s a foolproof plan.
But each year,
the Yulin Dog Meat festival brings controversy
and tons of bad publicity to Yulin.
So why doesn’t the local government stop
it?
Well, because it relates to an even greater
issue
the Communist Party wants to cover up:
poverty.
Yulin is in Guangxi—
one of China’s poorest regions.
There is a huge number of people
who can’t find jobs
and many families struggle
to make ends meet.
According to The Independent,
“many of the dog meat sellers
are peasants or farmers
on a low income.
These people rely on dog meat
to raise money for their families...
the festival draws in big money
for local meat traders.”
So for these people,
the choice is grinding,
inescapable poverty,
or stealing people’s pets
and making some money
at the Yulin Dog Meat Festival.
A mainstay of Party propaganda
is that the Chinese regime
has liberated people from poverty.
The Party definitely does not want
the desperately poor rural masses
questioning that.
But how do local officials
keep up the money-making festival,
but get rid of the bad publicity?
Well, local officials came up with a briliant plan:
They tell animal rights activists on the down-low
that they’re going to ban the sale of dog
meat.
That makes headlines.
Then Yulin gets lots of good publicity
that the dog meat festival is over!
And then once the protests die down,
bam!
It’s hot dog season.
Hot dog season...
wait a minute,
I've got an idea!
One that could save Yulin's economy
and stop the dog meat industry.
What if instead of the Yulin Dog Meat Festival,
they changed it to the Yulin Hot Dog Festival.
Locals can stop killing pets
and start making sausages.
Nathan's could sponsor it.
And they'd get tons of great publicity.
Think about it.
Yulin:
Home of the World's Biggest Hot Dog.
And even we American imperialists
wouldn’t be able to say
anything bad about the festival,
since we have our own sacred
hot dog traditions,
passed down through tens of years.
So what do you think of
the Yulin Dog Meat Festival
or future Yulin Hot Dog Festival?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Remember, China Uncensored is possible
only because of support
from viewers like you.
If you want to keep seeing
more great episodes like this,
please go to our Patreon page
where you can contribute,
for example,
a dollar per episode.
Every bit helps.
Once again,
I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
See you next time.