On this episode of China Uncensored:
Move over, Global War on Terror,
now it's the People's War or Terror!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
China is a land of diversity.
There are 56 officially recognized ethnic
groups!
Although about 92% of people
are from the Han ethnic group.
But the important thing is that they all live
in harmony
under the loving guidance of the Chinese Central
Government.
Like Tibetans!
Those rooftop snipers are there to keep everyone safe.
Same goes for the less-talked about groups
like the Uyghurs,
a Turkic minority in the Xinjiang region.
Thousands of heavily armed troops
have marched through cities in Xinjiang
over the past week,
in mass military demonstrations.
As the region’s deputy Communist Party chief
says,
it’s to show “the caring and strong leadership
of the Communist Party Central Committee.”
Also to show that “all separatist activities
and all terrorists
shall be smashed to pieces.”
How will they do that?
With the "powerful fist of the People's Democratic
Dictatorship" of course!
You know about the Chinese military’s,
um, benevolence, in Tibet.
People in the West are pretty familiar with
the political situation there,
thanks in part to Gwyneth Paltrow-era Brad
Pitt,
and notorious foam visor lover, the Dalai
Lama.
Well, the same kind of Chinese military “benevolence”
happens on a regular basis in Xinjiang, too.
Xinjiang is a giant region in Western China
with roughly the land area of Alaska.
Like Alaska, it’s mostly uninhabitable.
And they also can see Russia from their backyards.
But unlike Alaska,
Xinjiang's reality shows have never really
taken off.
Sand Road Donkeys:
Truly an underappreciated gem.
But the ethnic Uyghurs living in Xinjiang
don’t get much media attention
compared to Tibetans.
Why?
Well, they don't have a lovable religious
leader
to be their spokesperson.
And it might also be because they’re Muslim.
Not Muslim extremists generally;
mostly moderate Muslims.
But the Communist Party doesn’t like moderate
Islam
any more than they like moderate Buddhism.
Any system of belief in a higher power
is seen as a threat.
So how to solve this problem?
For decades, the Communist Party has flooded
the region
with non-Muslim ethnic Han Chinese.
Which has now increased to 38% of Xinjiang’s
population.
And the CCP has recently implemented a loving,
big brother system of mass surveillance
like “grid management, face recognition
software
and big data analytics.”
And of course,
who could forget all the things the CCP
has banned in Xinjiang at various times,
because they’re too dangerous:
Beards, veils, traditional clothing, the internet,
and even, for civil servants,
fasting during the holy month of Ramadan.
Hey, fasting is dangerous.
You’re not yourself when you’re hungry.
I'm looking at you, Betty White.
Now it used to be that Uyghurs who were not
fully supportive
of their benevolent communist overlords
were called “splittists”—
the same term used for Tibetans.
But after 9/11,
the Communist Party adopted a more politically
savvy label:
terrorists.
According to Beijing Cream,
“Everything—from the theft of sheep to
a land seizure protest
to a fight with knives—
can now be labeled as ‘terrorism,’
as long as Uyghurs and Han are involved in
the conflict.”
It’s lead to what state-run media are calling
“the People’s War on Terrorism.”
And if your neighbor turns you in
for being a terrorist sympathizer,
which they get a reward for by the way,
you might find yourself subjected to,
shall we say,
“enhanced interrogation techniques.”
Unless you then turn in your other neighbors
for being terrorists.
I mean, that technique worked so well
during the Cultural Revolution.
That's why there's not a single counter-revolutionary
left in China today!
Fortunately, the Party has put up colorful
propaganda
to educate the Uyghurs
about potential terrorist activities.
Like sharing banned information on video CDs.
Or installing a satellite dish.
News is dangerous.
And don’t wear veils.
You’ll be much happier without.
And if those birds become a problem, why,
there’s always friendly soldiers nearby
to shoot them down.
So if you see a group of Uighurs
happily reading Party propaganda
in front of a Chinese flag,
you can bet it has something to do with
the Xinjiang party chief saying,
“We shall load our guns, draw our swords
from their sheaths,
throw hard punches and relentlessly beat,
and strike hard without flinching
at terrorists.”
All under the watchful eye of the 40,000 security
cameras
set up in Xinjiang’s streets, public places,
and mosques.
And now the latest news,
they're going to use GPS surveillance
to keep track of every car in the region.
This is not to say there are no real terrorist
problems
in Xinjiang.
It’s just that when the persecution of Muslims
in Xinjiang
becomes severe,
I imagine that Islamic extremists around the
world
will have an easier time convincing otherwise
peaceful Uyghurs
that violently rising up against the Chinese
government
is their only option.
Don’t worry though,
Chinese leader Xi Jinping has a plan.
“Build a ‘wall of bronze and iron’
to fight against terrorism.”
A wall?
This sounds like a job for Matt Damon.
So what do you think of the
"People's War on Terrorism" in Xinjiang?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.