On this episode of china uncensored,
the Chinese Communist party is not going to
like this interview.
Hi welcome to china uncensored I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
I'm here in Australia.
The country slash continent has been reeling
from the revelation
that the Chinese communist party
has been influencing Australian politicians.
But I sat down with New South Wales member
of parliament
for the Greens Party David Shoebridge—
a politician who’s not afraid to talk about
Beijing’s most sensitive issues.
Thank you for joining me today.
Are we doing this interview outside because
Green members
don't believe in indoor offices?
We have an office, but I always think it's
nice to get out in the park.
Sydney, thankfully, is blessed with some beautiful
parks.
Definitely.
Why don't you tell us a little bit about the
Greens,
just what you're about?
We're a party that's got four basic pillars
behind it,
which is ecological sustainability, social
justice,
grassroots democracy, and peace and nonviolence.
How is the Chinese Communist Party infiltrating
Australian politics?
I think the biggest impact of the Chinese
government
and the concern about the regime in Australian
politics
is this insidious self-censorship that we
see from Australian
politicians scared to call out obvious human
rights abuses in China,
scared to support democracy movements in places
like Hong Kong,
scared to really openly challenge China on
some of those
appalling foreign relations decisions,
such as the ongoing occupation of Tibet.
It's that self-censorship that I think is
so, so deeply frustrating,
and it's all because they fear a backlash
from China,
a backlash on trade, or a backlash on our
economic relationship.
Australia has one of the largest and deepest
economic relationships
with anyone is with China.
We have a massive trade relationship with
China.
But China buys our coal, and our steel,
and our iron ore, and our agricultural exports,
and our education services
not because they think we're a bunch of nice
guys,
not because we're friends and we all
sit around and have a cup of tea together,
not because they can come over
and tickle our bellies and we'll do what they
want.
They buy our stuff because it's
some of the highest quality and best priced
products
and services anywhere in the world.
They'll continue to do that whether or not
we call China out
for its systemic human rights abuses or not.
I can't understand why otherwise intelligent
people
in positions of power don't get that.
And what can Australian politicians do to
resist this influence?
They could show a bit of courage, they could
grow a backbone,
and they could just stand up for human rights
abuses
wherever they're happening on the planet.
That would be a good start.
I think that's asking for a miracle.
Well , you know, I don't think it's a miracle.
I think it should be the basic minimum standard
that citizens
across the world ask of their politicians.
So, for years, you've talked about
one of the party's most sensitive issues,
organ harvesting from prisoners of conscience.
How are you still in office?
I've definitely had direct attacks from the
Chinese consulate
when I raise things in our state parliament.
I find that remarkable.
I haven't had those direct attacks from any
other government,
even though I may raise sensitive issues about
U.S. foreign policy,
I may raise sensitive issues about Australia's
foreign policy,
and its engagement with other regimes.
It was when I raised the concerns about the
way China
goes about forcibly organ harvesting,
that's the only time that I've had that direct
pushback.
In fact, a letter came from the consulate
to
basically every MP in the state parliament.
Can you give us a specific example of some
of that influence?
I have a private member's bill that would
prevent Australians
or anybody ordinarily resident here from going
overseas
and engaging in unethical organ harvesting.
Of course, I view unethical organ harvesting
as a deep moral issue.
Just for clarity, what do you mean by unethical
trade in organs?
Any trade that was for a commercial reason,
any trade where there was a degree of exploitation,
and of course any trade where there was a
lack of consent.
I'd put top of that list what we see in China,
where we know there are organs being provided
through their massive transplantation system.
There are organs being provided, almost certainly,
from prisoners from conscience, and almost
certainly without consent.
Putting to one side the fact that China has
admitted that
they use the organs of executed prisoners.
If any Australian was to leave Australia
and engage in one of those trades in China,
or Egypt, or wherever,
that would be a very serious crime on the
statute books here.
If they returned, they would be found
ordinarily prosecuted for an offense
the equivalent of manslaughter.
What was the Communist Party's response to
that legislation?
Well, the consulate was less than chuffed.
Were they?
It may surprise you.
We had a briefing that we put on in the New
South Wales parliament.
When I was walking in the corridors of the
parliament,
I had a number of colleagues from different
parties saying that they supported it,
and giving me their personal support.
We put a briefing on.
We had some human rights experts and some
medical experts
come in to do a briefing about the bill
and why we were presenting the bill.
Meanwhile, we had a huge petition presented,
so there was strong public support for it.
We had more than a quarter of a million people
sign a petition in support of the bill,
so there was some political support for it
in the populace.
Individual MPs from different parties said
they supported it.
People generally don't like the idea of innocent
people being killed for their organs.
It's not a hard sell.
If you explain to people what the problem
is,
they clearly want us to do something about
it.
They expect their state and federal MPs to
do something about it.
We put the briefing on, but the morning of
the briefing,
a letter was sent from the Chinese consulate
to each MP in the state parliament,
basically saying, "The briefing is a dangerous
attack on China,"
that my office had worked with this dangerous
grouping called Falun Gong,
that this was a direct attack on China,
and this kind of behavior in Australian parliaments
prejudiced
the ongoing commercial relationship with China.
An extraordinary intervention.
How successful was that letter?
It was bloody successful.
We didn't get a single MP from either of the
larger parties,
the Labor Party or the Coalition.
They all backed out.
They all backed out, even though we'd had
a series of RSVPs.
So the head of China's organ transplant system,
Dr. Huang Jiefu,
has said they've stopped using organs from
executed prisoners.
I plainly don't believe those statements that
come largely
from the central Beijing bureaucracy that
say
they're no longer using executed prisoners,
they're relying only on donors,
because when you look at the numbers
in that most recent Matas and Kilgour study,
the size of the transplant industry in China
is massive.
Their pool of donated organs, given that there's
no history
of donation and there are cultural barriers
to it in China,
their pool or organs is tiny.
And something has to explain the shortfall
between
the tiny number of organs that would come
through their infant-
Transplant system.
Transplant donation system, and the massive
scale of their
increasingly commercial transplant industry.
Clearly, on any view, that's being serviced
by amongst other things executed prisoners.
For the Chinese to be in denial of that, they
can say what they like,
but the numbers just don't stack up.
Yeah.
I believe that report you mentioned, Bloody
Harvest,
puts the number at about 60 to 100,000 organ
transplants a year.
Yes, with a donation system that's providing
at best 10% of that.
So where's the shortfall coming from?
If Huang Jiefu can come out
and explain where the shortfall comes from,
I will believe him when he says that
it's not coming from executed prisoners.
Of course, Huang Jiefu has a history with
Australia.
That's one of the reasons why I think we have
an obligation
to challenge him on this.
He's been given an honorary doctorate from
our oldest
and most prestigious university, the University
of Sydney.
It's actually where I graduated.
I was going to ask.
You've done some digging into
Dr. Huang's relationship with the University
of Sydney.
Can you tell us a bit about that?
Huang Jiefu has been important from the eyes
of the University of Sydney
by establishing links with higher education
facilities
particularly in Beijing.
That then produces a large number of overseas
students
and commercial success for the University
of Sydney.
I would say primarily for that reason he was
being celebrated
and given an honorary doctorate,
to bolster the commercial interests of the
University of Sydney.
I found it remarkable that when
I raised concerns about his deeply unethical
history,
and he admits to transplanting hundreds if
not thousands of livers
from executed prisoners, he admits to that,
when I pointed out that that was a gross ethical
breach by any standards,
would be unlawful here,
the Sydney University administration and the
Senate simply ignored me.
For me, it was a clear case of them putting
narrow commercial interests
ahead of what I think should be
minimum ethical standards for our universities.
Didn't you sue them?
They were asked to release emails about this
relationship.
We have laws that are euphemistically called
“freedom of information” laws in Australia.
I think most Western democracies have them.
At least on paper.
We have the laws on paper.
I requested all of the communications that
went to the Senate,
and went to the university when they were
considering
granting him the honorary doctorate,
and what I got back was page, after page,
after page
of blanked-out documents,
because they didn't want to show the public
what they'd said
about him in recommending him.
It was entirely redacted.
I think we got one email that had gone to
all staff and students,
which we already had,
which largely led to our freedom of information
request.
All of the actual key documents,
the reasons they gave for giving this guy
an honorary doctorate,
all of that was blanked out.
You sued them to unredact that.
Yeah.
We had to take them to court to get them to
unredact it,
and we ended up getting a significant amount
of it unredacted.
And what it showed mainly was what they were
refusing to look at.
There was no information going to the Senate
or the decision-makers
about this man's history of engaging in illegal
and unethical organ transplants,
no mention of the fact that he'd engaged in
hundreds if not thousands
of liver transplants using the organs of executed
prisoners.
With none of that information going before
the Senate,
they just granted him the honorary doctorate.
It's like a rubber stamp.
To go back to the infiltration of Australian
society,
what can your average Australian do
in the face of Communist Party infiltration
into Australian society?
I think the first thing is it's a question
of perspective.
I don't pretend, and I don't think it's true,
that they've got some sort of tentacles that
go all through our society,
and they direct how our state and federal
governments operate.
It's not that, but they are willing to exercise
influence when
they feel like it's something that's seriously
challenging the regime.
They're very sensitive about organ harvesting.
They're very sensitive about Falun Gong.
You'll find almost no other MP actively running
those issues,
because they get monstered.
I think the best thing you can do, most Australians
could do,
is just spend more time with people from Chinese
heritage.
Get to know them.
Engage in those one-to-one citizen exchanges,
because the people of Chinese heritage and
descent
who have Australia as their home,
and we're super lucky to have them,
they cannot become, and I'd be deeply anxious
if they were to become,
the targets of what may become a racist backlash,
notionally targeted at the regime,
but the concern is it will end up being targeted
at
people of Chinese heritage living in Australia.
That would be deeply unfair.
That actually makes a lot of sense.
Are you sure you're a politician?
I take the view that there are so few people
in politics
who actually are willing to say it like it
is.
They're always trying to hedge their bets.
You know, “What would regime A think about
it?
What would this little sectional interest
in the community think about it?”
I think people want politicians, I hope,
to be trying to actually say the truth,
not trying to doublespeak.
The Chinese Communist Party often accuses
critics
of racism or intolerance to silence them.
How can we raise legitimate concerns about
the Party’s actions
and not be racist?
Well, I think you've just got to be extremely
careful to distinguish
between the actions of a government and the
actions
and the intents of a nation's people...
In my mind, the Chinese people need to be
an ally with us in this.
They suffer far more from the authoritarian
nature of their government
than we do.
I get a cranky letter.
They suffer from a regime
that is willing to jail them if they speak
their mind,
or wish to exercise a faith
that that organization doesn't agree with.
Or remove their organs.
Or remove their organs, kill them and remove
their organs.
In Australia, which has a very, very ugly
history of racism,
and a big part of that racism has been directed
against
people of Chinese descent, people of Asian
descent, Asian heritage,
I think it is very hard to have that discussion
and to work out
where to draw the boundaries.
I think we need to acknowledge that.
A lot of sensitivities there.
And quite rightly sensitivities.
In fact, the former Prime Minister John Howard,
as recently as 20 years ago,
was toying with an actively racist immigration
policy again.
That is very raw and real in Australia,
and that means when you're engaging
in a critique of the Chinese government,
you have to make it abundantly clear that
we're standing
in solidarity with the Chinese people, both
there and here.
When you bring up sensitive issues like organ
harvesting,
are you ever concerned that this might cost
you votes?
I actually don't think that speaking up
for human rights costs you votes.
We're a party that has a fundamental belief
in core human rights and social justice issues.
If we're not willing to speak up about this,
then who would?
I actually think the great bulk of people,
whether it's Australia,
or the United States, or wherever, they actually
want politicians
to I think stand up and challenge power when
power is behaving badly.
They want them to tell the truth.
Basically, they want them to tell the truth
simply.
And I understand you take a lot of your constituents
out for hikes in the bush.
Yeah.
We have a very successful Greens bushwalking
club.
The only problem with it, sometimes it's too
popular,
and we have too many people out on our walks.
I feel like a bit of a sheepdog trying to
keep
40 or 50 people on track for a bushwalk,
but we're blessed in Australia, particularly
in Sydney.
We're surrounded by national parks, amazing
places,
easily accessible within a day.
For me, that's one of the reasons I'm in politics,
to protect and celebrate those natural parts
of the world.
That's great.
Maybe next time I'm in Australia,
we can do another interview in the bush.
Yeah, let's go to the Blue Mountains.
We can do the Grand Canyon, one of my favorite
walks.
Sounds great.
Thank you very much for joining me today.
No problem.
My pleasure.
Always good to speak.
I just want to thank everyone who contributes
to China Uncensored on Patreon.
It's a website where people can support our
show.
Thanks to you we were able to come out to
Australia
and talk to people like David Shoebridge.
Visit Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored
and learn how you can support the show.