A new virus is killing in China
While China’s military is on the move
Plus, can things really get worse?!
That and more on this week’s China news
headlines.
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
This episode is sponsored by Surfshark.
Because you should be using a reliable VPN
whenever you go online.
So...you know, it’s as if things couldn’t
get any worse.
My generation grew up with the threat of global
terrorism,
came of age during a global financial meltdown,
and now we’re trying to raise kids in a
pandemic.
On top of all that a giant asteroid
is going to fly by the Earth next month.
NASA says it won’t hit us...
but can we really trust NASA?
I mean, NASA’s covered up how the aliens
killed JFK on 9/11!
Think it can’t get worse?
Bears are coming out of hibernation early.
Bears.
Go back to sleep, bears.
There’s nothing out here for you.
And now, potentially more deadly than the
CCP coronavirus—
or CCP Virus, for short—
...a new virus has emerged in China!
Ok, Hantavirus is not new.
It’s just newly emerging.
Again.
There have been outbreaks before.
According to a Swedish scientist,
“It spreads from rats [or] mice
if humans ingest their body fluids.
Human-human transmission is rare.
Please do not panic,
unless you plan to eat rats.”
What else am I supposed to eat!
I live in New York City.
Rats are all that’s left after hoarders
took the bread!
Well, there’s still plenty of gluten-free
bread.
But clearly we’d ALL rather eat rats.
What’s that, Shelley?
There are actually several types of hantaviruses
that can cause different diseases,
and I can get sick just from breathing the
air
around contaminated rodent droppings?
I am never taking the subway again.
What’s that, Shelley?
Subway rats don’t carry hantavirus?
Oh good.
So I can still eat them.
According to the US Centers for Disease Control
and Prevention,
hantavirus infections are rare.
But the types of hantaviruses most commonly
seen in Asia
have anywhere from a 1 to 15 percent mortality
rate.
That’s potentially much higher than the
CCP Virus.
Though communism itself also has a very high
mortality rate.
Speaking of which,
China has lifted travel restrictions in Hubei
province.
Hubei is the epicenter of the coronavirus.
Unless you believe the Chinese Communist Party
when they say it really began in America.
And I thought NASA conspiracy theories were
intense.
Tens of millions of people in Hubei province
have been under lockdown for two months.
But China’s National Health Commission
said there were no new coronavirus infections
and so the restrictions could be lifted.
And when have Chinese authorities ever lied
about numbers?!
However, as we’ve reported before,
there could be a second wave of the CCP Virus
already spreading inside China.
As the lockdown is lifted,
people who have the CCP Virus but aren’t
showing symptoms,
could continue to spread it around China and
the world.
But if you’re concerned about the Chinese
Communist Party
doing another round of coronavirus cover-ups—don’t
be!
China’s premier Li Keqiang is warning local
officials:
no second cover up.
So if any local officials are currently covering
it up,
the solution is simple:
They should cover up their coverup.
But Chinese officials are very concerned
about a second wave of infections.
That’s why they just issued this statement,
banning all foreigners from entering China,
even with a valid visa.
Remember when China and the WHO
were telling everyone travel bans were unnecessary?
And a Chinese diplomat compared travel bans
to turning away Jewish refugees during the
Holocaust?
Yeah, that happened.
Meanwhile, a concerned Chinese father
has created a safety pod for his baby.
“This baby safety pod is modified from a
cat carrier backpack.
It has an electronic fan system.
It can offer a totally isolated environment
when going out.
It can provide a safe and comfortable environment
for the baby.”
So, people around the world are isolating
themselves,
practicing social distancing and avoiding
contact with others,
while this guy runs around with a baby pod?
I guess we’re living in Death Stranding
now.
Great.
The CCP Virus has devastated the world.
So isn’t it nice that the CCP—
the Chinese Communist Party—
is selflessly extending
a “helping hand to countries around the
world
in the global battle against COVID-19?”
As state-run media says,
“The Chinese government has announced that
it will provide medical supplies to 82 countries.”
Which makes it sound like they’re donating
supplies, doesn’t it?
But in most cases they’re not actually donating
them.
The countries have to pay for them.
Now it’s not a problem for the Chinese government
to sell medical supplies.
That’s fine.
But then using that as propaganda
to make it sound like they’re generously
donating supplies
and saving the world from the disease that
they caused?
That’s low.
Incidentally, 80% of coronavirus test kits
'gifted'—aka sold—
to the Czech Republic by China didn’t work.
Shots were fired as Chinese boats
rammed a Taiwanese coast guard vessel.
And that was the second time this month.
On top of all the military harassment of Taiwan,
“Taiwan’s government says China has intentionally
hampered its efforts to get virus information
direct from the World Health Organization.
China blocks Taiwan’s WHO membership
as it considers the island merely one of its
provinces.”
Shameless and disgusting...
is what the CCP called Taiwan.
A Chinese official said,
“The use of the epidemic to stir up
cross-Taiwan Strait confrontations
at a time when the outbreak in Taiwan
is picking up is shameless and disgusting.”
And again, for clarity, that was the Chinese
Communist Party
criticizing Taiwan for being shameless and
disgusting.
That’s like the pot calling the magical
pink unicorn black.
Meanwhile, China’s Maritime Militia is fanning
out
in disputed territorial waters in the South
China Sea.
We did a whole episode about
the Maritime Militia back in September.
They’re a fun bunch.
The point is, just because
you exposed the world to a deadly pandemic,
doesn’t mean you can’t keep throwing gasoline
on the fire!
Wow, reminds me of Twitter.
I wonder if there is some kind of catastrophe
the Chinese Communist Party is trying to distract
people from.
Last week I told you that the Chinese government
kicked out reporters from the New York Times,
Wall Street Journal, and Washington Post.
Well this week, the the papers penned this
open letter,
begging the Chinese regime to let them back
in.
I mean, what the Chinese Communist Party
did to them was really unfair!
I mean, all three papers had tried so hard
to be good to the Communist Party.
Like by not covering sensitive topics.
And by letting the Communist Party directly
put propaganda
in their newspapers as paid advertising.
You really want the Chinese Communist Party
to let you back in?
Start writing articles about how the Party
kills Falun Gong and Uighurs for their organs.
Put those on the front page.
Do it every day.
Pretty soon, the Party will figure out
it’s better to have you in China,
where they can still control you.
China has launched three new
military surveillance satellites into orbit.
But despite the success,
celebration was muted as technicians
applied appropriate social distancing.
Now while Chinese military surveillance satellites
may sound scary, don’t worry,
they “will be used for electromagnetic environment
detection
and related technological tests.”
Just trust the Chinese military.
And with the knowledge the Chinese military
has a bunch of surveillance satellites overhead,
I think now’s a good time to tell you about
the VPN Surfshark.
When you go online, everything you do is being
tracked and logged—
by the websites you visit and your internet
service provider.
And in many cases, by the government.
And if you’re in an authoritarian country
like China,
this kind of tracking can put you
at risk of surveillance and even arrest.
So I recommend you use Surfshark to protect
yourself online.
When you use Surfshark’s CleanWeb mode,
you’ll be protected from trackers, plus
a lot of ads and malware.
And with Surfshark,
you can connect as many devices as you want.
Try it out with a 30-day money back guarantee.
Surfshark has a special discount for China
Uncensored fans.
Go to https://surfshark.com/uncensored
and use the code UNCENSORED to get 83% off
a 2-year plan
and one extra month free.
Protect yourself online today!
Click the link below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.