On this episode of China Uncensored,
live election coverage from Beijing...
sort of.
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
As a member of the media,
I have to say that nothing gets us more excited
than an election.
It’s like sports for news!
Winners and losers,
ridiculous 3D graphics,
and 30 people yelling over each other
on live television.
Plus, who doesn’t love a surprise ending!
“He’s won the 2016 US presidential election.
One of the most extraordinary elections
any of us have ever seen.”
Well, since China Uncensored is about China,
I had to watch the US election last year
from the sidelines.
But now, it’s my turn.
It’s what I’ve been waiting for the last
five years.
Yes, it’s time for the 19th National Party
Congress
of the Communist Party of China!
Think of it like the Republican
or Democratic National Conventions.
Participants travel from across the country,
wearing the colorful native dress of their
regions.
It’s a hugely staged event where delegates
“vote” on predetermined outcomes.
And there are some crazy after-parties.
I hear former premier Zhu Rongji
throws the best EDM ragers,
if that’s your thing.
But there is one tiny little difference.
Since the Communist Party is the only Party
in China,
the people they chose at their congress
will be the ones who rule the country
for the next five years.
You see, as an organization,
the Chinese Communist Party sits on top of
the Chinese government like a giant parasite.
The kind that mind controls its host into
doing
whatever the parasite wants.
So while the Party’s top leaders
also hold government positions,
it’s their Party positions that really count.
For example,
Xi Jinping holds the title of President,
but he was only appointed President
because he holds the top Communist Party position:
General Secretary.
But most people outside China
don’t understand how this works.
So the 19th Party Congress is a great opportunity
for state-run media to make up complete lies
about how China has democracy
and meaningful elections.
“During the Party’s National Congress,
elections are also held for the Central Committee,
and the Central Commission for Discipline
Inspection.”
Yes, it’s just like an election.
And that’s why,
even with no ballots cast yet,
we here at China Uncensored are able to project,
with 99.9% certainty,
that Xi Jinping will be “elected” to another
five-year term
as head of the Communist Party.
It’s a bold prediction,
but we will stake our reputation on it.
But just because Xi isn’t going anywhere,
doesn’t mean there’s nothing to watch
here.
There’s been huge speculation
about who’s going to be in
the next Politburo Standing Committee,
the seven men in charge of the Communist Party.
There’s even an online game
where you can pick your own Standing Committee.
Just like Fantasy Football.
They wouldn’t take my pick though,
which was Xi, Xi, Xi, Xi, Xi, Xi, and Xi.
What?
It could happen.
In a show of power,
Xi Jinping opened the 19th Party Congress
on Wednesday
by making everyone else sit through
his three and a half hour long speech.
Wow, I guess they don’t teach public speaking
at the Central Party School.
But everyone thoroughly enjoyed the speech,
as you can see from this thrilling montage
of past and current Party officials
listening attentively.
Xi Jinping’s speech was called,
“Secure a Decisive Victory in Building
a Moderately Prosperous Society in All Respects
and Strive for the Great Success
of Socialism with Chinese Characteristics
for a New Era.”
Or to paraphrase,
“Xi Jinping is Large and in Charge.”
But here on China Uncensored,
we’re not going to just tell you what was
in Xi’s speech.
No, we’re taking coverage of the Party Congress
to a whole new level.
Our very own Shelley Zhang
is reporting live from Beijing.
Shelley, isn’t it great to be back in the
motherland?Yes, Chris, it’s great.
You don’t seem excited.
I’m super excited.
You seem kind of...upset.
Why would I be upset, Chris?
I don’t know why you’d be upset.
This is a great opportunity for some on-the-ground
action.
Mmm, right.
Just one question, Chris.
Why did you send your only Chinese correspondent
to Beijing?
Isn’t it obvious?
You speak the language,
you blend in.
You can go undercover,
get the real story.
If I went,
I’d stand out like a sore, white thumb.
Are you kidding me?
First of all, I don’t blend in.
I’ve had to pretend to be Korean three times
today.
And if you were here and you got caught doing
this,
yeah sure, you’d get roughed up a little,
accused of being CIA,
and then deported on the next flight back
to New York.
Me?
I could end up spending the next three years
in a black jail in Hunan,
making Christmas lights with only one kidney.
Are you suggesting you want to leave?
What do you think?
No!
You can’t leave now.
China Uncensored is the number one comedy
news show
about China based in New York
and you’re our woman on the ground!
You’re not a quitter, are you?
I can’t believe you...fine.
Fine.
Let’s just get this over with.
That’s great!
I knew you wouldn’t let us down.
Because you’re a team player.
So Shelley, tell us about the color on the
ground.
The atmosphere.
Which faction has the best butter cow?
No one has a butter...
Wait, I almost forgot.
Put on the hat.
No.
Come on.
I’m not putting on the hat.
Put it on!
I’m not putting on!
Look, I’ll put on the hat, too.
Then we’ll both be wearing the hat.
There.
Isn’t this more fun already?
So much fun.
So Shelley, let’s get down to it.
What’s the theme of this year’s Congress?
National rejuvenation.
Really?!
Xi only said it like 50 times in his...oh
no.
So in other words, Xi Jinping wants to make
China great again.
Yes.
And you didn’t want to wear the hat.
But let’s keep going.
Are there going to be any surprises
during the 19th Party Congress?
Without a doubt.
Really.
Does it involve who’s going to be “elected”
to the Politburo Standing Committee?
Signs point to yes.
Wow.
Can you elaborate on that?
Reply hazy, try again.
Wait.
Are you...
reading this off a Magic 8 ball?!
You have problems with my sources?
Why don’t you come over here then,
and I’ll go back to New York.
Actually, I’m fine here.
Look, Chris,
there’s a reason Chinese politics is called
a black box.
You can’t tell what’s really happening
because each faction will only leak information
that’s to their own benefit.
The media might have “inside sources”
but that means nothing.
They have no idea what’s going on.
So it’s exactly like the US election.
Except for the part where I’ll get arrested
for being here.
Alright, let’s cut to the chase.
There’s only two things
that we need to know from the Party Congress.
One:
Does Xi Jinping have enough power to reshape
the Politburo Standing Committee in his image.
And Two:
Does Xi Jinping have enough power to get named
Chairman of the Communist Party.
Chairman, eh?
The big C.
That would be a huge move.
Would Xi really do that?
Don’t underestimate Xi Jinping’s ambition.
Some analysts are like,
oh there’s no precedent for doing these
things.
But since Xi’s been in power,
he’s completely overhauled the military.
He’s spent five years going after his political
enemies.
He’s going to change the Party to what he
wants it to be.
So you’re saying that Xi’s not a precedential
kind of guy.
Did you really just do that?
Pretty good, right?
So what about the Politburo Standing Committee?
How could he change that?
I don’t even want to…
Come on.
What if I promise not to make any more puns?
Ok deal.
It starts with Wang Qishan,
Xi’s ally and head of the anti-corruption
campaign.
Wang is 69,
so according to the “seven up, eight down”
precedent
started by former leader Jiang Zemin,
Wang is supposed to retire.
But Xi might try to keep him on, anyway.
So we’re looking to see if Xi
can keep him on Wonger than expected?
What did we just talk about?
Sorry, it won’t happen again.
Ok.
If Xi keeps Wang,
it means Xi is powerful enough to shake things
up,
especially since Jiang’s faction is attacking
Wang.
Or Xi could let Wang retire,
but reduce the number of Standing Committee
members
from 7 to 5,
which would also give him more control.
So we’ll have to Xi how Wong this goes on.
I really hate your puns.
Hey, don’t be a Party pooper.
But seriously, can Xi Jinping become chairman
and change the standing committee?
It’s hard to say.
Xi’s not as powerful
as the Western media makes him look...
not yet.
When the Congress ends next week
and we see the new Standing Committee,
we’ll know how much Xi can change the Party
in the next five years.
So after the Party Congress,
there’s the after Party Congress?
You know the best part about all of this?
What?
I could have told you all of this from New
York.
Speaking of that,
did you get my email about sneaking into
the Great Hall of the People
and getting us some exclusive footage?
Uh, Chris, I gotta go.
Uh, Shelley?
I’m sure she’s fine.
Thanks Shelley!
And there you have it,
the latest from Beijing.
The 19th Party Congress will go on,
and on, through next Tuesday.
And by then,
we’ll know slightly more
about what’s going to happen
over the next five years.
What are your predictions?
Leave your comments below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Want more great China Uncensored content?
Sure you do!
Then go to ChinaUncensored.tv.
Every Friday, we upload a complete half-hour
episode,
before it gets chopped up and put on YouTube.
So go to ChinaUncensored.tv now to check it
out.