Tensions between Taiwan and China\h
are at an all time high.
But Taiwan has extended an olive branch.
How’d that turn out?
Welcome to China Uncensored. I’m Chris Chappell.
Boy, tensions between China and Taiwan\h
have been getting really bad lately.
All of China’s thinly veiled threats\h
after the US sold weapons to Taiwan.
All those Chinese warplanes flying over Taiwan.
I mean this is getting nuts. Even Japanese anime\h
celebrities can’t escape China’s campaign over\h\h
Taiwan. Uhh, Shelley, are we playing mad libs\h
with the script? Oh, no, it’s a real thing.
This has all been in the lead up to\h
Taiwan's National Day, which was October 10.\h\h
National Day really upsets the Chinese\h
Communist Party, because it kind of gives\h\h
the impression that Taiwan is its own\h
country with its own national holiday.
That’s why the Chinese Communist Party does\h
things that look crazy to normal countries,\h\h
like telling Indian media how to cover Taiwan’s\h
National Day. By not calling Taiwan a country.
That kind of attitude leaves the\h
Party wide open to trolling.\h
And India really delivered. Indian politicians\h
wished Taiwan a happy national day.
And Taiwan National Day started trending in India.
One local Indian politician put up a Happy\h
National Day sign outside the Chinese embassy.
And someone even commissioned\h
this Taiwan is not China cake.
Meanwhile the President of Taiwan\h\h
Tsai Ing-wen tweeted her thanks to\h
all of Taiwan’s dear friends in India.
And started talking about\h
her favorite Indian food.
So, the Chinese Communist Party\h
tried to control Indian media,\h\h
leading to a national backlash in\h
India and an India-Taiwan lovefest.\h\h
Once again, the Chinese Communist\h
Party scores! Against itself.\h
Speaking of India, we just did an episode on our\h
other show, America Uncovered, about the Quad, an\h\h
alliance to counter China. And India is a big part\h
of that. I’ll put a link to that episode below.\h
But back to Taiwan’s National Day. In her\h
National Day speech, President Tsai extended\h\h
an olive branch to the Communist Party. She\h
called for meaningful dialogue with China.
That’s great! Authoritarian regimes always\h
respond well to talking things out. So\h\h
what was China’s response?
Well, just hours after her\h
speech, Chinese state-run CCTV\h\h
aired this video of China’s military\h
launching a simulated invasion of Taiwan.
Well, I guess that’s a form of dialogue. But\h
perhaps they could make themselves clearer.
“Taiwan denounced China for releasing a forced TV\h
confession of a Taiwanese businessman. The man has\h\h
been missing in China for over a year due to his\h
support of Hong Kong's pro-democracy movement.”
Huh, so they’ve kidnapped a Taiwanese\h
citizen. But I think the Communist\h\h
Party’s actions could still really be open to\h
interpretation. Can they be a little clearer?
“In its annual work report this\h
year, the Chinese government\h\h
removed the word ‘peaceful’ from long-standing\h
references to ‘reunification’ with Taiwan.”
Okay, let me see if I can understand this dialogue\h
coming from communist China. They’re saying:\h\h
They are highly militarized, they\h
kidnap other countries’ citizens,\h\h
and they’re planning invade a democratic\h
country to murder their people.
Okay, the message is crystal clear.\h
There’s only one way to take that.\h\h
China’s bond market is incredible! Buy buy buy!!!
But surely the Chinese Communist Party\h
can at least appreciate the effort\h\h
by President Tsai Ing-wen\h
to deescalate the situation.
Recently Taiwan’s Foreign Minister\h
told NPR that Taiwan would not\h\h
seek formal ties with the US right now.
That’s got to make the CCP happy. So surely,\h
they’re willing to back down a bit, right?\h
Well, here’s Hu Xijin the editor in chief\h
of my favorite Chinese state run media,\h\h
the Global Times.
“The change of tone indicated\h
the Tsai administration\h\h
has fathomed the severity of a possible military\h
conflict with Beijing over its provocations.”
Hu added, “Beijing must not ‘be fooled\h
into believing the gesture of goodwill\h\h
of the ruling Democratic\h
Progressive Party of Taiwan’”\h\h
and that “continued military muscle-flexing\h
is the only answer to cross-strait stability.”
So...if Taiwan makes a move like it’s\h
going to seek formal ties with the US,\h\h
China will threaten to invade. If Taiwan\h
backs down and says we can resolve things\h\h
through dialogue, China will threaten to\h
invade. Well at least they have options.
And now it’s time for me to\h
answer a question from one of you,\h\h
who supports China Uncensored through\h
the crowdfunding website Patreon.
Ronny Ager-Wick asks, “Is there any way\h
that a country who has been tricked by\h\h
China's debt trap diplomacy can get out of it\h
without paying? What would happen if they just\h\h
stopped paying and defaulted on the loan?\h
Could they declare the "investment" illegal\h\h
and thus reject China's demands? Or could\h
they have a revolution, a new constitution,\h\h
and thus be regarded as a new country,\h
leaving China to collect from the old regime?”
Ohh, great question. This in fact has happened.\h\h
In Malaysia. Malaysia was hugely in debt to\h
China. To the tune of 34 billion dollars.
That was thanks to Najib Razak, who was\h
Malaysia’s prime minister for nearly a decade.
Turns out he was very corrupt.
And a lot of that corruption had to do with\h
China. But before he got a 12 year jail term,\h\h
he lost the 2018 election to\h
this guy, Mahathir Mohamad.
Part of his campaign was about standing up to\h
China, which gets more and more popular with time.
He was openly critical of\h
China’s Belt and Road Initiative.
“None of our people are employed\h
as workers. None of our companies\h\h
are used for designing and planning and\h
supervising, et cetera. We gain nothing.”\h
\h
And after being elected,\h\h
he suspended four Chinese linked projects\h
worth about a total of 23 billion dollars.
That was worth about two-thirds of\h
all Malaysia’s Belt and Road projects.
Mahathir then began renegotiating those deals.
And it seemed to work. Some of those belt and\h
road projects restarted in 2019 after hiccups.
It follow[ed] “a rare agreement to cut its\h
cost by nearly a third to about $11 billion”
Great deal. Well, until those hiccups became a\h
gasping death wheeze because of the coronavirus.
Thanks for your question Ronny.\h
And if you’d like to have me respond to\h
your question or comment on the show for\h\h
hundreds of thousands of people to hear, join\h
what I call the China Uncensored 50 Army...
and support us in the battle against the Chinese\h
Communist Party. You can join for as little as a\h\h
dollar per episode on the crowd funding website\h
Patreon. You’ll also get some other cool perks\h\h
as well. Head over to Patreon.com/China\h
Uncensored to learn more. Link is below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell. See you next time.