On this episode of China Uncensored,
fun fact:
a live donkey,
and a tiger pit,
don’t go so well together.
Unless you’re the tiger.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
We’ve all been there, right?
You’re a shareholder in a zoo,
but the courts have for some reason
frozen the zoo’s assets for two years.
You can’t sell your stake.
Your money is stuck.
So what do you do?
Obviously, you hire a group of men
to steal the zoo’s donkey and goat.
Because you can sell them
to recoup your loses.
But then the zoo staff blocks your exit,
and is all like,
“Noooo, that’s illegal.”
So what do you do?
Obviously you get frustrated
and throw the donkey
in the tiger pit.
We’ve all been there, right?
On Monday,
zoo goers at the Yangcheng Wild Animal World
in Changzhou, Jiangsu province
watched in horror as the donkey
was forced down a slide
into a tiger pit.
The tiger pit,
having tigers in it,
proved to be a bad place
for that donkey to be.
Don't worry folks, the donkey was fine...
for dinner. The tigers ate it.
Luckily for the goat,
visitors and staff prevented the men
from throwing it in as well.
I wonder why they chose to throw
the donkey in first?
The video went viral in China
and the zoo has since apologized.
But this is just the latest scandal
involving animal abuse at zoos in China—
a country where,
let’s just say,
animal rights protections are a bit lacking.
Meet “the world’s saddest polar bear,”
as he came to be known.
He was being held in an interrogation room/exhibit
at the Grandview Aquarium in Guangzhou.
Footage of this very sad polar bear
went viral all over the world.
After public outrage at the deplorable conditions
the bear was living in,
the Aquarium decided
to move him out and make renovations.
The list of abuse goes on.
These guys were caught beating a black bear.
And then the guy taping it was caught.
This guy must be very confident the tiger
won’t confuse him with a donkey.
And ever wonder what would happen
if you force a bear and a couple of monkeys
into a bicycle race?
Pretty much what you’d think.
So what do you think?
Are you Team Tigger or Team Eeyore?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China Uncensored.
Once again, I’m your host, Chris Chappell,
see you next time.