China Attacks Australia
And joins the UN Human Rights Council
While Apple uses ethnic slave labor
That and more on this week's China news headlines
Welcome to China Uncensored. I’m Chris Chappell.\h
And I need your help. YouTube has been secretly\h\h
unsubscribing people, demonetizing us, and\h
not recommending our videos. So please,\h\h
hit that like button, share this episode, and\h
support us on Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
Revenge! That’s how Chinese state-run China\h
Daily is framing the relationship between China\h\h
and Australia. This editorial\h
accuses the Australian government\h\h
of “stigmatizing and demonizing”\h
the relationship with China.
Keep in mind, this is coming from the same regime\h\h
that called Australia the\h
poor white trash of Asia.
And has launched a trade war against\h
Australia for political grievances.
That’s because Australia has started to wise up to\h\h
the Chinese Communist Party’s campaign\h
of unrestricted warfare, and push back.
Part of that was related to a 2018 Belt and Road\h
agreement with the Australian state of Victoria.
The Australian federal government is now\h
considering cancelling that agreement.
Why? Because it could put the\h
work of Australian scientists\h\h
into the hands of the Chinese\h
Communist dictatorship.
The China Daily editorial says\h
this “is obviously intended\h\h
as an act of revenge by Australian\h
Prime Minister Scott Morrison.”
You know, I’m not sure China Daily understands\h
what it wrote. Revenge implies that someone\h\h
wronged you. Surely China Daily isn’t saying\h
the Chinese regime wronged Australia? Are they?
2020 is finally over! And to kick off 2021,\h
China will be starting a three year term\h\h
on the United Nations Human Rights Council!
What? You thought this year would be better?\h
Haha, enjoy your indefinite lockdown, you schlebs.
But from a certain point of view, China joining\h
the human rights council actually makes sense. You\h\h
see, the Chinese Communist Party has first-hand\h
experience with how to violate human rights.
A new report from Buzzfeed news has identified\h
hundreds of detention centers for Uyghur Muslims\h\h
in China’s Xinjiang region, and “At least 135\h
of these compounds also hold factory buildings.”
They identified these factories from\h
satellite photos from Planet Labs.\h\h
Here you can see six factories, highlighted in\h
blue. They tend to be long rectangular buildings.
This the 21st Century. Who would\h
be using ethnic slave labor?\h\h
Well, for one, Apple’s longtime supplier!
“Lens Technology, which makes iPhone glass\h
and is owned by China’s richest woman,\h\h
received Uighur Muslim laborers\h
transferred from Xinjiang.”
That’s on top of several other Apple suppliers\h\h
that have also been accused\h
of using Uyghur forced labor.
Apple is taking these accusations\h
very seriously. So seriously in fact,\h\h
that they’re lobbying against a bill\h
that would stop Uyghur forced labor.
But that’s not enough for Apple. No, they\h
are dedicated. According to a new lawsuit,\h\h
Apple also punished an American employee\h
for approving an app critical of Beijing.
But I don’t want to sound like I’m\h
being too hard on Apple. Because\h\h
there’s plenty of criticism to go around!
The EU has struck a major\h
investment deal with China.
Great! Now the EU can make lots of\h
money off an authoritarian regime\h\h
that uses concentration camps and slave labor!
But don’t worry, because as part of the deal,\h
“China has agreed to ‘make continued and\h\h
sustained efforts’ to ratify international\h
conventions on banning forced labor.”
Good. Continued and sustained efforts. Not a\h
promise to end Uyghur forced labor. No penalties\h\h
if they don’t. And certainly no inspections\h
to see if they are. This is about trust.
And considering how well China honors its\h
international commitments, like the One Country,\h\h
Two systems model in Hong Kong, I’m sure the\h
Uyghurs will be fine. But more importantly,\h\h
Europe's corporate elite will get richer.
But it’s not just European elite that benefit\h
from this investment deal. It’s the whole world!
That’s why this deal is just like China and the EU\h
jointly presenting a New Year gift to the world.
According to my favorite\h
state-run media, the Global Times,\h\h
this is about “win-win cooperation”\h
and “peaceful development.”
Welcome to 2021!
But there is some good news.
On Dec. 21, U.S. Secretary\h\h
of State Mike Pompeo announced new visa\h
restrictions on Chinese Communist Party\h\h
(CCP) officials believed to have\h
engaged in human rights abuses and\h\h
their immediate family members. US Department\h
of Homeland Security acting Secretary\h\h
Chad Wolf also said his department was\h
looking at further restrictions on China.
Hold on, Chad Wolf?\h\h
That’s the Chaddest name I’ve ever heard.\h
I’m sure Xi Jinping isn’t too fond of him.
The Trump administration is also bolstering an\h
order barring U.S. investment in Chinese firms\h\h
with ties to the Communist military.
In a statement, Secretary of State\h
Mike Pompeo said “The Executive Order\h\h
applies to all transactions by U.S. persons,\h
including individuals, institutional investors,\h\h
pension funds, university endowments,\h
banks, bond issuers, venture capital firms,\h\h
private equity firms, index firms, and other U.S.\h
entities, including those operating overseas.”
The Trump Administration is pathetic. They really\h
should take a cue from the EU about how much money\h\h
can be made in China! At least American media\h
is warning American investors about missing out!
And coming up after the break, is the\h
coronavirus getting worse inside Mainland China?
Welcome back.
Remember how China beat the coronavirus in 2020?
Well, it’s 2021, and the coronavirus\h
is getting worse inside Mainland China.
Footage emerged of authorities putting\h
paper seals on residents homes.\h\h
If authorities find the seal is\h
broken, they assume the family\h\h
violated restrictions and will\h
be sent to a quarantine center.
I mean, that’s slightly better than Chinese police\h
just beating people up for violating restrictions.
It’s hard to know how bad the CCP Virus\h
is inside China right now. Of course,\h\h
it’s hard to know how bad it ever was. But\h
according to a new study, half a million people\h\h
may have had the CCP virus in Wuhan. That’s\h
almost ten times the official figure.
Now what’s really scary about this study,\h\h
is that it was done by the Chinese Center\h
for Disease Control and Prevention.\h\h
That’s run by the state. And so if China’s\h
CDC is saying the outbreak was 10 times worse\h\h
than official figures, that suggests to me that\h
the numbers are actually even higher than that.\h\h
So high, that they had to increase the official\h
figures because they couldn’t cover it up.
But at least from a certain point of\h
view, China did beat the coronavirus.
Speaking of the coronavirus,\h\h
it turns out that the Chinese Communist Party\h
has been suppressing coronavirus research.
This is my shocked face.
The Party is giving money to military\h
scientists researching the coronavirus,\h\h
but it is also “monitoring their findings\h
and mandating that the publication of any\h\h
data or research must be approved by a new\h
task force controlled by...Xi Jinping.”
Basically the documents show that the coronavirus\h
coverup goes right to the top. And meanwhile,\h\h
the Chinese Communist Party is still\h
trying to control the narrative\h\h
by claiming that the virus didn’t come from\h
China. Including from imported frozen foods.
Like I said, it was the pizza rolls all along!!
The 10 Hong Kong activists who were arrested after\h\h
attempting to flee the city on a\h
speedboat, have been sentenced.
Keep in mind, these Hong Kong citizens were held\h
and tried in Mainland China. Which is exactly\h\h
what last year's protests were\h
originally trying to prevent.
The activists were sentenced\h
to up to three years in prison.
Maybe the UN Human Rights Council should look\h
into this. And their newest member can help!
The sentencing of the ten\h
Hongkongers follows this:\h\h
A Chinese citizen journalist has been sentenced\h
to four years for reporting on the CCP Virus.
Zhang Zhan is a former lawyer. “For several months\h\h
she shared videos that showed crowded hospitals\h
and residents worrying about their incomes.”
But for challenging the state’s official\h
narrative, she got four years in prison!
She really should have just\h
waited until the CCP realizes\h\h
it can’t keep covering things up,\h
and changes its official narrative.
One of Zhang’s lawyers said that\h
she’s been on a hunger strike\h\h
since June to protest her arrest, because she was\h
punished for exercising her freedom of speech.
“When told that she could be\h
imprisoned...Zhang ‘quoted\h\h
a passage from the bible and said she\h
would expect herself to die in prison.’”
You can’t help but admire that kind of\h
courage. While also being horribly sad.
But coming up after the break, there’s\h
actually some good China news this week.\h\h
Coming from America.
Welcome back.
To end the week on a positive note,\h
there’s some good news related to China.
It comes as President Trump signed\h
a massive omnibus spending bill\h\h
on Sunday—which we talked about on\h
our other show, America Uncovered.
One of the dozens of random bills crammed\h
into it was this, starting on page 5,037:\h\h
The Taiwan Assurance Act of 2020.
It says the US should conduct regular sales\h
and transfers of weapons to Taiwan, in order to\h\h
enhance its self-defense capabilities, including\h
undersea warfare and air defense capabilities.
This bill represents a renewed US\h
commitment to lend military support.\h\h
That’s important, because Taiwan is facing more\h
and more threats from the Chinese military—which\h\h
I’ll talk about in a special episode tomorrow.
The bill also says the US should advocate\h
for Taiwan’s participation in international\h\h
organizations where statehood is\h
not a requirement. That includes\h\h
the United Nations and the\h
World Health Organization.
I just hope the US can get Taiwan\h
back into Birdlife International—the\h\h
bird watching group that kicked Taiwan out back\h
in September after facing pressure from Beijing.
I really don’t think Birdlife should\h
require statehood for members.\h\h
I mean, they don’t require it for the birds.
And speaking of things crammed into that\h
omnibus bill, let’s flip to page 5,090:\h\h
The Tibetan Policy and Support Act of 2020.
One of the cheeky things it does is seek\h
to establish a US consulate in Tibet.
And if the CCP won’t allow\h
that, which of course it won’t,\h\h
then the US won’t authorize any\h
new Chinese consulates in the US.
So there!
The bill also allows the US government to\h\h
sanction individual Chinese officials\h
who violate human rights in Tibet.\h\h
That includes officials who interfere with the\h
reincarnation of the Dalai Lama. Not kidding.
For more than a decade, the\h
atheist Chinese Communist Party\h\h
has sought to regulate Buddhist reincarnation.\h\h
Their long game is to eventually pick a future\h
Dalai Lama who they can make into a CCP stooge.
After the Tibetan Policy and\h
Support Act passed on Sunday,\h\h
China’s Foreign Ministry wasted no\h
time, insisting that “Reincarnation\h\h
of living Buddhas including the Dalai\h
Lama must comply with Chinese laws.”
And that the US is interfering\h
in China’s internal affairs.
But really, when it comes to reincarnation,\h\h
isn’t China interfering in the\h
Universe’s internal affairs?
And now it’s time for me to\h
answer a question from you,\h\h
a fan who supports China Uncensored\h
on the crowd funding website Patreon!
Jose Vega asks, “Chris, every\h
conservative is now on Parler.\h\h
You should be there too, so we can follow you.”
Well, Jose, I’m not a conservative. Or a liberal\h
for that matter. No, I think the whole left right\h\h
political spectrum is completely wrong. It’s more\h
like a political horseshoe. Because when you go to\h\h
the extreme on either side, it loops back in on\h
itself. And I... am at the top of the horseshoe.
I call it being politically regressive. I’m\h
a regressivist! I believe in things like,\h\h
mandatory abortions for all women and men.\h
Universal basic gun, starting at age 3.\h\h
And making schools unsafe spaces. Mainly\h
by releasing large apex predators.
Can’t argue about politics if you’re running for\h
your life. Unless you have really good cardio.
Anyway, I am on Parler. You can\h
follow me @Lord of the Uncensoring.
\h
Thanks for your question and your support Jose.
And if you want to ask me a question,\h
and help me fight YouTube censorship,\h\h
join the China Uncensored 50 Cent\h
army on Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.\h\h
Choose the amount you want to contribute per\h
episode. You can also set a monthly limit.
Once again, be sure to like, subscribe and share.
I’m Chris Chappell, see you next time.