On this episode of China Uncensored,
all aboard the Chinese train line in Kenya
everyone loves!
Uh...almost everyone.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Well folks,
great news!
China has built
a new railroad line in Kenya!
Hooray! Fireworks!
It’s a freight and passenger line
that connects Kenya’s capital Nairobi
to the coastal port of Mombasa.
It’s called the Standard Gauge Railway,
also known as the Madaraka Express.
With a top speed of 75 miles per hour,
it’s not exactly a high-speed rail,
but it is three times faster
than old British train line it’s replacing,
which was finished in 1901.
The one nicknamed the “Lunatic Express”
because of the huge costs
and the thousands of people
who died constructing it,
including being eaten by lions.
It was also subject to
constant delays and breakdowns.
But it did profusely apologize for each delay.
"Oh dear.
Terribly, terribly sorry.
My apologies.
Does anybody fancy a spot of tea?"
Anyway, this new Madaraka Express
is supposed to speed up travel,
reduce transportation costs,
and transform Kenya
into an economic powerhouse.
The rail was built by China Road and Bridge
Corporation,
a Chinese state-owned company.
Which explains the awkward slogan,
“Connecting Nations,
Prospering People.”
Yes,
may you live long and prospering, people.
The train line is part of China’s
“One Belt, One Road” Initiative.
In a nutshell:
One Belt, One Road is China’s plan
for global domination.
It involves building huge infrastructure projects
around the world—
like seaports, train lines, and bridges.
They’re supposed to help with trade,
which, in China’s view,
means extracting raw materials
from poor countries
at low prices,
and selling finished made-in-China goods
back to them.
Oh, and putting everyone in debt to China.
Kind of like colonialism,
but with less guns.
So the Chinese regime
has big plans for Kenya.
The new Madaraka Express
created thousands of jobs in Kenya.
Let’s check in with the locals
and see how happy they are.
“The youth stormed the Chinese rail camp
site,
attacking and driving away workers indiscriminately.”
So, pretty happy.
That footage was from a riot last August.
You see, the railway did create
thousands of new jobs.
But not for Kenyan locals.
According to Quartz,
“One of the biggest gripes
is that Chinese companies in Kenya
import \htheir own labor.”
So a lot of jobs just go to Chinese workers.
As for the Kenyans who do get work,
well, those protests happened
because workers wanted a raise—
from two dollars fifty cents
to five dollars...
a day.
People who asked for a raise
were allegedly fired.
But paying low wages
is not the biggest problem.
Since China Road and Bridge Corporation
began construction of the railway
a few years ago,
it’s been accused of firing workers
without cause,
dredging sand from Kenyan beaches
for construction material,
and even stealing water
from local communities.
To be fair though,
they have organized basketball games
for local employees,
a point they're very proud of.
Why, just look at all of these proud Kenyans!
And China Road and Bridge Corporation’s
treatment of workers
is not an isolated incident.
This article by the Open Society Initiative
for Southern Africa
talks about the horrible conditions
in Chinese-owned firms across Africa.
One Chinese mine had to be
“closed down five times,
largely because of non-conformity
to mine safety rules and poor sanitation.”
There was “an outbreak of cholera.”
And at one construction company,
“Almost all workers lacked
individual protection items
such as helmets, boots, and gloves.”
But back to the rail line in Kenya.
It cost 3.2 billion dollars to build,
and there are more rail line extensions
with even bigger price tags
in the works.
But the Kenyan government is only paying
for 10 percent of it in cash.
The other 90 percent is financed
with a loan from China’s Export‑Import
Bank.
Basically, it buries Kenya in debt.
According to the South China Morning Post,
“Kenya’s external debt now amounts to
seven times its annual budget,
with China accounting for nearly
60 per cent of those loans.
Loans from China have grown by 54%
between 2010 and 2014.”
And as this Kenyan commentator points out,
“That’s our tax money.
These are loans
that our children will pay.”
Oh, and there are concerns about corruption.
Now I’m no expert in how much
large scale railway projects cost.
The most I ever owned
was Reading Railroad and B. & O.
One day, Short Line,
you will be mine!
But this railway in Kenya
is apparently way more expensive
than it should have been.
Al Jazeera reports that
‘‘Kenya’s railway costs [per kilometre]
are almost 40 to 50 percent higher’
than some of Kenya’s neighbouring countries.”
To be fair,
part of the higher costs
are related to technology,
but that doesn't account for all of
the large price tag.
Where did the rest of the money go?
There are also environmental concerns
that many critics feel weren’t addressed.
Phase two of the railway
will cut right through an important national
park.
And some are concerned construction was rushed
so that the current president
could have his flagship project completed
just in time for elections in August.
So all aboard the Madaraka Express!
The price is just decades of debt
to a new colonial power.
So what do you think about this stunning example
of the One Belt, One Road Initiative?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching his episode
of China Uncensored.
Once again, I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Good news, everyone!
Today we’re launching the China Uncensored
Mystery Crate!
Subscribe, and every month you’ll receive
a mystery box that contains
an assortment of items related to topics
we've talked about on the show,
personally curated by me!
Let’s see what’s in this month’s box.
Oh, a bottle of China’s sacred territorial waters.
A facemask designed to protect against Beijing smog.
A slightly used suicide net from Shenzhen—
don’t ask.
A handwritten note...
"Help, I'm stuck in a Chinese labor camp
making cardboard boxes."
Hmm, wonder how that got in there.
And finally,
powdered rhino horn
from the extremely rare silverback rhino,
the last of which was killed to make
this potent male vitality powder.
What’s that Shelley?
Ok, the powdered rhino horn
is extremely illegal.
The box was made by Chinese slave labor.
And no one wants a used suicide net.
What do you mean,
I'm terrible at picking things to go in boxes?
Fine.
You know what?
It's time for Plan B.
I’m going to leave this mystery box stuff
to the professionals,
by partnering with Loot Crate!
It is also a monthly mystery box,
but it will contain actually cool
and totally legal stuff like collectibles,
apparel, gadgets, art,
and epic gear.
It’s basically Comic-Con in a box.
And they’ve agreed to give China Uncensored fans
a 10% discount.
Just enter promo code, BRIDGE10.
Click here now to check out Loot Crate.
Click here.
And I'll throw in some powdered rhino horn.
Just kidding.
Because that would be illegal.