Massive protests in Hong Kong
may have saved Taiwan.
from a Chinese military invasion,
at least for now...
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I'm Chris Chappell.
Joining me again is Ian Easton,
Senior Director of Project 2049 Institute
and an expert on Taiwan and Asia security
issues.
Thanks for joining me again.
Chris.
It's a great pleasure.
Thanks for having me back.
Well, so the first time I had you on back
in 2018
we talked about China's 2020 plan
to be ready to invade Taiwan
and now it's a few weeks until 2020.
Is China still going ahead with that
or do they need a 2021 plan?
That's a very good question.
So, I've been thinking about this issue,
and I checked,
and the 13th five-year plan,
which they're on now,
doesn't actually end until the end of 2020.
Oh, why didn't you tell me that last time?
Well, I didn't know.
Oh.
But having said that, I'm still skeptical
that the PLA is going to be ready in time.
I think that if Xi Jinping were to order the
PLA
to invade Taiwan today or even next year,
there's a high probability of failure on his
part.
I think he would lose.
The question is, does he know that?
I mean, he's a dictator,
so are his generals going to tell him the
truth
if he decides now's the time?
Well, so with the trade war
and the slowing economy
and the situation in Hong Kong,
do you think with all of,
with China distracted by all of that,
that might let Taiwan off the hook?
I think in the near term it probably will.
Most countries, even countries
as powerful as China has become,
prefer to deal with one crisis at a time
or to at least minimize the number of crises
they have to deal with at a time.
And so I would expect that as long as Hong
Kong
is very problematic right now
and as long as the United States
continues to show that it's truly serious
about strategic competition with China,
as we've seen with the trade war
and with other more competitive posturing
that
the Trump administration has taken,
I think it's unlikely that China
is going to attempt the invasion of Taiwan
in the near future.
Although, that's speculative.
Nobody knows the future.
And certainly my beliefs
could be falsified by events,
but I would not expect that to happen
in the very near future.
It's more of a longer term threat.
Okay.
So in the longterm,
is Taiwan still a flash point?
Oh, absolutely.
I think Taiwan is arguably
the most dangerous flash point on the planet,
and it's going to become more dangerous
over time for a variety of reasons.
Such as?
So, China is growing its military power
and as China increases its military power
and as Taiwan's own military defensive power
and the United States' power in the region,
in a comparative sense, starts to diminish
over time,
that is going to make Taiwan a much more
attractive target for CCP expansionism.
Well, I know lately there's been
a lot of traffic in the Taiwan Strait.
Why is it so popular?
You mean traffic in terms of the Chinese military,
or the U.S. Navy?
There's the U.S. Navy,
there's the Chinese Navy.
Yeah, absolutely.
So a few weeks ago,
Taiwan's minister of national defense,
Yen Teh-fa, testified before Thailand's,
Taiwan's parliament that they had tracked
over 2,000 Chinese flights in the Taiwan Strait
area over the past 12 months.
Wow.
And that they expected that trend to continue
or possibly increase.
And that included Chinese bombers that
are strictly in Taiwan,
Chinese intelligence aircraft,
Chinese fighter planes,
and also a lot of drones.
And so, what we're likely to see in the coming
months
is China ramping up its air and Naval activity
around Taiwan in order to exhaust Taiwan's
military.
So for every Taiwanese, excuse me,
for every Chinese sortie around Taiwan,
the Taiwanese Air Force has to respond.
They have to scramble their fighter aircraft
to go respond to it.
When you see a blip on your radar screen coming
at you,
you can't identify from the radar screen itself
what that is.
And so that's why Taiwan has to
scramble fighter aircraft
so they can actually get visual identification
to see if it's a drone or a bomber or something
else.
Well, every time they do that,
that disrupts their pilot training.
It's a lot of resources that are expanding
in terms of fuel and manpower,
and over time that has the potential
to significantly weaken Taiwan's air force.
And their Navy as well,
to the extent that they're responding
to all the Chinese Naval activity around Taiwan.
They've done the same to Japan,
around the Senkaku Islands.
They've done the same to countries
in the South China sea.
Some people call it gray zone operations,
and we can certainly expect
that they're going to do that,
well they're already doing that to Taiwan.
Gray zone meaning...?
Meaning it's hostile,
but nobody's getting shot.
Okay.
So non-kinetic.
So it's pushing to the brink of war, but not-
You're pushing it to the brink of war
in a very calculated fashion,
but not going over the break.
Well, so what about U.S. arms sales to Taiwan
because there's been some record-breaking
numbers this past year.
Yeah, so the Trump administration
has responded to some of the Chinese coercion
against Taiwan with arms sales.
So we've notified to Congress
the sale of new tanks to Taiwan.
I think that's 108 new Abrams main battle
tanks,
which are the most advanced tank on the market.
And then also new F-16 fighter jets,
66 of them,
which is enough for about three squadrons.
And that's a very significant announcement
because the United States since the 1990's,
as a matter of policy,
has not sold Taiwan new fighter jets.
So there was an announcement of a sale in
which was fulfilled around 1997/98,
but since then there've been no new fighter
jets
sold to Taiwan because fighter aircraft
are considered a strategic asset.
And so this was something that
the Bush administrationshied away from.
The Obama administration shied away from it.
And now this,
the Trump administration has taken sort of
a new tack
and has decided no,
Taiwan really needs those fighter jets.
So that's one of several things administration
has done to try to shore up Taiwan's defensive
position.
But overall, it's a really challenging situation
that Taiwan faces and there's no amount of
arms sales
that the U.S. can provide.
I mean, no matter how much Taiwan spends on
its defense,
it'll never keep up with the threat that they
face.
Well, what other kind of support
is the U.S. giving to Taiwan?
How is it doing?
Well, there's a range of things
that the United States government
has started to do in terms of sending
high level officials to Taiwan.
So for example, the State Department
has been very good about sending
Deputy Assistant Secretaries of State to Taiwan,
in some cases very publicly,
and they participate in open forum.
They give public speeches,
they meet with the President of Taiwan
and they do so in an unabashed way.
We've also recently seen the Pentagon do the
same thing.
They sent an official of the same rank.
It's a civilian equivalent to a two-star,
maybe three-star General,
who just went to Taiwan for the first time
for private meetings there on defense issues.
These type of moves may seem,
they may seem small,
but when you compare them to where we
were just two or three years ago,
that was almost unthinkable.
So these are things previous administrations
have not-
Previous administrations never even
seriously considered doing anything like that.
They were terrified of what Beijing's reaction
might be.
And they allowed themselves to,
I guess, be intimidated.
And so they would not send any officials
over the rank of a Colonel to Taiwan.
So sending a two-star General equivalent
is pretty significant and the United States
has also
sent actual uniform military officers to Taiwan.
And we've started to do regular patrols
of the Taiwan Strait
and to make that public as well.
And so there are a number of steps
that the government has taken to try to support
Taiwan,
because again, Taiwan by itself is in a very,
very difficult situation.
There's no way they can keep a favorable military
or political balance across the Taiwan Strait.
And so, if you asked me what kind of grade
the Trump administration deserves,
is something we've talked about in the past,
I would say that compared to the Obama administration
or the Bush administration before it,
or the Clinton administration before it,
the Trump administration probably deserves
an A plus,
in terms of support for Taiwan.
But there's another way to look at it.
Is it enough?
Is the Trump administration keeping up
with the pace of the threat against Taiwan?
Is it keeping up with the changing facts on
the ground
and there I think the administration
would have to deserve a much lower grade
because it is very,
very difficult to keep up with all the things
that China is doing that are directed at Taiwan,
and by extension,
the United States as well.
So what do you think the U.S.
could be doing to earn a solid A,
at least an A?
Well, it would be difficult.
I think there's a lot of inertia
that builds up after 40 years of executing
a certain policy.
Its policies not something,
as I understand it from the outside
as just as a researcher,
it's not something that you can turn on a
dime.
And so for 40 years our policy
has been to keep Taiwan at a distance and
to,
in many ways,
make our Taiwan policy through Beijing
to constantly be calculating
if I do this with Taiwan,
what will that mean for U.S. China relations?
What will Beijing's reaction be?
There's still a lot of that mentality, I think,
in many places across the bureaucracy.
But it is changing.
And so if we fast forward to the future to
2025 or 2030,
what we might expect to see would be not only
U.S. patrols and the Taiwan Strait
but regular U.S. ship visits to Taiwan
and to have ships in Taiwanese ports,
to have troops in Taiwan,
perhaps a few thousand troops on a rotational
basis,
to have military exercises with the Taiwanese
military,
both at the training ranges in Taiwan
and the United States to see regular exchanges
of high level visitors from the United States
to Taiwan,
all the way up to the four-star level
and their civilian equivalents,
and to be moving towards a much more
normalized diplomatic relationship with Taiwan.
I think absent that,
the probability of a major,
very dangerous crises or even a war
across the Taiwan Strait
is very high over the next 10 years.
So what was the concern people had
about what China would do to the U.S.
or Taiwan if the U.S. shows more support?
You know, that's one of the things
that that's funny about fear
is sometimes people are the most afraid of
the unknown.
And in many cases people didn't know.
You know, if you're a diplomat
at the state department and your boss asks
you,
what can I expect from China?
If I go visit Taiwan for example,
or if I write this letter in support
of something Taiwan is doing,
or if I say something at the United Nations
or something of that nature,
in many cases a diplomat couldn't tell you.
They wouldn't know, but there was a fear of,
well they could do this,
they could do that,
they could do the other thing,
and none of it would be particularly pleasant.
In many cases it would be as simple
as an angry phone call and over time,
a démarche or an angry letter
from the PRC Embassy here in Washington.
And over time, that seemed to,
at least in some cases,
have a certain way of almost conditioning
people
in the U.S. government to anticipate
in advance what the Chinese Communist Party
wanted and then to give it to them,
or conversely to anticipate
what they didn't want and then to avoid that.
It's hard to imagine that the U.S. government
can be turned by an angry letter from Beijing.
Not one, but if you imagine
hundreds of thousands of them
over a 40 year relationship
combined with meetings that are canceled
combined with getting the cold shoulder at
a summit.
All these things have an effect.
It also has an effect when you have
so many former U.S. government officials
making a lot of money in China or in Hong
Kong
through their business connections
with the Chinese Communist Party.
That also has obviously an effect as well.
So what has the Chinese reaction been
to this higher level of U.S. support for Taiwan?
Chris, that is a really, really good question.
In many ways, their reaction has not been
nearly
as terrifying as I think
what many people argued it would be.
Certainly this was something
people worried a lot about,
what would their reaction be?
And I think those that worried
a lot of probably been a little disappointed
or maybe now are relieved to see
that the United States can do much more
in support of Taiwan and not set off
a potential crisis in the Taiwan Strait.
How do you think the protests in Hong Kong
have impacted Taiwan?
Well, I think they've served as a wake up
call for many people in Taiwan.
For the past 20 years,
those in Taiwan that favored
a closer relationship with Beijing,
argued that Hong Kong was a success story.
That actually Hong Kong showed
that you could be annexed
by the Chinese Communist Party
the way Hong Kong was back in '97
and the results would not be so bad.
And anybody who had visited Hong Kong before
this year,
certainly before 2014,
would say this is a very pleasant city-state.
Very well run, very wealthy
and a lot of great things going for it.
And so there were those in Taiwan who said,
Hey, maybe one country,
two systems is not so bad.
Maybe that could work for us too.
Certainly that's what the Chinese Communist
Party
wanted to promote,
and it's something they did promote
very heavily across the Taiwan Strait.
Sort of like if the U.S.
isn't giving us much support
and the alternative is war invasion from China,
why not do this seemingly better alternative
of one country, two system?
Exactly.
The sense I think for some politicians in
Taiwan
was that the United States had abandoned them
in 1979
when we switched diplomatic relations.
And what would the PRC and not the ROC,
the Republic of China,
because previously before 1979 Taiwan
was an ally of the United States.
We had diplomatic relations,
we had an embassy in Taipei,
we had troops in Taiwan,
we guarantee Taiwan's security.
After that,
there was a deep sense of betrayal,
and there were those that said,
well, the international community
no longer recognizes us as a real country.
The United States is keeping us at a distance.
China's threatening us with war
if we go fully independent.
And so we have no alternative other
than to do a lot of business with China,
and ultimately maybe the best deal
we could get would be a Hong Kong
plus maybe something even better
than what Hong Kong had.
And so there was a number of people in Taiwan
that held this view.
I think it was a relatively small number.
I think it was a minority of people,
perhaps a small minority,
but that group has really diminished in size
over the past six months,
because if people around the world
can now see that the Chinese Communist Party
doesn't keep its promises,
and we're all being exposed to image after
image
of extreme police brutality
and unprofessional behavior
and a lot of report after report,
including reports from China Uncensored,
have shown that Hong Kong is not a model
that anybody else in their right mind
would want to follow.
And so I think it really has served
as a wake up call for Taiwan
and I think it's probably influencing
the current presidential elections as well.
Any predictions for the 2020 election in Taiwan?
Well, Taiwan is going to have
it's next presidential elections
on January 11th of 2020,
which is coming up fast,
and currently President Tsai Ing-wen of the
DPP
appears to have a significant advantage
over Han Kuo-yu, her KMT opponent,
probably in part because she has taken
a much stronger position standing up
for Taiwanese sovereignty
and standing up for things like democracy
and support of the protesters in Hong Kong.
Whereas the other political party
seems to have more mixed messages on that.
And so I think this is something that is,
has spoken to a fair number of people in Taiwan,
although polls can be misleading
and certainly that's what the polls would
say today.
I think she's up about 30 points over her
opposition,
but polls can be misleading
and you never know what ultimately will happen
here
in a few weeks when people in Taiwan go to
the polls.
Well thank you so much for joining me.
We'll have to check in again in 2021
to see about the 2020 plan.
Sounds good.
Thanks for having me, Chris.