On this episode of China Uncensored,
Super babies are the future.
No, not that kind of super baby.
The kind that's genetically engineered -
in China!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I'm your host, Chris Chappell.
It's an old story:
A crazed scientist with delusions of grandeur
embarks on ethically questionable research
and creates a monstrosity.
Of course, that's pure science fiction. I mean,
no scientist could get research grants for that much money!
No, you need the kind of money only a government has -
to bring together teams of scientists
to work together...
to create ethically questionable monstrosities.
And for that, China has the rest of the world beat.
Did you know, and I kid you not,
basketball star, Yao Ming
is the result of a selective breeding program
set up by Mao Zedong over 50 years ago?
But why leave it to clumsy methods like natural breeding
when we stand on the cusp of a paradigm shift for humanity?
Genetic engineering!
This has huge implications.
But while the rest of the world has barely begun to think about it,
China has been spending big on research and development.
At a major economics meeting earlier this year,
the Chinese Communist Party announced a five-year plan
that would allocate 41 billion dollars to science,
including genetic engineering research.
In the near future, genetic engineering will have a huge impact on human kind.
And I know, it's tempting to say, "hey, that's great!"
But what's the future of this technology
in the hands of the Chinese Communist Party:
an authoritarian regime that kills its own citizens
for their organs,
controls the media
and silences dissent?
I sat down with biotechnology policy expert
Jamie Metzl, to find out.
Jamie, thank you for joining us on the show.
Now you speak a lot about genetic engineering.
For a lot of people, that's not a topic they think about.
Where is this technology now, and where is it going?
They way I like to describe it is,
we are on the verge, have already begun
a genetics revolution that's going to
transform not just how we do medicine
not just how we make babies,
and the nature of the babies we make,
but our evolutionary path as a species.
So in 2003 was the end of the Human Genome Project
which was the first sequencing of the human genome.
And what that essentially did was turn biology
into an information technology.
So we, as humans, we are made up code.
We are beginning to understand and read that code.
And what that is means is that our own biology
will come to be seen as being as hackable
as information technology systems.
So with these new technologies,
we're gonna be able to eliminate a lot of genetic diseases,
We're going to live longer, healthier
more robust lives.
But there are some very big, very significant
moral, ethical challenges.
And we're going to need, as a species,
and nationally and individually,
to find the right balance between decisions that we're making
for our good,
and potential dangers that we may unleash
that could harm us.
Very good point! And so now
let's talk about China,
because this ties in very much with what you just said.
What currently is the Chinese regime doing
that we might consider
unethical in regards to
genetic research?
I know they've been investing a lot of money into that.
First, let's talk about what they're doing.
Because the Chinese government,
to its credit,
recognizes, like the United States government recognizes
that genetics and biotechnology
is going to be incredibly important for the future of
medicine and even the future of national competitiveness.
And that's why, in China and the United States,
there are massive precision medicine initiatives.
So precision medicine
is the recognition that, in the future,
unlike the general medicine we have today,
that if someone has cancer they get chemotherapy,
and you don't know, until you have that treatment,
whether you're the kind of person that would respond to that kind of treatment.
With precision medicine,
your genetic code,
your sequences genome will be the foundation of your medical record.
So before you try anything,
We'll know a bit more about
are you the kind of person that would respond to this kind of treatment-
So it's like custom tailored...
Exactly. Personalized medicine. That's exactly the point.
And it will be a different model for how we treat,
but also for how we develop new treatments
including drugs and how we test.
So there's a lot of good in what China
and the United States,
and others are doing to invest
in the realization of this future
of precision medicine and biotechnology,
and genetic technologies that have the potential
to help everybody.
The danger, though, is
that these tools are extremely powerful.
So these same tools.
that can help us live longer, healthier, more robust lives
can also be used to create dangerous bioweapons.
They can be used to interfere
with the human germline,
our heritable genetics.
And that doesn't mean it's always wrong,
but there needs to be
some kind of
some kind of ethical standard
so we can make big decisions if we're changing
the nature of our children and our children's children.
We need to have a context for thinking about it.
And the fear many people, myself included, have about China
is that there's a massive pressure to move forward
very aggressively, which is not necessarily bad.
And there are even some decent laws.
But there is a Wild West environment
and a Wild West culture
where people are taking some very big risks.
And the controls,
on one hand the controls
to establish parameters around those risks aren't
fully established.
And at the same time, there's a tremendous pressure
To continually have advances, to continually break new ground
and in some way bring glory to the state.
So what are the implications of China's genetic rise?
Well, on one hand, it's good
because I always say that, with China,
engaging in so much intellectual property theft,
it's almost a double taxing against the rest of the world.
On one hand,
China has been stealing intellectual property
from the rest of the world.
On the other hand, all these brilliant, creative people in China
rather than creating something new,
are putting a lot of energy into stealing and adapting someone else's thing.
And so I think that
the more that China's brainpower
is deployed on doing new things,
solving new problems, in my mind,
that's a much better allocation of that very important resource.
So if there are more people in China that are working
at the frontiers of genetic science,
I think that's a plus.
But it will be very important
that we are all talking to one another
so we don't get in difficult situations where
we are moving in different directions.
Particularly when there are big ethical issues at play
that could influence our future evolution as a species.
Then that gets into the issue of national security.
Is there a national security risk for the US in any of this?
Different societies will have different views
on how to apply these genetic technologies. And so
it could be that there will be
countries, and let's just say, for example,
the United States is one.
Maybe Vatican City will be another,
where we, collectively, aren't comfortable
with germline, genetic, heritable
mutation - particularly of unborn babies.
And so we draw that line.
But it could be that other societies,
- and let's just take China as one potential example -
are comfortable with it.
And they're saying, "Well, we can
use these technologies, we can eliminate
genetic diseases.
We can, maybe at some point in the future,
engineer people to be smarter or more
resistant to disease or something else.
So if that were to happen,
What would we do?
What would the country that says "we don't wanna do it" do?
We ban people from those other countries,
from coming here, from procreating with our citizens?
Would we do genetic tests of everyone entering the country?
And you could see how with genetically modified crops,
which aren't even that bad for you,
people have gotten so up-in-arms,
people are destroying property, destroying people's fields.
What would people do
in that kind of situation?
So it's not just a China-US issue.
It's a global issue.
But there's a real potential tinderbox.
Now, I read your book, The Genesis Code,
where you talk a lot about these issues.
You know, I'm a huge science fiction fan, and this really holds up.
But you set it in the very near future,
only 2020, right?
2023.
So that's only a few years away.
Why did you set it so close to today?
Well, the reason is
I write science fiction
not so that people can not-think.
But so that people will really think of the implications for today.
I felt like, somebody goes and sees wonderful science fiction like Star Wars,
But they're not thinking,
"Oh jeez, if I have a Wookie at home,
where is he gonna sleep?"
What are "droid rights?"
What I wanted was for people to read this book and say,
"hey, this world feels very familiar!"
And these issues, in some way, feel far off,
But in other ways they just feel like they're right here.
So is China genetically engineering babies?
No.
Not to my knowledge.
Are they in a position where this is something they could start doing in the near future?
Well certainly China and Chinese companies
are doing a lot of research,
like people in the United States and elsewhere are,
on understanding the genetic
fingerprint, if that's the right word,
off all kinds of traits, including intelligence.
At BGI-Shenzhen, they have a thing called the
Cognitive Genomics Initiative,
where they're really trying to understand
what genetic combinations make up extremely high intelligence.
Whether, once they and we all,
understand that,
China would be in a position
to use embryo selection to select
people who are likely to have higher IQs.
Nobody knows the answer to that question.
But when we look at China's recent history,
you could at least suggest, believe that there could be
an openness or willingness to do that.
China is very comfortable with population engineering
through the One Child Policy,
with significant environmental engineering.
With South-to-North water diversion program,
Three Gorges Dam...
Willing to take children away from their families
to place them in their Olympic sports schools for the glory of the state...
So if there was this technology,
if and when this technology matures to a point
where it could be used for
population enhancement,
Would China or other countries be open to that?
I think the answer to that is potentially, "yes."
So it's the question of, "what would
genetically engineered super babies have on the world?"
Certainly, super babies
is the future of our species. And some
individuals, groups, countries will opt out,
and some individuals, groups, countries
will opt in.
But in my view, it is inevitable
that we will be using these technologies
first to eliminate disease,
but over time,
to select for perceived positive traits.
And so if the United States
continues to have
say, moratoriums on this, but China continues to advance along these lines,
what could the potential consequences be for this country?
As genetic technologies mature,
different countries will come to different conclusions
about how they'd like to use them.
If a country opts out,
there may be consequences for competitiveness.
And if a country opts in,
it may face challenges that we don't even
understand because they would be
messing with a very complex system.
And so there will be huge implications whether it's the United States and China
or any other combination of entities.
This is going to be a huge issue moving forward.
Alright, well Jamie - thank you very much for joining us.
Once again, the book is Genesis Code
and there's a sequel out now called Eternal Sonata.
If you are interested in reading the book,
we provided a link below
where you can buy The Genesis Code.
I do recommend it. It's a fantastic book.
Jamie, thank you for joining us.
My pleasure, thank you.