On this episode of China Uncensored,
Rumors of a coup?
Sounds like a coup for this show!
US China trade war?
Fake news!
And finally, why pollution in China is a good
thing.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
The rumor mill is churning in Beijing!
Word on the street is a coup attempt was launched
against Chinese leader Xi Jinping.
There were reports of gunfire near the heart
of the capital…
...from anti-Xi groups trying to overthrow
him.
But here’s where it gets really weird.
The rumors say that black rain frog and former
former Chinese leader Jiang Zemin,
had teamed up with wood face and former leader
Hu Jintao
to overthrow Xi Jinping.
And THAT...is incredibly unlikely.
Hu Jintao was the head
of the Chinese Communist Party between Jiang
and Xi.
Hu’s on first?
Xi’s on first!
Ok, now it’s just more confusing.
But anyway, before Xi Jinping became the leader
of China,
there was Hu Jintao.
And before him, Jiang Zemin.
And before him, Deng Xiaoping.
Jiang Zemin was jealous that Hu Jintao
got to become the leader after him,
because Jiang didn’t get to pick his own
successor.
So Jiang constantly tried to undermine Hu,
and also possibly tried to kill him that one
time on a boat.
Unfortunately for Jiang, he didn’t manage
to sink Hu’s battleship.
In any case, I think it’s safe to say Hu
Jintao did not team up
with Jiang Zemin to overthrow Xi Jinping.
But rumors can be a powerful force in Chinese
politics.
“Given the Party’s control over the media
and the secretive
nature of its political processes,
gossip and rumours have long been the stuff
of informal comment on the issues of the day,
and the means by which alternative accounts
of Party rule circulate.”
In fact, this latest incident isn’t even
the first time rumors
of a coup against Xi Jinping have circulated.
Shortly after Xi Jinping was appointed
Chairman of the Communist Party in 2012,
there were rumors there were gunshots heard
in Beijing
and that officials tied to Jiang Zemin tried
to stage a coup.
And while the actual gunshots were never confirmed,
years later,
a Party official publicly said that several
people in Jiang’s
faction did try to get rid of Xi Jinping.
All those people are coincidentally now in
prison.
Funny how that happens.
So will these latest rumors be confirmed?
I don’t think so.
It’s next to impossible for there to be
a Jiang-Hu alliance.
But, another attempt by Jiang’s faction
to stage a coup,
that is possible.
One thing the rumors do show though,
is that the factional struggle within the
Chinese Communist Party
is alive and well.
Can’t wait for the next episode of General
Hostility.
So those coup rumors may just be lies.
But you know who else is good at lies?
The US!
You see, according to Chinese state-run media
the People’s Daily,
...the idea that China steals US technology
is totally made up.
What the US is really doing, is trying
to “demonize China and fool the world.”
Yeah, where does the US get the idea
that China steals American technology?
I know those fighter jets look almost the
same,
but actually they’re slightly different...
...the way these two action figures are slightly
different.
And that’s truly special.
Speaking of US lies, did you know the US case
against Chinese trade is fake news?
That’s according to Yu Yongding, of the
Chinese state-run
Chinese Academy of Social Sciences,
and member of the People’s Bank of China.
He says Chinese firms would never steal US
technology.
They don’t need to.
They have so much money.
He goes on to say that no one wins a trade
war.
Except China.
China will win this trade war.
Last week we talked about Apple installing
Chinese censorship programming
in every single iPhone they make.
Well, Apple carries on its tradition
of one-upping its previous innovations.
Because now, Apple is handing all of the iCloud
data
for Chinese users to a Chinese state-run telecom
company.
The move was praised by my favorite
Chinese state-run media, the Global Times.
But the good news is, this will never affect
iCloud users outside of China.
Right?
Moving on.
China’s pollution levels have hit a record
high.
I know that sounds bad.
But it’s actually great news!
You see, according to the latest research,
trees in Beijing actually grow quicker thanks
to all the pollution.
In fact, if pollution actually went down,
“more trees would have to be planted to
help absorb
the greenhouse gases that cause global warming.”
So fighting pollution will actually make global
warming worse.
By the way, that study was funded by the Chinese
government.
The study also found that swallowing the lies
from Chinese state media
is very nutritious and will keep you full
all day,
without packing on the pounds.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And before you go, it’s time to answer questions
from fans
who support China Uncensored with dollars
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
Jeremy Lim asks,
“Is there any hope left for a real Hong
Kong democracy?”
Jeremy, you don’t consider choosing between
three politicians
selected by the Chinese Communist Party real
democracy?
One of the agreements the Chinese Communist
Party
made with the UK for the handover of Hong
Kong,
was that in just a few short years,
they’d have universal suffrage,
and could directly vote for their Chief Executive.
Well, that date kept getting pushed back.
And back.
Then the Communist Party finally said, ok,
you can have your universal suffrage,
but first we get to pick the candidates.
That’s what sparked the 2014 Hong Kong Umbrella
Movement.
Where I got to see Hong Kong democracy up
close.
To give the Party credit,
they realized that wasn’t a good idea.
So they just went back to the old system,
where a small group of influential citizens,
mostly with ties to the Communist Party,
get to choose the Chief Executive.
But hey, at least Hongkongers still get to
vote
for their legislative members, right?
Until democratically elected lawmakers started
getting purged…
And thrown in jail...
And disqualified from running in elections…
I’d say Hong Kong is winding up with less
democracy
than it had at the end of British rule in
the 90s.
Thanks for your question Jeremy.
I’m now depressed.
Wait a minute!
All I need to do is think of the amazing support
of all the fans of the show!
That chases the clouds away.
Remember, China Uncensored is made possible
by the support
from my amazing fans.
So I’m asking, if you’re able,
consider supporting China Uncensored
through our Patreon website.
You’ll have a chance to get your questions
answered on the show,
and get some neat stuff for your support.
Once again, thanks for watching this episode
of China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
You, too, can get your question answered on
this show.
Go to patreon.com/chinauncensored.
The link is below.
Or click this square orange button.
I answer questions from supporters who contribute
a dollar or more per episode.
Because without your support,
we couldn’t keep making China Uncensored.
Click the link to contribute.