On this episode of China Uncensored,
Chinese tourists behaving badly.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
Now you may have heard that Chinese tourists
do not have the most sparkling of reputations.
But good news everyone!
I was checking out the state-run CCTV’s Facebook page.
You know, the one that would be banned inside
China.
And it turns out,
China National Tourism Administration has
laid out,
“nine kinds of misbehavior sufficiently
serious,”
to get a person put on the tourism blacklist.
That means potentially no leaving China for
2-5 years!
Yes, they may prevent their own citizens from
leaving China for behaving badly!
So here are the 9 things Chinese tourists
are forbidden from doing.
Number 9
Interfering with aircraft or public transport
Like in March when a man opened the emergency
door
to get some fresh air while waiting for takeoff.
Or when one guy deployed the slide so he could
get off the plane quicker.
That cost 15,000 dollars to fix.
In fact, in the first 6 months of 2015 alone,
this happened 15 times.
Number 8
Damaging public facilities
Like poor poor Shanghai Disneyland.
A month before it even opened,
thousands of tourists trashed the grounds,
stomped the gardens,
umm, did other stuff
and clearly did not stay on the path.
Number 7
Offending local traditions, cultures or living
habits
So Malaysia is a mostly Muslim country,
and it has a...
conservative view about nudity.
For example, when four foreigners stripped
naked
on the top of the sacred Mount Kinabalu,
they were blamed for the earthquake the killed
16 people just a few days after.
So it was maybe a bad idea that this group
of Chinese tourists
took all these nude photos on a Malaysian
beach.
Number 6
Destroying cultural and historical relics
Now, I can’t read ancient Egyptian hieroglyphics,
but I’m pretty sure this didn’t originally
say “Ding Jinhao was here”.
Yes, in the ancient Luxor temple,
the one in Egypt, not Las Vegas,
a teenaged Chinese tourist carved his name
on the wall.
Number 5
Participating in gambling, prostitution or
drug use
Well what’s the point of even being on vacation
then?!
Dongguan has earned the nickname “capital
of sex” in China.
Where people travel specifically to participate
in gambling, prostitution or drug use.
In 2014, authorities led a massive prostitution
bust.
They arrested 67 people and shut down 12 brothels.
This one has the
“I can see you on the toilet from my uncomfortable
bed” theme going on.
Number 4
Threatening the public safety
This image speaks for itself.
That’s a gun.
On an airplane.
It's probably fake,
but since people have now been escorted off
planes for doing math,
this is still a bad idea.
Number 3
Damaging the ecosystem and breaking wildlife
protection regulations
Nanjing is known for its beautiful cherry
blossoms.
They look especially nice when people shake
off all the petals
so they can take a nice photo.
Though, I do have to say,
climbing that tree in those heels is pretty
darn impressive.
Number 2
Perpetuating “low-taste or superstitious”
ideas.
Well, these tourists are certainly being superstitious
And finally number 1
Other behavior that causes a negative impact
Ah how wonderfully vague.
I wonder if defecating in public counts?
But before you start filling up the comment
section
with hate speech about Chinese people, think
about this:
You don’t really have this problem with
people from Taiwan.
Or Hong Kong.
This happens in a society where the Chinese
Communist Party
has spent 60 years ruining traditional culture
and values
so they could establish their own ideology.
In fact, among these things that the Chinese
government
is telling its tourists not to do,
are things the government specifically told
them to do
just a couple generations ago.
Like destroying cultural relics.
Smashing public property.
And disrespecting local traditions.
So, really, how much of the blame should we
really put on Chinese people?
And if you want to learn more about how the
Chinese Communist Party
specifically destroyed Chinese culture, watch
this video.
So what do you think of the Chinese Tourism
Administration’s prohibitions?
Leave your comments below!
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next
time.