On this episode of China Uncensored,
I would not have wanted to be in China this
week.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Super typhoon Mangkhut hit Southeast Asia
earlier this week.
First, it devastated parts of the Philippines,
leaving more than 80 people dead and dozens
missing.
Then the storm passed through Hong Kong
and the nearby Chinese city of Shenzhen,
where at least 5 people were killed.
Destruction is everywhere.
And this natural disaster has also left behind
a destructive trail of...vertical video.
But at least we have images of
some of the worst devastation as it was happening.
Like this giant crane falling off
the top of a skyscraper under construction.
The footage from this Category 5 typhoon is
mind blowing.
Here’s another crane, this time swinging
around and...
barely missing the window.
Yeah, the winds were a little on the strong
side.
Strong enough to take down anyone attempting
to venture outside.
Including the poor food delivery guy.
Ok, what kind of a jerk orders delivery during
a typhoon!?
On the plus side, it looks like that jerk
won’t be getting any food.
Even the toilets weren’t safe from the typhoon.
And boy am I glad I wasn’t staying at the
Sheraton in Shenzhen.
At least this one’s not vertical video.
As you can see,
a lot of people’s homes and businesses in
the Philippines
and China have been destroyed.
So be sure to keep the people in the typhoon’s
path
in your thoughts and prayers.
And before we go,
it’s time when I answer a questions from
a Patreon supporter—
someone who contributes a dollar or more per
episode
to keep this show going.
Coralline Algae asks,
“A few years ago there were many news stories
about more male babies being born than female
babies.
It was reported that this caused difficulty
for some Chinese men looking to find a wife.
Is this still an ongoing problem?
Has it been getting worse,
or was the issue overblown by western media?
No, that’s a real problem.
“Out of China’s population of 1.4 billion,
there are nearly 34 million more males than
females –
more than the entire population of Malaysia.”
And this is a problem for many reasons.
When you have that many single young men,
often who also struggle to earn a basic income,
well, the situation is ripe for violence.
It’s also fueling sex trafficking from other
parts of Asia.
That’s why China earned the spot
of one of the world’s worst human trafficking
offenders,
according to the US State Department.
There are actually lots of issues
that the Chinese Communist Party’s “family
planning” policies
have caused, so many that it could be an entire
episode.
Let me know in the comments below
if you’d be interested in seeing that episode.
Thanks for the question, Coralline.
And if you want to see your question on the
show,
become a member of the China Uncensored 50-cent
army on Patreon,
for as little as a dollar per episode.
Link is below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Don’t get blown away by not knowing the
latest China news!
Subscribe to China Uncensored for more.
Be sure you click that bell icon
so you’ll be notified when there are new
episodes.
And help the show out by sharing it with your
friends and family.