The US could be defenseless
Against Chinese hypersonic weapons
Another Canadian is sentenced to death
And spies are everywhere!
That and more on this week’s China news
headlines.
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
This week’s China news headlines.
China’s hypersonic weapons are posing
a serious threat to the United States.
That’s according to a meeting this week
of the American Foreign Policy Council.
China’s “hypersonic missiles will be capable
of delivering
conventional or nuclear warheads anywhere
on the globe
with a flight time measured in mere minutes.”
Good, I hate waiting for anything.
Hypersonic weapons, according to a professor
of aerospace engineering at Michigan University,
are “rocket-boosted to high altitude
and may be launched from land, sea or air.
They fly far faster than any other weapons—
more than 3,000 mph
and potentially up to 10,000 mph—
which makes them difficult to identify,
avoid or shoot down.”
And that might mean
they could get through US defense systems.
According to one of the speakers
at the American Foreign Policy Council,
“These newly developed hypersonic missiles
can potentially penetrate U.S. ballistic missile
defenses
and possibly target and destroy an early warning
radars
and/or aircraft carriers in the event of a
future conflict.”
This is a big problem, not just for America,
but for Taiwan.
Not that Taiwan needed more problems.
A senior defense official told reporters
at the Pentagon earlier this year
that as China’s hypersonic weapons technology
improves,
it might make Beijing more willing to take
risks
it wouldn’t have before.
“They are getting to a point where the PLA
leadership
may actually tell Xi Jinping
that they are confident in their capabilities.”
And I would just like to remind any of the
PLA leadership
watching that I’ve always been a big fan
of Xi Jinping.
Ask anyone.
Back me up on this one, guys.
You might remember
that the Chinese Communist Party has been
a little upset
with the Canadian government since last December.
That’s when Meng Wanzhou,
the CFO of Huawei that was arrested in Canada.
The US had requested Canadian authorities
arrest and extradite her—
because she’s suspected of violating US
sanctions on Iran.
And even though China has asked Canada very
nicely
to ignore the rule of law and let Meng go,
that has not yet happened.
And now a second Canadian
has been sentenced to death in China.
This Canadian was allegedly dealing drugs
in China,
just like the first one sentenced to death
earlier this year.
What a coincidence.
These drug dealing Canadians, eh?
I should know.
I’m addicted to maple syrup.
Anyway, Canada is saying the Chinese Communist
Party
is arbitrarily applying the death sentence,
to which they replied Canada totally has “double
standards.”
Which, considering Canada abolished the death
penalty
n the 1970s,
I’m not quite sure what they mean.
In addition to the two Canadians sentenced
to death,
“Two other Canadian citizens,
former diplomat Michael Kovrig
and businessman Michael Spavor,
are also being held by China and face
accusations of harming national security.”
And if they’re watching the news,
I’m sure they’re very worried right now.
I’m just kidding.
They don’t show that kind of news inside
China.
A former CIA agent who allegedly
conspired with the Chinese Communist Party
is expected to plead guilty.
He’s being charged with trying to give
secret information to China.
But for some background,
this was happening at the same time as
the CIA’s network inside China was being
exposed.
Agents were arrested or killed.
So I don’t imagine the CIA is too happy
with the guy.
And the CIA are not the friendliest people
under the best of circumstances.
Though to be clear,
Lee was not charged with being the mole
who brought down the CIA network in China.
The cause of that is still unknown.
Though Lee is a suspect.
Speaking of the CIA, spies!
Spies everywhere!!!
That’s the message Chinese authorities have
for the good people of Beijing.
And a new directive has asked the public
to get involved in rooting them out.
Because asking the public to root out spies
definitely won’t result in baseless accusations.
It’s not like there’s a history of that
in communist China.
Let me spin you a little yarn
about the on going US-China trade talks.
The US might be putting duties
of up to 460% on Chinese yarn.
Okay, I mainly just wanted to make that pun.
Look, I spend all my days researching
incredibly depressing things.
Just give me this.
Three Chinese banks may have violated
US sanctions on North Korea,
and a US judge wants their records.
The three banks are accused of funneling
over 100 million dollars into North Korea.
China is one of North Korea’s only real
allies.
Well, China and Russia.
Ok, China, Russia, and Dennis Rodman.
And they’re the only thing keeping the economy
afloat.
Like, a healthy layer of fat
keeps the Dear Leader afloat in a tub of water.
The Chinese Communist Party has been
really trampling on Hong Kong’s freedom.
And Taiwan is calling out the Hong Kong government
for going along with it.
Hong Kong denied entry
to 68 Taiwanese Falun Gong practitioners
who wanted to join a parade being held in
the city,
to expose the persecution of Falun Gong in
Mainland China.
Such delicious irony.
If I didn’t know better,
I would say the Chinese Communist Party
isn’t honoring the one country two systems
policy!
I don’t want to jump to any conclusions
though,
that really wouldn’t be fair.
And I’m afraid I have some bad news.
It’s going to be harder for all of us to
bring home the bacon.
The price of pork is expected to jump
because of the ongoing swine flu in China.
One industry expert told CNBC,
“If I really like bacon,
I’d be kind of stocking up.”
Ummm...excuse me,
I have to go now.