A War for Taiwan is brewing
As China’s military ambitions surge
Can the world turn back the tide?
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
This episode is sponsored by Daily\h
Pnut. The news can be a tough pill to\h\h
swallow—especially when it’s about war.\h
But that’s why you’ll love Daily Pnut,\h\h
which gives you the news each day in\h
small doses—part humor, part substance.
So, Taiwan is preparing for war\h
against China. I mean, it should.
The Chinese Communist Party\h
has vowed to conquer Taiwan.
And Chinese jets have been\h
harrassing Taiwan constantly.
In mid June, China sent a record\h
28 fighter jets toward Taiwan.
And recently China deployed stealth fighter jets\h\h
to their military units that\h
monitor the Taiwan Strait.
That deployment was announced\h
on Chinese state-run media.\h\h
Which seems kind of counterproductive,\h
since they’re supposed to be stealth jets.\h\h
“Look at how stealthy our jets are!\h
Here’s exactly where we’re sending them!”\h
But the Chinese military’s increasing\h
incursions on Taiwan’s airspace\h\h
have put a tremendous strain on the Taiwanese\h
military, as well as the Taiwanese people.
Now, in an interview with CNN,\h
Taiwan’s Foreign Minister Joseph Wu\h\h
says Taiwan is preparing for war.
(We need to prepare ourselves\h
for a possible conflict…\h
We hope it doesn't happen. War between\h
Taiwan and China is in nobody's interest…\h
At a time when China is trying to\h
expand its authoritarian influence\h\h
Taiwan is on the front line.
China’s expanding authoritarian influence is\h
exactly why the US has been increasing support for\h\h
Taiwan. That’s true of both the Trump and Biden\h
administrations. And that tells you something.
Recently, “The U.S. and Taiwan\h
agreed to hold regular talks\h\h
on issues ranging from technology supply\h
chains to meat imports following their\h\h
first Trade and Investment Framework\h
Agreement meeting in five years.”
And Taiwan is pushing for a\h
free trade deal with the US.
Obviously the Chinese Communist\h
Party is not happy about any of this.\h\h
It interferes with their plan to make Taiwan\h
completely dependent on China economically.
Actually, that’s pretty much their\h
plan for the rest of the world, too.
Anyway, the Communist Party has particularly been\h
targeting Taiwan’s Foreign Minister Joseph Wu .
Party member Zhu Fenglian, who’s a spokeswoman\h
for China’s Taiwan Affairs Office, said “Joseph Wu\h\h
has repeatedly and arrogantly\h
provoked ‘Taiwan independence.’”
“We will take all necessary\h
measures to severely punish\h\h
such ‘Taiwan independence’ diehards\h
for life in accordance with the law.”
Taiwan independence? Taiwan *is* independent.\h
That’s why it’s not under Communist control.\h\h
As for the threats, Minister Wu has this to say.
They cannot tolerate Truth. And\h
if they keep saying they want to\h\h
pursue me for the rest of my life, I'm not\h
really concerned about that. So for that,\h\h
I think it's an honor to be\h
targeted by the Chinese government.
I like this guy.
A Chinese Communist occupation of Taiwan\h
would be a disaster for the Taiwanese people.\h\h
Look at what’s happened to Hong Kongers.
And Hong Kong was never even a fully independent\h\h
democracy. To transform the democratic Taiwan into\h
a part of the authoritarian PRC would be brutal.
Which is why many countries\h
are concerned about Taiwan.
Japan’s deputy defense minister says Taiwan\h
must be protected as a democratic country.
And yes, he called Taiwan the c-word. Country.
He also said the world needs to “wake\h
up” to China’s threat to Taiwan.
China responded by saying his comments were\h
“highly sinister, dangerous and irresponsible”.
What’s really sinister and dangerous is\h
the Communist Party’s military ambitions\h\h
in the South China Sea. All of\h
China’s neighbors are worried.
Chinese warplanes have skirted\h
Malaysia, aimed at showing dominance.
Indonesia and the US are\h
building a multimillion dollar\h\h
maritime training center\h
together to counter China.
And the US State Department just\h
approved a multibillion dollar arms\h\h
deal with the Philippines, the biggest one yet.
And that’s specifically to “enhance the\h
Philippines’ ‘minimum deterrence’ capability\h\h
as it grapples with an ever-more\h
assertive China in its adjacent waters”.
Meanwhile, the USS Ronald Reagan\h\h
has entered the South China Sea for\h
routine freedom of navigation operations.
This does not necessarily mean war will happen.\h\h
If a strong deterrence can be maintained, that’s\h
actually the best hope we have of preventing the\h\h
Chinese regime from starting a war against\h
Taiwan or in the South China Sea. But that\h\h
all depends on whether the world truly wakes up\h
to the threat of the Chinese Communist Party.
And this episode is sponsored by Daily Pnut.
I know you like following the news. And Daily Pnut\h
gives you interesting news stories to read every\h\h
day. They’re fast, timely, and entertaining. Just\h
subscribe to their email newsletter. It’s free.\h\h
And you can read it on your\h
phone, computer, or tablet.
It’s a great way to filter out the noise and\h
learn more about world news that matters.
There’s more than a quarter million\h
other readers already. So join for free.\h\h
Click the link to Daily Pnut\h
in the Description below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell,\h
thanks for watching China Uncensored.