The US-China Trade Deal is getting postponed...
again.
Battle at the UN
And all your favorite Chinese knock off toys!
That and more on this week’s China Uncensored.
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
This week’s China news headlines!
Hey, you know that trade deal President Trump
said
he wanted to sign with China?
Well...it still needs a little work.
According to a US official,
the deal just isn’t ready to even be put
on the table.
Which is a good thing because the APEC meeting
where the deal was going to be signed has
been cancelled.
I’m surprised.
I wonder why Chile canceled it.
But hey, this isn’t Chile Uncensored.
So back to China.
The US and 22 other countries are criticizing
China in the UN.
It’s mainly about the Chinese regime
building concentration camps for the Uighurs,
a Muslim ethnic minority.
But do you really think getting criticized
by 23 countries
is going to faze China?
Ha!
China’s fought back with 54 countries
who praised their counter terrorism efforts.
It’s like the UN version of the Sharks and
the Jets.
But hey, those 54 countries have a point.
The Chinese regime is obviously locking people
up
in order to safeguard their human rights.
I mean, is there anywhere you could be
more safeguarded than in prisons?!
Unsurprisingly many of these 54 countries
are known for their own stellar human rights.
Like Russia.
And Egypt.
And Pakistan.
China then also reminded the US
that talking about human rights
is really not helpful for a trade deal.
Really, I don’t think the Communist Party
gets the change the US government’s China
policy.
Whatever happened to the good old days
of don't criticize us and you’ll make lots
of money?
Speaking of lots of money,
China wants it!
It might have something to do with
China’s lowest GDP growth in 27 years.
And that’s why the Chinese Vice Minister
of Commerce
is saying China is open for business!
He says China will allow more foreign investment,
and hey, we won’t steal your technology
anymore.
Which is kind of like saying,
“Yeah we stole from you in the past,
even though we lied and said we wouldn’t—
but this time we’re not gonna.
Pinky swear.
So hand over the money.”
Which means now's the time to do business
in China.
Seriously, there’s like a billion people
there,
think about how much money you can make!
And this time there’s no downside!
Fool me once...shame on... shame on you.
Fool me, can’t get fooled again.
In related news, Senator Marco Rubio
and other lawmakers are hitting China hard!
With a bill to block government pensions
from investing in China.
To be clear, US government pensions
are not currently investing in China...
but they’re thinking about it.
Rubio’s bill is...not so much a bill yet,
as it is a promise to introduce a bill...
which will then would be debated for months
in committee,
and then it might get voted on,
and possibly even passed,
and then it’ll have to go through
the House of Representatives for a rewrite
and then another vote...but I tell ya,
a year or two from now
it’s possible it could become a law.
So watch out, China!
Our government’s got fangs.
But from another perspective,
IT’S ABSOLUTELY INSANE
THAT US GOVERNMENT PENSIONS
WOULD INVEST IN CHINA.
Who thought that would be a good idea?!
What’s that, Shelley?
Oh, the same brilliant financial minds
that told everyone else to invest in China.
What could go wrong.
Yesterday was Halloween.
And in Hong Kong,
the scariest things on the streets were the
Hong Kong police.
Yeah, I’ll take zombies over that any day.
Over the last four months,
Hong Kong police have gotten so scary,
that the Apple Daily even printed a cut-out
police mask
so you can traumatize all of your friends.
But Hongkongers learned a valuable lesson
this Halloween.
Never try to trick or treat in front of the
police.
Because it’s always gonna be a trick.
Ouch.
You might be wondering how
all those anti-authoritarian protests in Hong
Kong
actually get organized,
since the movement seems to have no leaders.
Well, it’s often done through online forums
and messaging apps.
The most popular app being used is Telegram,
while the most popular online forum is called
LIHKG,
which is like Reddit.
Parts of Reddit.
The Hong Kong government is now
targeting Telegram and LIHKG.
By giving itself the power
to “stop online users from publishing any
material
deemed to be promoting or inciting violence.”
I imagine “promoting or inciting violence”
would include, for example, organizing a peaceful
protest
where police decide to pepper spray innocent
people in the face.
That man clearly incited the police officer
to violence.
China is doing its part to clean up the oceans.
By filling them up with plastic.
China’s ocean waste surged last year.
And that’s according to official data,
so it might be even more.
How is that cleaning up the ocean?
Simple.
If the ocean is filled up,
you can just sweep the excess off the top.
Hey, look!
It’s my favorite DZB Character, Gokok.
Wait a minute, something’s not right.
Oh no, it’s a Chinese knockoff!
Just one of a million fake toys seized in
Shanghai.
There was a whole factory devoted to making
knockoffs
of Pokemon, One Piece, Gundams and more.
At least they didn’t rip off my favorite
videogame character,
Korby.
The raid seized 42 million dollars worth of
knock offs.
Now this actually happened back in August,
but this is the first I heard of it,
so I’m sharing it with you.
Bandai Namco was so happy about it,
they even rewarded Shanghai police with this—
a golden unicorn Gundam.
About the only thing rarer than a golden unicorn
Gundam,
is a 67 year old woman giving birth.
Yawn.
Last month an Indian woman gave birth to twins
at 73.
And with that stunning conclusion,
it’s now time for me to answer a question
from one of you—
a fan who support China Uncensored
with a dollar or more per episode,
by contributing through the crowdfunding website
Patreon.
Emmitt A Ray asks,
“When do you think China's massive imbalance
of boys to girls
is going to hit the boiling point?
It seems they are putting men around the world
on construction projects to keep them out
of China
and not thinking about their chances
of getting married and having a family.
At some point that seems like a rebellion
waiting to happen.”
Oh boy, what a question.
So in case you hadn’t heard,
there are 30 million more men in China than
women.
It’s such an issue even state-run media
talk about it
That my friends is the result of government
population planning
known as the One Child Policy.
Don’t worry,
China is trying to deal with this in a variety
of, well,
shortsighted or terrible ways.
As you mention,
shipping off a lot of Chinese men
as part of construction projects around the
world
as part of the Belt and Road initiative.
Then there’s things like forcing Uighur
women
to marry Han Chinese men.
And this shortage of women is also a big part
of why
China is a world leader in human trafficking.
North Korean refugees in particular are victims.
As are women from Southeast Asia.
So as horrible as it is to say,
the Communist Party may have found ways
to avoid the problem hitting a boiling point.
In the way they handle most things.
By creating other problems
that will one day hit a boiling point.
But don’t worry!
Those are problems for another day.
Thanks for your question, Emmitt.
Most of China Uncensord’s income
comes from direct viewer support through Patreon.
So as a reward to our supporters,
I answer a question from our Patrons
at the end of some of my episodes.
Visit patreon.com/chinauncensored to find
out more.
Thanks for watching.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.