A new weapons sale to Taiwan
Could destroy half of any Chinese invasion force
And China is not happy
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
This episode has been sponsored\h
by Surfshark—because you should\h\h
be protecting your identity whenever you\h
go online by using a VPN like Surfshark.
The Trump Administration has\h
announced plans for a huge\h\h
new weapons sale to Taiwan,\h
worth 2.4 billion dollars.
And if you’re saying, hey Chris, didn’t you just\h
report that last week? No, you’re confusing this\h\h
week’s 2.4 billion dollar weapons sale with\h
last week’s 1.8 billion dollar weapons sale.
In fact, the Trump Administration has been\h
selling so many weapons to Taiwan lately,\h\h
it’s getting a bit hard to keep up.
This is the second arms deal in\h
a week and the ninth approved by\h\h
the State Department since Donald\h
Trump became president in 2017.
But this isn’t just up to the State Department.\h
Arms deals also need to be approved by Congress.\h\h
So these two latest weapons sales have\h
been sent to Congress for a 30-day review.\h
It shouldn’t be a problem, since there\h
is bipartisan support for arming Taiwan.
And this latest weapons sale is a doozy.\h
It, “includes 400 Harpoon anti-ship missiles, 100\h
launcher transporters, radar and support systems.”
The Harpoon anti-ship missile is a subsonic\h
weapon with a range of about 78 miles.\h\h
It’s not just an anti-ship missile though. It\h
can also strike missile launch sites or ports.\h\h
Taiwan already has Harpoon missiles,\h
but those are launched from submarines,\h\h
ships and aircraft. This new one is a land-based\h
system that basically fills in the gaps.\h
So, should a Chinese invasion force\h
come across the Strait of Taiwan,\h\h
the Harpoon missiles would be able to strike\h
Chinese invasion forces, as well as the ports\h\h
they’re launched from, and any of the hundreds of\h
missiles China has permanently aimed at Taiwan.
The Chinese Communist Party is\h
obviously very upset that the US is\h\h
mucking up their invasion plans for\h
Taiwan. China has said it will impose\h\h
sanctions on US defense manufacturers\h
Boeing, Lockheed Martin, and Raytheon.
These companies probably aren’t too\h
worried, though. Lockheed says that\h\h
China provides “considerably less\h
than 1%” of the company’s revenue.
And while Boeing does a lot of business in China,\h\h
the Chinese sanctions would only be on Boeing’s\h
defense unit, which does not do business there.\h
I mean, China wouldn’t want to\h
sanction the entire company, because\h\h
China kind of needs all of the planes\h
that Boeing is building for them.
Meanwhile “China’s defence\h
ministry spokesman Ren Guoqiang\h\h
said the US arms sale to Taiwan could not\h
work and would only lead to a dead-end.”
And he’s right. It will lead to a dead\h
end. For any Chinese invasion force.
Taiwan is saying the new weapons\h
would give it the capability\h\h
to destroy half of any invading Chinese force.
What about the other half? I guess\h
that’ll be America’s job. Maybe.
And this episode is sponsored by Surfshark.
Whenever you go online, you should be using a\h
VPN like Surfshark to protect your identity.\h\h
Everything you do online is\h
being tracked and logged—by\h\h
the websites you visit and your internet service\h
provider. And in many cases, by the government.
And if you’re in an\h
authoritarian country like China\h\h
this kind of tracking can put you at\h
risk of surveillance and even arrest.
So I recommend you use Surfshark\h
to protect yourself online.
When you use Surfshark’s CleanWeb mode,\h
you’ll be protected from trackers,\h\h
plus a lot of ads and malware.
With one account, you can connect\h
as many devices as you want.\h\h
Try it out with a 30-day money back guarantee.
And Surfshark has a special discount for China\h
Uncensored fans. Go to surfshark.com/uncensored\h\h
and use the code UNCENSORED to get our special\h
deal that includes 3 extra months for FREE.
Click the link below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell. See you next time.