A shadowy Communist agency
Is responsible for infiltrating free societies
And Hong Kong
is losing the fight
Welcome to China Uncensored,
I'm Chris Chapell.
Joining me today is Dr Sonny Lo,
an author, professor and political commentator.
Thanks for joining me.
Hi, my pleasure.
So one of your areas of expertise
is the United Front work in Hong Kong.
What is the United Front?
The United Front was originally the strategy
of the Chinese Communist Party to cooperate
with the Nationalist Party in China
during the early 1920s and later during the
1930s
to fight against the Japanese
so that both sides can form a kind of alliance
to deal with the Second World War.
The United Front work later on has evolved
into
an instrument used by the Chinese Communist
Party
to win the hearts and minds of the people.
And in the context of Hong Kong,
United Front means that the Chinese government
has to do everything in order to win
the hearts and minds of the Hong Kong people.
So what are some of the goals of the United
Front?
Who are they targeting in Hong Kong?
The goals of United Front is to number one,
to win the political support of the ordinary
people
and secondly to get the support of the Hong
Kong people
who would support not only the local government
of Hong Kong,
but also the central government in Beijing.
And thirdly, United Front work aims to prevent
the local Democrats from grabbing more seats
in the legislature
and also the district councils because in
the minds of Beijing,
if the political opposition in Hong Kong
can get into political power,
then the situation in Hong Kong would be tipped
in favor of the opposition rather than Beijing.
So basically the goal is to make Hong Kong
less autonomous
and more in line with the Communist Party's
goals.
In the minds of Beijing, United Front work
can coexist with the autonomy of Hong Kong.
Because in the minds of Beijing,
if United Front work is successful,
then the pro-Beijing forces would garner sufficient
public support
and capture most of the seats in the legislature.
So how does the United Front infiltrate a
Hong Kong society?
The United Front work infiltrates into Hong
Kong society
by using many interest groups like women,
like labor unions or like district [inaudible]
or even like neighborhood associations.
Many of these interest groups were formerly
pro-British before 1997
but after 1997 most of these interest groups
have turned to Beijing mainly because of political
loyalty
and also because of financial incentives.
Because Beijing has dished out a lot of
financial and monetary incentives
to all these leaders of the interest groups.
And most importantly,
the leaders of the interest groups
have been appointed to the Chinese People's
Political Consultative Conference,
the Chinese National People's Congress.
So in terms of status, inference and power,
those co-opted Hong Kong elites,
they feel that they are more politically powerful
than ever before.
Is it just special interest groups
or is the United Front involved in the education?
Business sector?
The United Front work also involves deeply
in the business sector
because many business people are highly pragmatic.
They want to do business with China,
they don't want to antagonize China.
So the business sector is particularly vulnerable.
The least vulnerable sector in Hong Kong
or to put it in another way,
the most resistant sector to United Front
work
is the education.
Because in the education sectors,
many intellectuals, academics, students,
they are highly post materialistic if you
like.
In other words,
they attach importance to values like human
rights,
democracy, sustainable development, civil
liberties,
and they are less interested in material incentives.
So from this perspective,
the education sector is the least vulnerable
to United Front work.
I'm curious, you talked about the business
sector.
How can you tell the difference between United
Front work
and just organic natural exchanges
between mainland China and Hong Kong?
The organic exchanges between mainland China
and Hong Kong
involves some more formalistic levels of exchange,
like for example, you know,
business associations interacting with
the Chinese government departments.
Before United Front work,
it can proceed from formal to more informal
co-optation.
That is to say they try to make friends with
you
and in the process of making friends,
they try to woo your side to support their
side politically.
So gradually the co-opted targets become their
friends,
and even solid supporters.
So it is a kind of a longterm movement to
win friendship,
to change friendship to political loyalty.
And when we're talking about the United Front,
the United Front is actually a division of
the Chinese Communist Party itself, correct?
The United Front Department within the Chinese
Communist Party
is mainly responsible for United Front work.
However many other Chinese departments
are also dealing with United Front work.
For example, in the case of Hong Kong
we have their liaison office,
which is the representative office
of the Central Government in Hong Kong
and it is also responsible for United Front
work.
And quite often when the mainland Chinese
government departments
come to visit Hong Kong,
they may interact with some of
the business associations in Hong Kong.
And quite often United Front work is defined
broadly.
That is to say to win friendship,
to interact with our potential friends
and then to gain their political
and economic support in the long run.
So United Front work in China
is not conducted solely by the United Front
department.
It can be conducted by many other departments
as well.
So sort of like a whole of society method
of subverting and changing a society
to be in line with the Communist Party of
China?
Yeah, we can describe it as a kind of mechanism
in which various Chinese departments
are engaging with their opposite numbers,
so as to win the hearts and minds of the targeted
people,
targeted interest groups and targeted organizations.
So how successful has United Front work been
in Hong Kong?
Actually, United Front work
has been quite successful in Hong Kong,
particularly since the 2012
when the anti national education campaign
was launched by many young parents
and also students as well as intellectuals.
However, the October the,
the September to December Occupy Central movement
in 2014
constituted a strong resistance to United
Front work in China.
Many young people in Hong Kong together with
intellectuals,
they were determined to push for democratization
by using the Occupy Central movement, in 2014.
It failed, and so United Front work in China
has deepened further,
until this year when the government of Hong
Kong led by Carrie Lam
decided to introduce an extradition bill
and that extradition bill alienated many young
Hong Kong people
as well as ordinary people,
because many people were frightened that such
extradition bill
would probably lead to the possibility
that many Hong Kong people would be transfer
from Hong Kong to mainland China.
So United Front work that has its limitations.
The limitation is that with the education
sector
being very resistant to United Front work,
the extradition bill has failed to win
the hearts and minds of the ordinary people.
So what is it about the education sector
that makes United Front work not work?
The education sector is characterized
by very independent minded intellectuals
whose understanding of China
is not really through ideological indoctrination
or even socialization.
Unlike the mainland Chinese intellectuals
and students
who were educated in the mainland,
who are socialized and indoctrinated to combine
the cultural identity with the political identity
of accepting the CCP rule in the mainland.
In Hong Kong, traditionally the colonial rulers
were very loose in educating Hong Kong people
not to mention about Chinese nationalism.
So in Hong Kong traditionally and historically
the education system did not inculcate strong
patriotic sentiment
in the psyche of many young people.
And after 1997 this perhaps semi-colonial
education legacy persists.
Not only that, with the era of globalization,
many young Hong Kong people understand China
not through the textbook but through the Internet.
So in that sense the education sector in Hong
Kong
is highly autonomous.
So how does the United Front respond to things
like the Umbrella Movement or the extradition
bill protests,
much of which is student led,
student and teacher led?
The United Front, you know,
machinery responds to the Umbrella Movement
by resuscitating or reorganizing the youth
groups in Hong Kong.
They try to organize many pro-Beijing youth
groups
to support mainland's policy towards Hong
Kong
such as the recent Greater Bay Area plan
in which young people of Hong Kong
are encouraged to do business in China,
to work in China and even to reside in China.
However, the opposition to the extradition
bill
has dealt a severe blow to China's United
Front work in Hong Kong
because many young people are proven to be
very resistant
to the idea of political and economic integration
between Hong Kong and mainland China.
And I know the United Front is very active
in countries around the world.
How does the United Front work in Hong Kong
tie into United Front work globally?
United Front work in Hong Kong cannot be easily
translated into foreign countries for several
reasons.
Number one, in other foreign countries,
there are many overseas Chinese who have long
been assimilated
into the mainstream society of these countries.
So they are not so vulnerable to United Front
work.
Secondly, United Front work conducted by China
tends to focus on the individuals,
like the individuals, politicians or the individuals
who tend to have a emotional attachment to
China.
So in other words,
United Front work in Hong Kong is one thing.
United Front work, you know,
conducted by China in foreign countries
remains a relatively underdeveloped
and under-researched topic,
which is a fascinating one.
So with elections coming,
what chances do the pro democratic factions
have against the United Front?
Because of the protests of almost a million
to 2 million people against the extradition
bill,
we can safely anticipate that in the upcoming
November district council elections,
the localists and the Democrats
will have a strong political comeback.
However, whether the government of officials,
including the electoral officials responsible
for elections,
whether they allow some localists to run in
the elections
remains to be seen
and it will probably become a controversial
issue
because some localists advocate the idea
of quote self determination end of quote,
which is legally and politically unacceptable
to both Beijing and the Hong Kong authorities.
So there's going to be an effort
to make sure pro-Beijing forces win?
There will be such a thrust to ensure that
candidates who are,
you know, relatively pro-Beijing who support
the basic law
and also the SAR government
will be allowed to run in the election.
However, the localists who are now anti government,
anti China,
they may face the possibility of being
disallowed to run in the election.
So this will possibly be a bone of contention.
So with United Front active around the world,
why should other countries like the United
States
care about what's happening in Hong Kong?
Countries like United States can care about
Hong Kong
because Hong Kong can be regarded as a semi-democracy.
Hong Kong doesn't really look like a democracy
as with the West,
but Hong Kong has a pluralistic society.
We also have civil liberties combined with
the rule of law.
Hong Kong is a good indicator of how China
may democratize in the long run.
So in that sense Hong Kong is extremely important
to the West
because Hong Kong's existing civil liberties
and also pluralistic system
belong to the universal values shared
by many western democratic countries.
In that sense,
Hong Kong situation deserves to be observed.
So Hong Kong can show an example of how China
could become more democratic,
but could it also show the world
the ways in which the Chinese Communist Party
undermines democratic institutions?
In a sense, yes, because the extent to which
China
penetrates and infiltrates into the semi-democracy
of Hong Kong
can illustrate that kind of erosion of autonomy.
Do you think the US should be concerned about
the United Front work in general?
Well, many foreign countries are actually
concerned about
United Front work conducted by China in general
because of the perception of the China threat,
many countries like a United States, Australia,
New Zealand,
they have been highly concerned about United
Front work
conducted by China in their countries.
To that extent,
I think United Front work can be regarded
as
a potential threat to the national security
of these countries.
In particular, if United Front work involves
say provision of a donation to, you know,
politicians in America, Australia or New Zealand
and that donation may be orchestrated
by pro-Beijing groups and individuals.
And in this scenario there may be a possibility
of violating the domestic law of foreign countries,
just like the case of Australia.
So United Front work sometimes can trespass
or step into the boundaries
or direct bottom line of the foreign countries.
So you United Front work can be potentially
problematic
and controversial because of the campaigning
and the electioneering activities
conducted by the pro-Beijing groups
and individuals in foreign countries.
So what is the future of United Front work
after these extradition protests?
I think after the extradition protest,
United Front work has to be resuscitated,
reorganize, rearrange in such a way as to
win
the hearts and minds of the people of Hong
Kong.
In the short run,
China's United Front work in Hong Kong,
will encounter tremendous obstacles.
I don't think that United Front work conducted
by China
will really be easy in Hong Kong
mainly because many Hong Kong people,
they tend to treasure their civil liberties.
They tend to have their post materialist values
and they tend to be less materialistic.
In mainland China, many citizens are encouraged
to adopt a materialistic attitude towards
society and economy
and exactly because of this focus and emphasis
on materialism,
mainland China doesn't have significant inroads
towards political liberalization and political
democratization.
Hong Kong is very different.
Hong Kong traditionally has a very strong
liberal minded society.
In that sense,
I anticipate that United Front work
conducted by China in Hong Kong
will still encounter tremendous obstacles
from now to the year 2047.
When the One Country Two System policy ends.
Yeah.
And we can expect that
with such strong opposition to China's United
Front work,
one country, two system, will likely continue.
And mainly because a one country two system
was originally designed by Deng Xiaoping
to appeal to Taiwan for reunification.
Given the fact that one country two system
has become so turbulent and problematic
and given the fact that Taiwan
is unwilling to accept the one country two
system easily,
we can boldly anticipate that Beijing
may prolong the idea of one country,
two system so as to appeal to Taiwan for reunification
so as to buy time for Taiwan to consider
or reconsider this one country, two systems.
And I imagine the United Front
is very active in Taiwan as well?
Yeah.
United Front work
is also trying to penetrate into Taiwan,
but Taiwan has very strong local Taiwan identity
and that kind of resistance to United Front
work
is even stronger than the case of Hong Kong.
So we can see this interesting tug of war
between Taipei and Beijing in the coming years.
So somebody wanting to learn more about you
or the United Front,
where should they go?
What should they do?
I think to learn more from a United Front
work,
they can assess China's policy not only towards
Hong Kong
but also towards Taiwan.
And secondly, outside observers have to understand
and assess whether China's policy in Hong
Kong and Taiwan
are opposed by the local people.
And that kind of opposition and resistance
can be regarded as good indicators of the
extent
to which United Front work can work or cannot
work.
And you have an upcoming book, is that right?
Yes.
My book on China's new United Front work in
Hong Kong
will be published soon.
That's the name of the book?
Yes.
All right.
We'll keep an eye out for that.
Thank you so much for joining me today,
it was a pleasure to hear about the United
Front.
Thank you.