Hi, Chris Chappell here.
I just landed in sunny Florida,
where I'm going to interview Chinese leader Xi Jinping
during his visit with President Trump this
week.
Ok, so it didn't go so well
last time I tried to interview the paramount
leader
of the Chinese Communist Party in 2015.
Sure, I may be banned for life
from the Waldorf Astoria in New York.
But you know what they say:
Second time's a charm.
Palm Beach Florida.
One of the richest towns in America.
Home to more than 25 billionaires.
An oasis of sun, surf, sand...
and strip malls?
Oh right.
I'm in West Palm Beach.
It's kinda like how West New York
is actually in New Jersey.
Palm Beach is...
all the way over there.
Right across the water there
in Palm Beach,
the leader of the free world
is meeting the leader of the unfree world.
I’m of course talking about President Donald Trump
and Chinese leader Xi Jinping.
And what better place for Xi Jinping
to get a taste of American culture
than Florida?!
I’m sure he and Trump
have lots to talk about.
North Korea
Trade
Plus they can share tips
on how they both handle factional infighting
in their administrations.
Now the last time Xi Jinping came to the US,
I didn’t get the interview I wanted.
But this time, I’m more confident.
I’ve already sent off my interview request
via fax
to the Chinese Embassy.
Because the only way to make a media request
with the Chinese Embassy
is by fax.
I still haven’t heard back.
but this is going to happen.
I just have to figure out how to get...
over there.
Darn it!
Shelley!
The road's closed!
I need another way
to get across the bridge!
Ok, listen to me carefully.
Turn the car around.
Park it in a strip mall.
And walk across the bridge.
Seriously?
It's the only way across.
Making it to Palm Beach
was harder than I imagined.
But I was finally here.
I'm headed to Xi Jinping’s hotel,
the Eau Palm Beach Resort & Spa.
But first,
I decided to pick up a gift for him.
The Chinese are all about guanxi—
relationships!
That’s why I’m going to get Xi
some authentic Americana
at the most American place I could find.
But inside Cracker Barrel,
everything seemed to be made in China.
China.
Chiiiinaaa!
Oh, how ’bout this one?
Still China.
But then I realized, back in 2015,
Trump had already given me the answer!
“If you were President,
would you throw him a big dinner?”
“I would not be throwing him a dinner.
We’ve had this conversation.
I’d get him a McDonald’s hamburger and
say
‘We got to get down to work.’”
Now I just have to find a McDonalds.
No McDonald's in Palm Beach.
Go back to West Palm Beach.
As I finally approached Xi Jinping’s hotel,
huge groups of mostly Chinese people
were waiting to greet the Chinese leader.
And they were all wearing red shirts and hats.
We're just curious where you guys got the shirts.
The hats, the shirt, and the bags
were given to us when we got on the bus.
What bus?
From the local Chinese organizations.
Organizations most definitely not tied
to the Chinese government.
Do any of those organizations
have ties to the Chinese government
or are they...?
Uhhhh
And as I waited alongside these people
who all came here totally independently,
I saw Xi Jinping’s motorcade come by,
and I knew I had my chance.
No, wait!
Xi Jinping,
can I get an interview with you?
Xi! Xi!
I think he’s in the next one, for sure.
Mr. Xi, Mr. Xi!
Can I get an interview with, please?
No no wait wait!
Mr. Xi!
Some days you just can’t get an interview
with the leader of the unfree world!
I blew it.
But I knew the interview was waiting for me...
just behind that fence,
guard towers and rows and rows
of security personnel.
Security is pretty tight.
But I’m getting this interview
one way or the other.
Because there’s one thing
the Secret Service didn’t count on.
And that’s that Chris Chappell
is the three-time regional Topanga Canyon
regional
Father Son foot race champion.
Let’s just see them try to catch me.
Shelley!
I'm going to make a run for it.
I need you to get me past the Secret Service.
What?
No.
Why not?
Professional courtesy, Chris.
We do not mess with the Secret Service.
Also, I’m pretty sure they have guns.
But I can dodge bullets!
No, you can’t.
Fine.
I'll just join Mar-a-Lago.
That'll get me in there.
The initiation fee is $200,000.
What?
No.
Just give it up, Chris.
You know Xi Jinping
has never given a TV interview
to Western media, right?
That's great!
I'll be the first!
I'm going for it.
They caught me instantly.
Fine.
I may not be able
to get to Xi Jinping this time,
but I'm not giving up.
You hear me, Xi!
Someday, the interview will be mine!
I know!
I’ll just have to fly to Beijing!
On second thought, maybe not.
But you know,
Fort Lauderdale is only an hour away.
You know what that means?!
China Uncensored Spring Break Gone Wild!!!!
Xi Jinping, you really missed out today.