The Chinese Communist Party gains more influence
Over Europe
But a new effort in the UK
is seeking to change that.
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
Europe’s financial elite are in bed with
the Chinese Communist Party.
The EU abandoned human rights to get a China
investment deal.
But some in the British government are trying
to make sure the UK doesn’t make the same
mistake.\h
For more, I spoke with Benedict Rogers, the
Co-founder and Chief Executive of Hong Kong
Watch, and Deputy Chair of the Conservative
Party Human Rights Commission.
Benedict, as always, it's a pleasure having
you on.
Thank you.
It's always a great pleasure to be with you.
It seems like every time we talk, there's
been another horrible thing that's happened
in Hong Kong.
Last week, the Hong Kong government arrested
more than 50 pro-democracy activists.
What do you think of the international response
to that?
I think the international response has not
been anything like what it should be in proportion
to the significance of these arrests.
This was essentially the final dismantling
of what existed as a democracy movement.
That's not to say the democracy movement won't
try to carry on.
But in formal terms, it was the biggest mass
arrest in one swoop that there's ever been
in recent years.
And the international community's response
was some strong words, but very little else
and even those strong words were rather lost
in the midst of everything else going on.
So I definitely want to see more action.
Well, definitely seems like the Communist
Party chose to make those arrests on a very
particular day, January 6th, almost as if
they knew the rest of the world would be distracted
by something else.
Well, absolutely January the 6th, was a pretty
dark day for democracy, in terms of the arrest
of people in Hong Kong, in the morning, Hong
Kong time for the simple crime in [inverted
commas 00:00:01:40] of trying to carry out
an election.
And of course it ended with the very ugly
scenes in Washington, DC, a beacon of democracy
around the world as well.
So at whilst I wouldn't compare the two, and
I think America's democracy is strong and
Hong Kong's freedoms are being dismantled,
so it would be wrong to compare them.
But nevertheless, they both have happened
on the same day.
And that was a very alarming.
You worked on the UK Conservative Party Human
Rights Commission Report on China, which is
called The Darkness Deepens, very cheerful
by the way.
The report calls out the mendacity, brutality,
inhumanity, insecurity in criminality of the
Chinese Communist Party.
You don't mince words there, do you?
We don't, but it's a report that is based
on hours and hours of testimonial evidence
that was presented to the Conservative Party
Human Rights Commission in hearings throughout
much of last year, and pages and pages of
written evidence.
And that evidence was submitted by a wide
range of sources, all essentially saying the
same thing.
I think what's significant about this report
is that, there are other reports that highlight
particular issues, the Uighurs, the situation
in Hong Kong, Tibet and so on.
There's very few reports that I've come across
that put the whole picture together and show
that the CCP, is not only committing a very
likely genocide against the Uighurs and dismantling
democracy in Hong Kong, it is across the board,
it is Christians, it's following Gong practitioners,
its civil society, activists, lawyers, bloggers,
et cetera.
It's an 88 page report with a long list of
tragedies.
And it follows, of course, the report that
the commission published in 2016, which was
titled The Darkest Moment.
And the reason for that title at that time,
was that one of the people who gave evidence
then said that the situation in 2016 was the
darkest moment since the Tiananmen massacre.
With Hindsight that title was perhaps a bit
premature and hence The Darkness Deepens.
I don't know if that's funny or tragic?
Yeah.
Well, it's very tragic in reality, but you
have to keep a sense of humor in very dark
times.
And we found ourselves as a commission, faced
with that linguistic challenge, what title
did we give this?
If we titled it the darkest moment four years
ago?
Well, so then what's the next one going to
be called if it gets worse?
I think we'll have to come to that when we
get to it.
But any suggestions there, let me know.
Just a stream of swears.
Well, okay, so hopefully won't get to that
point.
So what actions does the reports suggest the
UK take against the Chinese Communist Party's
human rights abuses?
Well, it calls first of all for a comprehensive
and coordinated thorough review of UK-China
policy across government departments.
So not just the Foreign Office, but across
relevant government departments.
And for a total reset and recalibration of
that relationship.
It calls for targeted sanctions, which have
not yet been applied, it urges Britain to
work with our allies to lead the establishment
of a coalition of the free world to act as
much as possible together.
That shouldn't mean the lowest common denominator,
countries should be as robust as they possibly
can be.
But there is a need for the democratic world
to unite and coordinate much more than they
have been because essentially, we need to
form a united front to counter the CCP's united
front.
I like the sound of that.
I know recently, some UK Members of Parliament
have suggested a genocide amendment to the
UK trade bill.
What is that?
Yes.
So that is an amendment that was pioneered
in the House of Lords by people like Lord
Alton and quite amazing range of members of
the House of Lords, former cabinet ministers,
the former head of the Royal Air Force, the
former head of our intelligence services,
former Supreme Court judges, and whole range
of other really distinguished figures.
And it now goes to the Commons next week.
And what the amendment tries to do is two
things, firstly, to create a mechanism whereby
people who believe there was a case of genocide,
and this applies not simply in the case of
China, but genocide anywhere, wherever it
happens, can come to the High Court of England
and Wales and ask the High Court to make a
preliminary determination as to whether the
evidence does suggest genocide or not.
And the consequences of that, if the high
court does conclude that it's genocide, under
this amendment the government will be required
not to enter into a bilateral trade deal with
the states that are found to be committing
genocide.
So if a trade deal is already in place, that
should be revoked, and if it isn't in place,
steps towards one should be stopped.
That's the effect of it.
And it was designed to answer a very simple
problem, which is that for decades now, this
isn't always the position of other governments.
But the British government's position has
always been, it's not for governments to determine
whether something has genocide, it's for the
courts.
That's a perfectly logical theoretical position
to have, but the problem with it is the International
Court mechanisms are very unsatisfactory,
and particularly in the case of China, you're
never going to get a referral.
So this is an amendment designed to get out
of that vicious circle.
Well, you certainly phrase that in a very
polite way.
But so it sounds pretty straight forward.
Don't trade with countries that commit genocide.
But it seems like the UK government is not
happy about it.
So if the genocide amendment passes, would
the UK government actually apply that to China?
Well, that's the big question.
If it passes and becomes law, and if then
a case is brought to the High Court of England
and Wales in regard to the Uighurs, for example.
And if the High Court concludes that what's
happening to the Uighurs is genocide, then
under the law, the UK would not be able to
negotiate a trade deal with China in those
circumstances.
Now, realistically, there's going to be quite
a long timeframe to complete all those steps.
But nevertheless, if it passes, it would send
a very important message.
And it would be law that people can go to
the court, see if the court decides it's genocide.
And if it does, the government must abide
by the requirements of that amendment.
So, speaking of trade, the EU has recently
announced a major investment deal with China.
How would this deal affect human rights in
China?
The EU's deal is one of the most appalling
deals that I've seen.
And what was so striking about it was the
timing of it.
Firstly, it came a few days after the European
Parliament itself, one of the EU's main institutions
had passed a resolution calling for targeted
sanctions, calling for access to the camps
in Xinjiang and very importantly calling for
any investment deal to have particular standards
around labor rights.
And just a few days later, the European Commission
and the member states completely ignored the
European Parliament and went ahead with this
deal that has no safeguards on human rights.
It has maybe a few vague promises by the CCP
to move towards signing various international
agreements, but we all know what to think
of the CCP is word.
We can't ever take the word for anything other
than essentially an untruth.
And coming just a short time before the transition
in the United States as well, it sends a pretty
bad signal to the new administration in the
U.S. I think most people agree, it's a bad
deal in itself, and it was very bad timing.
And I hope that the European Parliament and
other member states will reconsider it before
it's too late.
Is it too late to do something about the EU-China
investment deal?
Well, it has been signed.
So in that sense, probably is too late, but
I think there were steps that EU could take.
I said when the 53 were arrested in Hong Kong,
that in response to that, the EU should immediately
revoke and reconsider the deal.
Unfortunately, they didn't listen to me.
But I think we need to keep up the pressure
on the EU itself and on member states to take
action going forward.
If they can't revoke the deal, then at least
they need to balance it with other measures,
including the application of targeted Magnitsky
sanctions.
You're a part of two upcoming events about
human rights in China that people can join
online.
Can you tell us about those?
Yeah.
So the first, later today on the 13th of January,
is the launch of the Conservative Party Human
Rights Commission Report, The Darkness Deepens.
And that's an online event, I've tweeted about
it, there's an event invitation out there
people can register.
And at that event, we will have some very
amazing speakers, Iain Duncan Smith, who is
the former leader of the British Conservative
Party, but also the co-chair of IPAC, the
Inter-Parliamentary Alliance on China, we'll
be speaking at it.
So will Nathan Law, the highest-profile exiles,
Hong Kong activist, Rahima Mahmut, who's a
very high-profile Uyghurs campaigner, Simon
Cheng, who you may recall was a British consulate
employee in Hong Kong, who ended up in jail
in China and suffering some horrific torture
there.
And Dr. Teng Biao, a pre-eminent Mainland
Chinese exiled lawyer and an activist.
And I'll say a few words as well, so that's
the lineup at that event.
And then tomorrow, Thursday, the 14th of January,
the Macdonald–Laurier Institute, think tank
in Canada together with Hong Kong Watch, IPAC
and a number of others, has a big online conference
on human rights in China as a whole.
And with a number of politicians and prominent
activists speaking at that and looking at
what are the ways forward to addressing human
rights in China.
I'll definitely put links to those events
below, and I hope everyone watching definitely
checks that out.
Benedict, it's always great to have you on,
thank you for being here.
Thank you very much for having me.
Thank you for watching.
I’ve put the links to those events in the
description below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.