On this episode of China Uncensored,
a rose by any other name,
would smell as sweet.
Unless you call the rose by its Tibetan name.
Then it would smell like the inside of a prison
cell.
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
When you think of the happiest place on Earth,
what do you think of?
Yes, Tibet.
Why, its capital keeps ranking first
on Chinese state-run media’s list
of happiest cities in China.
And surely a CCTV poll wouldn’t lie.
After all,
that’s the closest thing to voting
that anyone in Lhasa might ever get.
Let’s take a look at the details.
Wow!
Big data analysis reveals that
70% of Lhasa citizens
felt extremely happy in 2016.
And why wouldn’t they?
The Chinese Communist Party
has done great things in Tibet.
For instance, according to my favorite
Chinese state-run media The Global Times,
reincarnation is finally being well managed
by the government.
“Regulation gives government decisive rights
on reincarnation issue.”
What a thrill!
And who could forget how the loving message
of the Communist Party’s national congress
spreads across Tibet.
Through friendly soldiers and police—
there for everyone’s safety.
Wait a minute,
I think I know how they conducted
that happiness poll.
With such friendly soldiers and police
asking you questions,
of course you’d be extremely happy!
Yes, Tibet is the happiest place on Earth.
Minority rights for China’s ethnic Tibetans
are even guaranteed in the Chinese constitution!
Particularly their right
to speak the Tibetan language.
It says,
“All nationalities have the freedom
to use and develop their own spoken
and written languages
and to preserve or reform
their own folkways and customs.”
So what happens when an ethnic Tibetan
tries to get Tibetan schools
to teach the Tibetan language?
He gets put on trial for inciting separatism,
a charge that carries a 15-year prison term.
And Chinese courts have a 99.9% conviction
rate.
So he was put on trial for doing something
that’s explicitly allowed
according to China’s constitution?
I know what you’re thinking.
How could the officially atheist government
that regulates reincarnation do anything so
hypocritical?
Well, it has to do with this documentary
the New York Times made about
Tashi Wangchuk two years ago.
Tashi observes that the Tibetan language
and culture are dying out,
largely because they’re not being
taught in schools.
So he develops a plan—
take Chinese law at face value.
According to the Chinese constitution,
a Chinese citizen has the right to sue any
official.
And officials have been blocking Tibetan schools
from teaching the Tibetan language,
something that violates China’s constitution.
So Tashi decides to go to Beijing
and use the Chinese legal system
to sue local officials for violating
the Constitution.
But we all know how the Chinese legal system
really works—or, rather,
doesn’t really work.
So big surprise—
he gets detained, tortured,
and then put on trial.
And the New York Times documentary
is used as evidence against him.
So just a little reminder to Tibetan dissidents:
Don’t talk about China’s problems
to Western media.
Or to Chinese officials.
Just don’t talk about problems at all.
That’s how you get to be the happiest city
in China.
So Tashi Wangchuk has now been detained
for two years.
He finally went on trial,
on January 4.
So in New York,
three activist groups organized a protest
outside the Chinese consulate.
“Actually, it’s a state set-up.
There’s no legal system.
And the fact that Tashi Wangchuk
actually said that he wanted to work
in the Chinese legal system
and ask for Tibetan rights,
and even then being turned into jail.
So legally it’s a state set up that
no matter what you do,
you end up in jail.”
“Why are Chinese authorities targeting Tashi?
I mean, if speaking Tibetan is subversive,
shouldn’t they just detain everyone?”
“So Tashi Wangchuk is a surprise for everyone,
that’s why.
Because he tried to fight a case
in the Chinese legal system.
And now he’s in prison.
So that means there’s no justice in China.”
“I think this trial right now that’s taking
place
is really exposing the true face
of China’s colonial ambitions.”
“Well that’s funny because
it’s China that’s always accusing the
West
of colonialism.”
“Yeah, I mean it’s been like
one of the oldest arguments ever used,
is whenever someone tries to say
the Tibetan people should be free.
They’ll be like,
‘What about the indigenous population,
what about the natives?’
And right now actually,
you see a lot of countries actually
trying to make amends,
they’re saying, ‘We apologize for this,
we want to make a difference,
and a lot of works still needs to be done.’
And the Chinese government,
they’re not even trying to get there.
They’re basically trying to wipe out Tibetan
language
and people who protect it,
like Tashi Wangchuk.”
“But what does China need to apologize for?
Tibetans are so happy.”
“Yeah, that’s definitely not true.
If Tibetans were so happy,
why do they not let China Uncensored into
Tibet?
Film the happiness, they won’t.”
“They’re using the New York Times documentary
as so-called evidence.
Do you think he could use the defense
that the New York Times is fake news?”
“I have no comment about that.
That’s a whole ’nother issue.”
“But international attention is growing.
And during Tashi’s trail recently on January 4
there were diplomats from five different embassies
traveling to Tibet for the first time.
And that’s something big,
and that’s why right now there is no conviction...
In fact it is not Tashi on trail right now.
It is the Chinese justice system.”
“Could you teach me a Tibetan phrase,
something useful.
How about:
“Help, I’m being detained by Chinese authorities”?
“Ngala gyami mangmi gi simsong, ngala rokpa
jhe-da.”
“How about just ‘help’?”
“Ngala rokpa godu.
We say ‘I need help.’
We don’t have one word.
Ngala rokpa godu.”
“Still too complicated.”
Well, if learning Tibetan is that hard,
I can’t imagine what it’s like when
the government is actively trying to stop
you.
And you know,
the crazy thing about Tashi Wangchuk
being tried for “inciting separatism”
is that he specifically told the New York
Times
he was not advocating for a free Tibet.
He wanted to sort out the issues
within China’s legal system,
by using the legal system.
Oh wait,
I see why that’s subversive.
So what do you think of Tashi Wangchuk’s
case?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Hey, you know what makes me happy?
When viewers like you check out ChinaUncensored.tv.
That’s our website,
where you can see more great content from
us,
including half hour episodes
you won’t see on YouTube.
That’s ChinaUncensored.tv.
I’m feeling happier already.