Tesla’s China honeymoon is over.
The US and China agree on climate cooperation
Plus, Australia cancels a suspicious deal
with China.
That and more on this week’s China news
headlines
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
This week’s China news headlines
Things aren’t going so well for Elon Musk
and Tesla in China.
I tried to warn you, Elon.
I tried.
This week was the Shanghai Auto Show.
A perfect opportunity to show off the new
Tesla.
Except they got upstaged by protests.
Protests, in China?
It’s a little sus, and I’ll get to that
in a minute.
This video from the protests went viral.
This woman climbed on top of a Tesla and started
saying some not very nice things.
Her t-shirt says “The Brakes Don’t Work”
and “Invisible Killer.”
Invisible Killer?
You mean Elon Musks has an invisible car?!
How does he not lose it?
The woman was later dragged off by security
guards.
But, “The incident overshadowed an announcement
[Tesla] made the same day...the automaker
would start developing some of its vehicles
in China from scratch—with new models that
would incorporate ‘many Chinese elements.’”
Ohh, many Chinese elements?
Like ethnic slave labor?
Anyway, the Tesla protest, “hit a nerve
in China, sending complaints about the company
ricocheting across the Chinese internet.”
That’s interesting, considering how tightly
the Chinese Communist Party controls the Internet.
Things don’t go viral for very long unless
the internet censors allow it.
Maybe it was the fact most of these social
media comments came to the conclusion they
should just buy Chinese cars instead of Teslas.
Interesting.
This story was so big, even state-run media
covered it.
I know, Chinese state-run media covering a
protest in China.
Interesting.
Not only that, “The Central Political and
Legal Affairs Commission, a high-level Communist
Party body...accused Tesla of arrogance and
of endangering Chinese consumers by selling
defective products.”
Interesting.
It’s almost as if the Communist Party itself
has taken issue with Tesla.
Tesla has now apologized for how the protester
was handled.
And it was totally inappropriate.
That’s not how you treat protesters in China.
You’re not supposed to let them criticize
you in public!
You're supposed to drag them outside and beat
them *before* they do any protesting.
It’s unclear to me what the quality of Tesla’s
China-made cars are.
In February, Chinese regulators summoned Tesla
for a rare public rebuke over its quality
record.
Then they banned military and state employees
from using Tesla.
The Chinese regime accused Tesla of gathering
data on Chinese drivers.
Which, of course they do.
That’s how Tesla’s automated driving system
works.
It collects user data.
But now the Chinese regime has arbitrarily
labeled it a national security risk, so they
can have leverage over Tesla.
Elon Musk may be a smart man, but when it
comes to China, he’s been making the same
stupid mistake Western businessmen have been
making for decades.
Elon Musk went into China with big dreams.
But Chinese competitors stole his technology,
with government support.
Now the Chinese government is using legal
warfare to squeeze Tesla out of the China
market, and promote home-grown companies.
This always happens!
Why are smart people so stupid?
Chinese leader Xi Jinping has some pretty
harsh words for...no country in particular
At the annual Boao Forum for Asia Xi criticized
efforts by some countries to “build barriers”
and “decouple.”
He said “The world wants justice, not hegemony.”
Yeah, Xi didn’t say which country in particular
was building barriers and decoupling.
But I’m going to go out on a limb here and
guess he was talking about...Palau.
And you know who’s going to stand up for
the world against global hegemons like...Palau?
The Chinese Communist Party.
Don’t worry, world.
Xi Jinping says that “China will never seek
hegemony, expansion, or a sphere of influence
no matter how strong it may grow.”
Sure.
That’s like when I tell myself I’m not
going to eat Cheez-its while my hand is literally
in the Cheez-it box.
Meanwhile, the Chinese Communist Party is
gearing up for its 100th birthday.
And like most 100 year olds, it's decrepit
and falling apart.
But that’s not the message they’re going
with.
They want people to follow the Party forever.
The Party is pushing “Patriotic films.
History lessons.
Mass weddings.”
Just like Mao intended.
The anniversary is July 1.
And to get everyone in the spirit, the Party
is cracking down on anyone who makes illegal
comments on history.
And that might even include former top ranking
Communist Party members.
Like Former Premier Wen Jiabao . He wrote
a touching memorial to his recently deceased
mother.
It got censored.
Why?
Well, in the article he, in a rather roundabout
way, called for more fairness, justice, humanity,
and liberty in China.
Yeah, that’s not gonna fly.
Premier Wen Jiabao also wrote that his time
as the second highest ranking official in
the Communist Party was quote “like walking
on thin ice.”
Being a Communist Party member is tough.
Just look at what it did to the number one
guy at the time, Hu Jintao.
This is him as a young man.
And this is him as the head of the Party.
His nickname was woodface.
It’s been a great 100 years for the Party.
War, famine, cultural destruction, and lots
and lots of labor camps.
So much to celebrate.
And the Biden administration is celebrating
by making a new agreement with China.
More after the break.
Welcome back.
The Biden Administration and the Chinese Communist
Party have made an agreement to cooperate
on climate issues.
The agreement came days before Joe Biden will
hold a virtual summit of world leaders to
discuss climate change.
Just what our planet needs—politicians spewing
hot air.
Of course, China is the world’s largest
emitter of greenhouse gases.
China burns more coal than the rest of the
world combined.
And that’s why the US has to work with China.
Climate change is a global issue.
And we can only solve it if we work together...with
regimes that break their promises.
Why does no one ever listen.
But at least China is doing one thing to combat
climate change.
After stealing US technology, China now makes
most of the world’s solar panels.
And they’re much cheaper now.
Because they use ethnic slave labor.
Fighting climate change, protecting human
rights—who says you can’t do neither.
This week, Biden met with Japanese Prime Minister
Yoshide Suga.
It was his first in person meeting with a
world leader.
And the point was to project unity against
China’s assertiveness.
And to make sure America can get more of this...
And less of this...
We did a full episode covering the meeting
on our other channel, America Uncovered.
Check it out, the link is in the description
below.
Chinese hackers are compromising dozens of
government agencies, and defense contractors.
Hackers were able to exploit a VPN called
Pulse Secure that many US government agencies,
and just normal companies, were using so their
employees could work remotely.
And good news, the hacking is still going
on.
But in some actual good news, Australia has
canceled a major Belt and Road deal with China.
Which of course angered China.
This is the state of Victoria.
It’s biggest city is Melbourne.
It’s the San Francisco of Australia.
You may remember it for having one of the
longest and harshest Covid lockdowns in the
world.
Years ago, Victoria’s leadership made several
high profile deals with China as part of the
Belt and Road initiative.
That’s China’s global investment and infrastructure
plan that gets up to some pretty shady stuff.
But those deals have now been scrapped.
That’s under a new Australian law that gives
Australia’s federal government the power
to stop deals that Australia’s states have
made with foreign governments.
And get this.
“Two other deals between Victoria and the
governments of Iran and Syria have also been
scrapped.”
Making deals with China, Iran, and Syria?
What was the state of Victoria getting up
to?!
I say, not enough.
If Premier Daniel Andrews really wants to
bring his state a brighter future, it’s
time to buy nukes from Kim Jung-un.
Although Victoria seems a little eager to
make deals with authoritarian regimes, it’s
not alone in potentially having its deals
with China cancelled.
“The law may still allow the federal government
to review and overturn memorandums of understanding
between Beijing and the state governments
of Western Australia, South Australia and
Tasmania.”
That last deal was a real whirlwind.
Like I said, the Chinese regime is not happy.
Hu Xijin, the editor-in-chief of my favorite
Chinese state-run media, the Global Times,
tweeted:
“A formal agreement has been cancelled so
easily.
Australians, is your country a uncivilized
rogue that deserves stern admonition and punishment?”
Oh Hu.
Were you trying to insult Australia or compliment
it?
Because Australia’s entire brand is “uncivilized
rogue.”
It’s what makes them so charming.
And now time to answer a question from a member
of the China Uncensored 50 Cent Army, fans
who support the show on Patreon.
brazzjazz asks “Mova Globes all seem to
depict Taiwan as part of China, I have checked
several globes on their website.
Why would you accept such a company as your
sponsor??”
Excellent question Brazzjazz!
We actually did a whole episode on it, called
How China Is Secretly Changing Everyone’s
Maps.
The link is in the Description.
But here’s the gist.
MOVA Globes, like many Western companies,
had their products made in factories in China.
But then the Chinese government required that
all their maps sold in China, or printed in
China but sold abroad, had to have China’s
official version of the world map.
That meant some MOVA Globes were being printed
with China’s 9 Dash Line and Taiwan labeled
as part of China.
But the good news is that MOVA pulled its
manufacturing out of China a couple years
ago.
And MOVA was open and honest with us about
what happened, and helped us expose what the
CCP is doing.
They’re not printing China’s version of
the map anymore.
Like if you order this 6” Black and Silver
model, it no longer has it.
But some of the other sizes and models still
do—at least until their stock runs out.
So if you want to make sure the one you order
doesn’t have the Nine-Dash Line, contact
MOVA’s Customer Care.
Thanks for your question brazzjazz.
And thank you for watching.
If you’d like me to answer one of your questions
on the show, head over to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored
and join the China Uncensored50 Cent Army!
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.