On this episode of China Uncensored
Donald Trump and Kim Jong-Un
have solved the nuclear crisis—
thanks to China.
The Chinese Coast Guard is caught stealing
fish near the Philippines.
And the story you’ve been waiting for,
a Chinese doctor pulls a live leech
out of a guy’s nose.
Really, just skip to that part.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
Now I wasn’t personally in Singapore this
week
during the summit between Donald Trump and
Kim Jong-Un.
But you know who also wasn’t?
China.
Probably.
Actually, maybe they were listening in.
Who knows?
But even if they weren’t officially there,
that didn’t stop Chinese officials from
taking credit
for all the positive outcomes.
Yes, China’s role was “indisputable.”
Getting Trump to agree to halt America’s
big joint military exercise with South Korea?
That was originally China’s idea.
And if Trump starts lifting sanctions on North
Korea—
which he has not done yet, by the way—
but if he does,
that’s also China’s idea.
And having the summit end in paperwork instead
of nuclear war?
Obviously, China’s idea.
And the lunch menu?
Definitely China’s idea.
Chinese telecom company ZTE
has lost about 3 billion dollars this week.
Which makes me feel a lot better about
how much money I’ve lost in student loans.
Ok, not really.
3 billion dollars is about 15% of ZTE’s
stock value.
But it’s still the world’s 4th largest
maker
of telecommunications equipment—
things like cell phones and routers.
Back in April, the US had put a seven-year
ban on ZTE,
forbidding it to buy any parts from US companies.
That’s because ZTE had violated US sanctions
by selling
made-in-America parts to North Korea and Iran.
I’m sure it was an honest mistake.
As part of a settlement with the US government,
ZTE has to pay 1.4 billion dollars in penalties.
It also has 30 days to fire “all members
of its leadership
at or above the senior vice president level.”
OK, so it fired a few people.
No big deal.
Wait, what’s that, Shelley?
“That could result in about
40 senior executives being replaced”?!
How many senior vice presidents does a company
need?
About 40, I guess.
The Chinese Communist Party has plans to put
a radio frequency ID chip in cars across China
starting July 1st.
Officials have described it as a way to
“help ease worsening traffic congestion...
partly because clogged roads contribute to
air pollution.”
Which is why it’s being implemented by...
the Ministry of Public Security.
Now while whole chip-tracking-your-car thing
may sound like some scary,
big brother type surveillance plan,
don’t worry!
It’s voluntary.
For now.
That’ll change on January 1st.
Then it’ll become mandatory for all new
vehicles.
But even without this ID chip program,
the Ministry of Public Security can still
track wherever you go.
They’ve got 200 million surveillance cameras
across the China,
and they can already track your car by its
model, color,
and license plate number.
Speaking of vehicles,
truck drivers across nine provinces in China
have been protesting.
They’re gathering in parking lots,
and even on major highways.
The truck drivers complaining about high gas
prices
and excessive highway tolls.
But also they’re kind of mad about how they
police
keep harassing them.
“Overthrow the CCP!”
Overthrow the Chinese Communist Party?!
Whoa!
People aren’t supposed to think like that!
No!
They’re supposed to be patient
while the Chinese Communist Party fixes all
the problems
it totally didn’t cause in the first place.
And now, off the roads and into the sea.
The South China Sea.
Where Filipino fishermen are accusing
the Chinese Coast Guard of stealing their
fish.
Now, I know,
it seems unfair that people who have boats
like this
would need to steal food from people who have
boats like this.
But the Chinese ambassador explains.
“This is not harassment.
This is not confiscation.
It is some sort of barter trade.”
Yes, the kind of barter trade where
a Chinese Coast Guardsman boards a fishing
boat,
and puts their fish into his laundry basket.
And in return, the Filipino fishermen get...angry.
That’s a good trade.
Man, it sucks when your crimes get caught
on video.
And finally, the story you’ve been waiting
for.
A Chinese doctor removes a live leech from
inside a guy’s nose.
Yeah, I’d be surprised too if I were that
guy.
He’s a 51-year-old from Yunnan province.
Apparently, he’d been suffering from a nosebleed
for ten days,
when he finally decided, “You know what?
Maybe I should see a doctor about this.”
And the doctor decided,
“You know what?
Maybe some random person should stand next
to us
and shoot a video of this thing.
It’s going to be amazing.”
The guy thinks he got the leech in his nose
when he went swimming in a river.
Which is why I’m never going swimming again.
And that’s it for this week’s headlines,
but stay where you are,
because it’s time for another fan question
from one of our amazing fans
who supports China Uncensored on Patreon.
T Yoc asks:
“Do you think it is still worthwhile going
to China
even with all that’s been going on?
I’ve been accepted for a study abroad opportunity
in Shanghai,
but a lot of the stuff I hear has me second
guessing
due to safety and political concerns.”
Great question.
Going to China could be interesting...
but also unnerving.
Everyone has a different experience.
If you decide to go there,
there’s obviously things you should be careful
about.
Like don’t talk about politics in class.
And use a VPN when you go online—
not one made in China.
And of course,
don’t go swimming in any rivers.
On the plus side,
you’ll probably meet a lot of cool people.
Look, you’ll be fine if you follow all the
rules.
But just keep in mind,
authorities could be monitoring what you do.
And don’t try to break anyone out of a labor
camp.
I know a bunch of China Uncensored fans
are actually foreigners living in China.
So maybe you guys can help out, too.
Give him your advice in the comments below.
What’s it like as a foreigner studying in
China?
What should you be careful about?
And to everyone,
thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Well, that’s all folks.
But remember,
there’s lots more great China Uncensored
episodes to see.
That’s why you can click here and here
to watch some of our recent episodes.
And click this orange button to support us
through the website Patreon.
We’re funded mainly through support from
viewers like you.