bjbj,(,( On this episode of China Uncensored,
this is why they don t allow guns in China
Logo Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I m
Chris Chappell. Civilians in China aren t
allowed to own guns and there s a good reason
why. Local officials couldn t get away with
stuff like this. No, this isn t photoshop.
Its the home of Luo Baogen, a farmer in China
s Zhejiang Province. There used to be a village
there, with over a thousand people living
in it. But they all moved out four years ago
when construction on a new freeway began.
Everyone except Luo that is. He and his wife
weren t given enough compensation by government
contractors. So they just built the road around
it. But you know, it doesn t matter that you
make a crappy road that endangers people s
lives. Whats most important is that you show
an elderly couple who s BOSS OF CHINA! And
don t think this is a one-time thing. It s
happened over and over and over again. It
s so common that they have a name for it,
nail houses. They stick up out of construction
sites like nails, waiting to be hammered down.
So this is what the world s second largest
economy looks like. According to Amnesty International,
forced evictions and demolitions are on the
rise. Since the Chinese government technically
owns most of the land in China, corrupt officials
are able to seize land and sell it to contractors,
often to pay off debt. Since it s their own
government doing it, people really don t have
many options. So you end up with stories like
this: Chen Xuxing didn t want to move out
so the developer sent thugs to beat him up.
He was hospitalized for two months and when
he went back home, this was all that was left.
Then there was Wang Jiazheng. He lit himself
on fire, even as the bulldozers were at his
front door. He died a week later. His family
was not allowed to see him. According to Amnesty,
between 2009 and 2011 there have been 41 cases
of self-immolations over land grabs. In one
incident, after 36-year-old farmer Wang Shujie
ignited himself, police rushed forward and
shot him dead. I guess burning to death wasn
t fast enough for them. Construction was already
delayed, after all. So what happens when armed
police acting under corrupt officials beat
and murder unarmed civilians? Well, sometimes
they make their own guns. This is from back
in 2010. Yang Youde built homemade cannons
out of a wheelbarrow, pipe, and fireworks
to fend off violent demolition crews. His
story became such a hit that shortly after,
someone made an online game called, The Nail
Household Versus Demolition Team. You play
as the Ding family, select family members,
strategically place them and kill hordes of
demolition crews that come your way. Each
level becomes progressively harder until inevitably,
the house is brought down, Ding family and
all. Seems kind of ironic they call it the
People s Republic of China. That s all for
today. Once again I m Chris Chappell, thanks
for watching this episode of China Uncensored.
hQB5 [Content_Types].xml #!MB ;c=1 _rels/.rels
theme/theme/themeManager.xml sQ\}# theme/theme/theme1.xml
G$$DA : BR \{i5@R V*[_X ,l\Y Ssd+r] 5\|E Vky-
V4Ej 6NGU s?^V * 7;wP EBU` 5<V8
LStf+] C9P^ wB>VD GGHPXNT, /M,W m2iU [[v _Xtl
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.rels 6?$Q
K(M&$R(.1 [Content_Types].xmlPK _rels/.relsPK
theme/theme/themeManager.xmlPK theme/theme/theme1.xmlPK
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.relsPK
<a:clrMap xmlns:a="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/main"
bg1="lt1" tx1="dk1" bg2="lt2" tx2="dk2" accent1="accent1"
accent2="accent2" accent3="accent3" accent4="accent4"
accent5="accent5" accent6="accent6" hlink="hlink"
folHlink="folHlink"/> Chris Normal.dotm Chris
Microsoft Macintosh Word PICT$ kZo\{g9^ g9g9Z
kZg9c kZg9Z kZg9s o\{g9c kZg9kZc kZkZs 4kZkZc
g9g9^ g9g9kZg9g9c kZkZg9g9c g9kZc g9g9w o\{kZkZs
kZo\{kZo\
g9kZkZs kZg9s g9kZo\{o\
o\{kZw kZkZ^ g9g9w g9g9s g9o\{c g9o\{ g9kZc kZkZg9g9c
g9o\{g9kZc g9kZkZs o\{o\{w o\{o\{w o\{o\{c o\{kZ\{
o\{kZs o\{o\{^ o\{kZw kZo\{o\{ kZg9o\{s g9g9s o\{o\
g9g9Z kZg9g9Z kZg9Z )g9^ kZg9^ g9o\{c g9kZc
g9kZg9^ kZo\{ g9kZw o\{o\{ kZo\{o\{w o\{o\{w 6g9Z
kZo\{o\{Z g9kZg9Z kZkZZ o\{g9Z o\{kZV Dg9R kZo\{Ns^
g9Nso\{c o\{o\{c kZkZg9o\{c 'g9c kZNsZ Nsg9V ,o\{c
g9kZZ o\{g9^ g9g9Z g9kZkZ^ g9g9Z o\{kZR g9g9kZg9kZ^
g91c g9g9kZg9g9c kZg9g9c g9kZkZc kZg9kZw g9g9kZ^
kZg9s o\{g9g9o\{^ kZo\{g9o\{o\{w o\{kZw o\{o\{kZs
o\{o\{s kZo\{s o\{kZw o\{o\{w o\{o\{ g9kZs kZg9kZ
o\{o\{s o\{$s g9o\{o\{w g9o\{c o\{g9w g9kZo\{s g9kZw
kZg9c kZg9g9s g9o\{c g9kZg9c kZo\{c Cg9Z kZg9kZZ
kZkZc g9o\{c o\{kZs g9o\{c kZkZZ kZg9g9o\{ kZo\
g9o\{o\{w o\{kZo\{s o\{g9s g9kZg9o\{g9g9o\{g9^ kZo\{o\{c
kZkZg9kZo\{kZ^ o\{kZkZc g9kZc kZkZs kZg9kZs
g9g9o\{g9o\{g9g9o\{kZo\{o\{^ ?g9V kZg9V o\{g9Z o\{kZw
o\{kZkZs o\{/kZc o\{kZo\
o\{kZkZ\{ g9o\{^ o\{o\{kZkZw o\{kZo\{o\{w g9g9kZkZw
kZg9kZo\{o\{g9g9V o\{g9c kZg9kZV o\{g9s o\{g9s
o\{g9 kZg9s kZg9w kZg9g9c g9kZg9o\{w kZo\{g9
,kZZ kZkZg9Z g9g9c g9g9^ g9g9kZc kZo\{c g9o\{g9g9^
kZo\{s kZo\{o\{s o\{kZs o\{o\
g9o\{c kZo\{ &kZs o\{o\{s o\{o\{s kZo\{s o\{kZs o\{g9
o\{kZw o\{o\{g9w o\{kZs o\{kZo\{o\{ g9g9c o\{g9c g9g9s
g9+o\{Z o\{g9o\{c o\{g9V kZg9c o\{g9c kZo\{c g9g9kZg9c
o\{g9c kZg9Z g9o\{^ g96Z NskZZ g9g9Z o\{kZ^ g9o\{kZg9c
g9g9s o\{o\{s Title Microsoft Word 97-2004 Document
NB6W Word.Document.8