On this episode of China Uncensored,
Trump punishes Chinese company ZTE—
and then...he says he wants to help them
get back in business?!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
US President Trump has been—
and this may shock you—
a source of controversy.
But in one area,
even some of his harshest critics have been
supportive.
"One of the few areas where the president
and I agreed—
and I was vocally supportive of him—
was his tough approach to China.
In fact,
I said at one point that I'm closer
to President Trump on China
than I was to President Obama or President
Bush.
And he saw that in the newspaper
and sent me a handwritten note thanking me.”
Wait...Donald Trump sent Chuck Schumer
a handwritten note?
See?
Donald Trump is literate!
How dare the media slander him!
“You are fake news.”
Anyway, Senator Schumer had praised
the Trump administration’s move against
the Chinese telecommunications giant ZTE.
Last month, the US banned ZTE from buying
American technology for 7 years.
It was punishment for ZTE violating the terms
of
a sanctions settlement with the US.
You see, ZTE had illegally shipped
equipment with American parts
to North Korea and Iran...283 times.
When they were caught,
ZTE agreed to pay more than a billion dollars
in fines.
They also agreed to punish the executives
who were involved.
But the US Commerce Department says that ZTE
rewarded the executives instead.
Which led to the new ban on ZTE
buying American technology.
And that’s all but left China’s
second largest telecommunications company
dead in the water.
That’s why it was shock when, a few days
ago,
Trump tweeted he would work with Xi Jinping
to get ZTE back in business...fast.
Obviously a lot of folks in the US were less
than happy.
Some even went on to suggest Trump was maybe
possibly bribed.
And others outright said it.
That accusation came from reports
that Chinese state-owned company
paid half a billion dollars to an Indonesia
Development firm
that’s building Trump-branded hotels a golf
course.
That doesn’t look good.
But it turns out, that’s probably not what’s
going on.
The Indonesia deal was signed before Trump
got elected,
and...according to the main company involved,
they haven’t actually signed
the $500 million loan deal with China.
So Trump is not getting a Chinese bribe
for helping ZTE.
Of course...maybe Trump will still get
free tickets to the Indonesian resort,
“An immersive world of magic and adventure”
that features, “a variety of thrill rides
and adventures
interwoven with original stories and themes
from Indonesia’s rich cultural heritage.”
Although as president,
he should get that anyway if he wants, right?
Probably Trump saying he’ll help ZTE
has more to do with using it as a negotiating
tool
in trade talks with Xi Jinping.
Some critics of China,
like US Senator Marco Rubio,
don’t think that’s a good idea
because of espionage concerns.
But only time will tell whether it’s the
right move.
Or frankly, whether Trump will actually
do anything to help ZTE at all.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored,
once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Time for another question from a Patreon supporter!
Jake B asks:
“Have you guys ever received a physical
or financial threat
over a specific video or the channel directly?”
We’ve had two minor death threats.
That Matt only told me about much, much later.
But the main threat to China Uncensored is
financial.
It’s hard to find advertisers,
because they’re afraid of the Communist
Party retaliating.
We’re still working on it, but it’s really
hard.
And that’s why we rely mainly on support
from viewers like you, Jake!
And to all our viewers who support us on Patreon,
remember to leave your comments below this
video
on our Patreon website, and I’ll answer
them
at the end of my videos.
And if you’re not a Patreon yet,
click here to support the show you love.