On this episode of China Uncensored,
pollution solutions that will blow your mind,
part 2!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
China has declared war on pollution.
The Chinese regime is pumping $277 billion
dollars
into coming up with solutions for the smog
problem.
Along with, you know,
all the coal they’re pumping into the atmosphere.
And there are some crazy ideas
about how to solve China’s smog problem.
So many that I had to make a second list.
So if banning barbecues a
nd attaching sprinklers to the tops of skyscrapers
seemed like insane solutions,
wait till you see these next 10.
Number 10
Canned Air
Sometimes, life imitates art.
Spaceballs is art, right?
Well, as far out as that sounds,
one crazy Chinese millionaire actually did
it.
The same guy who tried to buy the New York
Times.
And lied to a room full of homeless people.
And sang karaoke to a room of journalists.
Ugh, who’s going to solve that noise pollution?
Number 9
Ventilation Corridors
Beijing sure has some tall buildings that
can block airflow
and let smog linger.
And so somehow,
in an already-built city,
the Chinese regime plans to create ventilation
corridors
to blow the smog out.
There will be five large corridors,
each over 1600 feet wide.
Wondering how they’re going to do that?
Me too!
Fortunately, they’ve given no time frame
for the project.
I wonder how the smog and hot air will mix?
Number 8
Blame green technology
How dare you,
a foreigner,
criticize China for its pollution.
Because as the director of the
Anhui Provincial Environmental Protection
Authority, said
“China is a big exporter
and many foreigners have been benefiting
from China’s green products.
However, the pollution incurred during the
production process
are left in China.”
If China weren’t making so much green technology,
there would be no pollution!
Other than what comes from burning almost
as much coal
as the rest of the world combined.
Gotta love the ideas Chinese officials come
up with.
Like Party official from Yunnan who suggested
China should punish this insult by foreign
countries
by using “dams to store water so that it
won’t all flow
to other countries and be wasted.”
Number 7
Toss it into your neighbor’s yard
If burning tons of coal in Beijing
is causing all this smog,
the solution is simple—burn less coal...
in Beijing.
That’s where coal by wire comes in.
It means “turning coal into electricity
and transmitting it directly from the mine
where it is produced,
instead of transporting it to power stations
and then to consumption centers.”
In other words,
build your water-guzzling,
disgusting coal plants in faraway places like
Inner Mongolia
and Xinjiang
where people are poor and there’s hardly
any water.
And then send the energy over thousands of
miles to the major cities.
It’s worked so well, that
“there has been a 23 per cent improvement
in the Beijing-Tianjin-Hebei area.”
And Xinjiang,
where the Uighur minorities live,
is now home to “six of the ten most polluted
cities in China.”
Number 6
Cloud Seeding
Simply wash away your pollution.
“It has become a tradition in Beijing
to seed the clouds before public holidays...
to make rain,
disperse pollution and ensure clear skies
on the day.”
It’s one of the tricks they used for the
Olympics!
Silver Iodide is shot into the sky,
and it helps creates ice crystals.
Those melt and the pollution comes down with
the rain.
Worried what liquified pollution might do
to you?
I’d worry more about the silver iodide.
It’s toxic.
Number 5
Give up
That’s right, give up.
The pollution is here to stay.
But, when trouble comes along,
why not take a cue from the wily ostrich.
Only instead of burying your head in the sand,
wrap it in a bubble!
Then the pollution can’t get to you.
China is considering biodomes.
What I like best about this idea
is it will be absurdly expensive.
So the rich will get to breath clean biodome
air,
while the rest of us can enjoy being out in
the pollution.
And yes,
this is how bad China’s pollution has gotten.
China’s elite are seriously considering
living in bubbles,
even at the risk of living out that terrible
Pauly Shore movie.
Number 4
Allow me to break the ice
What if you could treat pollution particles
like this?
Simply fill the skies with liquid nitrogen,
freeze the pollution,
and let gravity do the rest.
Because what could go wrong
with spraying industrial coolants into the
air?
And don’t worry,
creating a rain of pollutants is perfectly
safe.
Probably.
Maybe.
Ok, there’s nothing to back that up.
Number 3
Red Alert
When China issued two pollution red alerts
just a week apart
they knew something had to be done.
So they raised the threshold for red alerts.
And there hasn’t been one since.
Number 2
Floating Jellyfish
Check out this idea.
Oh, sorry, that’s the Matrix.
I should have known.
This is the idea
Giant, hydrogen filled jellyfish floating
in the skies.
Because floating sacs of hydrogen always work
so well.
In this actual plan submitted
as part of a competition,
pollution would be absorbed through the
head of the jellyfish,
sent down to the plant tubes,
and turned into drinkable water.
Huh,
I wonder if they ever thought of maybe...
not burning so much coal as a solution.
I’m just throwing that out there.
I’m no scientist.
But maybe that would make more sense
than giant floating jellyfish!
Maybe that’s number 1?
Number 1
Change the face of the planet
Oh are you serious?!
I kid you not,
they have tried leveling mountains to clear
out pollution.
They got about halfway before they gave up.
And it made no difference in air quality.
That was in 1997.
And they’re still trying it.
But have they done anything to actually cut
back on coal?
Well...
they released statistics that show coal consumption
is dropping.
But can we trust that?
Well, last year, it was discovered that China
had been
“under-reporting its consumption for years,
after a different set of statistics were revised,
with the figure for 2012 alone going up 17%.”
Statistics with Chinese characteristics.
And according to the World Resources Institute,
in 2012,
the Chinese regime planned to make 363 new
coal fired plants,
which “amounts to an almost 75 percent increase
in coal-fired generating capacity.”
Yes,
the Chinese Communist party would rather level
mountains,
or fill the skies with toxic chemicals
or giant floating jellyfish
than cut back on coal power.
What do you think about that?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.