Millions of Uyghur Muslims in Xinjiang
have been put in Chinese Concentration Camps
While the international community debates
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
Is what the Chinese Communist Party\h
doing to the Uyghurs genocide?
Sure, they’re being put in\h
massive concentration camps.
And chained, shaved Uyghurs being\h
rounded up onto trains sure looks bad.
And of course independent\h
reports confirm it’s genocide.
The problem is, there’s a lot of money to be\h
made in China! Just look at its bond market!
This is why you get companies like Apple and Nike\h
lobbying against the Uyghur Forced Labor Act.
It’s hard to carry on normal relations\h
with a country committing genocide.\h\h
And so many Western democracies that say they\h
stand for human rights, are waffling about\h\h
whether to label what the Chinese Communist\h
Party is doing to Uyghurs as genocide.\h
The Trump Administration labeled it\h
genocide. But now the Biden administration\h\h
is reviewing that decision.
Canada’s parliament also labeled it genocide.
But Canadian Prime Minister Justin\h
Trudeau and his cabinet didn’t want to.
Australia and Turkey have\h
rejected the genocide label.
I mean, just because what the Chinese\h
Communist Party is doing to the Uyghurs\h\h
is evil, doesn’t mean it’s that bad,\h
right? We can still do business with them.
Which is why today I’m having on Uyghur\h
writer, linguist and activist Abduweli\h\h
Ayup to talk about what it was like for him\h
inside one of these Chinese concentration camps.
Thanks for joining me today.
Thank you for having me.
So, for some reason, there's an international\h
debate going on about whether what the Chinese\h\h
Communist Party is doing to the Uyghurs\h
genocide. Now, you have firsthand experience\h\h
with what is happening to the Uyghurs. How\h
did you end up in a concentration camp?
It is because of I had the Uyghur\h
mother language kindergarten,\h\h
and the because of this,\h
China put me in the prison.
You are, so you were put in a concentration\h
camp because you tried to start a kindergarten.
Yes, it's because of we are\h
Uyghur, and I'm willing to have\h\h
my Uyghur kindergarten for Uyghur kids.
To save your language.
To save, to preserve their language.
So, what happened to you once you\h
were inside the concentration camp?
When I was inside the concentration\h
camp, first of all (silence)\h\h
rape, it happened, and then\h\h
torture: electric, electricize, electric with the\h
electric stick, electricize it and indoctrination\h\h
with propaganda against Uyghur culture, and\h
against Uyghur identity and against human dignity.
And this, this is basically how all\h
the Uyghurs are treated in these camps.\h\h
It doesn't matter if they try to cooperate or not.
It's all Uyghurs are experiencing\h
like this in the concentration camp.\h\h
It doesn't matter, you are cooperating or not.\h
There is less or more, heavier or lighter,\h\h
but it's happening through every Uyghur\h
who are in concentration camp right now.
How do you have heavier or lighter rape?
Lighter is the ones happened only once, like me.\h
And heavier is the one who happened repeatedly.\h\h
And lighter is the one happened only once\h
or twice. But the heavier one is for a long\h\h
time with different position. And mainly aim is\h
just ruin your dignity. Just ask others that,\h\h
just ask other prisoners, other camps detainees\h
that. Yes, this is the step you're willing to\h\h
have if you are not cooperate with us. If you\h
are not lose your dignity, lose your identity,\h\h
lose your culture. This is the ending;\h
this is the like challenge you will have.
Oh, God. So what happens to the\h
family members outside the camps?
The main problem is for them because they don't\h
know what happened to them. The like I stayed\h\h
there in 15 months, and my family members that\h
don't know they are a mind and what am I doing?\h\h
Am I alive or not? This kind of like it is very\h
hard when you think that like at the time I asked\h\h
the interrogator that yes, sentence me 10 years,\h
15 years it's okay. But tell me when then I will,\h\h
I will see my parents. When I will see my family\h
members. When I will see my daughter and my wife.\h\h
Like there's no this kind of exact date. There is\h
no like exact, exact like saying that, yes, you\h\h
are this. And you will have this in this amount\h
of time. There's no this kind of like, like.
There's no rule of law.\h
There, there's like a main\h
thing is there is no logic.\h\h
There is no specific rule you need to follow.
And again, this happened to you because you\h
tried to start a Uyghur language kindergarten.
Yes, it's because of I'm going\h
to have a kindergarten in Ürümqi.\h\h
I had my kindergarten in Kashgar.
Did they, did they charge you with anything?\h\h
I can't imagine them charging you\h
with trying to run a kindergarten.
First of all, they charged me as a separate\h
test and then charge me as a, like a\h\h
CIA agent and then. Oh yeah, I forgot\h
that, and then the religious extremist,\h\h
because of I asked the food, it is halal or not,\h
just 1 question. It's not it's halal or not.\h\h
And then like charge me as a extremist, but\h
that then. I haven't accepted any accusation,\h\h
and at the end, they charged me economic crime. It\h
means that illegal fundraising for kindergarten.
How did you get through it?
Oh, because of my (silence) my strongness,\h
I will not admit anything. I wouldn't admit\h\h
anything. I wouldn't admit any crime. I wouldn't\h
accept any accusation. I said I'm innocent.\h\h
Actually, I'm innocent, and like they\h
interrogated me 6 months and torture me 6 months.\h\h
And as I told you, first 3 months, it's\h
horrible. It's really bad. But after 3 months,\h\h
I get your strick that electric and electricizing\h
or like torching or hanging me up or beating and\h\h
like get your strick. And I try to keep my stance.\h
I keep my, I try to keep my dignity, and it works\h\h
at the end. Like yes, I'm the one I will never\h
obey. I will never say yes, I will never admit.
How do you get used to something like that?
You have to because, in that circumstances,\h
there's 2 ways. One, keep your dignity and keep\h\h
your stance; another is follow the instruction.\h
If I follow the instruction, I know what will\h\h
happen. It's life in prison. And it's like\h
a terrorism or extremism or separatism. Man,\h\h
because of I admitted that because of I supported\h
by a 4th Foundation, Chinese Government accused\h\h
me as a, like a CIA agent. If I accept that,\h
yes, I have done this, and I need to say more,\h\h
and I need to create something. I need to\h
make up something, what they have done.\h\h
And if I say yes to a accusation of\h
separatism, I will say something more.\h\h
And if I say like, say yes for a religious\h
extremism, I will say that I will say,\h\h
do something more. I just, during the\h
interrogation, I said that I gave lecture\h\h
more than 2000 students and they will upset\h
and they will not happy for this interrogation.
If they know this, I'm think\h
write it down that (silence)\h\h
optimally created, train it 2000 terrorist, and\h
then the next day it came to me that you said you\h\h
trained the 2000 terrorists? No, I never said\h
that. I said I gave lecture to 2000 students.\h\h
What you said that? No. I haven't\h
let me to sign under the, under the,\h\h
under the paper. I said no, because I said\h
students, not terrorist. I haven't trained\h\h
anything, anyone to do something. I just gave a\h
lecture. I just gave a lecture to them. Look, if\h\h
I signed, but at the bottom, that yes. Yeah, that\h
will be ending. And then I will be the terrorist.
Yeah. It just, it, to me, it sums up the\h
communist party perfectly. They, they\h\h
try to start a kindergarten. They put you in\h
a concentration camp. So you've been trying to\h\h
raise awareness about the genocide of Uyghur's.\h
What do you think of the international response?
I think that first of all, we have\h
this recognition from US Government,\h\h
and the Canadian Parliament, and the Netherlands\h
Parliament. It's good. First of all, the,\h\h
the recognition is very important, and\h
second, we need international action,\h\h
and we need international support. I hope we\h
will have in the future, and the first of all,\h\h
this recognition, this genocide, this\h
recognition is important. And second, and if it\h\h
work, if it works, if it will like effect, it\h
depends on how are we honest and how are we\h\h
integrate and how are we take the real\h
action? It's that step I'm waiting for.
Why do you think some people, some Governments\h
are resistant to calling it a genocide?
I think it's mainly because of a\h
money issue. It's a trade deal,\h\h
and China is the second largest economy in\h
the world, and the international supply chain\h\h
are working right now. And the China played an\h
important role in this international supply chain.\h\h
And the international businessmen door is national\h
company like Apple, like Nike. They don't want to\h\h
cut this international split\h
supply chain. But we cannot\h\h
ignore and the weak, like a for\h
example, that it's okay to their\h\h
shoes from some companies, and it's okay to\h
not to wear Nike shoes. But it's not okay to\h\h
ignore humanitarian tragedy happening\h
there; ignore genocide is commenting there.
Yeah. I think the issue is if you call, once\h
you say China is a country committing genocide,\h\h
you can't have international businesses doing\h
business with China. You can have the president\h\h
of the United States shaking hands with the\h
leader of a country committing genocide.
Yes, of course. Like if we, for example, that\h
the US Government recognize Chinese Government,\h\h
they commit, committing genocide. And at the\h
end, shake hand with the like criminals it means\h\h
that it is a genocide. The Chinese Government is\h
committing the genocide. It means that they are\h\h
not the normal state and not the normal party.\h
They are group of criminals, and how do you shake\h\h
hand with the criminals and how do, how do you do\h
business with the criminals and how do you have a\h\h
normal diplomacy with the, with the criminals?\h
And we have like, criminal should be in prison,\h\h
should be in the court. Not, not should be in the\h
court, not be in the prison right now because it\h\h
has all of the criminal like genocide. If\h
you are discussing with the genocide. Yes,\h\h
it's okay with the debate, and the way the like\h
talk and with the, it's okay, but all that the\h\h
claim that this is a genocide and then talk about\h
business and something else. It's not honest.
Yeah.
It's not integrity.
Yeah. Maybe Disney couldn't\h
film Mulan and Xinjiang,\h\h
and thank the Public security bureau there.\h
That's involved in the genocide of your people.
Yes, of course; first of all, Disney\h
shouldn't feel very close. Shouldn't feel\h\h
the place very close to concentration camp, a few\h
kilometers away. The second, they shouldn't thank\h\h
the, the Public security who are implementing\h
this genocide right now. And the third,\h\h
they should know what they are doing. They claim\h
openly that like thank Public security bureau or\h\h
something like that. It, it means that some\h
international company, they don't care. They\h\h
don't care our audience. They don't care their\h
customers. They don't respect their customers.
Yeah, and I can definitely say this episode\h
is non-sponsored by Disney+ or Nike.
Yeah.
And for anyone watching, who\h\h
wants to do something about this evil that's being\h
committed, what do you have a message for them?
We should know what we are eating. Is\h
it related to Chinese Forced Labor? We\h\h
should know what we are wearing. Is it related to\h
China Forced Labor? And then we spent our money.\h\h
Is it related to supply chain connected to\h
Chinese Forced Labor? Now, I can say that\h\h
it is a big economy and the Uyghur Forced Labor\h
is everywhere; not only in our hometown and every\h\h
Chinese provinces, we have Uyghur Forced Labor.\h
So, it's impossible to say that this, this product\h\h
related to forced labor; this product is not\h
actually all related together; they are connected.\h\h
So, we should think that what we are buying.\h
It means that we are feeding the Chinese\h\h
atrocity and we are supporting Chinese Government\h
committing suicide. So, we need to be aware of it.
A 100% agree. Thanks for joining us, and\h
thank you for keeping up this good fight.
Thank you for having me, and thank\h
you for make Uyghur arranges.
And if you’d like to hear more from\h
Abduweli Ayup, check out the interview\h\h
we did with him on the China Unscripted\h
Podcast. I’ll put a link to that below.
Thanks for watching. It’s important people\h
learn about what’s happening inside China.\h\h
So be sure to tell your friends and family. Once\h
again I’m Chris Chappell. See you next time.