On this episode of China Uncensored,
a beauty queen gets the axe.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
You know,
it sure seems like the Chinese Communist Party
is trying to get down, with the land down
under—
Australia.
In fact, I was there a couple months ago
specifically to uncover how the Party
is attempting to infiltrate Australia—
through politics, business, and even community
groups.
Which is why I really admire
shows like the ABC’s The World.
Even though the ABC,
the Australian Broadcasting Corporation,
is a huge mega company that has some
pretty significant deals with the Chinese
Communist Party...
The World invited yours truly to go on air
this past March,
and talk about some of the things the Chinese
regime
wants to keep censored.
So I was very sad to hear that at the last
minute,
The World decided to cancel a live interview
they’d scheduled with Chinese rights activist,
former Miss World Canada,
and friend of the show Anastasia Lin.
Anastasia is in Australia promoting
two of her new movies, Reunion,
which deals with forced organ harvesting
of political prisoners in China,
and In the Name of Confucius,
a documentary about how China’s
state-backed Confucius Institute
is undermining democracy in countries like...
Australia.
And China Uncensored is sponsoring one of
her events.
So why did The World cancel the interview
with Anastasia,
after working on it for a week?
Apparently, a producer there
told Anastasia’s representative over the
phone
that she was being cut because higher ups
in the ABC
were concerned about Anastasia’s quote “affiliations.”
Whoa.
Pretty surprising,
since ABC has done more than most big media
companies
when it comes to covering the Chinese Communist
Party’s
infiltration into Australia.
But...maybe there’s a bit more infiltration
that needs to be exposed.
Now in response,
the ABC released this statement saying the
story,
“has no basis in fact,”
and “the producer...
does not recall ever using the word ‘affiliations.’”
In other words,
Anastasia is a lying liar and no one should
believe her.
Wow, funny, that’s what the Chinese Communist
Party
always says about her.
Go figure.
One little problem.
That phone conversation was recorded.
The Australian, another media company,
“can reveal that the conversation between
the producer
and Ms Lin’s representative was recorded
to protect her legal interests,
in case her version of events was disputed.”
Uh oh.
Now according to Australian law,
that recording can’t be released to the
public
unless the ABC gives permission.
And guess what?
They haven’t given permission.
Now for legal reasons,
I’m not supposed to say
whether I’ve personally listened to or not
listened to
any specific audio recording.
But I can say that a very credible source
has confirmed
that an ABC producer did indeed
tell Anastasia’s representative
that it was “a decision from….
higher-ups…
about some of Anastasia’s affiliations.”
Now the ABC didn’t clarify what “affiliations”
meant,
because this conversation—
which was recorded—
never happened.
But “affiliations” might refer to how
Anastasia Lin
practices Falun Gong—
a meditation practice persecuted in China.
She had won Miss World Canada in 2015,
but then was banned from competing
in the finals inside China.
Not to worry.
The ABC has a section on their website
for lodging a complaint.
I’ve provided the link below in case you
have any.
And I’d just like to point out,
I don’t necessarily blame the show The World,
or its producers,
or its host for this.
We don’t know who those higher ups are,
if they’re higher ups in The World or the
ABC itself.
But after it came out that there was a recording,
ABC suddenly decided to release this article
about Anastasia’s work on organ harvesting.
What great timing!
Which just goes to show you:
It’s either totally a coincidence,
or all that international pressure
really does have an impact.
So what do you think about the ABC cutting
Anastasia
for her so-called affiliations?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored,
once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Thanks for watching.
It’s hard for a controversial show
like China Uncensored to get advertisers,
and a lot of our YouTube videos get demonetized.
And that’s why we rely mainly on your support.
So click this orange button to visit our Patreon
website,
and help us make China Uncensored even better.