Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
This June 4 is 29 years since the Tiananmen
Square Massacre.
Or as they call it in China…
But while the Communist Party encourages collective
amnesia,
one tiananmen survivor has dedicated his life
to making sure people remember.
I sat down with Fang Zheng
during the Oslo Freedom Forum in Norway.
Thank you for joining me Fang Zheng.
Hello.
So why did you join the student protests in
1989?
It was very natural.
I was a senior in college at the time.
And like all of the young people at the time--
we were full of hope for our country.
We loved our country.
We wanted to express our wishes so that the
country
could be even better.
So in 1989,
during the student protests,
We brought up issues,
such as eliminating government corruption
and profiteering,
and wanting greater freedoms.
These appeals were our aspirations,
so of course I joined the protests.
So you say you were there because you loved
your country.
But it became clear that maybe the Communist
Party
didn't feel the same way about the students.
Yes, this was a huge tragedy.
The Communist Party cared more about its power.
They separated the interests of the Communist
Party
from the interests of the people.
Even though the Party said that
they represent the people's interests,
at that time we truly experienced
how the Party put its own interests
above the people's interests.
When faced with the will of the people,
they chose to use military repression and
bloodshed.
It was a real tragedy.
I think that in a lot of people's minds,
the image that comes to mind
when they think of the Tiananmen Square Massacre
is Tank Man—
one man stopping a row of tanks.
I think what a lot of people in the West
don't know is that most of the tanks did not
stop.
Actually, these are two different scenes.
Yes, many people think of the Tank Man photo.
But that happened on June 5.
On June 5,
there was this courageous young man
who walked into Chang'an Avenue
and stopped a row of tanks.
The tanks did stop and that became a famous
photograph,
a symbol.
But many people don't know that
the Chinese Communist Party's massacre
really started before that, on the night of
June 3 to June 4.
My own misfortune is that on June 4 around
6 am,
I was also on Chang'an Avenue,
but this time when faced with a crowd of people,
the Chinese government's tanks did not stop.
They charged us directly from behind
and killed many people on Chang'an Avenue,
creating a huge tragedy.
I was crushed by a tank and lost both of my
legs.
So I want to let everyone know
that during the Tiananmen Square Massacre,
in terms of the relationship between tanks
and people,
Tank Man represents one part.
But the tanks also really attacked and crushed
many people,
and I hope everyone can remember this.
You were there with students from your university.
What happened when you got word that the tanks
were coming?
At that time we were already retreating from
Tiananmen Square,
retreating back to our universities.
We had reached Chang'an Avenue (liu bu kou).
We didn't think that the tanks would rush
us from behind.
At that point, the tanks had already taken
over Tiananmen Square.
We were withdrawing from the square,
so we never thought that the tanks would attack
us from behind.
The tanks also threw smoke bombs,
which were exploding around us, causing chaos.
We couldn't see clearly.
To tell the truth,
we couldn't see the tanks until they were
quite close to us.
We didn't see the tanks coming and charging
towards us.
Because they came from behind, we didn't know.
What happened when the tanks caught up to
you?
It was very chaotic in that section of the
road.
At that point,
I was walking with a young woman from my university
and she fainted from the smoke.
I was trying to help her so I picked her up
and turned around.
Very quickly, just as I turned around, the
tanks drove up to us.
I didn't have any time to run or hide.
I could only push the young woman to a safe
spot,
but I myself was crushed by a tank.
Of the other people who were in that same
part of the road
at the same time,
we know that at least 11 people were crushed
to death,
and many others were injured like me.
What was going through your head when you
got hit by the tank?
You can't say you were thinking about anything,
because you can't really think.
It was only three to five seconds
from when I first saw the tank to when I felt
it crushing me
and lost consciousness.
I wasn't thinking about much.
I felt a few things,
I felt the tank starting to roll over me,
it felt like I was being squeezed.
I also felt, right before losing consciousness,
I had some awareness,
the last thing I remember is seeing the white
of my bone
sticking out of my leg.
That was the last image before I lost consciousness.
It happened very quickly.
So, you were a prominent student athlete at
the time.
What did the Communist Party say happened
to you?
Of course, after the June 4th Tiananmen Square
Massacre,
the entire country was in a state of
total censorship and total control.
The political atmosphere was totally different.
For the students like me who had been injured,
they first thing they wanted was for us to
shut up.
They didn't want us to tell other people
the truth of what had happened to us.
They put a lot of pressure on me.
Of course they didn't admit that a tank crushed
me.
They didn't want me to say that fact,
they wanted me to change my story.
They even put a lot of pressure
on the young woman who I rescued,
until she was afraid to see me,
and she denied the fact that we were together
when the tanks came.
The Chinese government has all the power.
If you don't come to terms with them,
they'll stop you from going to college, from
graduating,
you can't get a job, you'll have no income,
or they'll put all sorts of pressure on your
family members.
So a lot of people will choose to lie,
or to comply with what the government wants.
A lot of people did this.
But I'm glad that I did not compromise.
I persisted in telling my real story,
my real experiences, to everyone.
That's why afterwards I suffered
a lot of injustice and persecution.
Not having freedom, being arrested,
having my house searched, not being able to
get a job, etc.
The price of telling the truth in China is
still quite high,
that is the current reality.
Why did you insist on telling the truth?
Because I felt that it was quite simple.
A person should not have to deny
the basic truth of his own experiences.
I think you first of all have to be responsible
to yourself.
I also persisted because the Chinese government
is afraid of us telling the truth
because they know the crimes they committed
on June 4th,
and they are afraid that everyone will know.
So even though it was hard,
I think persevering was worth it.
You must have felt a lot of despair during
all of this.
How did you carry on?
I did feel a lot of despair and regret.
But I was still surrounded by the love and
care
of my family and friends.
There are still many people out there
who care about justice and have a conscience.
The people around me gave me a lot of love
and encouragement.
My family and friends are one of the main
reasons
I could keep this up until today.
So even afterwards, you were a very accomplished
athlete.
But you weren't allowed to participate in
international events.
Why was that?
I think that one of the Chinese government's
biggest worries,
it was afraid that other people would find
out how I was really injured.
A lot of people actually already knew.
But for the Chinese government,
the more they could bury it, the better.
So they took away my right to compete in international
games
and stopped me from having the opportunity
to participate in athletic events for the
disabled.
For all these years, the main reason was to
cover up the truth,
bury the facts.
They don't want people to \hbring up June
4,
they don't want people to know about June
4.
Why is the Communist Party so afraid?
Of course everyone knows that a criminal
is afraid that their crimes will be exposed.
And they know they committed a huge crime.
Criminals don't want people to know about
their crimes back then.
That's quite natural.
In terms of both the international community
and in China,
for the past 29 years,
they have used propaganda and other methods
to cover up the truth,
and they have been successful to a certain
degree.
Many young people barely know anything about
what happened back then.
There's almost no way for them to get this
information.
And through these cover-up methods and propaganda,
the international community also pays
less and less attention to this issue,
so they've been able to get away with their
crimes until today.
So I feel like they've basically succeeded.
If so much of the world is forgetting what
happened,
why do you still speak out about the Tiananmen
Square Massacre?
There are two main reasons.
One is that this is something that happened
to me, personally.
Of course I don't want people to forget something
that I experienced.
But the more important reason is that after
June 4,
the Chinese government still continued its
repression and persecution.
The June 4 incident is not over, it's not
finished.
For examples, the victims of June 4 still
suffer persecution in China.
The Tiananmen mothers, whose children were
killed,
have still not received justice.
The June 4 issue has never been truly resolved.
The truth has not been revealed,
it's not clear to people.
How many people died on June 4?
Who made the decision?
Why did the tanks come after us, to kill us?
All of these things--there is no truth.
Until the truth is uncovered, I must speak
out,
to remind everyone not to forget.
How were you able to leave China?
After 1989, I had no freedom for a long time,
so getting a passport was even more out of
the question.
During the 2008 Beijing Olympics,
I had a chance to get a Chinese passport
as a type of exchange with the government.
In 2008, the international community
had a lot of requirements towards China,
and China had made a lot of promises
to the international community,
like letting in journalists to do interviews.
At that time I had many interactions with
foreign journalists
who came to my hometown to interview me.
At that time,
Chinese government was most worried about
keeping me in my hometown.
As long as I didn't go to Beijing,
it was ok.
Before this,
I had applied for a passport many times,
because I felt this was part of the normal
rights of a citizen,
but they refused me each time.
The Domestic Security Bureau told me they
couldn't give me a passport.
One day between the Olympics and the Paralympics,
a German reporter called me and wanted to
come interview me.
I knew him and so I said yes.
We arranged a time to meet.
He also wanted me to take him to interview
another disabled person.
But two hours before we were going to meet,
the police found out about it.
They were either tapping my phone or the reporter's
phone.
They came to my house and took me away for
a chat.
They told me that they knew a reporter was
coming to interview me.
They told me, we can let you speak to him,
but we can't let you take him to interview
other people.
We can give you two choices:
if you cooperate with us,
we can consider giving you a passport,
but if you want to go with him and take him
to interview others,
we can't give you a passport.
So I met with the reporter and told him the
police knew he was here.
That they had already visited me
and they knew what we were going to do.
He was very nervous about how the police managed
to find him.
We were meeting in a hotel,
and there were many people who looked like
plainclothes police.
I told him the whole situation,
about how the police wouldn't let me go with
him
to interview another disabled person,
and if I went there would be consequences
for everyone,
but if I didn't go, they would give me a passport.
The reporter decided to give up on the other
interview.
He said, even if I just report the story of
what happened with you and the police,
that's still a pretty significant story.
So we didn't end up working together
and going to interview other people,
and he left to go to Sichuan to interview
others.
He then published the story of my encounter
with the police
when he returned to Germany.
The Public Security Bureau felt that I had
cooperated
with their request and didn't cause them more
trouble,
so they gave me a passport on August 28, 2008.
In 2009, with the help of the US government,
my family and I were able to come to America.
You've said that the most effective weapon
against the Chinese Communist Party
is not to forget what they want you to forget.
Why is that?
This has been one of the most difficult problems
in China,
under the Chinese Communist Party's rule,
this type of memory war.
The Chinese Communist Party has continuously
committed crimes
against the Chinese people during different
periods of history,
over and over again,
from when it first started to rule to the
present day,
almost 70 years now.
But why is it still successful?
The biggest reason is that through propaganda,
brainwashing, and thought control,
they've made people unaware of what happened
in the past.
They've separated each part of the past,
over and over again.
So young people will have no idea about the
crimes
the Party has committed in the past,
so they will still believe and have illusions
about the Party.
In this way,
the Party will be able to continue their rule
and their methods are working.
But if we expose their errors and their crimes
and let people know about the past continuously,
so that the memory is not broken off,
it will be harder for them to rule,
harder for them to continue their crimes.
It's a similar principle to how after World
War II,
the Nazis couldn't continue, they were destroyed,
because of how the Europeans and the Jewish
people
exposed the Nazis' crimes, publicized them,
and kept the memory alive so that people
could fully understand their crimes
and they could not continue.
But in China,
we haven't done this with the Chinese Communist
Party's crimes,
so they have been able to continue.
This is one way we can oppose them.
This is the resistance of memory.
When we were young,
because of our brainwashed education,
we did not know many of the things the Communist
Party
had done in China's past.
Today, many young people growing up in China
with information control and this brainwashed
education
also don't know what happened on June 4.
Each generation is separated.
History is isolated.
The truth is severed.
That means we haven't done enough.
So one of my biggest responsibilities now
is to tell more people about this so they
will know,
I especially hope that young people in China
will know about this.
You used to be a Communist Party member.
I'm wondering if you officially quit?
When I was in college,
I joined the Communist Party, in 1987.
At that time we had a certain amount of faith
in the Party.
Although we had just come out of,
and we were against the personality cult of
Mao Zedong,
we still had faith in the Communist Party.
Afterwards, we found out that
just opposing personality cults wasn't enough--
there was something fundamentally wrong with
the Communist Party as an organization.
We need to have a good system,
relying on a ruling party doesn't work.
But at the time we didn't realize this.
Now we've slowly realized that China
can't just depend on a ruling party,
we need a good system,
only then can we have a normal country and
avoid tragedies
like the June 4th incident.
After June 4,
the Communist Party wanted me to lie,
they wanted to me to use my Party spirit to
cover up the truth,
they said it was in the Party's interests.
I couldn't accept this because I felt the
Party's interests
were in conflict with the people's interests,
that the Party spirit was against the human
spirit.
I couldn't accept this,
so I naturally left this organization.
I know you don't have any hope for the Chinese
Communist Party,
but do you have hope for the future of China?
One must have hope.
I do have hope for the future of China.
But right now,
I don't have much confidence, to be honest.
There are many difficulties.
In the short term,
I can't see any definite reasons for hope,
but we must still keep going with a hopeful
attitude.
Because ultimately China will become a normal
country,
it will become like other countries,
there's no doubt about that.
It's just a matter of how long it will take.
Thank you so much for sharing your story with
us.
I can assure you that on China Uncensored,
we will never forget the Tiananmen Square
Massacre.
Thank you.