On this episode of China Uncensored,
Leaders of the 20 biggest economies
meet at the world’s most awkward lunch table.
Got a pirate problem?
Try putting Chinese troops in Djibouti.
And Chinese human rights lawyer
Liu Xiaobo just passed away.
We, will not be making jokes about that...
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Chinese dissident and Nobel Peace Prize laureate
Liu Xiaobo passed away on Thursday.
The cause of death was subversive thoughts—
which then led to terminal liver cancer.
At least that’s what the Communist Party
would like you to think.
Actually,
he was serving an 11-year prison sentence,
where years of mistreatment
didn’t exactly do wonders for his health.
But rather than “Chinese Dissident Liu Xiaobo
Dies in Prison,”
the Chinese regime felt that
“Chinese Dissident Liu Xiaobo Dies in Hospital
Care
Granted by the Benevolent Party”
sounded like a better headline.
So when his health got so bad
it was clear he was going to die,
they released him on medical parole
to a hospital, where he got the best care,
while still guarded 24/7.
They even allowed foreign doctors to look
at him.
So I mean, no one’s going to blame
the Chinese Communist Party, right?
Look, state-run Global Times
lays it out so clearly,
“It’s Liu’s personal misfortune
to have been diagnosed with cancer,
but this has nothing to do
with his imprisonment.”
Riiight.
Just like it was also Liu’s personal misfortune
to have all those subversive thoughts
in the first place.
It’s a tragic situation all around,
but on the bright side,
at least Norway can sell salmon to China again.
That’s right,
after Liu got the Nobel,
the Chinese regime punished Norway
by no longer buying their salmon.
Even though Norway doesn’t decide
who gets Nobel Prizes.
You can’t make this stuff up.
Speaking of awkward international relations
with China...
maybe you can relate to this.
You’re in an intimate moment
with someone you care about,
and you...accidentally call them
by the wrong name.
Well, that’s what happened to the US
and China earlier this week.
Last weekend was the G20 Summit,
an annual meeting of the leaders
of the world’s 20 largest economies.
And while President Trump and Chinese leader
Xi Jinping
both happened to be there anyway,
why not hold bilateral US-China talks
on the side?
What could go wrong?
Apparently this: an official White House statement
released ahead of the meeting
accidentally called China
the “Republic of China”—
and not, as it should have been,
the “People’s Republic of China.”
Because “Republic of China”
actually means Taiwan.
You have to add “people’s”
to make it communist.
Awkward!
It’s ok though.
An apology was made,
and accepted.
I think these two will be just fine.
Wait a minute,
what’s that Xi is putting on Trump’s back?
Speaking of being friendly with world leaders,
Russian President Vladimir Putin has become
the first non-Chinese leader
Chinese people weren’t allowed to criticize.
It couldn’t have happened to a nicer guy!
During the G20,
netizens in China discovered
they couldn’t even mention Putin’s name
without their posts being blocked.
Now, Putin and Björk have something in common:
They’re both blocked on Weibo,
China’s version of Twitter.
Also, they both appreciate
the grace and beauty of long-necked birds.
But you might think,
hey, censorship doesn’t affect China’s
savviest Internet users;
a lot of them just use VPN software
to jump over the firewall—
presumably to access the banned Icelandic
experimental electro-pop music
they’ve all been craving.
Well, that’s about to change.
The Chinese regime wants to stop people
from using VPNs.
Unless they’re government-approved VPNs.
Which kind of defeats the purpose.
Which would once and for all
make the Chinese Internet, really an Intranet.
The Chinese Internet blocks foreign social media
like Facebook, Twitter, and YouTube,
as well as what the outside world calls
“facts.”
But people still get access using VPNs—
at least for now.
But don’t worry,
I have a feeling people will still be able
to fully enjoy their daily visits
to the English language Twitter account
of state-run People’s Daily.
A panda live stream!
Wow.
Give me more.
But if China doesn’t have your heart,
at least it has Djibouti.
China has just sent troops
to its first overseas military base.
It’s in Djibouti.
Don’t worry,
it’s for “anti-piracy” efforts.
Not this kind of piracy;
China doesn’t care about that.
They want to stop this kind of piracy.
This is absolutely not
a sinister communist plot
to invade Djibouti.
And those troops are lucky to be in Djibouti.
Because the Chinese Communist Party
is downsizing its People’s Liberation Army
to under a million troops.
Before the first round of layoffs
hit in 2015,
there were 2.3 million soldiers
in the People’s Liberation Army.
But I guess with even under a million,
there’s still enough troops to put in Djibouti.
I know, this video was fantastic.
You're welcome.
But it doesn't stop here.
You can watch this and two more segments on ChinaUncensored.tv
right now.
Yes, we're posting entire half-hour episodes to our website
with segments that aren't on YouTube yet. So click here and check it out!