Welcome to tonight's
event, a panel discussion
on the hidden agenda of
China's silent invasion.
Speaking of silent, please take a moment
to silence your phones.
Tonight, we'll be talking
about the Chinese
Communist Party's efforts
to influence Australia
though political donations,
clandestine operations and intimidation,
and the growing awareness of these issues.
Here tonight to discuss these topics
and how they are affecting Australia,
I'm joined by three panelists.
Dr. Feng Chongyi, Associate
Professor in China Studies
at the University of Technology Sydney,
and an adjunct professor of History
at Nankai University, Tianjin.
Dr. Feng's current research,
yes, round of applause.
(audience clapping)
Dr. Feng's current research focuses on
intellectual and political development
in modern and contemporary China.
Then, we have Dr. Kevin Carrico.
He teaches contemporary Chinese society
and modern Chinese history in the
Department of International
Studies, Languages and Culture
at Macquarie University.
Round of applause, please.
(audience clapping)
His research examines
nationalism and ethnicity
in China, Tibet, and Hong Kong.
He's also the author of The Great Han -
Race, Nationalism, and
Tradition in China Today.
And, finally, there are the end,
we're joined by Chen Yonglin.
Please, round of applause.
(audience clapping)
He is a former Chinese diplomat
in the Sydney Chinese Consulate
who defected in 2005.
Mr. Chen became the first
whistleblower to reveal
that a network of Chinese
spies exists in Australia.
He's also a member of the
Australia Values Alliance
which opposes the influence
of Beijing in Australia.
And I'm Chris Chappell,
host of China Uncensored
a New York based, English
language satirical news show.
Looks at China and how
it affects the world.
So, let's begin.
(audience clapping)
Thank you.
Turn on the microphones, okay.
First, let's take a look
at the overall picture.
What is the Chinese Communist
Party doing in Australia?
And that's an open question
to whoever likes to take it.
- I think they're, I think that
what the Chinese Communist Party is doing
is denying the full diversity of opinions
that exist within the humanity
that's broadly labeled,
you know, Australians of Chinese heritage,
or Chinese Australians, okay.
And this is an approach, of course,
that is taken within China
through the silencing of
voices that are critical of,
or oppositional to the government,
and of course, the CCP
does that very well,
and it's been doing it for, you know,
nearly 70 years, okay.
Having lived in the US,
and engaged quite a fair bit
with Chinese communities there,
and also having lived in Sydney,
I have found that, in
terms of media options,
in terms of activities,
I do think that there is
considerably more influence
from, sort of, Beijing
backed, State narratives,
in the media and in activities in Sydney,
than we see in most cities
that I've visited in the United States,
and I think that's a problematic situation
that needs to be dealt with more fully
so that the full diversity of viewpoints
within the community can be expressed
and everyone can have an opportunity
to participate in Australia's
democratic system.
- And Dr. Feng, in your own words,
what is the Chinese Communist
Party doing in Australia?
- (laughs)
I think the Chinese Communist Party today
is extremely successful in implementing
this United Front strategy in Australia.
With my little eyes (laughs),
I can see the extensive
network had been establish
in all aspects of our life in Australia.
In business, in government, in media,
in education, anywhere you mention,
you can see the very extensive
network had been created.
- So the next question is why is
the Chinese Communist Party
trying to influence Australia?
- Oh, should I say it?
Thank you, thank you.
Okay, talking about, sorry,
talking about the 2004,
the embassarial conference,
Hu Jintao
especially mentioned the
strategy on Australia.
It's called the peripheral,
it's to see Australia
as a peripheral area,
as neighboring country,
in China it's called
(speaks foreign language).
That's border, Grand Border Strategy.
So, in that time, China
start to see Australia
as a neighboring country,
but traditionally Australia
is pretty far away,
it's, geographically it's far away,
across the South China Sea.
And because, the decision
on this is because
Australia has rich of resources,
energy resources, high
grade mineral resources,
and China can rely on,
China to use Australia resources,
that's one of the main reason.
From that year, China
started FTA negotiation
with Australia,
so after 10 years, until 2015,
FTA agreement was reached.
But of course, China attached
many conditions on that.
The one thing I was to, unfortunately,
I was unable to get a
copy of a coded report
submitted by ambassador
Fu Ying at that time.
He proposed to the central government
that China can sacrifice
a lot on agricultural area
to exchange for Australia
political and strategically
compromise in area like the
ANZAC treaty with the US,
may be compromise if
there's any war happen
in future across the Taiwan strait, yes.
- I would largely agree
with what Yonglin has said
and I'll try to remember to speak up.
The way that I view things is that
I do think there is, sort of, a narrative
within China, pushed
by the official media,
also pushed in popular culture,
that China is, sort of,
reemerging onto its,
you know, proper place in the
global hierarchy of nations.
And I believe, you know, ideally speaking,
that wouldn't be a bad thing,
but the issue that emerges
is that the political system, of course,
in China, poses a number of problems,
and creates
a situation in which
one finds it difficult
to be very enthusiastic
about what is known as, you know,
what is termed as the rise of China.
- And Dr. Feng, your thoughts?
- I think I have a little
different idea on that.
I do not see that, it
as a strength, a strong,
that once extend its influence outside.
I see it as a weakness.
We all know that the diplomacy
is extension of domestic politics.
The Chinese Communist regime back home,
especially after the collapse
of communism in 1989, 1991?
The Chinese Communist
regime had very, very strong
sense of regime insecurity.
So all these activities,
United Front strategy
aim to create favorable
international environment
for the survival of this outdated regime.
We call it post-authoritarian,
now surrounded by democracies
all over the world.
It's extremely
intensive insecurity,
the sense of insecurity
that push them to create this
United Front strategy for survival.
- Kevin, you have some thoughts?
- Oh, yeah, yeah, I would
say that we actually agree
it's just that I think there's
a considerable difference
between, sort of, the
rhetoric and the reality
and I would agree that, while, you know,
official media puts off these
airs of great confidence,
in reality, you know,
we are clearly talking
about a very, very insecure regime,
that spends even more on internal security
than it spends on military.
- Are you saying we can't
trust Chinese state run media?
- (laughs) I think that might
be a fair assessment, yes.
- Alright, well, let's move on
to some recent issues
with Australian politics.
What are some of the specific tactics
the Chinese Communist Party uses
to influence Australian politicians?
Chen, you might, you
used to work for them,
you might have some ideas.
(audience laughs)
- (laughs) Yeah, the
tactics in for Australia
is in China called all around diplomacy
establish relations with, including,
the final stage with Australia is called
strategic partnership,
or something like that
- [Chris] Sounds so friendly.
- Yeah, sounds very friendly.
And the
The work on Australia is in all around,
all these fields, including politically,
building up a personal relationship
with Australian leaders and politicians,
so, you can see in the past 12 years,
there're huge, hundreds
of Chinese leaders,
officials visited Australia,
to establish a relations
with three levels of
Australian government.
And also, China called cultural exchange,
actually we all know that China
has no culture to
exchange after communism.
(audience laughs and claps)
So you can now there's
almost, there's nothing
Australia return visit
or performance in China,
almost, there're only some concert,
a few concert, symphony,
a concert like that, others--
- Chen, I'm curious, when
an Australian politician
is given one of these
all-expenses paid trips to China,
what kind of things do they get to see?
- They will see that Australia
economy all rely on China.
But Australian politician,
they see only the surface,
but actually China rely
on Australia resources.
That's why they work so hard, and,
but it seems Australian politician
easy to be persuaded, lobbied.
- That's a very interesting point,
I've heard a lot, since
I've been in Australia,
about how, even from
Australian politicians,
how reliant Australia is on
China as a trade partner,
but that's very interesting
that you say it's the other way around.
Kevin, I'd like to ask you,
if you could share some
information with us
about one Sam Dastyari.
(audience sniggers)
- Well, yeah, Sam Dastyari, huh,
what can I say about him?
(audience laughs)
Uh, he is, uh
- [Chris] Keep it, you
know, family friendly.
(audience laughs)
- Yeah, you know, yeah.
I mean, you know, as I understand,
these people can be very litigious.
But, perhaps,
- [Chris] That's true.
- Sam Dastyari
made friends with
some people
who appear to have,
perhaps, complicated
relationships with the party,
the United Front Work Department.
What happened, as I think we all know,
is that Dastyari, I think
we've established firmly,
made some very embarrassing statements
about the South China
Sea at a press conference
that, not only went against
his own party's policies,
also went against
Australian national policy,
and also, I think is fair to say,
went completely against all logic
in terms of anybody who's actually
studied the history of
the South China Sea,
and recent developments in it.
- It is kind of concerning to
see that the South China Sea
may be extending all the
way down to Australia.
Dr. Feng, what have you seen
as the Communist Party's
tactics to influence
the politics of Australia.
- You talk about one aspect
of the United Front strategy,
I mean, for Chinese, we all know
that's (speaks foreign language),
that's, a part of (speaks
foreign language),
that's to make friends,
to create connections.
But there's another aspect,
is (speaks foreign language),
to attack, to kill, to destroy.
It actually, not only
to make friends with,
close to China and act on the,
on behalf of the Chinese Communist regime,
but also if you look at
the Chinese community here,
the local politicians, the party,
they have been very
successful to make sure
that any anti-communist candidate
will not get the
nomination, will not.
You mentioned John Hu the other day,
he was a very good example
that if you are not working closely
with the Chinese regime, Communist regime,
you will be sidelined,
may lose your position,
and then you will not get the, so called,
Chinese community support.
A lot of associations have been work
as proxy of the regime out there.
- So this is affecting who
gets elected in Australia.
- Yeah, I agree with Professor Feng
that (speaks foreign language) that means
united and conquered.
The, of course, through
the political donations,
political donations is just
a way of establishing personal relations.
There's always a purpose when someone
tries to give money to you.
And, of course, the Australian party's
habit to receive that,
they needed to fulfill
their promise on the table.
- One thing, I'd like to jump off
of something you said, Dr. Feng.
What happens to Australian
officials or politicians
who criticize the Chinese Communist Party,
or who stand up for groups
the party doesn't like,
like Tibetans, or the
Falun Gong practitioners?
- He's working in the Chinese government,
he know how to deal
with them, huh (laughs)
But as you can see, friends and enemies.
The Chinese Communist
Party, that's ruled in China
almost 70 years now, they
have very strong team
to do very good research on politicians
or any other pro-de-mics.
Who are their enemies,
who are their friends?
If you are labeled, or
identified as enemies
you will not get invitation,
you will not get the service.
You mentioned that donation to parties,
but also very lucrative
work opportunities,
business opportunities have been created
for Chinese friends, like,
Keating, Paul Keating,
like Bob Hawke,
a lot of them have been offered
very good job as advisor,
of consultant on the board,
and actually these retired politicians,
if you look at them,
have become super rich
after their retirement.
If you check their income,
you may find out many of them did that.
But for others, you will not
get that kind of service,
invitation, or, yeah.
- So it can be very profitable
to be in league with the
Chinese Communist Party,
and less so if you're the other direction.
- (laughs) that's right.
- So Chen, actually
your job when you worked
for the Chinese consulate was to monitor,
I believe, it's called
the five poisonous groups?
- Yeah, five groups including
democracy activists,
Falun Gong, Falun Gong was a priority
when I was in the consulate,
but later it goes a little bit down.
Falun Gong, Tibetan group,
Eastern Turkestan,
and also Taiwan, so these
- Very poisonous groups.
- These, all these groups is actually
the enemy of the Chinese regime,
but it's, you can see that
it's domestic politic of China.
These people, but Chinese regime see them
as anti-China forces, like foreign forces,
so they are not foreign,
they are not foreign,
these democracy activists.
So, at that time, I was
also in a, pretty shocked
at my major job was dealing with these,
have different opinions,
and I was very shocked as well.
- Kevin, what are your
thoughts on the issue?
- Well, I think that's
very revealing, sort of,
the labeling of people
with different opinions as
inherently foreign, right?
And that, I think, reveals the, sort of,
homogenizing aims of the party state.
This desire to say, we
all have the same opinion,
we all agree, and everybody
who disagrees is not Chinese,
Is not, you know
- Racist.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And, you know, this goes back
to the friend, enemy distinction, you know
that Professor Feng talked about,
and that, unfortunately, I
think, after all these years,
all these years after the first article
in Mao's collected works,
which raises the question,
who are our enemies,
who are our friends?
This type of thinking, I would say,
unfortunately, still, very much dominates
the party state's approach
to Chinese society
and the outside world more broadly.
- And this touches on something
you were mentioning earlier Dr. Feng,
Chinese leader Xi Jinping has called
the United Front Work Department
the communist party's magic weapon.
So, let's talk about it.
What is the United Front?
- Actually the magic weapon metaphor
was created by Mao in
an article written 1949.
It's three magic weapons.
One is United Front strategy,
the other is arms struggle,
and yet another is the...
(mumbles in foreign language)
party leadership.
That everything should
be under the control
or leadership of the party.
And this United Front,
what I already mentioned
is two part.
Related, two part.
One, is to identify friends,
actually within that period of time
it's actually during the Chinese civil war
between the communist party
and the nationalist government.
They actually create the
so-called second front line.
A lot of friends of dem-ya
and even for government
officials, and the national army,
a lot of rebellion and revolt
within the republican government
to defect into the
communist, very successful.
And that is the, to get the friends,
and then for the other part,
that's to identify the
enemy, to do away with them.
It last for now, it's
seven or eight decades now,
if look at the democracy movement,
leaders since 1989 especially,
they are all marginalized.
Not only in China, but also
in the whole societies,
in Australia, in United States, anywhere
because they are virtually sealed off
from any business opportunities.
It's very unfortunate, if
you look at those leaders.
They are all end up, poverty,
loss of those social connections,
and there's no opportunity
for them to get rich.
The only opportunity can offer to people
is that if you work for the party,
or work with the party.
Otherwise, you will be
isolated, marginalized
or even destroyed.
You know, a lot of people have been jailed
for more than 10 years, five years, yes.
- Dr. Carrico would you like to add
your thoughts about the United Front?
- Well, I think there are people who are
considerably more specialized
in this matter than me, right?
- [Chris] You may pass it
on to Chen if you like.
- But I would say that,
how shall I say it,
there have been a number of individuals
who have been, in recent years,
there have been suggestions that
"Oh, this person could be
involved with United Front work",
and the response has unanimously been
"I'm not involved in United Front work,
"I don't even know what
"the United Front Work
Department is", right?
But to take such claims
seriously, I think,
is to completely misunderstand
the United Front approach,
in so far as nobody says
"Oh hey, by the way, I'm United Front
"and I'm here to share my
thoughts with everyone".
It's not something that's
publicized, I believe,
one could even argue that in some cases,
someone could be engaging
in United Front related work
without, perhaps, even fully being aware,
right, of what they're doing.
So it's a very complex system
that I personally can't
fully wrap my head around,
but I do think it is worthy
of closer discussion and scrutiny.
- Mr. Chen, your thoughts
on the United Front?
- Yeah, United Work Front actually
is based on the Chinese community,
I mean, the overseas influence,
and, of course, will extend
to some old friends of China,
there are many old friends
of China around the world
like Dr. Henry Kissinger, and, like...
I don't have any meaning
of despising these important politicians
and in here, in Australia, Gough Whitlam
was regarded as the
great leader, of course,
I respect him in his, what
he has achieved in history,
including, especially,
relations with China.
And, but unfortunately, you know, the,
some of these old friends
will become a negative
in the current time for the people.
Politicians like...
We will a very, I once, you know,
visited Gough Whitlam's office,
and Gough Whitlam was very proud that,
he told us that he
trained Mark Latham, okay.
And he introduced us
to his then secretary,
Steven Chaytor, and he told us that,
told the consulate general Liao Zihong
and that Steven Chaytor will
be the future labor leader.
And in, of course later, in 2007,
Steven Chaytor was elected
as a New South Wales MP.
And of course, he fade
from his political career
because of some scandal.
And he's obviously, you
know, by making such friends,
China benefited a lot to
get inside information,
and that's just a small case.
I'm not saying that Gough
Whitlam has done anything wrong,
but what China benefit
from such relations.
- Well I think we've really established
how the Chinese Communist
Party is having a big impact
in Australian politics.
Let's move on to Australian universities.
What is the role of the
Chinese Students and Scholars
Association, or CSSA?
How do they influence
Australian universities?
- As a former leader of (laughs)
overseas Chinese students, overseas,
actually I was sent to the UK
for a joint PhD program at the UK.
At that time I was party's, actually,
and by extension, I was appointed as
one of the leaders,
president, vice president,
of the Chinese Students
and Scholars Association.
At that time, actually, we
enjoy a lot of privilege.
The consulate and the
embassy get us a lot of money
to run a house that whoever the leaders
who live in there, you
do not need to pay rent.
Even the electricity, water, everything,
all the bill are the picked up
by the consulate and the embassy.
And we also have so-called
operational budget
that you can travel long,
you can have meeting weekly or monthly,
and then we have the task to report
the political, ideological affairs
of the Chinese students to
the embassy, to the consulate,
and work very closely with them.
There is a regular meeting,
because we were educated
that if you are student leader,
from kindergarten you have
(speaks foreign language),
class monitor and
whatsoever, that's your duty
to serve the party state,
and report the whatever
political activities,
ideological conditions of
your colleagues, students.
That is the basic operation
I experienced as a leader.
- I have a considerable
amount to say about this
but I'll try to keep it short.
I teach contemporary Chinese issues.
I talk about difficult topics
in the classroom,
and over the past, you know,
five years of teaching,
as I've discussed with the media,
I have had students whose
discussions of sensitive topics
have made their way back, via reports,
to their families in China.
And that is a development that
I find very, very disturbing
that something that's
discussed in the classroom
in the United States or in Australia
is transmitted back to China
and used in a threatening way
to talk to people's families.
Now, I spoke to media about
this at various points.
In response, China Daily
published a hit piece against me,
alleging that I had said that
all Chinese students are spies, okay.
I never said that, nobody's
ever said that, okay.
And in discussing with colleagues,
discussing with friends,
people who opposed me
participating in this activity,
people have also told me,
ah, people are saying to me,
"Somebody told me all
Chinese students are spies."
Okay, first of all, I've never met anybody
who said all Chinese students are spies.
Second of all, if somebody
actually does say that,
they're an idiot, okay.
It's not at all true that all
Chinese students are spies.
There is, however, a situation in which,
as a result of monitoring,
whether through CSSAs,
whether through people who
are politically connected,
there are situations in
which Chinese students
in Australia can feel uncomfortable
sharing their viewpoints
if they have a viewpoint that diverges
from the Chinese party state.
So I'm, I wanna point out that
I don't think everybody
involved in CSSAs is a spy.
I do want to say that there are situations
in which CSSAs are used to monitor
and report on other students,
and when that happens,
those instants should be
treated very seriously
and action should be taken.
- Yeah, all the CSSA actually
belongs to the Chinese regime.
At the beginning,
the Chinese,
there's an Office of Education
in the Chinese embassy and the consulate.
Their task, main task, is
to manage these students,
and because, you know, right now,
each year, like 120 Chinese
students study in Australia.
A lot of them may have to return to China.
Of course, there's, a lot will stay,
and there's always a risk for the regime
that if these large number
of students return to China,
bring back the thoughts of human rights,
or democracy, or freedom of speech.
And so, it's a really important job
for the Chinese overseas mission.
And usually, if there's, like
in New England University
in Australia, in the
northwest of New South Wales,
there is no CSSA,
the education council will, at that time,
travel to the New England University,
and, to install one in the university.
So, in each university there is one CSSA.
And then, above that, there
is called a state CSSA.
It's called New South Wales CSSA,
or Victoria CSSA,
or Canberra CSSA.
So, that is convenient to control.
It's like the structure
in the Chinese community.
There's a top one.
That top one is the
Chinese Council for the Promotion
of Peaceful Reunification,
and some others like Chinese,
the organization of the
Chinese Associations,
or FCA, in Victoria,
it's called Federation of
Chinese Associations in Victoria.
That is easy to manage, to control.
They just collect the
heads of these groups
and make instruction,
the instruction will
pass down to individual.
That's the power structure.
- I think it's stunning
the way you've all revealed
how the Chinese Communist
Party is silencing critics
in the Australia government,
and in the Chinese
communities in Australia,
and in universities.
That's actually quite horrifying.
I wanna bounce of
something Dr. Carrico said.
The Chinese Communist
Party often accuses critics
of racism or intolerance
in order to silence them.
Is there a way to bring
up legitimate concerns
about the party's actions
and also not be racist?
- Maybe I'll let them say it first.
(audience laughs)
- [Chris] Why, why do you say that?
- Because he's European
(audience laughs)
appearance, you don't want
to be accused as racist.
(laughs) this is an outrageous
accusation, actually.
We all know, what you define as racism.
Racism is
discrimination or prejudice
based on the collective
identity as race or ethnicity.
When you with criticism against a regime
to protect ordinary Chinese in China,
or the resident of Chinese communities
here in Australia or in United States,
that's nothing to do with racism.
These kind of accusation is based on the
party strategy again
to conflate
the Chinese state government
and the Chinese nation, or Chinese people.
And then whatever you attack,
or you criticize the regime,
they label you as racist
to attack the Chinese.
So this is a very traditional
and sometimes effective trick
to stop those legitimate
discussion or debate
on what should we do about these
what's said, the communist,
some people even don't want
to label it as a dictatorship.
You don't, if you with
criticism, you are racist.
And then, that means,
you should allow them
to do anything against Chinese
people or other people.
Actually those people
who accuse these critics
are sometimes, and not always,
sometimes are actually based on racism.
When they actually argue that
the Chinese are different.
Chinese only deserve dictatorship,
only deserve despotism.
They do not deserve human right.
They are not capable of democracy,
they're lower blood, they need control.
It's extremely racist ideas, actually,
when they put out these propositions.
- I would agree, indeed, that
it is racist,
it is orientalist to assume
that the government that the
Chinese people have today
is the government that they deserve.
In fact, this is a government
that has been forced upon people,
and continues to force itself upon people.
And I think that, as Professor Feng said,
the real racists are the people
who have lower expectations
for the Chinese people,
and want to deny them
their basic human rights.
- Those are very good points,
but have you ever considered
you might be racist against Chinese?
- [Kevin] (laughs)
- So I think now, what's important
is what can all Australians
do about this issue?
- Well--
- I'll choose
alright go ahead.
- Yeah, yeah. I mean, I'll go.
You know, I don't have
any political connections,
there's not really much
that I can do, in reality,
besides write some
articles and do some talks.
But in that sense, that is what
I would encourage people to do,
to really resist, not
only overt censorship,
to resist pressures that come from above,
to resist pressures from the party state,
but also to resist, sort of,
the pressures in your mind.
You know, every time I do a lecture,
and I mention Taiwan, you know, I think,
oh how should I say Taiwan (mumbles)
the Republic of China, Taiwan Province.
You know, at the end of the day,
Taiwan is just Taiwan, you know.
I know that a lecturer was
given a lot of pressure,
got into a lot of trouble
for referring to Taiwan as a country,
but, you know, this is slightly ridiculous
to deny the fact that a place
with its own borders, own
military, own currency,
own economy, own political system,
to pretend that it's not a country.
Many, you know,
governments along the world
sort of play along with this game,
but I think that it's important
for people in civil society,
for people in university positions
to not play along with this game,
and to, you know, perhaps
live and speak in truth
about the realities of China
and Asia as a whole today.
- Dr. Feng, your thoughts?
- Yes, a little, one thing I would expect
from Australian government,
or the public in general,
that is to somehow protect my
compatriot, the Chinese here.
They come all the way,
thousands of miles away,
to this country in order to enjoy
human rights, freedom, democracy.
But unfortunately, the Chinese influence
or interference kept so strong
that they're actually kept
under the shadow of the Chinese,
the extension of Chinese
communist regime there.
When you look at the media,
it's dominantly told the party line,
almost identical with People's Daily,
or the central station
(speaks foreign language)
but in China.
When you look at the Chinese
associations all around,
the overwhelming majority of them
actually have been controlled
by the Chinese party state,
or work for the party state.
And the
the resident of Chinese cal-le-gy here,
they should be able, they
should have been able to,
what we call, integrated into
the normal political life,
to accept new ideas of freedom,
democracy, human right,
and become a active and informed citizen
within this multicultural democracy.
So, they need protection to
enjoy political civilization
available to other
communities in Australia.
- [Chris] And Chen, please,
share with us your thoughts.
- I think the Australian can do a lot.
The most important thing is to protect
Chinese Australians,
real Chinese Australians.
And, the, because right now,
the CCP's infiltration is massive.
Most of the current Chinese organizations
run pro-CCP.
They either been
infiltrated or controlled.
They're affiliated to
the Australian Council
of Promotion of Peaceful Reunification.
And the
the majority of Chinese migrants,
mainland Chinese, I mean,
mainland Chinese migrants are very quiet.
They are silent majority
because they have been
scared of China politics
and they don't want to get involved.
They have, there are many
connections with mainland China.
They worried about the visas,
they said, "Oh my parents are getting old,
"and I need to see their last,
"for the last time" and they worry about,
because Chinese, you know, very
cherish the family relations
and
the majority are silent.
Of course, but now, and since 2016,
majority want to say something,
want to, because last
time the Chinese community
were shocked that the concert
praising the mass murder Mao Zedong
was going to be held
at the Sydney Town Hall
and Melbourne Town Hall.
And later, some people stood up
and to campaign against it.
And later, against the
Chinese Revolutionary Ballet.
That's a propaganda
piece, brainwashed piece,
it's called, we call it
fascist asiatic aesthetic.
And, the Red Detachment of Women.
It used to be, the Chinese Red Ballet
used to travel around the world,
they met little criticism,
and this time, in Australia,
they met a huge criticism
from the public,
especially the voice of the
silent Chinese majority.
And I hope the Australian
can hear the voice of
silent Chinese majority.
And especially now, the
Foreign Transparency,
the Foreign Influence Transparency Scheme,
is just want to protect
Chinese Australian interest,
because we can't allow
these fake community
to represent the majority
of mainland Chinese.
And the, it's
not targeting only to China,
but all foreign influence.
The government is trying to
protect the Chinese Australians,
and why there're so many disagreement?
It seems they try to say
"I represent the Chinese community".
They represent Chinese community.
They claim they represent
the Chinese community.
Because China has say that
this law is against China.
And China is worried about its
worried about its force,
its power, its influence in Australia.
I believe there will be,
still will be some,
you know, some more debate on this.
Otherwise, you can see that
there's no infiltration at all,
and there will be more.
I can see the last time,
there's about 30 China experts,
they said China experts, who,
to air the views submitted
to the parliamentary committee
on security intelligence
that they are against the law.
This law, Foreign Influence
Transparency Scheme is nothing
but to protect the
Australian national interest.
The US have a Foreign
Agent Registration Act.
That's the same thing.
And it runs well, if US
want to put into practice.
- One final question before
we wrap up for a Q and A,
what is the communist party's end goal?
What happens if nothing is done?
- You know, you know, you
know their objective? (laughs)
It's,
I think when we talk about
this transparency scheme
or whatever the legislation amendment,
to me, it's almost too late.
I already mentioned
from the very beginning
the Chinese Communist Party state
has extremely successful
to establish its network
within the Chinese community,
Chinese community in particular.
And extends to education,
business, government, everywhere.
So, it's fully understandable
that you have got this
very strong reaction
because they already
part of the party state.
They are extension of the
power, of the influence
of the party state, here in Australia.
If nothing is done,
this divided and rule,
you have enemies, you have friends
that you are got on board
with the party state.
You get rich, you get influence,
and then you actually battling
from both sides, Australia and China,
within the government, within education,
within business.
And then if you are a
dissident in this sense,
you lose everything.
So that is if nothing is done.
This will be quite,
at least less pleasant
situation will continue
and then will,
quite miserable situation
for guys like me, like Yonglin,
or like many people among you here.
- [Chris] And Dr. Carrico.
- Well I assume the end goal is
a win-win mutually beneficial relationship
in which all sides are happy.
No, no, that was a play on words.
But I don't really like
to predict the future.
I would just say that at the moment,
I do know that people,
even living outside of China,
are still concerned, right,
about political influence
from the party state.
And if nothing is done, I
think that interference,
that influence will continue to grow.
Those fears will become ever greater,
and there will be ever
less room for people
of Chinese descent and,
you know, for all of us
to really contribute to open discussion
of the challenges facing Australia
and the region as a whole.
And that is an endpoint that
I would not want to see.
- [Chris] And Mr. Chen.
- Yeah, sorry, I want to mention again
about the so-called submission
of ideas of 30 scholars.
I found two of them actually
are the head of Confucius Institute,
and can they represent the academic views
or represent the Chinese community?
- [Audience] No, no.
- So, there's one is a Confucius
of University of Adelaide,
the other is the Confucius--
- [Audience] Sydney U
- [Kevin] Yeah, Sydney and Adelaide
- Yeah yeah. And also, I
found at least two of them
actually used to work for
China Daily, in China.
So they born in China,
they grow up in China,
and then they came to
Australia to do academic work
to influence Australian society.
And I'm not saying they're Chinese agent.
But anyway, they, we needed
to know their background,
need to know background.
And some of them scholars,
whatever you say,
scholars, that they've been research
funded by the Chinese donors,
and including, of course,
even some of ambassador,
former ambassador of Australia,
and, the, even I've said
that when Gough Whitlam
established relations with China,
that's a good move,
wise move for Australia,
but now, it's not wise,
as the United States already confessed
that it's a bad move to judge China,
that China will automatically
turn to democracy
after the economic growth.
And that's the wrong decision.
And obviously, some of academics
may just stick to that track,
I think they need to renew their brain.
They need to renew their brain.
(audience laughs)
They just, they should not
just stick to their China,
are these academics travel
a lot in mainland China,
of course, I don't know
how much benefit they've got from China,
but anyway, they have been
the target of lobbyist.
And the Chinese, you know,
for the Chinese community,
the Chinese blood is an asset.
It doesn't mean that all Chinese
will connected to the CCP,
but it's easy target,
because of their connection with China,
their ancestors in China,
and they usually, sometimes, you know,
because of proud of nationalism,
proud of racism, or
Chinese race is superior,
and, and, and
that easy to be lobbied,
and, but that doesn't mean, you know,
like I said that, the
Professor Feng also said,
that the
Mr. Kevin Carrico
and he said "All Chinese are spies".
That's wrong, that's wrong.
The, but still, Chinese students
are very easy to be coerced,
because most, as we know that background,
Chinese, all Chinese,
you know, when I grew up
in China, I was brainwashed.
And I then went to
foreign affairs college,
and I have a chance to
know the outside world.
I can read the voice of America,
can listen to the voice of America,
can read Time Magazine,
Newsweekly, and all these.
And even get education,
get teachings from the,
some, at that time,
volunteer experts to teach us language,
and they taught us Western philosophies.
And, there're not many
Chinese who have such chances
to struggle, to get rid of the brainwash,
but of course, nowadays,
because of internet,
a lot of Chinese have stand up
and the netizens against the regime.
- Well thank you very much
for all of your thoughts.
I do feel our brains have been
renewed from this discussion.
Unfortunately, we are now out of time,
but I want to thank you
all for coming tonight
and the incredible passion
I've seen in the audience.
Let's have another round of
applause for our panelists.
(audience claps)