On this episode of China Uncensored:
I am full of prejudice against China.
And arrogance.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
You know, when I went to public relations
training for...um
no US government agency in particular...
they taught me how to respond to tough questions
from nosy reporters:
You turn the tables.
Knock them off balance.
Beat them at their own game.
And it seems China’s Foreign Minister Wang
Yi
has had similar training from the Chinese
counterpart to the...
no US government agency in particular.
Earlier this month, Wang and Canada’s Foreign
Affairs Minister
held a peaceful joint press conference in
Ottawa.
When suddenly, this so-called Canadian reporter,
Amanda Connolly,
tried to undermine China by asking a question
about so-called “human rights.”
And this was Wang’s response:
“I have to say that your question is full
of prejudice against China and arrogance.
I don't know where that comes from.
Now: Release the five-pointed question attack!
“Have you ever been to China?
Do you know that China has lifted more than
600 million people out of poverty?
And do you know that China is now the second
largest economy in the world,
coming from a very low foundation?
Do you think development is possible for China
without protection for human rights?
And did you know that China has written protection
and promotion of human rights into our constitution?
Answered the question with more questions.
And you know what?
Wang’s questions make a really good point.
China has the second largest economy in the
world.
And nothing says “human rights” like the
right to make money.
As state-run media tells us every year.
“The Chinese government released its annual
white paper on human rights on Monday morning,
highlighting progress made in 2014
The 14,000 word Human Rights Report looked
at the improvements in people's livelihood,
including higher incomes.”
See? China has created its own, more favorable
definition of “human rights.”
Hmm... where have I seen this kind of thing
before?
War is peace!
Freedom is slavery!
Ignorance is strength!
I mean, sure, the so-called “Freedom House”
organization
gave China a freedom ranking of 16...
out of 100.
But they’re full of prejudice against China.
And arrogance.
And I doubt they’ve ever been to China.
And let me remind you,
as Wang Yi did,
that China has protection and promotion of
human rights written into its constitution.
For example
—and these are all real—
China’s constitution guarantees:
The right to vote
Freedom of speech
Freedom of religion
Freedom of the press
and Freedom of assembly
Wait, what are those asterisks?
I see.
But look: If you didn’t like Wang Yi’s
response to that reporter’s question,
don’t blame him!
“Blame Canada! Blame Canada!”
That’s right. Blame Canada’s Foreign Affairs
Minister Stéphane Dion.
Because the reporter had actually addressed
her question at him.
"Stéphane Dion just stood quietly by as this
went on."
That’s right. As you can see in this footage
the reporter shot,
Dion didn’t interrupt,
and didn’t call Wang out afterwards.
And really, isn’t that a problem, too?
Chinese authorities pull a bunch of jerk moves,
and foreign governments stand by like some
polite Mountie.
If China is going to change the definition
of human rights
in order to make the world think it gives
people freedom
then really, shouldn’t we call them on it?
So if you were Canada’s Foreign Affairs
Minister,
what would you have said to Wang Yi?
Leave your comments below.
And if you like China Uncensored,
join my 50-Cent Army on Patreon.
For a contribution of just 50 cents per episode,
you can help improve the human rights of this
show.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell. See you
next time.