On this episode of China Uncensored,
Hong Kong wants you to shut your mouth
and keep quiet.
Or you could go to jail.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Hong Kong.
Pearl of the Orient.
Returned to Chinese rule in 1997
under the One Country, Two Systems policy.
That means Hong Kong gets to keep
all of its freedoms, until it doesn’t.
Well, good news everyone.
The Chinese Communist Party is no longer trying
to subvert the rule of law in Hong Kong.
It’s already succeeded.
You may remember Joshua Wong.
He was a student leader
in the 2014 Hong Kong Umbrella Movement
and friend of the show.
Well, he’s been sentenced to jail.
Again.
In August, Wong had been sentenced
to six months in jail for unlawful assembly
during the Umbrella Movement.
He served two months locked up,
and then was released on bail in October
while he appealed his verdict.
But after getting out on bail,
Wong committed a very serious crime:
Exercising his right to free speech.
He led protests,
wrote op-eds for global newspapers,
And led more protests.
The good news is that Hong Kong courts
remembered that Joshua had already pleaded
guilty
to another crime they hadn’t yet
gotten around to sentencing him for.
Oops.
So on Wednesday,
they sentenced him to another three months
in jail.
This time, the charges weren’t for unlawful
assembly—
he’d already served time for that.
This time,
it was for not obeying a court order
to leave that unlawful assembly.
See?
There are always more crimes
they can charge you for.
In addition to Joshua Wong,
pro-democracy activist Raphael Wong
received four months in jail.
And another 14 people were given
suspended sentences and steep fines.
This harsh sentencing is probably meant
to be a warning to other activists in Hong
Kong:
Shut your mouth or we’ll trump up some charges.
Welcome to One Country,
One and a Half Systems.
So what do you think about all the new crimes
they keep finding to charge Joshua Wong with?
Leave your comments below.
T
hanks for watching this episode of China Uncensored.
Once again I'm your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Want to learn more about Joshua Wong
and the situation in Hong Kong?
Head over to our website ChinaUncensored.tv.
There you can see more great episodes of China Uncensored,
that you won’t see on YouTube.
Click here.