On this episode of China Uncensored,
the biggest China news today.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
I’m in Hong Kong this week
as part of our Pivot to Asia Tour.
And if you’ve been following the situation
here,
you’d know that huge things are happening.
On Friday,
pro-Beijing forces in the Hong Kong government
made a move that could expel four pro-democracy
lawmakers
from office.
And that could open doors for the government
to pass an anti-subversion law
that could be the biggest threat to freedom
that Hong Kong has faced in 20 years!
Not to mention it makes a mockery out of Hong
Kong's democratic process
and the one country, two systems policy
that's supposed to protect the people of Hong
Kong
and shows the Chinese Communist Party's increasing
encroachment here.
Wait, what’s that Shelley?
Oh, everyone wants me to talk about Donald
Trump instead.
Apparently, the US president-elect has,
shall we say,
trumped all this seriously freedom-threatening
news by...
making a phone call to the president of Taiwan.
Or as Trump claimed on Twitter,
she totally called him first.
Now what’s the big deal?
Presidents of lots of countries have called
to congratulate Trump.
The difference is: Taiwan is not a country!
Just ask the Chinese Communist Party.
They claim Taiwan as a province of China,
and have forced almost every other country—
including the United States—
to agree to the “One China” policy.
That’s where everyone collectively pretends
Taiwan
is somehow not an independent country—
despite it having its own government, currency,
and military.
So to avoid upsetting the Chinese Communist
Party,
no US president or president-elect
has had a direct phone call with a Taiwanese
president
in 40 years.
Instead, the US has an unofficial relationship
with Taiwan,
in which we promise to help them defend themselves
if China invades,
but we can't refer to them as a government.
Until Donald Trump.
That’s a phrase I think I’m going to be
hearing a lot
over the next four years.
Anyway,
Chinese officials expressed their anger over
this incident—
also a phrase I think I’m going to be hearing
a lot
over the next four years.
Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi gave reporters
the standard line on Friday,
about how "Adherence to the ‘One China’
policy is the cornerstone
of the healthy development,” yada yada yada.
Chinese officials also lodged a formal diplomatic
protest with the US.
Now some people in the lamestream media
say Donald Trump had the phone call because
of his business interests
in Taiwan, like plans to build Trump Hotels
there.
Others claim he did it out of ignorance
of the nuanced diplomatic relationship.
But maybe...
he’s just trolling China.
It would be a bold move to change the US policy
toward Taiwan.
It's just not clear if that's what's actually
happening.
And one possible repercussion here
is that the Chinese Communist Party won't
make a fuss with the US,
but will instead take out their anger on Taiwan.
What's that Shelley?
Oh.
That's already happened.
Anyway, now that the US media has obsessed
over this phone call
like high school girls freaking out over a
text
with the most popular guy in school,
maybe we can get back to talking about the
apparently
second most important piece of China news
today.
Hong...
Wait, what's that Shelley?
What do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.