On this episode of China Uncensored,
the future of Chinese law enforcement is...
“Exterminate! Exterminate!”
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored. I’m your
host, Chris Chappell.
Perhaps someday I, too, will be replaced by
a robot.
“Welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host, Sarcastabot 3000.
Have you ever noticed that sometimes things
seem one way,
but are actually a different way?
Ha ha ha ha.”
But until that day,
it’s my job to show you this:
The possible future of Chinese law enforcement.
Meet AnBot.
This concept robot was developed by China’s
National Defense University.
It was unveiled last month at the Chongqing
Hi-Tech Fair.
Soon, all Chinese people can enjoy
the ’round-the-clock surveillance that was
once reserved
only for dissidents and human rights lawyers.
Now I know it looks suspiciously like a cross
between
a Dalek from Doctor Who and an a giant Tamagotchi.
But don’t worry!
The AnBots won't get sick if you forget to
clean up after them.
And they aren’t bent on exterminating all
inferior species.
Just people with inferior political views.
No, just kidding.
They’re not here to kill you.
Yet. They’re still just in the concept phase.
According to state-run People's Daily,
one purpose of the AnBot is
to “help with police officers’ anti-riot
missions.”
And to do that,
it comes equipped with a helpful “electrical
anti-riot device.”
Hmm... I wonder where they got the idea
of a weaponized robot for urban deployment.
“It gives me great pleasure to introduce  you to the future of law enforcement: ED-209.”
Where nothing could possibly go wrong.
Um, anyway, the AnBot’s device is probably
more like a taser.
And tasers are pretty much harmless.
Oh.
At least you can outrun it.
At 11 miles per hour.
Or until you can find a staircase.
Anyway, the AnBot is designed mainly for patrolling,
which it can do autonomously
as in, it will roam around on its own,
unless someone specifically controls it remotely.
And it can watch and listen to anything around
it,
so keep those subversive thoughts to yourself.
But before you think,
“I can’t believe China would deploy robot
police on an unsuspecting populace,”
well, the AnBot...looks suspiciously like
a Chinese knockoff
of the American K-5
an unarmed robot police unit developed two
years ago in Silicon Valley.
Wow. I'm not sure if that was an ad for robot
police
or our new robot overlords.
One of the creators says:
“It can see, feel, hear, and smell.”
Ah, the future. Where robots can smell your
fear.
But for now, this is all just theoretical.
Techies showing off their prototypes.
But if they were ever deployed in China, well,
watch out.
Because if this happens again,
the tank driver bots won't be programmed to
stop.
So how do you feel about the impending future
where robots become the police?
Leave your comments below.
And if you like China Uncensored,
please consider supporting us on Patreon.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell. See you in the future.