Australia, the land down under.
So far under, it’s starting to stink.
The name’s Chappell.
Chris Chappell.
People call me “Agent.”
They also call me in when no one else will
do the job.
But business these days was slower than a
hibernating koala.
And that’s when she walked in.
You’re not very tall.
I try to be.
You’ve got a case.
Someone’s making trouble down in Chinatown.
Would you call it, big trouble?Wrong genre.
Try again.
Sorry, angel, I don’t see why that’s any
of my business.
Because you uncensor stuff.
That’s what you do.
What’s with the car?
In case anyone wants to go for a spin.
Just don’t drive too fast.
Speeding was the least of my worries.
This new case smelled like trouble with a
capital T.
I just hope Australia won't be the land
where I’m buried six feet under.
Chris, what are you doing?
You’re just staring at me.
Australia was founded by a bunch of criminals.
Today, they’re called politicians.
I got word about John Hugh,
a former politician who was a founding member
of something called the Australian Values
Alliance.
If someone was ruffling up the feathers of
the local Chinese,
that’s a good place to start.
So, you're one of those racist Australians
who hate Chinese people.
Well I'm Chinese myself so how can I be racist
against Chinese?
He had a point.
And he also had a pretty good idea who was
really behind
this Chinatown chop suey.
The Chinese Consulate in Sydney plays a large
role,
so called managing the local Chinese communities
here.
So how do Chinese Australians feel about this
influence
the Communist party's trying to have?
Well, most people keep silent,
and they may have to obey and accept the kind
of influence,
because if you stand up,
actively campaign against them,
you probably don't get a visa to visit China.
Then you are separated
from your other family members and friends.
And perhaps they have properties in China
or business interests.
What do you think you could be done to tackle
Chinese Communist Party infiltration in Australia?
First of all, don't fear of the authorities,
because they cannot really control this country.
We are not under China control.
Not yet.
And hope will never.
We are not part of Chinese territory here.
Secondly, is to expose their tactics,
what they do to you, to the general public,
and let other people be aware those tactics
they use
to try to scare you off or win you over.
So, don't be silent.
Don't be silent.
That's right.
I should have known it was my old nemesis,
the Chinese Communist Party.
This whole situation had their dirty red fingerprints
all over it.
But I needed more on what they were doing
in Chinatown,
and how.
Time to rattle some cages.
Shelley, I want you to call the Chinese embassy.
Make ’em sweat.
Stay away from the United Front!
Sorry, I don’t speak Australian.
Someone didn’t want me getting any closer.
It’s not the first time I’ve gotten a
kick out of a case.
But I was about to find out I wasn’t the
only one
with a boot on my neck.
Great, now no one will want to talk to me.
I thought you were trying to quit
I'm down to two packs a day.
I’ve tried the Chinese embassy multiple
times.
I don’t think they want to talk to you.
Yeah?
Sounds like they’d get along with my ex
wife.
You don’t have an ex wife.
Don’t remind me…
When you hit rock bottom,
you can’t get any lower.
Not until you bring out the jackhammer.
Trying to solve this mystery was like looking
up the nostrils
of a sleeping wombat.
Pitch black and twice as smelly.
I decided to get out and clear my head.
This must be the place.
Who are you?
My name is Shen An.
I've been in Australia almost 30 years.
Shen An was in deep with the Chinese Australian
community.
He had information for me about the United
Front
and their shady partner,
the Australian Council for the Promotion
of the Peaceful Reunification of China.
What is the United Front Work Department?
The peaceful reunification of China
that control by United Front of China.
That organization in Sydney, in Australia,
is their agent.
Then through this agent control a couple hundred
so-called
Chinese community organizations in Sydney.
And it's all tied to the United Front?
Yeah, all under the control.
I call Australia the disaster area
of this sort of influence from Chinese CCP.
Can you give me some examples
of how they operate?
Easy...
First, they, Chinese government they control
most of Chinese media in Australia...
by using money to corrupt most of the media.
Not only Chinese media.
You mean English language media?
Yeah, that's right.
Not only Chinese,
English language media as well,
but the situation getting worse and worse.
How does the communist party manipulate
the Chinese Australian community?
Through their so-called "community leaders."
I can say 99% of those community leaders,
they are manipulated by.
99%?
99.
Almost like 100%.
How are critical voices silenced?
For example, John Hugh was denied to entry
China.
That's one of the way they do that.
You're not allowed to go back to the country
you born.
You're not allowed to meet your friends or
relatives in China.
Also, they try to isolate you people in Chinese
community.
They try to ruin your names.
They turn you into the enemy.
Yeah, yeah.
Turn you to the enemy.
For example, we against the Chinese communist
regime,
but now lots of Chinese, obviously Chinese
in Australia.
They look at you like you are against our
government,
our party.
Do ordinary Chinese Australians know what's
happening?
Not too many ordinary Chinese.
What does this mean for Australia?
Well, communist party in my eyes in my mind
is the evil in the world, in human history.
It's the monster.
It can only bring disaster to human society.
I can tell you my experience, personal experience.
We suffered.
I know the Chinese communist party's nature.
Their nature is to control
and never give up their power to the people.
That's the so called communist party.
Things were spinning out of control
faster than a Tasmanian devil.
But I wasn’t any closer to rumbling the
United Front.
And that’s when I got the feeling someone
was following me.
You know, you’re not a very good private
dick.
No, but I am a good public one.
Hello?
What?!
Shelley, we’ve got a break.
Some kookaburra’s got proof this goes right
to the top!
I am the son of the Red Revolution.
Zhang Xiaogang.
Brainwashed by the Communists in China,
he fled to Australia, where he tried his hand
at
the dirtiest business of all—
politics.
You're talking about ideological education
to brainwash the next generation.
Brainwash every- yeah, every worker in the
company,
or government office, or school.
So, I don't like this, so I complained.
And so, my colleagues say,
"You should be quiet."
Because, if you speak out, maybe get in trouble.
Zhang got in trouble, all right.
He got involved in the pro-democracy movement
in China.
And when he came to Australia,
the Chinese Communist Party followed.
An Australian political party, the Unity Party,
asked Zhang to run in a local election.
But then the leader, Peter Wong,
got a call from the Chinese consulate.
Peter Wong said, "Consulate asked me why
you put pro-democracy movement activist as
your candidate?"
"If you do so,
we will ask Chinese community to vote against
you."
So Peter Wong said,
"Maybe you can make a deal,
say you quit from the pro-democracy movement
and ask Consulate to give you a visa,
go back to China."
I said, "No, I can't do that."
You said no?
I don't want to do any deal with the Chinese
Consulate.
I still want to fight for democracy, for human
rights.
So the Chinese Consulate was essentially trying
to
undermine Australian democracy?
Yeah.
Everywhere.
What are some other ways they pressured
the Chinese-Australian community?
The fear if they do anything,
or say something wrong...
then they deny you a visa to back to China...
In most of the Chinese member,
China community to have a relative in China
-
maybe their parents,
maybe their brothers, sisters-
and they feel you have no chance to go back
to see your relative.
There's a great pain, you know?
So the Communist Party basically holds Chinese
Australians’ families
inside of China as hostages.
Yeah, exactly.
So what can the Chinese-Australian community
do in response to this?
Well, I think most members of the Chinese
community-
Majority, don't really feel this is a problem...
Most of them actually, thinking about making
money.
They don't want to make trouble with the Communist
party.
I really need the Australian society
to understand the Communist regime,
what they are.
Many people think, "Oh, come on, China is
good.
The economy booming,
look's nice and organized."
But, the double-faced.
When they need you or doing business there's
a face.
But, when they're trying to control you, a
different face.
I had a bitter taste in my mouth.
Like I’d eaten a bucket of vegemite.
The Communist Party had its clapper claws
everywhere.
No place was safe.
No one can be trusted.
How can you fight something like that?
Thanks doll.
Almost got me in the pipes.
Forget it Chris.
It’s Chinatown.
And that’s when it hit me.
In a world where the Chinese Communist Party
makes everyone into an enemy,
you’ve got to find someone to watch your
back.
Here, this one’s on me.
Shelley, I think this is the beginning of
a beautiful friendship.
We’ve known each other for ten years.