On this episode of China Uncensored,
the friendship between China and Pakistan
is
"higher than the mountains" and "deeper than
the oceans."
Especially when it comes to doing their best
to not fight terrorism, together.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored. I'm your
host, Chris Chappell.
Pakistan. A beautiful country that borders
China and India,
and is unfortunately home to a lot of terrorists.
As you may know from reading the news, or
watching Zero Dark Thirty,
Osama Bin Laden was hiding in Pakistan until
his villa was raided by Navy SEALs.
So it's no surprise that another violent organization
with ties to Al-Qaeda is also based partly
in Pakistan:
Jaish-e-Mohammed, or JeM.
According to the US government's National
Counterterrorism Center,
JeM has openly declared war on the United
States.
A JeM member may have been involved in the
killing of an American journalist in 2002.
And JeM is responsible for a number of deadly
attacks in India
including allegedly the recent attacks on
Pathankot Air Force station,
where seven Indian soldiers were killed.
Now you might think JeM should be labeled
a terrorist organization.
And in fact, the United Nations would agree.
"JeM is an organization that has been declared
a terrorist organization way back in 2001
by the United Nations."
But you know who's apparently not a terrorist?
The leader of JeM: Masood Azhar.
And that's because...China.
In Washington, DC last week,
Pakistan and China joined together in blocking
the United Nations from putting Azhar on the
UN terror blacklist.
China said he does not meet the UN's requirements
for being labeled a "terrorist."
They did not elaborate.
As you can imagine, this has caused a major
uproar in India
where a lot of innocent people have been killed
by Azhar's organization.
"The Indian establishment here was really
angry at the manner in which the designation
of Maulana Masood Azhar as a terrorist has
been blocked by China."
But since this happened on April 1,
at first I thought it was a joke.
You know, that the leader and financier of
a terrorist organization would himself somehow
not be labeled a terrorist.
But apparently China doesn't joke around.
But wait a second, doesn't Pakistan want to
get rid of terrorists, too?
Well, it's complicated.
Partly, it has to do with Kashmir.
Not this cashmere. This Kashmir.
Pakistan, India, and to some degree China
all have competing claims to this region.
Since the partition of India in 1947,
India and Pakistan have fought not one but
three wars over Kashmir.
And over the years Pakistan has trained militants
to fight on its behalf.
Like the ones who later formed JeM.
JeM's goal is to take back Indian-controlled
Kashmir.
They're, you know, "freedom fighters."
See? The Pakistani government doesn't support
terrorism.
It's just that not everyone agrees on who's
a terrorist.
I mean, China calls this guy a terrorist.
And because JeM is helping stake Pakistan's
claim in Kashmir,
the Pakistani government isn't really trying
too hard to get rid of them
even though many people in the government
don't like JeM's tactics.
So why would China support Pakistan on protecting
JeM's leader?
Because China and Pakistan are besties.
And by besties, I mean their friendship is,
and I quote,
"Higher than the mountains,
deeper than the oceans,
stronger than steel,
dearer than eyesight,
sweeter than honey, and so on."
And by "and so on" I assume the ambassador
meant "mightier than the threat of global terrorism."
So why are China and Pakistan so close?
Well, they've been friends for a long time.
In 1950, Pakistan was one of the first nations
to recognize the CCP's rule of China,
and to break ties with Taiwan.
And you know what else makes for great political
friendships?
Money.
“China is Pakistan’s second largest trade
partner,
and a huge investor in Pakistani infrastructure
and shipping routes.
The two countries trade roughly 10 to 12 billion
dollars a year as of 2013.”
And that trade includes things like nuclear
technology.
And also guns.
In fact, Pakistan is the world's biggest buyer
of Chinese weapons.
In their latest deal,
Pakistan bought eight Chinese submarines for
five billion dollars.
I assume they'd come in handy if Pakistan
ever got into a war with,
I don't know, India.
Again.
Now I'd like to believe China's Foreign Minister
Wang Yi when he said last year that,
“Fighting the scourge of terrorism is the
responsibility of every country.
China has always been an active participant
in international counter-terrorism cooperation.”
But I think this article in state-run Global
Times may be more revealing.
So what do you think about China's support
for Pakistan?
Leave your comments below.
And if you like China Uncensored, please click
below to support us on Patreon.
Once again, I'm Chris Chappell. See you next
time.