A massive skyscraper shakes
Bitcoin prices plummet
And China expands its nuclear arsenal
That and more on this week’s China news
headlines
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
And these are this week’s China news headlines
The Chinese Communist Party has prided itself
on how it’s transformed China into a land
of glittery skyscrapers.
The problem is all those skyscrapers are made
in China.
This video shows people in Shenzhen fleeing
in panic as a skyscraper, almost 1000 feet
tall, starts wobbling and swaying, even though
there was no earthquake or bad weather.
People inside the building were evacuated,
and an investigation is ongoing into—why
a giant skyscraper just randomly started wobbling.
But experts “found no safety abnormalities
in the main structure and surrounding environment
of the building”.
Other than the fact the building wobbles!
These have been a bad couple of weeks for
the public image of Chinese construction.
Last week, a man was left dangling from one
of China’s infamous glass bridges, after
the glass shattered in strong wind.
There’s a big problem in China of construction
corruption.
Officials or contractors often siphon money
from construction, during each phase of the
project.
So the end result can be dangerously unstable
buildings.
It’s such a common problem, Chinese people
have a name for it—Tofu Dreg Construction.
Because it’s like the buildings are made
of the scraps left behind from making tofu.
That’s right, not even tofu.
Tofu scraps.
So in a way, it's appropriate that a Titanic
replica is now under construction in China.
If that falls apart, it’s just being historically
accurate.
Speaking of things collapsing—the price
of Bitcoin.
We partly have a Chinese government crackdown
to thank.
Chinese authorities said the crypto market
was too volatile so restricted trading, which
caused a volatile drop in the price of crypto,
including BitCoin.
But if you’ve lost a bunch of money, don’t
worry, China is helping out.
With over half a million dollars in counterfeit
currency.
This is one of the tactics of the Chinese
Communist Party’s economic warfare against
the US.
China is flooding the US with fake goods.
In 2019, Customs and Border Patrol made almost
28,000 seizures.
Those goods would have been worth $1.5 billion
dollars if they were genuine.
And almost half of those fake goods came from
China.
So considering the economic warfare China
is waging against the US, you’ll probably
be wanting to invest in Chinese stocks with
ties to the Chinese military.
Well fear not, a Trump era ban on doing just
that has been postponed!
But you’d better move quick.
You only have until June 11.
Buy now!
A former American university professor has
been sentenced to 37 months in prison for
lying on grant applications.
He was trying to get millions of dollars in
federal grant money to do research in China.
As part of his sentence, he was also “ordered
to pay more than $3.4 million in restitution
to the National Institute of Health and approximately
$413,000 to The Ohio State University.”
If he’s having a hard time raising the money,
maybe he could invest in Dogecoin?
And after the break, the US may be falling
behind China on science.
But there’s a plan to change that.
Welcome back.
Some fear the US is falling behind China in
the sciences.
So the Senate is considering a $120 billion
dollar investment to counter China.
It’s a bipartisan bill.
It is led by Democratic Senate Majority leader
Chuck Schumer and Republican Senator Todd
Young.
You see, the US kind of realized the problem
of having China dominate things like the medical
equipment supply chain when the coronavirus
hit.
China is rapidly expanding its nuclear weapons
arsenal.
That’s a concern for the US and Russia—who
have a regular nuclear dialogue to make sure
things don’t go Duke Nukem.
However, China doesn’t seem to be willing
to join these nuclear arms talks.
According to U.S. disarmament Ambassador Robert
Wood “Despite the PRC’s dramatic build-up
of its nuclear arsenal, unfortunately it continues
to resist discussing nuclear risk reduction
bilaterally with the United States.”
But as world-ending catastrophes go, China
is willing to work with the US on climate
change.
Working to fight climate change can actually
be good for business.
Especially the business of ethnic slave labor.
A new report this week found China is using
Uyghur forced labor to make parts for solar
panels.
And China makes about 70% of the world’s
solar panels.
The Chinese Communist Party has been in propaganda
overdrive to cover up their genocide of the
Uyghurs in Xinjiang.
I talked about that in a previous episode.
One of the Party’s propaganda tools is releasing
videos from Uyghurs.
“Chinese state media have published dozens
of the videos praising the Communist Party
and showing Uyghurs angrily denouncing former
U.S. Secretary of State Mike Pompeo for declaring
a genocide in the far west Xinjiang region.”
The Party has been claiming that people made
these videos totally spontaneously and out
of their own free will.
Because they’re just so, so angry at Mike
Pompeo.
But in a very shocking twist, it turns out
the Chinese regime ordered Uyghurs to make
these videos.
The Associated Press obtained a screenshot
of a text message sent to government officials
in Xinjiang, telling them to find Uyghurs
to make these videos.
And the text even spelled out what these Uyghurs
should say in their totally spontaneous videos:
“Express a clear position on Pompeo’s
remarks, for example: I firmly oppose Pompeo’s
anti-Chinese remarks, and I am very angry
about them...Express your feelings of loving
the party, the country and Xinjiang (I am
Chinese, I love my motherland, I am happy
at work and in life, and so on).”
Very convincing.
You know, after years of bending Hollywood
to its will, you’d think the Communist Party
could get some better screenwriters.
Unfortunately, the man who leaked this government
text to the AP has now been detained for “instigating
splittism”.
At least until he makes a video about how
much he loves the Chinese Communist Party.
Totally spontaneously and out of his own free
will.
The genocide of Uyghur Muslims in China is
part of the reason there’s a growing call
for a Boycott of the 2022 Beijing Olympic
games.
This week, Speaker of the House Nancy Pelosi
joined that call.
Specifically she’s calling for a diplomatic
boycott.
That’s where individual athletes would be
allowed to go and compete.
But US officials would not attend the games.
There’s a new job in China—organ donation
coordinators.
You see, China has been rapidly expanding
its organ transplant industry.
Lots of money to be made there.
Most of those organs come from religious and
ethnic minorities, like Falun Gong practitioners
or Uyghur Muslims, who are killed for their
organs.
China didn’t have any voluntary organ donation
system until 2011.
Unless you count the system where the Party
“volunteered” Uyghurs and Falun Gong.
But even after the Party started a separate
system for people to actually voluntarily
donate their organs, not many people used
it.
So that’s where organ donation coordinators
come in.
“Their role is to convince families of dying
patients to agree to donate their loved one’s
organs.”
Except according to a former organ donation
coordinator, that usually means screwing poor
people.
“[He] recounted one case involving a very
poor family.
Their dying family member could still have
been saved with proper medical treatment.
But the family decided not to proceed with
this.
Instead, they chose to starve him—and cash
out.”
Yeah, don’t get an organ transplant in China.
And a Chinese propaganda ploy in Turkey backfired
badly.
China hosted a drawing contest for highschoolers
called China in My Dreams.
Students were supposed to submit artwork that
best described the ties between China and
Turkey.
And boy did they ever.
Here are some examples.
Xi Jinping surrounded by Uyghurs skulls, and
another that shows a man dressed in clothing
made of the PRC flga putting his hand over
a Uyghurs mouth, expressing the idea that
uyghurs have no freedom of speech.
Yet other social media users have shared drawings
on various themes: uyghurs hanged by nooses
made from China's flag; uyghurs who were killed
by a sword while china and Turkey carried
on their 'friendship;' and the Chinese state
representatives demolishing mosques, impressioning
uyghurs.
I so love it when the Communist Party’s
propaganda initiatives blow up in their face.
And now it’s time to answer a question from
a member of the China Uncensored 50 Cent Army,
fans who support us and our efforts to expose
the truth about the Chinese Communist Party
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
Nikolay asks: “Chris, In a case of war,
what do you think will happen with US companies
that pander to CCP, like YouTube and Twitter?”
Well Nikolay, I’d hate to see an actual
boots on the ground war between the US and
China, but if something like that were to
happen, many Western companies, not just the
tech companies like YouTube and Twitter, would
be screwed.
In fact, one of the first things the Communist
Party would do is to seize the factories and
assets of any American companies that are
operating inside China.
Right now, these companies think the China
market means big business and big bucks.
Of course it never works out that way.
But if the American public decided they wouldn’t
give their business to companies with ties
to China, those companies would change how
they do things.
And the great news is it doesn’t need to
take a war for that to happen.
Right now, you can start buying from competitors
who don’t invest in China, or boycott companies
that turn a blind eye to the Chinese Communist
Party.
Hit ’em where it hurts—in the wallet.
Thanks for your question Nikolay and your
support.
And a big thank you to everyone who supports
China Uncensored on Patreon.
We could not do this show without you.
So thank you for joining us in the fight to
expose the Chinese Communist Party to the
world.
If you’re interested in joining, head over
to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
You’ll get a bunch of cool perks, including
the chance to have me answer your question
on the show!
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next
time.