On this episode of China Uncensored,
foreign aggression in the South China Sea.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I'm your host Chris Chappell.
The South China Sea!
A vast body of water rich in natural resources.
It sees 5 trillion dollars worth of shipping
pass through it every year.
And it's under attack!
Yes, one country has been aggressively pursing
its own selfish interests in the region,
angering its neighbors
and possibly even incurring the wrath of Neptune.
And that country is...Japan!
What, you expected me to say China?
I mean, sure Chinese ships took over the Jackson
Atoll in the South China Sea.
But it's the South China Sea.
It clearly belongs to China.
Just like my mother's pantry cabinet.
Filled with China--'s sovereign territory.
The latest news is that, according to Reuters,
a Japanese submarine and two warships will
sail to the Philippines and then on to Vietnam.
Understandably, China is upset.
It's outrageous!
Remember the last time Japanese warships sailed
through that area, the disputed Spratly Islands?
Well, Chinese foreign ministry spokesman Hong
Lei sure does.
"Japan occupied China's Spratly Islands during
World War Two,
so we are on high alert for Japan's moves
in the South China Sea."
Yes, World War Two!
Gahhh, do you remember the aggressive territorial
expansion of the Japanese Empire?
That's why China is now actively engaged in
preserving peace in the region.
Ok, well, ignore that time this Chinese ship
accidentally rammed a Vietnamese fishing boat
in disputed waters back in 2014.
And these artificial islands they're building
and filling with
military-grade runways, missiles launchers,
and radar.
"China is clearly militarizing the South China
Sea,
and you'd have to believe in a flat earth to
think otherwise."
Hey, some people do believe in a flat earth.
And while we're at it,
let's pretend those Chinese airplanes in the
night sky are just shooting stars!
"Can we pretend that airplanes in the night sky are like shooting stars?"
Anyway, maybe China's alleged military actions
are really just simple misunderstandings.
Like what happened earlier this month
when some Filipino fishermen mistakenly thought
Chinese naval vessels
had "seized" the disputed Jackson Atoll in
the Spratly Islands.
And chased them off with guns.
But in reality, the Chinese were just helping
tow a grounded Filipino ship,
which somehow no one knew about other than
the Chinese, and...
"China advised the fishing boats in nearby
waters to leave in order to ensure navigation
safety and operating conditions."
See? China is just looking out for everyone's
safety.
Oh, well that was back in 2011. Ignore that.
Anyway, China's more recent, ummm, appearance
at the Jackson Atoll is understandable
considering the "provocation" by the Philippines.
You see, the Philippines is seeking international
arbitration over territorial disputes in the
South China Sea
arbitration that China has flatly rejected.
Obviously. I mean, it all belongs to China
anyway.
Look at all those navy ships they have there.
Why involve the international community?
Now Chinese ships have since left the Jackson
Atoll.
Yet despite all of China's efforts to preserve
peace in the region,
warships from around the world are flooding
the area.
Not just Japan, but also the US,
and India.
And there's even a North Korean ship there...somehow.
So clearly it's not just Japanese aggression
China has to worry about.
As Fu Ying, a spokeswoman for China's National
People's Congress, said,
“If you take a look at the matter closely,
it's the US sending the most advanced aircraft
and military vessels to the South China Sea."
Yeah, what's up with the US throwing its weight
around,
holding joint military exercises on its own...with
the Philippines...and Japan...and India.
Clearly no one wants America there.
China's doing a fine job maintaining order
there all by itself.
So ask not for whom the bell a-tolls.
It tolls…for China. It's China's bell.
It has been since ancient times.
So what do you think of China's Jackson Atoll
occupation
I mean solidifying of its long-held, totally
legitimate claims?
Leave your comments below.
Be sure to subscribe for more episodes of
China Uncensored.
And also check out our Facebook page.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell. See you next time.