Taiwan is in a life or death struggle
against the Chinese Communist Party.
And one man’s struggle with brain cancer
put him right in the middle.
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
The Chinese Communist Party is aggressively
expanding around the world.
All you have to do is listen to what Communist
officials are saying.
Take one of China’s top diplomats.
Yang Jiechi.
In 2010, China was challenged by other members
of ASEAN about the South China Sea Dispute.
Yang thundered in response, “China is a
big country and other countries are small
countries, and that’s just a fact.”
Very diplomatic.
So China is a big country.
And the CCP uses that weight to swallow up
smaller nations, by buying off their leadership.
Take the Solomon Islands, an archipelago nation
in the Pacific.
It was one of the few remaining countries
that recognized Taiwan.
That is, until China bought off the central
government in 2019—in exchange for switching
allegiances to the PRC.
The Solomon Islands government even quietly
leased one of the islands to China without
telling the people living there.
And of course, there are bribes.
Daniel Suidani is the premier of Solomon’s
Islands’ most populous island, Malaita Province.
He says China offered him bribes.
But to Beijing’s surprise, Suidani refused
to be bought off.
And he’s become a big thorn in the Chinese
Communist Party’s side—because he demands
transparency and accountability.
And now, he’s at risk of being put on trial
for treason, for traveling to Taiwan for brain
cancer treatment.
I have Mr. Suidani with me now for more.
INTERVIEW
Thank you for joining me today.
Thank you.
Chris: So let's talk about what's called "the
switch" in the Solomon Islands, when the government
decided to switch diplomatic relations from
Taiwan to China.
Why did that happen?
Premier: First of all, I didn't agree with
the switch at all because the idea of a switch
was not in the policy agenda of the government,
And that issue of the switch hasn't been talked
about to the people.
So that idea, when the switch come over from
ROC to PRC, the switch become new to the people
because they haven't talked about during the
national campaign for the national general
election in 2019.
So the whole agenda of the switch was not
in the policy agenda for the general election
in 2019.
Premier: So that is why my government and
the people do not agree with what the national
government is doing in terms of the switch
from ROC to PRC.
Chris: So in general, the people of the Solomon
Islands aren't really supportive of the switch?
Premier: No.
And I'm speaking on behalf of my province,
the Malaita Provincial Government and the
people.
We are not happy with the switch for a few
reasons.
One, the process that has been leading up
to the switch, we believe, is not well followed.
It was hijacked because the government said
during a few months before the switch, that
they will consult with agencies in the government,
that before deciding on the switch, there
are four committees that should be given report
about the switch before the government can
switch to [inaudible 00:02:50] in regards
to the switch.
Premier: But that doesn't happen.
They don't have the reports, but then they
made the switch without the reports that they
relied on.
Secondly, because China is a communist country,
and the values that they have is so different
from the democratic values and the principle
that we have in Solomon Islands.
And it's a Christian country, and we uphold
the principles of the democracy.
So that is one of the reason why most Solomon
Island people of the nation didn't happy with
the switch.
Chris: Well, so if the people of the Solomon
Islands aren't really happy with the switch,
why did the government of the Solomon Islands
decide to recognize the People's Republic
of China, the communist party?
Premier: That is what at the moment is the
biggest question in people's mind, on how
the government decide to switch to a PRC,
because we are expecting a wider referendum
to the people so that they can well aware
of a system of government in terms of the
CCP.
So at the moment with the government, the
national government, it is not a whole of
the people of the Solomon Islands that agree
with the switch.
But it seems that some of those who in the
DCGA are the ones who support a switch from
ROC to PRC, not everyone in the country.
So the switch is, even at the moment, is not
going down well with the people.
Chris: So it's basically something that only
a small number of elite in the central government
wanted.
Premier: Yes, yes, that's correct.
Chris: So what has Chinese influence brought
to the Solomon Islands?
Premier: what I've seen at the moment in the
province, there is nothing.
There is no developments have been seen.
The province is where 80% of the people live.
In terms of infrastructure and other development,
there is nothing happening.
But the only thing I've seen, well, they used
to talk about is the infrastructure for the
Pacific Games in 2023.
And that's the only development where the
China and the DCGA government had been involving
much in the country at the moment.
Chris: So then this is very strange.
If most of the people in the country didn't
want the switch, and if China isn't bringing
a whole lot of infrastructure development
to the Solomon Islands, you got to wonder
what was the motivation for the government
to make the switch.
It's a big question.
Premier: That question is also what we, as
the people of this nation, are still asking
ourselves what actually really happened to
the switch and why the government agreed to
switch without consulting the people of Solomon
Islands, the nation as a whole.
Chris: So you are the premier of the biggest
province of the Solomon Islands.
And as I hear it, you aren't too popular with
the central government.
I think I can kind of imagine, but why is
that?
Premier: I believe in being representative
of the people.
We as leaders need to carry the cries of the
people.
We are just representing them.
So when my people disagree with the switch,
it is my duty as the leader of the province
to make sure that what my people like, I have
to fight and see that what they like is what
I will perform.
So in regards to the switch, as the largest
province in probably the province of Solomon
Islands, my people disagree with the switch.
So I will stand for what they aspire to.
So I will not agree with the switch because
that is the like of my people.
I am just a representative.
They elected me to represent them.
So I will always stand for what they like.
This is my belief as to being a leader of
that province.
Chris: So essentially you've become a thorn
in the side of the central government and
Beijing's plans for the Solomon Islands, whatever
those may be.
Premier: Yes.
They have been trying to find ways to get
into the province through development that
we have been aware of their involvement in
other countries as well.
The way they do, or they perform, developments
and they interact with the people is not good.
So we haven't got any better safeguards to
safeguard ourself in terms of the influence.
So therefore it would be appropriate for us
to keep them away from entering the province.
So we have made that decision and we stand
by.
Chris: So what do you think is China's goals
with the Solomon Island?
Why are they so interested?
Premier: I believe in terms of the interest,
most in the past Chinese are the ones who
involve more in this logging industry, and
now they are moving into mining industries.
Chris: So last year you called for a referendum
on making Malaita Province independent from
the rest of the Solomon Islands.
It never happened.
But why did you do that?
Premier: I was trying to find out, in terms
of the referendum, how many people are still
having the idea of become independent or another
form of government.
So the referendum is just to find out, a format
to find out, the minds of my people because,
see, we are the most [inaudible] province.
We need to find out what is in their mind,
what are the things now in the mind in terms
of the system of government that we are in
now, this is the aim of that referendum to
find out there, to go back and ask them so
that we can find out numbers, how many people
in the province still in favor of the independence
and maybe others in another form of governance.
Chris: When I made that announcement, they
said that was illegal.
It is unlawful to talk about referendum.
But in my view, I was thinking that this referendum
is just to find out from the mind of my people.
It is not actually going into independence
yet, but to find out from the people first
because we are their representative.
We need to find out from them “what do you
think?”
But the government think that this idea of
the referendum is unlawful.
So they really stopped me from doing it.
And they are not happy with my announcement.
Chris: I'm really getting a sense for why
the central government doesn't like you so
much.
Now I know you've been getting treatment for
brain cancer.
Now, what's interesting is how did that unexpectedly
get tied up in the Taiwan-China issue?
Premier: Yes, I've been sick for about six
months back in a country in Solomon Islands.
And I've been visiting doctors to check with
my severe headache, and they read the report
to me.
And they told me that I need to see a CT scan
machine, to go and have a CT scan to find
out what's happening in my brain.
So we get the report from the doctor, from
the Solomon Islands, and the only possible
way to have that CT scan, that the machine,
is to come to Brisbane.
Now, we find it a bit difficult because of
financial constraint.
We don't have the money because the charges
of that test is huge.
It's about 122,000 Australian dollars.
So it's really difficult for me.
So we asked our friends to help and contribute
some kind of money to help me and to get my
airfares to come to Australia, but that doesn't
work out.
Premier: So we asked the government to help
and still we haven't got any response from
them.
So our friends getting forth and helping me
out and putting a GoFundMe.
And that is when the Taiwanese government,
and I thank them for their help, and they
asked me to come to Taiwan, especially the
President Doctor Tsai Ing-wen, who is so generous
in allowing me to come here and looking after
me here in Taiwan.
So now I'm here in Taiwan because of their
help and friends who helped me do the GoFundMe
and find money to get me here for the important
medical checkup here in Taiwan.
Chris: So I imagine the central government
that's trying to make these relations happen
with China wasn't too happy to hear that you
were going to Taiwan to get this necessary
medical treatment.
Premier: Yes.
So actually, when we were trying to get the
formalities to come here or to come to Australia,
the government sent some office resource to
come and talk to me about my coming.
And they said, "We will happy to help you
if you go and see the prime minister and shake
his hand, and then we'll help you to go there."
So I said, "Oh, I will not going to do that.
It will be okay for me to die than to shake
the hand of the prime minister for that purpose."
Premier: So that is why I decide not to, because
when the government of Solomon Island think
of helping me, I assume that this is from
the People's Republic of China.
So I don't want to involve and to accept their
money.
Chris: Wow.
Well, so while we're filming this, you're
still in Taiwan.
I hear when you get back to the Solomon Islands,
you want to hold a democracy festival.
What is that, and why are you doing it?
Premier: I would like to hold this festival
because people need to look after democracy
carefully, because if we don't look after
democracy, if we don't share the idea and
the values of the democracy, we will certainly
lose it, So it would be best and good for
me to continue to talk to my people about
the importance of democracy and what is it
important for me and my people to hold on
tight to the government and to do the democratic
system of government, because that allows
everyone in our place to look after themselves,
freedom to move, freedom of speech.
You can do anything.
Premier: But in a communist country that we
are now seeing gripping in the country at
the moment, there are other things you are
not allowed to do, and there are things you
are not allowed to mention, even if you have
the right to do it.
So looking after democracy, one way of doing
it is to get people to a festival that they
will hear from our people that will talk about
the system of democracy and the principles
and the values that we hold dear to our hearts.
So it's good for me to encourage my people
to come and have heard some people who talk
about democracy so they can pass it to the
future generation of our place.
Chris: I've heard rumors that when you return
to the Solomon Islands, you may be put on
trial for treason.
Why do you think that is?
And what are you risking going back?
What would happen if you were put on trial
for treason?
Premier: In terms of the rumors about my arrest
from here, that they will arrest me on my
arrival, but I'm yet to see what part of the
laws in the countries that I breached in coming
to get a treatment here in Taiwan.
So they have that idea, and they told, they
going to the newspaper, and they wrote it
in newspaper that I will be arrested on arrival.
So we are still yet to find out whether this
information is true from the government or
it's just rumors, but we will see what will
happen when I go back to the country, Solomon
Islands.
Chris: Well, best of luck to you.
This is an important fight.
Beijing's influence really is expanding.
And it, as you say, it brings more authoritarianism.
It doesn't bring the nice infrastructure development
that they promise.
It brings people potentially being put on
trial for treason for getting necessary medical
help.
Premier: With that, from my view, because
I've heard that there are people in China
who attended medical here in Taiwan, and if
they are also charged for treason for coming
here for their medical treatment in here.
So I was at first a patient from the Solomon
Islands, a sick patient.
That is why I am here, for medical treatments.
So I don't see anywhere in the laws of the
country that I broke to come to have a treatment
here in Taiwan.
But we will see what the charges is or was
when I go back to the country because they
are promising to arrest me.
So I'm prepared for anything that comes on
my way back home.
And because I know for sure my coming is not
on any political business.
I am here for medical treatments only.
So that is my purpose for being here in Taiwan.
Chris: Well, thank you very much for taking
the time to join us today.
I know I and everyone watching you is going
to be following your story very closely.
Premier: Thank you very much.
And thank you for watching.
Be sure to follow China Uncensored on facebook,
instagram and twitter, where we’ll keep
you updated about Premier Suidani’s story.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next
time.