On this episode of China Uncensored,
it’s the end of the world as we know it!
And I feel fine.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
War between the US and China.
Many of you might think it would go like this.
“AMERICA!…”
Good luck, yeah.
Because that’s probably not going to happen.
And according to this report from the RAND
corporation,
it would actually be “ruinous,” “intense,”
and “destructive.”
And it would also probably be long and drawn
out.
Sounds familiar, somehow.
By the way, "thinking through the unthinkable"
apparently describes both war with China
and Jared Leto's method acting.
Anyway, back to the more appealing subject,
a War with China.
The report was commissioned by the US Army.
They love a good game of worst-case scenario.
Which is why the Pentagon actually has a plan
for a Zombie Outbreak.
And one of the report’s authors
is former chief intelligence adviser to Barack
Obama, David C. Gompert.
So, depending on your political leanings,
he either knows exactly what he’s talking
about
or is a complete idiot.
The report does acknowledge
that a war between the US and China is very
unlikely.
But even though the US’s military lead on
China
right now may look like Usain Bolt,
in ten years, the US might not be awkwardly
smiling.
China’s A2/AD
—or anti-access and area denial—
technology is making breakthroughs.
And by “making breakthroughs,”
I mean successfully knocking off technology
that China steals from the US.
China's A2/AD technology includes things
like land-attack and anti-ship ballistic and
cruise missiles,
a surface-to-air missile network,
and anti-satellite weapons.
Plus things like cyber warfare
and China's lesser known psychological warfare
tactics.
Like this secret experimental government footage
shows.
As you can see,
that Chinese opera cover of Rolling in the
Deep
has been carefully and highly weaponized.
And what has the US developed in this critical
field?
Wow, it's hard to tell which is more destructive.
And as China's technological breakthroughs
continue,
it will be, as the report says,
“increasingly difficult for the United States
to gain military-operational dominance and
victory,
even in a long war.”
“By 2025, U.S. losses could range from significant
to heavy.”
And this would be,
“a prolonged and destructive, yet inconclusive,
war.”
The good news is the report suggests
that neither side would be willing to use
nuclear weapons.
I mean, this isn’t a game of Civilization
with a rampaging Gandhi.
But there are plenty of hotspots for war with
China.
And each side is incentivized to strike first.
In other words, if something goes wrong,
like a Chinese vessel accidentally fires
on a Japanese ship in the East China Sea,
it doesn’t pay to take a moment and think
rationally.
After all, only the fate of the world hangs
in the balance.
However, not everyone agrees with the prediction
that China’s military is catching up to
the US,
or will be there even by the year 2025.
Sure, China has upped its military spending
to 155 billion dollars a year.
But America still spends about four times
as much.
And I hope at least a few billion of that
goes to developing military-grade earplugs.
So what do you think?
Would war with China be worse than the zombie
apocalypse?
How should the US respond to the threat of
weaponized Chinese opera?
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.