On this episode of China Uncensored,
China’s top actress has disappeared!
Or maybe has been disappeared.
China threatens more tariffs on the US,
in retaliation for US retaliation.
And a virus is infecting millions of Chinese
pigs.
I guess I’ll be taking a break from double-cooked
pork.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Chinese superstar actress Fan Bingbing seems
to have disappeared.
That’s Fan Bingbing who played Blink in
X-Men: Days of Future Past.
She’s the highest paid actress in China,
and the fifth-highest paid actress in the
world.
But since late July,
the 36-year-old actress hasn’t been seen
in public,
or really anywhere that people seem to know
about.
Her Weibo account has been silent.
No new dresses.
Not even a cute cat.
There’s also no word about why she’s gone.
But the Chinese internet loves speculation.
The current rumor is that she’s been abducted
by authorities for tax evasion.
I mean, she could be chillin’ on a beach
somewhere.
We don’t know.
But in May, a presenter on Chinese state television
leaked
a pair of contracts that supposedly showed
Fan Bingbing
double-billing for a production.
Basically, she had two contracts covering
the same work.
“The documents appeared to reveal an arrangement,
known as ‘yin-yang’ contracts,
wherein one contract reflects an actor’s
actual earnings
while a second, lower figure is submitted
to tax authorities.”
So it’s possible she’s been abducted because
authorities plan
to use her as a warning to other actors:
Pay your taxes, or else!
Fan’s disappearance is probably less dire
than that of the thousands of human rights
lawyers,
religious believers, and other dissidents
who are “disappeared” on a regular basis
by the Communist Party.
But it does show the overall repressiveness
of the system in China.
After all, if Kim Kardashian or Beyonce
wasn’t seen in public for two months,
no one would think they were being secretly
held
by the US government.
Too bad Fan Bingbing can’t teleport her
way out of detention.
In a move that’s been a long time in the
making,
the US Justice Department is requiring China’s
two biggest state run media companies—
Xinhua and China Global Television Network—
to register as foreign agents.
Over the past year, two Russian outlets,
RT and Sputnik, have also been required
to register as foreign agents.
What this means is there’ll be more limitations
to press credentials for all these media.
They’ll have less access to lawmakers and
other US officials.
This is causing a bit of a debate.
There are the free speech activists—
who don’t like the government deciding
what counts as journalism and what counts
as propaganda.
Then there’s national security experts—
who are happy these state-backed propaganda
outlets
are getting a little more scrutiny.
The law in question is the Foreign Agents
Registration Act.
It was created in 1938 to tackle covert Nazi
propaganda in the US.
But it was rarely used after World War 2.
Until recently.
Of course, state-run China Daily, who’s
distribution company
has long been registered as a foreign agent,
has not been that inconvenienced.
Why, you can see their newspaper boxes dotting
the streets
of major US cities like New York.
China is retaliating in the trade war with
new tariffs
on 60 billion dollars of American goods.
Which is a predictable response to the US’s
response...
to China’s earlier response to the original
US tariffs...
which were a response to China being a big
fat cheater.
President Trump commented on China’s latest
tariffs,
saying, “If there’s retaliation against
our farmers
and our industrial workers and our ranchers,
if any of that goes on
we are going to kick in another $257 billion.
We don’t want to do it,
but we’ll probably have no choice.”
Later he clarified he actually meant 267 billion
dollars.
But anyway, it’s not exactly tit for tat.
Since the US buys more from China than China
buys from the US,
the US is able to hit China with bigger tariffs.
And if the new tariffs Trump is threatening
go into effect,
tariffs would cover the majority of all US-China
trade.
So for all of you who wanted to boycott Made
in China products,
looks like a lot more people will be forced
to join you.
A deadly African swine fever is sweeping across
at least seven Chinese provinces.
The virus has killed at least 40,000 pigs.
It’s become a major disruption to China’s
pork industry.
And more importantly, it’s super gross!
And not gross in a cool way,
like that glow-in-the-dark pork from a few
years ago.
The good news is that the swine fever outbreak
is way too big to cover up.
So it’s forced Chinese authorities to address
it,
and state media to report on it.
But just to be clear,
state media says, it’s an African swine
fever.
And it’s happening despite China’s strict
controls.
And again, please remember that this is
not some kind of Chinese disease.
It’s “been circulating in neighboring
countries for a long time”.
The virus can apparently live in pork products,
including ham and salami, for a month or more.
And one of the reasons the infection has spread
globally
is that “pigs can become infected
if they eat contaminated food scraps.”
Wait, does this mean pigs are eating...pork?
Well, at least they’re not forcing Muslims
to eat pork.
Oh.
There is one piece of good news, though.
The virus only kills pigs, and not humans.
So while pork prices in China are going up—
you know, because so much of the supply is
dying—
at least it’s still safe to eat bacon.
Well, as safe as it ever was.
And finally, a “nightmare” incident between
Chinese tourists and Swedish police.
At least according to state-run media.
A Chinese family of three tried
to check into a hotel in Stockholm,
but apparently hadn’t made reservations
for that night.
So the hotel staff turned them away.
The Chinese family refused to leave,
and insisted on sleeping in the lobby.
So the staff called the police,
who used what the Chinese son described as
“excessive violence” on the family.
See for yourself.
“This is killing!
This is killing!”
It’s basically murder.
Just look at this cry for help!
Wow, he could be a professional soccer player.
All this, of course,
has blown up massively on the Chinese internet.
And China's Ministry of Foreign Affairs has
expressed concern
about the safety and legitimate rights
of all Chinese citizens visiting Sweden.
Which makes sense.
No one treats Chinese citizens worse than
the police in Sweden.
And before we go, it’s that time when I
answer questions
from China Uncensored fans who support the
show on Patreon,
the crowdfunding website.
Uchida O. asks
“Hi, Chris.
While Tibet is strategically advantageous,
wouldn't a complete pull-out go a long way
to making it appear
as though China is interested in human rights
and democracy?
What do you guys think it would it take
for the CCP to relinquish Tibet?”
Well, unfortunately for the people of Tibet,
the Chinese Communist Party will never, ever
let Tibet go.
It’s too strategically valuable.
For one, there’s gold in them there hills!
Or at least a variety of minerals and rare
earth elements.
Then there’s the border security that comes
with controlling Tibet.
I
t’s impossible to move an army through the
Himalayas.
But if the Chinese Communist Party didn’t
control Tibet,
then it wouldn’t have the Himalayas to protect
China’s western border.
And then there’s the fact that most of Asia’s
rivers start in Tibet.
That gives whoever controls Tibet tremendous
power over
all the surrounding nations.
If the Communist Party gave up Tibet,
then someone else would control the source
of these rivers—
including China’s rivers.
If you’d like to learn more about this topic,
see our episode Why China Will Never Allow
a Free Tibet.
Link is below.
Thanks for your question, Uchida.
And if you want to see your question on the
show,
become a member of the China Uncensored 50-cent
army on Patreon,
for as little as a dollar per episode.
Link is below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Well, sorry to say, that’s the end of another
China Uncensored.
But this isn’t goodbye!
Hit that subscribe button and turn the notification
bell on
so you know when we have more episodes.
And more episodes we will have.
A new one comes out every Monday,
Wednesday, Friday and sometimes Saturday!