Christmas in China is...
a little different
The Western holiday has taken on some new
traditions in China.
Today we’ll show you 7 ways China got Christmas
wrong
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Christmas.
The only time of the year when people come
together,
regardless of our differences,
to celebrate diabetes.
Now sure, the meaning of Christmas
has changed a bit over the years.
From celebrating the birth of Christ,
to celebrating all the stuff we can buy.
But the real meaning of Christmas changes
even more
when something gets lost in translation.
And this is especially true in China.
So here are 7 ways China got Christmas wrong.
Number 7
Christmas Apples
A Chinese Christmas tradition is handing out
these fancy cellophane wrapped Christmas apples.
They usually have a message printed on them,
like Merry X-mass...
...or I love you.
The reason for apples is because
the Chinese word for Christmas eve is Ping’an
ye,
which means a safe or peaceful night.
Apple is pingguo.
Different “ping”,
but it sounds like of like “fruit of peace.”
How do you like them apples?
Number 6
Holiday Confusion
In China, Christmas isn’t really the religious
and/or family holiday it is in the US.
That’s because the big family holiday in
China
is the Lunar New Year.
And no one in any culture wants to have to
travel back home
to spend time with their family more than
once a year.
Twice at most, if there’s turkey.
Plus, no one gets Christmas Day off of work.
Instead, everyone gets two weeks off for Lunar
New Year,
which is great because you definitely want
to take a vacation
along with 1.3 billion other people.
Anyway, all of that is why Christmas in China
is more of a hanging out with friends holiday.
Like Saint Patrick’s Day,
with less drinking.
Or New Year’s Eve,
with less...drinking.
Or for those with a sweetheart,
like Valentine's Day.
With more...trees.
It’s also one of the biggest shopping days
of the year.
So we have that in common.
But that brings us to…
Number 5
Christmas Dinner
So if people aren’t traveling to have
a big home-cooked meal with extended family,
what will they eat for Christmas dinner?
That’s where Western fast food chains
have stepped in to fill the gap.
After all, who wouldn’t want to
celebrate Christmas with this?
A classic Christmas turkey...pizza,
or a steak pizza,
or a shrimp pizza.
Yum.
Yes, Pizza Hut,
that is indeed a taste surprise.
And if I have too much turkey pizza,
I might even be willing to join in on...
Number 4
An actual war on Christmas
Twas the night before Christmas,
and all through the house,
hostile foreign forces were lying in wait
in order to undermine China.
At least according to some people.
“Christmas-bashers in China warn against
allowing Western culture to contaminate Chinese
civilization.”
For example, in 2006,
there was an open letter from Chinese intellectuals
warning that Christmas was just another tactic
in the West’s soft power invasion of China.
They warned,
"[Christmas celebrators in China] are doing
what
western missionaries dreamed to do
but didn't succeed in doing 100 years ago."
The letter added,
"Chinese people need to treat Christmas cautiously,
and support the dominance of our own culture."
One city “banned any Christmas-related events
or celebrations in the city's schools,
kindergartens and universities,
despite there being a Christian population
of over one million there.”
Another city had banners saying
“‘oppose kitsch foreign festivals’
and ‘stop Western culture from expanding.’”
They’ll be happy to know the Communist Party
is way ahead of them.
Number 3
War on Christians
The officially atheist Communist Party
has never been a fan of Christians.
Or really, any ideology or belief
that competes for the love of the people.
Because you can’t be both a Communist Party
member
and a religious believer.
And for non-Party members,
if you want to be Christian,
you have to worship at state-approved churches—
or face severe persecution.
And even if you do go to a state-approved
church,
there’s always the chance authorities will
come along
and tear down your cross.
Or make you take down pictures of Jesus
and replace them with pictures of Xi Jinping.
But you know what makes a great stocking stuffer?
Xi Jinping thought for a new era.
Speaking of stocking stuffers...
Number 2
Santa’s helpers
No, I’m not talking about how in China,
Santa’s helpers aren’t his elves.
They’re his “sisters.”
Something has definitely been lost in translation
there.
But anyway, it turns out the real Santa’s
workshop
isn’t in the North Pole.
It’s in China.
China makes a large percentage of the Christmas
decorations
and presents for the rest of the world.
So much for elves.
And Chinese state-run media don’t want you
to forget it.
“American fellows,
it is Christmas time,
a time to wake up,
have a strong cup of coffee,
and see what gifts a Chinese Santa Claus really
delivers.”
You see, some people might start thinking
that Made in China is a bad thing,
and state-run media wants you to know that
it’s great.
Well, it’s great for you.
Maybe not for the Chinese factory workers
who make everything.
That does not look healthy.
But strangely,
Chinese state-run media don’t seem to have
mentioned
how Christmas items might even be made
in Chinese labor camps.
Or prisons.
Importing products made from prison slave
labor
is illegal in the US, by the way.
But Chinese prisons manage to get away with
it
by hiding in the supply chain.
You know, once Santa finds out,
those prisons are definitely getting coal
in their stockings.
The stockings that they forced prisoners to
make.
Which brings us to...
Number 1
Smooth Jazz Santa
Even the most recognizable symbol of Christmas
has developed Chinese characteristics.
You see, in China, Santa plays the sax.
Maybe he and the little drummer boy
can get together and form a jazz duo.
But why does Santa play the saxophone?
The Washington Post devoted an entire article
to this mystery
and still couldn’t solve it.
The closest they got was that
“it may have to do with Chinese perceptions
of the saxophone
as romantic and cool.”
Saxophones are romantic and cool?
That explains why China is the only country
in the world
where people still like Kenny G.
The Washington Post writer also theorized
that maybe Bill Clinton’s saxophone playing
in the early nineties
inspired the saxophone Santas.
That seems a little far-fetched to me.
But if true,
we should all be glad that it was early nineties
Bill Clinton.
Because if it was late nineties Bill Clinton,
Santa would have been holding a cigar.
So what do you think about China’s Christmas
traditions?
And let me know what your favorite weird Christmas
tradition
is in the comments below.
Mine is listening to the Christmas Rap by
Crew X,
which my friends and I found in the 99 cent
store.
And don’t go anywhere,
because now is the time when I answer a question
from a member of the China Uncensored 50 cent
army,
fans who support China Uncensored
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
Vanities aks,
“My wife is a bit worried about ever saying
too much on Wechat
because of what the government might do to
her family.
Have you ever heard of families of outspoken
Chinese in America
ever being harassed back in China?”
You know, I hate to say it,
but your wife is probably right to be worried.
WeChat has some serious privacy issues,
which is why a lot of people are suggesting
you delete it.
The problem is,
WeChat is used by 800 million users in China,
so it is a gateway to China.
But the Chinese Communist Party has access
to everything you do on WeChat.
One report told the Committee to Protect Journalists,
“They believe officials accessed their WeChat
account
to surveil the journalist.
The reporter said that after using WeChat
to discuss visiting a friend in another city,
local community officers approached the friend's
family
and warned them not to let the journalist
stay.”
So that shows the Party is willing and able
to not only monitor you,
but also go after the people you chat with.
Private chat groups aren’t safe either.
Now those previous examples were about people
who were inside China using WeChat.
And there have been several cases of people
being jailed
or detained for what they wrote on WeChat,
again, in China.
I am not aware of any cases where someone
using
WeChat outside China has had their family
members
harassed in China.
But security experts say that WeChat outside
China
is just as insecure,
and can be monitored by the Chinese authorities.
And there have definitely been cases of Chinese
authorities
harassing the family members of Chinese dissidents
who are outside China.
So your wife should be careful with WeChat.
Thanks for your question, Vanities.
And remember,
if you want to have your question answered
on the show,
sign up to support us on the crowd funding
website Patreon.
Go to pateron.com/chinauncensored.
And a special Christmas thank you
from all of us at China Uncensored
to all the amazing supporters of China Uncensored
who’ve kept our show going all year.
Merry Christmas and a Happy New Year
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.