On this episode of China Uncensored,
welcome to the Danger Zone!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
A Chinese-American woman has been sentenced
to 50 months in prison
for, quote,
“conspiring to export and cause to export”
a few small items.
Little things,
like several advanced US fighter jet engines.
As well as a Reaper Drone
the kind that shoots Hellfire missiles.
I mean,
Christmas shopping is hard
when you’re buying for the Chinese Communist
Party.
They’re the regime that has everything
because they’ve already knocked it off.
Unfortunately for 45-year-old Wenxia Man,
also known as “Wency,”
she tried to buy her jet engines and Reaper
Drone
missiles sold separately
from someone who turned out to be
a Homeland Security agent.
It’s illegal to sell US weapons to China,
since the US government has had an arms embargo
in place since 1989.
I wonder why that happened.
But perhaps Wency Man’s biggest crime
was introducing the world to the name “Wency.”
I mean, what’s next?
Beberly?
Elizabreth?
Wait, what’s that, Shelley?
Oh.
Moving on.
According to court documents,
Man worked with a man whom she called a “technology
spy.”
Who was a spy?
What?
No, she didn’t work with Hu.
No!
When did I say Xi worked with Hu?
The spy’s name is Zhang Xinsheng!
And while Wency Man is in prison,
he’s safely inside China.
He “worked on behalf of the Chinese military
to copy items obtained from other countries,”
according to the official press release by
the US Department of Justice.
The Chinese regime was offering 50 million
dollars,
a million which would go to Wency Man.
And considering the maximum penalty she faced
was 20 years in prison,
she got off pretty easy
with just over a 4 year sentence.
The Chinese regime has been rapidly building
up its military.
But there are major technological gaps that
they haven’t figured out yet.
So why not just steal and replicate the technology
from countries that already have it, right?
China has particular problems designing jet
engines.
They have lots of little parts that move really
fast.
That’s the technical explanation.
And that’s why
“engines accounted for 30% of all its imports,
according to the Stockholm International Peace
Research Institute.”
Now this is shocking.
Imagine if the United States had to spend
billions
buying jet engines from Europe.
That wouldn’t instill too much confidence
in the latest multi-million dollar jet fighters
the US is rolling out,
like the F-35.
But that’s what the Chinese military has
to do.
Last November, the Chinese regime spent 2
billion dollars
to buy 24 Russian Su-35 fighter jets.
This is even when,
supposedly,
they have their own fighter jets
that should be capable of matching them.
But it turns out China’s air force gets
a lot of packages
marked “From Russia: With Love.”
One of the reasons the Chinese regime is so
dependent
on Russian and stolen US military tech is
say it with me
corruption.
In this article by the Epoch Times,
a manager at the Shenyang Aircraft Corp spelled
it out.
Company executives embezzled 16 million dollars
every year.
I mean,
why pay for expensive experts
when you can hire temp workers from 8 different
factories,
none of whom have the necessary training?
And since they were working on key parts to
the J-8 fighter jets,
Shenyang Aircraft Corp had to have repair
teams
on hand in case anything went wrong.
This is one reason why the Chinese military
has to steal.
They even steal for their movies.
Wait,
the Chinese military makes movies?
Check out Sky Fighters,
China’s 2011 answer to the 1986 American
movie
Top Gun.
There’s the runway scene,
the flying upside down scene
and the gifting of tampons to the female pilot
scene.
Oh wait,
that was just Sky Fighters.
And so when Wency Man,
running a struggling tech company in California
with her husband,
gets approached with a million dollar deal
to be a Chinese spy,
we really know that is the best China’s
military has to offer.
So what do you think about the case of Wency
Man?
And what can be done to stop the Chinese regime
from stealing US technology?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time!