Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I'm your host, Chris Chappell
I here, outside Hong Kong's legislative council building,
also known as LegCo.
In Hong Kong, some of the biggest news over the past few weeks
has been the oath-taking scandal.
Two newly-elected pro-indendence Hong Kong lawmakers
Sixtus Baggio Leung and Yau Wai-ching,
from the Youngspiration party,
took their oaths to join Hong Kong's Legislative Council.
But they brought out flags that said Hong Kong is Not China,
called Hong Kong a nation,
and referred to mainland China using a slur
used by the Japanese in World War II.
That did not go over very well.
The the controversy escalated when China's National People's Congress
issued a rare "interpretation" of Hong Kong's Basic Law
that effectively disqualified both elected lawmakers from taking office.
Now, Hong Kong chief executive and daywalking vampire CY Leung
has suggested implementing Article 23,
a Draconian national security law
that would basically allow Chinese police to go after anyone in Hong Kong
accused of “subversion.”
It would make Hong Kong’s freedoms look closer to those in Beijing.
CY Leung's government dropped another bombshell
when it announced it wants to disqualify four other pro-democracy lawmakers
who protested while taking their oaths of office.
Unlike the Youngspiration duo,
these lawmakers' oaths were accepted by LegCo
and they are already in office.
Don't worry, though,
the government promises there were "no political considerations involved" in their decision.
One of the targeted lawmakers is well-known activist Leung Kwok-hung,
also called Long Hair.
He’s clearly guilty of subversion,
because when he took his oath of office,
he held a yellow umbrella,
a symbol of the Umbrella Movement, and called for universal suffrage.
I sat down to interview this hostile subversive force earlier last week,
before the government announced it would try to remove him from office.
Mr. Leung, thank you for joining me today.
I know you're also known as "Long Hair."
Why is that?
Well, you can see it!
What can you call me when you see I wear this length of hair?
So, "Long Hair."
Is there a nickname you could give me, based on my physical appearance?
So you've lived in Hong Kong your entire life,
you've been a member of the Legislative Council for twelve years,
How have you seen the political situation in Hong Kong change over the years?
What happened after the PRC joined the WTO
their attitude toward Hong Kong,
or more precisely, their global strategy, has changed.
So you think that gave them the feeling that they could flex their muscles a little more?
Yes, yes, yes...
Now I heard rumors that recently there was a fight in the Legislative Council
that involved luncheon meat.
It sounds like you guy have a little more fun than the US legislature. Is that true?
The story is that, since I was a major filibuster,
a legislator from the pro-Beijing side -
he claimed that if I do the filibusting,
Per minute, it cost a lot of money,
he counted it by the luncheon meats.
That's why. I showed them the luncheon meat,
"You need to pay back the luncheon meat."
And then I throw it to them,
And they throw it back.
It's like a volleyball game or whatever.
If it really were about money, wouldn't you have thrown a more expensive cut of meat?
I know you were a big supporter of the Umbrella Movement.
How do you feel about it now, two years later?
I think a lot of people
got their first empowerment in their own life.
Hundreds of thousands of people turned to the streets
and blocked the roads for almost 80 days.
But the government didn't respond.
And eventually, the occupation died down.
And I think a lot of people, young people,
they feel very frustrated.
So I want to talk about the latest political issue in Hong Kong.
What's been the reaction in the Legislative Council
to Beijing's "interpretation" of Hong Kong Basic Law?
Well, I mean,
In the very beginning, we all know that it's a fake
because we're talking about rule of law.
The first thing you talk about is the constitution.
Okay, so,
the construction of the constitution was done by someone else
which is far away from our community.
So, you know, rule of law didn't really emerge.
Neither under the British rule, nor under the Chinese rule.
Do you think Yau Wai-ching and Baggio Leung crossed the line with their oath-taking?
At the end of the day, whether they're politically correct or politically right,
we need to pay full attention to facts that
they were chosen by tens of thousands of voters.
That is very important. That is
the essence of democracy.
Free choice, in a fair way, in a public procedure.
And justice.
And do you think their behavior can represent the young people of Hong Kong?
Partially. That's politics.
You can't represent all the people all the time.
So you also creatively took your oath.
Would you mind saying what you did?
It was in 2004,
and I wanted to change the content of the oath.
And someone told me you cannot do this.
And the government was very concerned, and I went to court,
and asked for judicial review.
Their opinion was that I cannot change the oath.
But I can add something before and after.
So I did it.
Of course I changed the slogan,
and bring a dress code that was different.
A yellow umbrella, which is a symbol of the Umbrella Movement.
So it's a protest.
And I know at least two other people from pro-Beijing organizations
have called for other lawmakers, pan-democrat lawmakers,
to be disqualified for their oaths, including you.
Are you worried about losing... - Six of them.
Six of them.
Not just two, it's six.
I mean, as I say, they talk.
If a government or something above the government
tried to tell the people of Hong Kong,
"Oh, this guy got your mandate, but I don't like him - he should go,"
I think it's totally irrational.
Because if you go to a rally, it's the most solemn thing in your life.
If you didn't say the oath proper,
and the officer will tell you, "please repeat it,"
What's so wrong about it?
If it's not okay, you should tell the oath taker
to do it again.
Because the most important thing is the mandate.
So are you worried at all about losing your seat?
No, why should you worry about it?
Can you worry about the rain?
And then the rain will not come down? I don't think so.
So at the end of the day, you think it's the people that have the power to make a change.
Yes!
They are the master! Who is the master of the master?
Come on...
And in response to the oath-taking controversy,
Chief Executive CY Leung has talked about reviving
the draconian anti-subversion law, Article 23.
Do you think there's a chance Article 23 could be implemented?
I don't know. I don't think it's the right time anyway.
I think
In 2003,
the Chinese side wanted to make the legislation through the Hong Kong legislature - why?
Because they promised Hong Kong people might have the opportunity
to enjoy universal suffrage after the 10th anniversary of the handover.
So in 2007, 2008, there may be a thing called universal suffrage in Hong Kong.
Okay, so what they want you to do is the legislation of Article 23 in order to secure that,
the candidate of the Chief Executive would be in control politically.
And then they fell.
And then, now, they change.
They're not so keen on the implementation of Article 23.
But they denied the universal suffrage.
So if - IF - the Chinese side wanted to do the, quote unquote,
implementation of universal suffrage, they would do the same thing. That's okay.
I would like to have the interpretation of Article 23
first, and then you might have some kind of, quote unquote, universal suffrage.
So I think they would like to try something.
What do you think that would mean for Hong Kong?
Well, it's like a sword just above your head.
That's hanging on a very thin hair.
One thin Long Hair.
Well, Mr. Leung, I really appreciate you taking the time
to be interviewed by us.
As a token of our thanks, I'd like to present you with
some luncheon meat.
Oh! Terrific!
I will save it, if they are going to,
my colleagues, the loyalists, are going to
walk out of the chamber in order to boycott the meeting,
they will enjoy your present.
I would say thank you, for them to you, very much.
Tell them it comes from China Uncensored.
Oh, terrific. Thank you very much indeed.
Thank you, thank you, thank you.
Thank you for the luncheon meat.