Hong Kong is under attack!
The Chinese Communist Party
is imposing its tyranny on the city
But the resistance is on the rise
This
is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Can music change the world?
Who knows?
But it might be able to at least change Hong
Kong.
That’s what Denise Ho hopes.
She’s is one of the biggest pop stars in
Hong Kong.
She also had a huge following in Mainland
China.
But she put all that at risk
by joining the 2014 Umbrella Movement,
a student led movement
to bring democracy to Hong Kong.
The movement was not well received by those
in power.
For resisting Beijing’s pressure,
Denise Ho found herself on the wrong side
of the law.
And then the Chinese Communist Party
canceled her tours in China,
and blocked her social media accounts.
But that hasn’t stopped her
from standing up for human rights.
I sat down with Denise Ho at the Oslo Freedom
Forum
to talk about the future of Hong Kong.
Thanks for joining me today Denise.
Thank you!
Thank you.
So recently two people from Hong Kong
have come out to say that they got asylum
in Germany.
How does it feel to have Hong Kong be a place
that people get asylum from now?
Well, you know, it's pretty ironic
because right now we are in faced of this
extradition law.
Yeah.
That is, you know, that Hong Kong government
is trying to impose on us.
But next week, actually,
we will be having a very big protest in Hong
Kong.
So, you know, we are fighting still
after five years from the Umbrella Movement
even though it's a pretty dim situation right
now in Hong Kong
since we try to shout out our opinions
but the Hong Kong government is just not listening.
Do you think it's possible to get a fair trial
in Hong Kong now?
I mean there's been legislators
that who have been kicked out of office,
Umbrella Movement leaders who have been arrested
and detained.
Is the court still free?
Well it really depends, you know,
which judge you get.
Okay.
Well that is my opinion.
If you are lucky, fortunate enough,
then you might get a judge that is unbiased,
and then he or she would look at the facts.
But from my point of view I think that some
of the trials
that went on during these five years were
quite biased.
Say for the Mong Kok Fishball Revolution,
you heard of it?
I have, why don't you say it for the audience?
For the Mong Kok Fishball Revolution
there were students and young generations
who were sentenced for up to seven or eight
years.
So, I mean, they probably had to be prosecuted
for the hassle that happened that night.
But is it fair to have such a heavy sentence?
We compare it a lot to what happened in 1967
when there was a revolution back then
with homemade bombs and all that,
and even back then the sentences
were not as strong as it is now.
And just recently the Umbrella Nine,
the activists who were involved in the Umbrella
Movement,
they were prosecuted and also sentenced for
a lesser sentence,
but still they were sentenced for half a year
or so.
But the fact is the Umbrella Movement
was not really started because of them,
they were just put on to the stage
just for intimidating the Hong Kong people
so that we won't get into another revolution
like the Umbrella Movement.
I know were Cantopop singers who openly came
out
in support of the Umbrella Movement,
and at the time the South China Morning Post
said that was career suicide.
So what made you do that?
Well it was really the, you know, the picture...
It was the moment when I saw the police the
87 tear gas bombs
onto the peaceful protesters that, you know,
I was just so angry at that moment.
It might seem not much for other places
where you get tear gas bombed all the time,
but for Hong Kong we never saw
such a harsh reaction from the government.
And the fact that the people who were on the
streets,
you know they were just every day, normal
people.
They had nothing, they had no weapons whatsoever,
and for the police to react in such a way,
it was so...
We got so angry and we were so frustrated
and the emotions that came out that day.
And on that moment I decided just I don't
care anymore
about repercussions that might come if I spoke
out.
So was it career suicide?
Half, half.
Half suicide.
Half suicide on the glamorous and extravagant
side
where I would get commercials and, you know,
the easy revenue that came from China.
That was totally cut off.
Yeah, you couldn't tour as much in China or
at all.
I can not even get into China.
I was banned totally,
and I was labeled "Hong Kong poison."
That's right.
But on the other hand,
I started my revolution of my own in the entertainment
business.
And in 2016,
when I was supposed to have a concert in the
Hong Kong Coliseum,
the biggest venue in Hong Kong.
And normally you would have sponsors backing
you up,
buying some of the tickets,
and I got none of that,
so what I did was I started a campaign
to crowd sponsor the concert.
And I broke up, you know,
like if normally the sponsorships
would be one million Hong Kong dollars,
then I broke it up into super small pieces
and I offered it to local businesses.
And in the end we got 300 local businesses
who backed us,
and also 50,000 sold out in hours.
That's incredible.
I almost wish more western businesses would
hear that,
so they might think twice about
"oh there are options beside just [crosstalk]”
Yeah there are, there are actually.
You know, well on the other hand
is because I have a strong fan base,
so I was pretty confident that
even when I'm banned from China
they would be supporting me.
But the key is you have to,
you have to be really flexible.
You can not ride on the old ways,
and you know you have to play a completely
different game
from what the traditional music scene is doing.
Well considering the levels of influence
the Chinese Communist Party is having in Hong
Kong,
have you ever considered singing mainly in
Mandarin anymore?
Well I did release two Mandarin albums,
but that was mainly for Taiwan,
you know the Taiwan market.
And also before the Umbrella Movement I was
touring in China.
I had this theater piece called,
what was it called?
And it was based-
Wait, the Dream of Black Mansions, Red Mansions?
Yeah, yeah.
And so I toured for three years in different
cities of China,
and I actually gathered quite a number of
fans
during the pre-Umbrella Movement years.
So the thing that I feel is a shame is that
I can not reach these fans as much right now,
but they get through, you know,
they find ways to get in touch with me.
Oh.
Yeah!
They have the VPNs in China,
and they just use that.
And, you know, you see all these comments
on Instagram, Facebook, and they are the support
from China,
but also at the same time the...
We call them the 50 Cents, like those who-
On China Uncensored we know all about the
50 Cent Army.
But it's quite ironic because they have to
get through the wall to come [crosstalk]
On the platforms banned in China to criticize
you.
Yes that is funny [crosstalk]
Well to criticize "Hong Kong poison," you
know, it's worth it.
So I know your family originally fled China
to Hong Kong
to escape the Chinese Communist Party
and when it got close to the handover
they went to Quebec, right?
Yes.
Why did you go back to Hong Kong?
Well this is something that my dad always...
you know, he's on me all the time
because they used up a sum of money for us
to get away from Hong Kong,
and then I was the reason that now
everyone is back in Hong Kong because of me.
But the reason why I decided to go back to
Hong Kong
was my attachment to the Cantonese,
the Cantopop, music scene as my childhood,
teenage idol was the Cantopop diva, Anita
Mui.
And so in 1996,
I decided to get back to Hong Kong
to do the contest that she did 15 years ago.
And by accident I won.
What do you mean by accident you won?
Well, you know, I was just a fan chasing my
idol
and I just wanted to get in touch with her,
try to get the glimpse of her.
But of course I really loved singing and performing,
but the main reason was because I wanted to
see my idol.
Yeah, but fate happened and I won,
and so I stayed in Hong Kong since 1997.
So I went back from 1997
and I started my music career since then.
How many years ago?
15? 20ish?
I know after the Umbrella Movement ended there
was sort of this idea that the young people
of Hong Kong
gave up or they were defeated, is that true?
In a way, yes, it was quite gloomy and difficult,
very difficult five years.
I mean at first...
I think the first two years people were still
fighting,
like people got really angry and frustrated,
and so there were different ways, you know?
Some people got very violent,
and well violent in the Hong Kong way.
And, you know, they were quite heavily criticized
by the pro-Beijing parties, which you know
they...
And they used that as a tool to-
To everyone.
Yes, yes.
And so that was when the prosecution
and the political reprisal happened.
And all those names that were detained
and arrested during the Umbrella Movement
some of them were jailed
and some of them were sentenced to different
periods of time.
And these two years it's been quite depressing,
depressing time for the Hong Kong people
and especially the younger generations.
I have friends with families
who chose to leave once again the city
like when my family did [crosstalk] in the
80s.
And most of them are young families with young
children.
I could understand, you know,
I could relate to them because if I had children
right now,
I would be quite worried about what education
they would be getting from the communist Hong
Kong government.
There are much lesser discussion about
what people should do in these times
because in a way we have tried a lot of things
and it just didn't work
because we don't have the democracy system
that we wish we had.
And so the Hong Kong government they just...
they just do what they want, they just...
they are not listening,
and they are passing laws quite unjustifiably,
and they're changing laws
in favor of the Beijing government.
Well with the new extradition law
has that changed how people feel?
Because I know there was another big protest
that happened because of that.
Yes.
In a way yes.
The discussions are warming up now,
and personally I hope that after these different
periods
of frustration, disappointment
that people would come to realize
that this is a very long war.
This is a very long battle that can not be
won,
a very long battle that can not be won
just within one or two years.
It's a very difficult process
and I think Hong Kong people are learning,
and we are a population that is educated
to be quick and instantaneous.
So the sought and notion of patience we
are just not very much accustomed to that.
So we are learning to be more patient
and to work our way through these very difficult
issues.
And just a few weeks ago we had
the first protest for the extradition law,
and since the Umbrella movement that was
the first time that the number of people surpassed
100,000,
and you know that is encouraging for those
who had been still working hard at it.
And so hopefully the next protest on the ninth
of June
would gather more people,
and even though we know a protest
might not change a lot of things,
but personally I think it is a form of unity
and where,
you know, people can see each other
and then we can get back into that notion
of
"we are not alone."
And we are, we are still here, we are still
numbered.
And something can still be done.
What kind of support for Hong Kong
would you like to see in the international
community?
Well, you know, as someone who has been
banned and rejected by global brands,
I think there is power in international unity.
Because what we see is
people are afraid of losing the China market,
so brands and businesses they choose to not
speak out
and they choose to stand on the side of money.
So I think that if the international market...
they realize that there are other choices.
I don't mean we have to ignore the China market
that is just part of the international market.
And so when people realize that that is not
the only choice
and we have more important values
and things that we should focus on,
I think that might gradually be a force
that we could rely on each other to gain back
some of the values and the virtues are so
important to us.
So where do you see Hong Kong in 2047?
In 2047?
That is-
That's the big year?
Yeah, that is something that I really have
no answer for.
I know what the reality is,
but at the same time I am still optimistic,
in a way that even the tyrants,
the big machines,
there are people behind it.
And so in a way people make mistakes,
and people make decisions that dry things
in various ways.
So now how many years we have?
20ish?
I can't do that math.
Yeah.
And so a lot could happen in this period of
time
and I try to stay not positive but optimistic.
And I mean we have to keep this optimism.
We have to keep this sought that we can make
a change
even though it might be baby steps,
but I think the power is really within the
people
and if we do not give up then who knows
maybe something would change along the way.
Well I think that's a great note to end this
interview on.
Thank you so much for joining us.
Thank you, yeah.
And keep up the good work in Hong Kong.
Okay, thank you.