On this episode of China Uncensored,
Vice President Pence has a few words for China.
Ok, 4,000 words.
Have you heard about Google’s China scandal?
Then maybe you should Google it.
And finally, you can’t spell patriotism
without approval from the Party.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Last week,
Vice President Mike Pence gave China a real
pounding.
In a 40-minute speech at the Hudson Institute,
a prominent conservative think tank in Washington,
DC,
Vice President Pence laid out the case
against the Chinese Communist Party.
America had hoped that economic liberalization
would bring China into greater partnership
with us and with the world.
Instead, China has chosen economic aggression,
which has in turn emboldened its growing military.
I would play the entire 40-minute speech,
but instead let me summarize it in 30 seconds.
Pence talked about some issues that might
sound familiar.
Like intellectual property theft,
trade violations, military aggression—
basically it came off like
a 40 minute episode of China Uncensored.
But with less jokes.
What’s that Shelley?
Ok fine, with fewer jokes.
See?
We’re hilarious.
Pence also said the Chinese regime is trying
to
undermine democracy in the United States.
Worst of all, China has initiated an unprecedented
effort
to influence American public opinion,
the 2018 elections,
and the environment leading into
the 2020 presidential elections…
Now that’s something President Trump
also said at the UN Security Council.
If you haven’t been paying attention,
some of Pence’s speech might seem a little
exaggerated.
The Chinese Communist Party is rewarding
or coercing American businesses,
movie studios, universities, think tanks,
scholars, journalists, and local, state, and
federal officials.
I mean, that is a lot of people to reward
or coerce.
But as the Wall Street Journal puts it,
“This isn’t a casual accusation.
For months,
a team of national-security officials has
been compiling
a study on the many ways China uses money,
power and rewards to affect the way it is
viewed in the US.”
As I’m sure you can imagine,
the Chinese Communist Party was not happy
about
Pence spreading all these malicious rumors
to undermine China’s harmonious society.
Which is why state-run Xinhua ran this article
called,
“Not-so-Bright Rumor-Spreading:
a Critique of U.S. Leader Using Absurd Arguments
to Defame China.”
And Chinese Foreign Ministry Spokeswoman Hua
Chunying said,
“This is nothing but hearsay evidence,
confusing right and wrong and creating something
out of thin air.”
Thin air?
Then I’m a magician,
because I’ve made six years worth of YouTube
videos
out of this stuff.
Of course, who knows what the future
of China Uncensored is on YouTube?
Because there’s more unsettling news
out about YouTube’s owner Google—
and its relationship with the Chinese Communist
Party.
At the beginning of August,
a Google insider leaked a secret project Google
was working on called Dragonfly.
It’s a search engine that would censor all
the things
the Chinese Communist Party doesn’t want
people to know about.
Pence even mentioned it in his speech.
For example,
Google should immediately end development
of the “Dragonfly” app
that will strengthen Communist Party censorship
and compromise the privacy of Chinese customers…
Google has not publicly responded to questions
about Dragonfly.
The closest thing we got to a response
was Head of Google’s search Ben Gomes telling
the BBC,
“Right now all we’ve done is some exploration,
but since we don't have any plans to launch
something
there’s nothing much I can say about it.”
I mean, they don’t have any plans to launch
something so...
wait, what’s this?
Gomes wants to launch Dragonfly “as soon
as possible”?
And get it “brought off the shelf and quickly
deployed”?
That’s from a leaked transcript
where Gomes told Google employees
the exact opposite of what he later told the
BBC.
Now I’m not saying that Google would do
anything it takes to get into the China market.
Would they censor their search engine?
Who knows?
Even a top Google executive can’t seem to
figure out
whether the Chinese Communist Party censors
its citizens.
This Wednesday was National Day in Taiwan.
It celebrates the founding of the Republic
of China,
aka, the government of China that now occupies
Taiwan.
And what better way to celebrate...
than with a military drill!
They called it a quote “simulated invasion
by opposing force.”
No particular opposing force, though.
I mean, it could be the People’s Liberation
Army—
which has vowed to conquer Taiwan.
Or it could be aliens.
I mean really, either is possible.
By the way,
Pence also talked about Taiwan.
America will always believe Taiwan’s embrace
of democracy
shows a better path for all the Chinese people.
C’mon, Mr. Vice President!
Is there even anything left for me to talk
about?
Let’s see here...
Ah, Hong Kong.
You didn’t talk about Hong Kong!
And the good news is...
there’s bad news from Hong Kong.
It looks like Victor Mallet,
the Asia news editor for the Financial Times
as well as
the Vice President of Hong Kong’s Foreign
Correspondents Club,
had his media visa for Hong Kong cancelled.
Why?
Well, no official reason.
The Chinese Communist Party has promised
to honor the one country two systems policy,
where Hong Kong gets to keep freedoms
the rest of China never had.
And the Communist Party would never not honor
its promises.
But the mysterious decision to reject Victor
Mallet visa
did happen just weeks after the Foreign Correspondents
Club
hosted a talk by a Hong Kong activist Beijing
really doesn’t like.
The Chinese regime has denied visas
to several journalists in mainland China
over the last few years.
But this is the first time it’s happened
in Hong Kong.
Could this be yet another sign of the Chinese
Communist Party’s
increasing erosion of Hong Kong’s freedoms?
I’m sure everything is fine.
And in this lovely article from the Financial
Times,
I learned the Trump administration
won’t talk trade with China at the G20.
...unless Beijing makes a list of concessions
first.
And since the IMF says the trade war
is going to hit China harder than the US,
the Chinese regime might not have much of
a choice
but to make some concessions.
Not that they won’t drag this out as long
as possible.
And finally, Qin An,
the director of the China Institute of Cyberspace
Strategy,
has finally released a hit new single
about China’s cyberspace strategy!
I know, you’ve all been dying to hear it
it.
It’s creatively called “Cyberspace Strategy
Song.”
Let’s have a listen!
A new territory for national governance?
Cyberspace:
It’s been Chinese territory since ancient
times.
The song was written for the 2018 China Cybersecurity
Week.
Where China will send a panda into orbit!
OK, sometimes I don’t fact check.
I just believe what’s in my heart.
And this is not even the first
Chinese propaganda song about Cyberspace.
In 2015,
the Central Cyberspace Affairs Commision
had this song,
"The Mind and Spirit of Cyberspace Security."
The director of the the Central Cyberspace
Affairs Commision
is Xi Jinping,
who is also the chair of
the Central Military Commission.
So hopefully the military and the cyberspace
commission
can work together more.
Because cyberspace is a dangerous place.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And before you go,
now is the time when I answer questions from
you—
the loyal members of the China Uncensored
50-Cent Army
who support the show on the crowd funding
website Patreon.
Damian Shale asks,
“Chris, how did Matt, Shelley and you meet?
Also , when did you guys get the idea for
making the show?”
Well, I met Shelley when I was working
in Langley, Virginia on a farm.
She had been sent to...
help me buy the farm...
but I charmed her out of it.
Eventually, we teamed up and went rogue.
Kind of an A-Team situation,
helping people in need.
There was this one family in Guatemala
we rescued from being killed by narco traffickers.
The family couldn’t afford to pay us, though,
so they gave us Matt.
But Matt made the team a little too...
unwieldy to be an elite rescue squad,
so we naturally fell back on the next best
thing:
a China themed YouTube channel.
And the rest is history.
We’re thinking of optioning the movie rights
to Hollywood.
Thanks for you question.
And do you have a question you want to ask
me?
Then join the China Uncensored 50-Cent Army
on Patreon.
You’ll get some cool rewards for your contribution,
including having the chance to have me
answer your question on the show!
So sign up at patreon.com/chinauncensored.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
As I mentioned,
China Uncensored is supported mainly through
direct viewer contributions.
Go to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored
or click this orange button.
Check out all the cool rewards you get
for being a Patreon supporter—
including, of course,
having me answer your questions on the show.