On this episode of China Uncensored,
Forget Uncle Sam.
China has Uncle Trump.
Chinese agents have infiltrated the US!
Don't worry,
Congress is doing what it does best:
Absolutely nothing.
And China's facial recognition technology
will keep you safe…
from committing thought crime.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
The number two guy in Xi Jinping’s anti-corruption
campaign
is saying corruption in China is so bad,
it could lead to a soviet style collapse.
Top Party officials have said
similar things in the past.
But will this unusually strongly worded warning
lead to lasting change and meaningful reform?
Of course not.
Xi Jinping will use it to strengthen his grip
on power,
which he’ll then use to further purge his
political opponents
under the guise of the anti-corruption campaign.
To be fair,
Captain Toadstool and his underlings
were pretty corrupt,
and you can’t blame Xi for purging them.
Speaking of strong leaders:
Uncle Trump,
the Grand Commander,
or Donald the Strong as they call him in China.
US President Donald Trump has a legion of
fans there.
Some online Trump fan groups even boast
tens of thousands of members.
As one Chinese citizen told the New York Times,
“He’s true to himself.”
Just like One Punch Man.
If One Punch Man had golden locks of hair.
And were president.
President Trump, by the way,
just finished his first official state visit
to China,
and we’ll have more on that after the break.
And back in the US, the annual report by
the U.S. China Economic and Security Review
Commission
has a piece of advice for Congress:
Chinese journalists should be labeled as foreign
agents.
The Chinese regime has rapidly expanded
its state-run media to the United States.
I mean, CCTV has an office
literally seven blocks from the White House.
According to the report,
state media’s purpose is not so much journalism,
but to spread propaganda
and spy for the Chinese regime.
After all,
if Russia Today had to register,
maybe the same should apply to Chinese state-run
media
and those who work for it.
Of course there’s another alternative to
dealing with
China’s creepy authoritarian control.
If you can’t beat ’em, join ’em!
The Chinese Communist Party has been taking
the concept
of a surveillance state to the next level.
Chinese companies have been working
on facial recognition software.
They hope that by analyzing hair,
facial dimensions, and skin color,
they can accurately track individuals.
And then use behavior recognition software
to predict whether they’re going to commit
a crime.
And also, just keep an eye on everyone
so they’re safe.
It’s all about safety.
I know, you’re jealous of the CCP’s progress
on facial recognition.
But don’t worry,
because that kind of technology
may someday come to the West!
Oh, it already has.
I mean, it still doesn’t work very well.
But not to worry,
because investors are pouring money
into facial recognition software—
and not just to unlock stupid iPhones
that have no home button.
Investors are flocking to the 6.4 billion
dollar
video surveillance market in China,
including “leading U.S. venture capital
firms
such as the China arm of Sequoia Capital,
which is one of the best-known
Silicon Valley venture capital firms.”
And I don’t know if the US can compete.
Because it just came out that China
now has more supercomputers than anywhere
else.
China has 202;
the US, only 144.
Come on, America.
How can we be a global superpower
if we don’t have the most supercomputers?!
And finally, Hong Kongers have not been reacting
well
to the new law that makes it illegal
to disrespect China’s national anthem.
Namely, they’ve been booing it.
But they might regret that action.
There’s a law in Mainland China
that disrespecting the anthem
could carry a three-year prison term.
That law hasn’t been passed in Hong Kong...
but some Hong Kong lawmakers want to.
Namely, the pro-Beijing ones.
Shocking, I know.
And at least one former Legislative Council
member
thinks that law could be applied retroactively.
In other words,
you might not want to be caught on camera
booing the Chinese anthem in Hong Kong right
now.
Because when your booing becomes illegal
years after you did it,
you could be spending time in an orange jumpsuit
with hardened criminals.
And student democracy leaders.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Oh say can you see,
by the dawn’s early light,
China Uncensored.tv!
That’s our website,
where we upload full half hour episodes every
Friday
that you can’t see anywhere else.
So check it out!