bjbj,(,( On this episode of China Uncensored,
what you don t know about the New York Times
Is Killing People Logo Hi, welcome to China
Uncensored, I m Chris Chappell. You know,
the New York Times is one of the few foreign
language news websites that s actually unblocked
in China. Why is that? If you saw one of my
earlier episodes, you know the New York Times
is being paid to publish Chinese propaganda.
It s called China Watch. They aren t the only
ones either; the Washington Post has a whole
site dedicated to it, but with a very obvious
warning that it isn t their own reporting.
And you know, the kind of stories you get
in these things are top notch. Like this one
about China s new leader Xi Jinping being
a caring listener. And he has dreamy eyes.
But hey, I get it. In America we like presidents
we can share a beer with. And look at how
well that turned out for us. But the New York
Times is taking it to a whole new level. You
know the Times has been criticized for failing
to report on the Holocaust. There s a book
about it called Buried by the Times. During
World War 2, in 24,000 front-page stories,
only 26 were about the Holocaust and in only
six were Jews mentioned as the primary victims.
Well, fool me once, shame on you. Fool me
twice; better buy the New York Post. Now it
s the Chinese regime s genocide of Falun Gong
practitioners in China that the Times is not
only ignoring, but actually helping. Since
1999, Falun Gong adherents have been the victims
of a systematic campaign of torture and terror,
including beatings, electric baton shocks,
injections with psychotropic drugs, forced-feeding,
rape and other forms of sexual abuse. Report
after report has come in about this from sources
like Amnesty International, Human Rights Watch,
the UN, and even the US government. In 2006,
an independent investigation even found massive
evidence that China at the state-level has
been forcefully harvesting the organs of still-living
Falun Gong practitioners for sale. A recent
US Congressional hearing lead to a dear colleague
letter signed by 106 US Senators demanding
the US State Department release what it knows
about it. But don t bother looking for the
congressional hearing or dear colleague letter
in the New York Times. They didn t cover it.
In fact, since 2001, there s been a sharp
decline in any reporting about Falun Gong.
In ten years after the persecution began in
1999, only 164 articles have been written
about Falun Gong, most were in the first two
years. Not only did the number shrink, the
tone of the articles they did publish dramatically
changed after 2001. Considering Falun Gong
is a persecuted group inside China, you d
think the stories would, I don t know, be
about China. But since 2003, not a single
meaningful article about Falun Gong inside
China was published. And it also seems to
me that if you were to report on a group suffering
genocide at the hands of the Chinese Communist
regime, you wouldn t use the Chinese Communist
regime as your main source of information.
But that s exactly what the New York Times
has been doing. So before 2001, Falun Gong
was described as a peaceful spiritual practice
with roots in traditional Chinese culture,
that were victims of a quote, propaganda blitz,
which recalls Maoist campaigns of the 1950s
and 60s. (Show in Video Edit-Mark Landler
s account from July 22, 1999 that describes
the practice as a fusion of the ancient Chinese
practice of qigong the channeling of vital
energies through breathing exercises with
elements of Buddhism and Taoism) But after
2001, suddenly Falun Gong practitioners began
to sound like THEY were the bad guys. In a
third of the articles the New York Times published
about Falun Gong, they described the practice
as a sect, or just used the term the Chinese
regime uses, evil cult. And it really stopped
sounding like they were even being persecuted.
In 2005, Jim Yardley of the Times wrote, Falun
Gong is waging an aggressive campaign to publicize
its allegations of mistreatment, which the
Chinese government has denied. It is impossible
to prove or disprove all of its specific allegations.
The next year, evidence for the forced organ
harvesting of still living Falun Gong practitioners
became public. I guess though the Times feels
that the burden of proof is on the victims.
That s how a sane world works, right? But
then they also started contradicting their
own reporting. In 1999, when the persecution
began, the Times cited figures put out by
China that there were 70 million people practicing
Falun Gong in China. But then in 2001, Craig
Smith wrote that the number was made up by
Falun Gong practitioners, and that quote,
Closer scrutiny suggests the movement in China
never numbered more than several million.
Which is funny because when he was working
for the Wall Street Journal, he wrote, some
government officials estimate that the number
of followers has reached 60 million or more.
s also written that Falun Gong practitioners
have, died as a result of confrontations with
the police or prison guards. Not from brutal
torture of an all-powerful regime crushing
dissidence, mind you, but just a confrontation,
between police and what he describes as a
sect that makes up numbers. I m sure they
just fell down the stairs. So if the Times
is your only source, you get the skewed image
that Falun Gong is a weird, extremist group,
that on the one hand could very well not be
suffering persecution, but at the same time
also have been crushed by the Chinese regime.
(image of NY Times article Falun Gong Manages
Skimpy Rally; Is Sect Fading?) And it s really
weird that there was such a big shift AFTER
2001. I wonder what happened, you know, it
s not like I have access to the inner workings
of the New York Times or the Chinese government
for that matter. Butttttttt, it does strangely
seem to coincide with an exclusive interview
the New York Times happened to pull off with
Jiang Zemin, then Chinese leader and also
the guy who started the persecution against
Falun Gong. And then suddenly after that interview,
the New York Times website became unblocked
in China and to this day remains one of the
few foreign news sites to be so. In fact,
Professor Jiao Buobiao said the New York Times
is the only international newspaper available
at Beijing University s library. And they
just happen to be towing the Party line about
the biggest human rights violation of the
21st century. Pretty random coincidence, huh?
I wonder if they make people in China pay
to see their website because I m pretty sick
of that myself. So from now on, if you re
looking for China news, I d suggest maybe
not reading the New York Times. Once again,
I m Chris Chappell, thanks for watching this
episode of China Uncensored. hRR~ hRR~ gd|I
hxz. hxz. hxz. hxz. hxz. hRR~ gdap gdrho gd|I
gdxz. hrho hrho hrho hrho hrho hrho hrho [Content_Types].xml
#!MB ;c=1 _rels/.rels theme/theme/themeManager.xml
sQ\}# theme/theme/theme1.xml G$$DA : BR \{i5@R
V*[_X ,l\Y Ssd+r] 5\|E Vky- V4Ej 6NGU s?^V
* 7;wP EBU` 5VD
GGHPXNT, /M,W m2iU [[v _Xtl theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.rels
6?$Q K(M&$R(.1 [Content_Types].xmlPK _rels/.relsPK
theme/theme/themeManager.xmlPK theme/theme/theme1.xmlPK
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.relsPK
<a:clrMap xmlns:a="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/main"
bg1="lt1" tx1="dk1" bg2="lt2" tx2="dk2" accent1="accent1"
accent2="accent2" accent3="accent3" accent4="accent4"
accent5="accent5" accent6="accent6" hlink="hlink"
folHlink="folHlink"/> Chris Normal.dotm Chris
Microsoft Macintosh Word Title Microsoft Word
97-2004 Document NB6W Word.Document.8