On this episode of China Uncensored,
if you criticize socialism,
does that mean you’re not being very sociable?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
US President Donald Trump spoke
at the UN General Assembly this week.
And it seemed to go well.
In less than two years,
my administration has accomplished more than
almost any administration in the history of
our country.
America...so true.
Didn't expect that reaction but that's okay.
A little laughter, and some applause.
But there are “some countries,” according
to Trump,
that just aren’t playing by the same rules
as everyone else.
For example,
countries were admitted to the World Trade
Organization
that violate every single principle on which
the organization is based.
Some countries abused their openness to dump
their products,
subsidize their goods, target our industries,
and manipulate their currencies
to gain unfair advantage over our country.”
“These countries use government-run industrial
planning
and state-owned enterprises to rig the system
in their favor.”
Yeah, “some countries”!
Not to name names here.
And I respect your self-restraint, Mr. President.
But it’s ok to say your favorite word!
China, China, China
The United States has just announced another
200 billion dollars in tariffs on Chinese
made goods,
for a total of 250 billion dollars.
Oh my gosh does the Chinese representative
have a black eye?!
Hang on, I’ve just received this letter
from the Chinese Consulate!
Apparently, China’s UN representative...
fell down the stairs.
Huh.
But the Chinese Communist Party wants you
to know,
if any country is being abusive, it’s the
United States.
“Now that the U.S. has taken
such sweeping measures of trade restrictions,
which is like putting a knife to others' neck,
how could we conduct negotiations?”
State-run Xinhua accuses the US of “trade
bullyism.”
Bullyism?
Bully-ism?
Wow, it’s like China’s even stealing our
insults...
and reverse engineering them,
and then trying to sell us badly-made knock-offs.
This is why we need tariffs, people!
It’s time to bring back those high-quality,
made-in-America insults.
Like “hornswoggler.”
That’s a real word.
Look it up.
I’m not hornswoggling you.
Wait, what was I talking about?
Oh, right.
How the US is the bully in this trade scenario.
Now I know you’re probably thinking,
“Wait, isn’t China the big dirty cheater
here?”
But how could that be?
China has just released a white paper on the
trade war
proving that it’s right.
Using facts.
That’s right folks, Chinese state-run media
wants you to know that this white paper includes
real facts.
Presumably to distinguish it from all the
previous white papers,
like the one about how China has made
“remarkable progress” in human rights.
It’s like when Domino's Pizza started advertising,
“Now made with real cheese!”
And they were hoping you would think,
“oh goody!”
But you were actually thinking,
“Wait, what did they use before?
And should I even be eating this now?”
But just because a pizza contains real cheese,
doesn’t mean it also contains real meat.
So while China’s new white paper on trade
may contain some real facts,
it’s a bit lacking in others.
Like the facts about China
relentlessly dumping products on the US,
forcing technology transfer,
and stealing America’s intellectual property.
But it’s not about whether the white paper
is true,
or partly true, or the pepperoni is actually
rat meat.
The point is, you shouldn’t worry.
Because China is looking out
for the world in the face of US aggression.
It says “[The US] has become the greatest
source of uncertainty
and risk for the recovery of the global economy,”
but “[China has] the support of
all countries in the world that reject protectionism,
unilateralism and hegemony."
Yeah, that’s right.
The Chinese Communist Party
is standing up for the rest of the world,
using its totally fair debt traps.
And my favorite Chinese state run media, the
Global Times,
said this week that in the US-China trade
war,
“China is honest and principled
and a major trade power with intensive strengths.
No one can take us down.”
But President Trump may have other ideas.
Not about any country in particular, of course.
“Virtually everywhere socialism or communism
has been tried it has produced suffering corruption
and decay.
Socialism’s thirst for power leads to expansion,
incursion and oppression.
All nations of the worlds should resist socialism
and the misery that it brings to everyone.”
That’s misery to everyone in general,
not necessarily everyone in particular.
Oh, c’mon!
There’s lots of countries
where people are suffering from socialist
policies.
That’s better.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And before you go,
now is the time when I answer questions from
you!
The loyal members of the China Uncensored
50-cent army
who support the show on the crowd funding
website Patreon.
David Blatt asks,
What is the impact of Hong Kong
handing over sovereignty of the train station
in Kowloon
that links it to PRC;
and what is their reasoning for this suspicious
occurrence.
That’s another step in the Chinese Communist
Party’s plan
to change one country, two systems—
the policy where Hong Kong gets to keep freedoms
unimaginable in the rest of China—
into one country, one system—
where things are much more harmonious.
Losing a piece of Hong Kong territory at the
train station
and having it be administered under Mainland
Chinese law
is a small but meaningful step toward that.
It would have been unthinkable ten years ago.
But bit by bit,
Hong Kong’s freedoms are vanishing.
In this case, in the name of convenience.
But so far,
the high-speed rail line doesn’t seem to
be
as popular as the government thought.
Thanks for you question David.
And do you have a question you want to ask
me?
Then join the China Uncensored 50-Cent Army
on Patreon.
You’ll get some cool rewards for your services,
including having the chance
to have us answer your question on the show!
So sign up at pateron.com/chinauncensored.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Well, sorry to say,
that’s the end of another China Uncensored.
But this isn’t goodbye!
Hit that subscribe button and turn the notification
bell on
so you know when we have more episodes.
And more episodes we will have.
A new one comes out every Monday,
Wednesday, Friday and sometimes Saturday!