China’s military is growing by “any means”
according to a new Pentagon report.
China is trying to read children's minds
And Uighurs are very happy.
Welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m Chris Chappell.
A new Pentagon Report released Tuesday
warns that the Chinese military
is using “any means necessary”
to transform into a deadly, superior fighting
force.
And it has its sights set on Taiwan.
In fact, the report says conquering Taiwan
“has served as the primary driver
for China’s military modernization.”
Which might be why a top Chinese general
recently said on the People’s Liberation
Army’s
official English-language website,
“If someone tries to split Taiwan from China,
the Chinese military will do whatever it takes
to safeguard national reunification,
national sovereignty and territorial integrity.”
China’s military budget has been expanding
every year.
The Defense Intelligence Agency estimates
in 2018,
total military-related spending will top $200
billion.
That’s three times what it was in 2002.
And while that is still dwarfed by the US,
which in 2018 spent $700 billion,
the report notes that
“China has not had to invest
in costly R&D of new technologies
to the same degree as the United States.”
In other words,
America spent the money on research and development,
and then China stole it.
“Domestic laws forced foreign partners
of Chinese-based joint ventures
to release their technology in exchange
for entry into China's lucrative market,
and China has used other means
to secure needed technology and expertise.”
And now that China is basically caught up,
it’s developing new weapons.
Defense Intelligence Agency director
Lt. Gen. Robert Ashley writes that
“[China is] on the verge of fielding
some of the most modern weapon systems in
the world.
In some areas,
it already leads the world.”
For example,
China has developed the world’s first road-mobile,
anti-ship ballistic missile system.
Those are specifically designed
to attack enemy aircraft carriers,
which would make US defense of Taiwan
that much more difficult.
The moon.
Man has walked on the moon,
driven on on the moon,
hit a golf ball on the moon.
What else is there to do?
Well, apparently this.
“China has released photographs of seeds
planted by its lunar probe
sprouting on the far side of the moon surface.
The cotton seed sprouts
are the first biological matter to grow on
the moon.”
Now growing something on the moon is a big
deal.
That’s because if anyone wants to go to
Mars,
being able to grow Moon sprouts is the first
step
towards growing Mars potatoes in human poop.
The moon lander was also
“carrying...yeast and fruit fly eggs.”
Well I know that will work.
Once fruit flies start hatching you can never
get rid of them.
Why do we even want fruit flies on the moon?
Next thing you know they’re going to start
filling the moon up with other pests
like mosquitos, spiders, and pandas.
And it all started with some cotton seeds.
What’s that, Shelley?
The plants are dead?
Yes!
No moon pandas!
In other surely not sinister scientific developments,
China has started scanning children’s brains
with experimental technology!
The brain scanning headbands,
“were used in a recent trial with 10,000
school children
aged between 10 and 17 in China.
Over 21 days,
students wore the headsets during class
and teachers could monitor their average attention
levels
using an app.”
I know, hard to imagine Chinese students
might have a hard time focusing
when they’re reading about Xi Jinping Thought
for A New Era.
Maybe they’ll be able to focus better on
classes
about the links between electromagnetic waves
and brain cancer.
But I know you’re worried about how soon
it will be
before American schools can enjoy
these child brain scans as well.
Well, no need to worry,
because they were designed by
the Massachusetts based BrainCo,
so hopefully we’ll have them in America
as soon as the China trials are done.
“When students use the focus one,
teachers can immediately tell when their students
are in a low attention state or high attention
state.”
This is not the future we were promised!
We were promised pink hoverboards.
Yet another vaccine scandal in China!
More than 100 children received expired polio
vaccines.
They were between 3 months and 4 years old.
This is terrible news.
Unless you’re an anti-vaxxer.
An unexpected side effect of these expired
vaccines
was violent protests over the weekend.
I guess parents were a little tired of Communist
Party negligence
putting their children’s lives at risk.
Sure, bad vaccines are used all the time in
China.
But as state-run media said after
the last vaccine scandal a few months ago,
Chinese vaccines are perfectly safe.
Hey, you know those vocational training centers
in Xinjiang?
The ones that are holding a million or more
Uighurs?
The ones that hostile foreign forces,
like journalists,
call “concentration camps”?
Couldn’t be further from the truth.
Why, a Reuters reporter was given an official
tour of one!
And this is what he saw.
Some of the chaperons said to me,
‘look, we're doing such a good job here,
that you in the West should really be learning
from us.’”
If you’re happy and you know it clap your
hands
I mean they said they were happy,
they knew it,
and they clapped their hands!
So please ignore any reports you may hear
about the vocational training camps actually
being used for cultural and ethnic genocide
with torture worse than death.
And finally,
this piece of calligraphy has been
a part of Chinese sacred territory
since ancient times.
1,200 years to be exact.
It’s a famous piece by
the greatest calligrapher in Chinese history,
Yan Zhenqing.
It’s called Requiem to My Nephew.
It belongs to Taiwan’s National Palace Museum.
But that’s not why the Communist Party is
so upset.
They’re upset because Taiwan lent it to
a Japanese museum,
and they hate Japan because,
you know...the Rape of Nanking in 1938.
Seriously.
According to the BBC,
the story is trending on the Chinese internet.
And people are furious.
One Weibo user said,
“Has Taiwan forgotten what Japan did to
us?
Do they know what the Nanjing massacre is?”
Now Taiwan’s history with Japan
is pretty different from the Mainland.
Taiwan was under Japanese occupation for even
longer—
from 1895 until 1945.
But in Taiwan,
Japanese occupiers were a little less rapey,
and a lot more build-y.
Anyway, the reaction in China,
or at least the reaction that’s been
allowed to stay on social media,
has been that Taiwan is crazy
and China needs to retake Taiwan.
Which fits in very nicely
with a recent speech Chinese leader Xi Jinping
gave.
Those are this weeks China headlines.
What do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And before you go, now is the time I answer
a question
from a fan who supports China Uncensored
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
Rodney Hall asks,
“Is it ever difficult to do China Uncensored
as comedy
when you know better than most that the CCP
holds China through mass murder,
mass torture,
and mass repression?
I would think that making jokes about a regime
that cuts its people up
and sells their pieces for cash
would make you want to cry, every day.”
Hey, you don’t know what happens after the
camera turns off.
It’s a river of sorrow up in here.
That’s why I grew the beard.
To catch all of the tears that were dripping
on the desk.
But yeah, most of the things we cover on this
show are very serious.
And it’s all having a very big impact on
people’s lives
whether they’re in the US,
China or anywhere else in the world.
But no one likes to hear depressing news all
the time.
But in the immortal words of Mary Poppins,
a spoonful of sugar makes the medicine go
down.
And not just for the viewers.
The humor helps all of us on the China Uncensored
team
write about this stuff without having to take
Zoloft.
Now Matt, Shelley,
and I all feel very passionately about China.
So how do we manage to make jokes?
Simple.
We built Sarcasti-bot 3000 to write them for
us.
He’s quite the...joker.
Joker?
I hardly knew her.
Ha.
Ha ha.
We...can’t shut him down.
Thanks for your question.
And if you’d to have a shot at getting
your question answered on the show,
sign up to become a member of the China Uncensored
50-cent army
by supporting the show with a dollar or more
per episode
through the crowd funding website Patreon.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.