Hong Kong is freaking out over the coronavirus
While the Chinese economy takes damage
As the international community shuts the door
on travelers from China.
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
The Coronavirus outbreak is really not going
well
for the Chinese Communist Party.
I mean, personally I’m more concerned about
all the people,
mainly in China,
who have gotten sick because the Chinese Communist
Party
tried to cover up the whole epidemic for more
than a month,
instead of stopping it when they had the chance.
But you’ve got to feel for the Chinese regime
just a little bit.
I mean, Chinese leader Xi Jinping even disappeared
for a little while.
That led to rumors that he was sick.
Especially after people began sharing a video
of him dry coughing.
There was also talk that maybe he had been
purged.
But, no such luck.
He’s back—doing the usual,
like hanging out with foreign dictators.
Hong Kong has reported its first death from
the coronavirus.
“The patient was a 39-year-old man
who had visited Wuhan and returned to Hong
Kong on Jan. 23.”
So far, at the time of this recording,
Hong Kong had 21 confirmed cases of coronavirus
infection.
Although Hong Kong isn’t particularly close
to Wuhan,
where the outbreak began,
Hong Kong does share a border with Mainland
China.
Hong Kong Chief Executive Carrie Lam was under
pressure
to block off all visitors from Mainland China
once the coronavirus began to spread.
She initially refused,
calling it “discriminatory.”
Which is dumb.
But not any dumber than the real reason she
refused:
She doesn’t have the power.
Actions like this would be under the control
of her masters:
the Chinese Communist Party.
And so Hong Kongers did what they’ve done
since June of last year.
They protested.
“Thousands of public sector healthcare workers
in Hong Kong on Tuesday
went on strike for the second day in a row
to demand immediate closure
of the city’s border with mainland China
to prevent the spread of the deadly coronavirus.”
But unlike any of the other protests over
the past several months,
this time, Carrie Lam actually caved...kind
of.
“The Chief Executive in Council will invoke
the Prevention and Control of Disease Ordinance
section 599.
We will invoke the power to put requirements
towards people coming from the mainland,
including mainland residents,
Hong Kong residents,
and other visitors.
They will have to enter into compulsory quarantine
for a period of fourteen days."
So, Lam is still not fully closing the border,
but there will be a mandatory quarantine
for anyone coming from mainland China.
Hong Kong has seen, shall we say,
not a lot of enthusiasm for the Chinese Communist
Party
and its influence in Hong Kong.
The fact that the coronavirus
is now spreading within Hong Kong’s borders
because of a Communist Party coverup...
that’s not making the situation better.
Especially when people remember what happened
during the SARS outbreak back in 2003.
A Chinese doctor who had been treating SARS
patients
traveled to Hong Kong and infected more than
a dozen other people.
Eventually almost 300 people in Hong Kong
died from SARS.
That was the most anywhere outside mainland
China.
So people in Hong Kong are scared,
lining up for hours,
even sometimes overnight,
to buy items like face masks and hand sanitizer,
which are running low.
There’s even been a run on toilet paper,
sparked by internet rumors.
Especially when a higher up in the World Health
Organization
had this to say.
“So we're sitting on the edge here...
So with a lot of hard work and also a lot
of luck,
we may be able to get ourselves out of this.
But you know the likelihood is not in our
favour."
And on that optimistic note, the coronavirus
is spreading around the world on cruise ships
and airlines.
“A cruise ship in Japan carrying nearly
4,000 people
has found cases of the coronavirus.”
Is that better or worse than just finding
cases of Corona?
So far two cruise ships are being quarantined,
the one off the coast of Japan, and one off
the coast of Hong Kong.
Passengers are not allowed to leave their
cabins.
Have you seen what most cruise ship cabins
look like?
It’s basically solitary confinement on a
boat.
Obviously the international community
is concerned about the spread of the coronavirus.
Many airlines are “suspending or restricting
flights to China
and several countries, including the United
States,
[and] banning the entry of anyone who has
been in China
over the previous two weeks.”
Cathay Pacific has even asked employees to
take unpaid leave.
They could pass the time with a case of Corona.
But the travel ban is affecting Chinese students
studying abroad.
In a show of support, 4,000 students in Australia
have signed a petition asking for a delay
to the start of university.
There are an estimated 100,000 Chinese students
studying in Australia
who are still abroad and currently locked
out of the country.
I can understand the concern of the Australian
government though.
University students shouldn’t have to deal
with cases of the coronavirus.
The worst thing university students should
have to deal with
are cases of Corona.
What’s that Shelley?
Okay, I’ll stop.
The coronavirus is also causing China’s
already sluggish economy
to stumble worse than a person drunk on…
I said I wouldn’t.
Some economists are warning GDP growth could
fall below 2%
According to CNBC,
“The 24 provinces, municipalities and regions
which have told businesses to cease operating
until at least February 10
accounted for over 80% of national GDP and
90% of exports last year.”
Chinese stocks are also plummeting to the
lowest level
since that stock market crisis in 2015.
But don’t worry, Chinese state-run media
are saying that
GDP will definitely not fall below 5%.
Which means that it won’t.
As long as you believe the official numbers.
The outbreak is also hitting Western companies
operating in China.
Tesla stocks took a hit after Tesla announced
it would not be delivering a scheduled shipment
of cars
because of the coronavirus.
So, to no one’s surprise,
Tesla over promised and under delivered.
Of course, American companies
that have already become less reliant on China
because of the US China Trade War
won’t be as affected.
So, as I’ve been saying for years,
you’re better off not doing business in
China.
And that’s it for this update on the coronavirus.
And as you may have heard me mention,
an inside source at YouTube has said that
YouTube
is targeting coronavirus coverage
as “too controversial for advertisers.”
All our episodes about the coronavirus have
been demonetized—
either temporarily or permanently.
It’s not that we’re trying to profit off
the misery of others,
but this is a form of censorship.
If a news show can’t generate income while
reporting the news,
it can’t survive.
YouTube would have shut down China Uncensored
years ago like this.
But fortunately, we have the support of viewers
like you,
who I call the China Uncensored 50 cent army.
Through your contributions on the crowd funding
website Patreon,
China Uncensored has survived to today,
so we can let you know about important China
issues that affect you,
like a deadly global pandemic.
So as a thank you to supporters,
I answer a question from them at the end of
some of my episodes.
Today’s question comes from Nightshade010101
“Have you guys considered posting your videos
to a different site?”
Good question.
Some folks have suggested that the way to
deal with YouTube censorship
is to just get off YouTube.
I’m definitely open to the idea
and if those of you watching have any suggestions,
please let me know.
However, despite all YouTube’s flaws,
it’s still an incredible platform
as far as video playback quality and viewer
reach go.
I want to reach as many people as possible
with China Uncensored,
and I’m not sure I could do that on another
site.
But I could be wrong, so let me know.
Thanks for your question.
And if you’d like to join the China Uncensored
50-cent army,
head over to patreon.com/chinauncensored to
learn more.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.