Pepe the Frog in Hong Kong?
The chosen one appears
And Social Media actually stands up to China
That and more on this week’s China Uncensored.
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
This week’s China news headlines!
Hong Kong has been in the midst of two months
of nonstop protests.
1.7 million people took the streets last Sunday.
They’ve been protesting an extradition bill
that would allow
Hong Kong authorities to send people to mainland
China for trial.
The people of Hong Kong say they’re fighting
for their freedom.
China calls it a color revolution backed by
the US.
The truth?
Hong Kong protesters are a bunch of white
supremacists!
Yes, that’s Pepe the Frog.
As the New York Times says,
“Pepe the Frog is a hate symbol,
a cheerleader of racism and anti-Semitism,
a friend of alt-right extremists.”
Yes...clearly that describes the Hong Kong
protesters
that have adopted him.
Some even spray painting him around the city.
There’s even a Hong Kong Pepe themed sticker
pack for Whatsapp.
So are the Hong Kong protesters a bunch of
Nazi white supremicists?
Um...no.
It turns out that Pepe symbolizes
something else to Hong Kongers.
One protester said,
“It just looks funny and captures the hearts
of so many youngsters.
It is a symbol of youth participation in this
movement.”
Or my personal favorite,
the protester who said,
“To me, Pepe is just a Hello Kitty-like
character,”
Hello Pepe!
Yes, that image will haunt your dreams.
Just like Pepe the Pooh.
You’re welcome.
But in some ways, perhaps Hong Kongers
have the purest understanding of Pepe.
Pepe was created more than a decade ago—
long before he was adopted by the alt-right
on 4chan.
And as Pepe’s creator says,
“In the end, Pepe is whatever you say he
is,
and I, the creator, say that Pepe is love.”
Pepe is love.
An employee of the British consulate in Hong
Kong
has been detained in mainland China.
Simon Cheng traveled to Shenzhen on business
for the consulate
where he was picked up for...well,
at first no one knew,
because the police refused to say why Cheng
was in detention.
But then they told my favorite state-run media
the Global Times
that they detained Cheng for soliciting a
prostitute in Shenzhen.
To which everyone said, suuuuuuure.
Yeeeeaaaaah.
Especially concerning was that fact that Cheng
was apparently detained after he already left
Shenzhen
and was on his way back to Hong Kong on the
high-speed rail.
That means he was most likely detained by
Chinese police
while he was already in Hong Kong at the West
Kowloon Rail Station.
Last year, Hong Kong and mainland Chinese
authorities
struck a deal to put part of the train station
under Chinese law,
instead of Hong Kong law.
At the time, people were worried about Chinese
law
being implemented on Hong Kong soil,
but as this case clearly shows,
they had absolutely nothing to worry about,
everything’s fine.
In fact, Cheng’s mysterious detention
will probably make Hongkongers even more enthusiastic
and reassured about the extradition bill to
China.
Everything is fine.
And since Simon Cheng was an employee of the
UK consulate,
obviously the UK is up in arms.
And by that, I mean
they apologized profusely to the Chinese government
for the inconvenience,
before retiring for afternoon tea.
Meanwhile, US Vice President Mike Pence
says Beijing needs to honor the treaty they
made with the UK r
egarding Hong Kong,
or else people might think China won’t honor
any deal.
Well, someone who worked on that deal for
China
had this to say on the UK’s Channel 4 news.
“Let me get this clear then,
the joint declaration is dead.
Correct?”
“No the joint declaration terminated
when the British government handed sovereignty
back to China
midnight June 30th, 1997.”
Which shows you just how difficult
a lasting trade deal with China will be.
Only a very special person would be able to
do it.
Well, here’s US President Donald Trump talking
to reporters
about the Trade War and standing up to the
Chinese regime.
“Somebody had to do it, I am the chosen
one.”
Surprised?
Well actually, this was prophesied back in
2014.
“You are the most talented,
most interesting and extraordinary person
in the universe.
And you are capable of amazing things,
because you are the Special.”
Yes, I’m saying that Donald Trump is President
Business.
Think about it.
“We got a hugger.”
Maybe.
In China’s often-forgotten special administrative
region—
Macau—
things aren’t going so well.
It’s time to vote for a new leader!
But don’t worry;
you won’t have to sit through endless campaigning
that drags on for two years.
Because in Macau,
there is only one candidate: Ho Iat Seng.
He’s the only person the Communist Party
approved to run.
He’s “a Beijing-backed former legislator
who is expected to cement China’s control
over the special administrative region
and distance it from escalating protests in
neighboring Hong Kong.”
Democracy in Macau is so much more harmonious
than in Hong Kong.
But some people are still standing up to the
Chinese Communist Party.
Like the mayor of Prague.
He’s been fighting against Beijing’s influence
in his city.
“He reinstituted the practice of flying
the Tibetan flag from city hall.”
“He allowed an exhibition on city property
commemorating the 1989 Tiananmen Square protests.”
“He hosted the leader of Tibet’s exiled
government
and made an official visit to the Taiwanese
capital, Taipei.”
“And he has called for Prague to renegotiate
its 2016 sister-city agreement with Beijing,
removing the acknowledgment of the one-China
principle,
which states that China, Taiwan and Tibet
are a single country
that should be ruled from Beijing.”
FYI, he’s a member of the Czech Pirate Party.
And speaking of, and I can’t believe I’m
saying this,
Twitter and Facebook have also
stood up to the Chinese Communist Party.
Both social media giants said they discovered
fake accounts
spreading disinformation about Hong Kong.
Those accounts have been deleted.
YouTube also disabled a bunch of channels
for spreading fake Hong Kong news.
Twitter also said it would block state-controlled
media outlets
from advertising on its site.
If only the New York Times and the Washington
Post
and the Wall Street Journal could hold themselves
to the same journalistic standards as Twitter.
But no, they’re very happy to have Chinese
state-run media
advertise in *their* publications.
The Chinese regime was quick to condemn
Facebook’s and Twitter’s actions,
saying that overseas Chinese have the right
to express their opinions.
And the irony caused the internet to explode.
15 papers from Chinese scientists have been
retracted
because they may have involved involuntary
organ donation.
That is, killing innocent people and harvesting
their organs.
The Chinese Communist Party was quick to defend
them,
saying it’s fine to murder Chinese people
as long as it’s for science...
or politics, or any other reason.
And then remembered they had meant to
cover the whole thing up.
Oops.
What China should defend is the rail lines
of the Belt and Road Initiative.
That’s Chinese leader Xi Jinping's trillion
dollar infrastructure plan
to bring the world a little closer to China.
A big part of that was a massive rail line
connecting China and Europe.
Well, China’s state-run China Railway has
now admitted
that most of the train cars have been empty.
“In one extreme case only one of 41 containers
on a particular train actually carried goods.”
Widespread waste and fraud in a state owned
enterprise
of a communist nation?
I’m shocked.
Shocked!
And finally, in China, love is not always
love.
“China ruled out legalizing same-sex marriage
on Wednesday.
A parliament spokesman said China’s legal
position on marriage
will remain between a man and a woman.”
That is so incredibly hypocritical.
Because the Communist Party once allowed
a human woman to marry a toad.
And remember, Pepe is a frog, not a toad,
so Pepe still gets to be love.
And that’s it for this week’s China news
headlines!
And now it’s time for me to answer a question
from one of you—
a fan who support China Uncensored
with a dollar or more per episode,
by contributing through Patreon.
Daniel Ortman asks,
“Could [the Trade War] break the CCP?
If so, why didn't we do it before?
Well, obviously, we didn’t have the chosen
one before!
Or as President Business would put it,
“I do blame past administrations for allowing
this out-of-control trade deficit to take
place and to grow.”
But it’s not just “past administrations.”
Because those presidents felt pressure from
the big US companies
that funded their political campaigns.
The China market seemed big and full of gold
and a lot of people and businesses thought
they could get a piece of it.
And so for many years, the US leadership
turned a blind eye to all the Chinese intellectual
property theft,
WTO violations,
and currency manipulation.
In fact, companies would sometimes
complain to US officials about China,
but then ask them to not say anything,
because they still wanted to do business there.
It eventually got so bad, though,
it couldn’t be ignored.
But even today, companies like Google and
Microsoft
partner with Chinese military universities
on research
that may be used in persecuting Chinese citizens.
Thanks for your question, Daniel.
And if you have a question for me
you want to hear answered on the show,
sign up to join the China Uncensored 50 cent
army,
by supporting the show with a dollar or more
per episode.
Again, YouTube is demonetizing us so much
we would have to shut down the show
if it weren’t for your support.
And to everyone,
thanks for watching!
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.