China has threatened to invade Taiwan.
Taiwan has been preparing.
But is Taiwan ready?
Welcome to China Uncensored. I’m Chris Chappell.
This episode has been sponsored\h
by Surfshark—because you should\h\h
be protecting your identity whenever you\h
go online by using a VPN like Surfshark.
Taiwan. A thriving democracy\h
of 24 million people.\h
Home of the Freedom Pineapple.\h
And the hottest flashpoint of 2021!\h
For years, experts have called\h
Taiwan the likeliest flash point\h\h
that would trigger world war 3.\h
That’s because of the Chinese Communist\h
Party’s plan for Taiwan “unification”.\h\h
Which is just a nicer way of saying invasion.\h
But a Chinese Communist takeover of Taiwan\h
would also endanger the rest of the world.\h\h
Taiwan is part of the first island chain in the\h
Pacific, along with Japan and the Philippines.
The Chinese Communist Party is already claiming\h
the bottom part of the first island chain,\h\h
with their nine-dash line in the South China Sea.
If they got Taiwan, too, that would\h
consolidate their power over much of\h\h
Asia. And it would also be a launching point\h
for them to threaten the rest of the Pacific.
Including US allies like Japan, the Philippines,\h
and Australia. And US territories like Guam.
Even Hawaii.
That’s a big reason why the\h
Pentagon should focus on Taiwan.\h
But the US doesn’t have an official defense\h
treaty with Taiwan. That means if the Chinese\h\h
Communist Party actually invaded Taiwan, the\h
US isn’t required by law to defend Taiwan.\h
That doesn’t mean the US wouldn’t defend\h
Taiwan, it just means it’s not guaranteed.\h
However, the US is required by law “to provide\h
Taiwan with arms of a defensive character.”
Enough to “enable Taiwan to maintain\h
a sufficient self-defense capability.”
In 2020 alone, US arms sales to\h
Taiwan totaled 5 billion dollars.\h
Of course, the Chinese Communist Party\h
has warned the Biden administration\h\h
to stop doing this. Or doing\h
anything to support Taiwan.\h
But other than throwing hissy fits at the US,\h\h
the Chinese Communist Party doesn’t have a lot\h
of options for how it can take over Taiwan.
It could move decisively to a full-scale\h
invasion to raise the cost of US intervention.
It’s possible that the Biden\h
administration would then decide\h\h
it’s not worth sending US\h
troops to defend Taiwan.\h
This is a risky move, though.\h
We’ve talked before about how\h\h
difficult it would be to launch\h
a full-scale invasion of Taiwan.
The Chinese regime could also\h
adopt a coercive strategy\h\h
that gradually increases military pressure\h
to bend Taipei to China’s demands.
This idea of gradual escalation is what\h
many people call gray zone warfare.
We did an episode about how the\h
Chinese regime is using gray\h\h
zone warfare against Taiwan by constantly\h
sending warplanes into Taiwan’s airspace.
This can ensure that China always maintains the\h
initiative, keeping Taiwan on edge constantly,\h\h
without going into full-scale conflict.
\h\h
This “war of attrition” is\h
already wearing down Taiwan\h\h
politically, militarily, and psychologically.
The Chinese Communist Party is trying to\h
make their aggression and militarization\h\h
the norm, “something that is not worthy of\h
any sort of response from other nations.”
So if other countries won’t respond to\h
the Chinese Communist Party’s actions,\h\h
is Taiwan’s military prepared\h
for a Chinese invasion?
I’ll get to that after the break.
Welcome back.
So is Taiwan’s military prepared for an invasion?\h
Taiwan has its eyes on increasing\h
its conventional weapon capabilities,\h\h
but many experts say that Taiwan\h
should stop spending its money on them.
That’s because those systems are\h
expensive and not necessarily useful\h\h
for the type of warfare that Taiwan\h
would face from the Communist Party.
This is why, a couple of years\h
ago, former Taiwanese Admiral\h\h
Lee Hsi-ming proposed what’s called the\h
Overall Defense Concept, or ODC for short.
“The ODC is Taiwan’s current strategy for dealing\h\h
with a potential Chinese invasion in\h
a resource-constrained environment.”
Instead of a traditional war of attrition, the ODC\h\h
redefines winning war against China\h
as “foiling the People’s Liberation\h\h
Army’s mission of successfully invading and\h
exerting political control over Taiwan.”
Admiral Lee says Taiwan should prepare to absorb\h\h
missile and air strikes and\h
preserve the ability to strike back.
The ability to strike back would rely\h
on an abundance of small, cheap weapons\h\h
like mobile anti-ship missiles,\h
portable anti-aircraft missiles,\h\h
advanced sea mines and fast missile boats.
What’s great about these weapons is that they\h
can be camouflaged and dispersed in urban,\h\h
coastal, jungle and mountain areas.
This makes it hard for the\h
PLA to search and destroy.
The ODC is an approach that Taiwanese\h
President Tsai Ing-wen supports.
There are, however, some bureaucratic challenges\h
that Taiwan faces in implementing the ODC.
“Efforts at defense reform face obstacles\h
from institutional opposition from senior\h\h
officers and a lack of time.”
On top of that, there’s also the\h
issue of Taiwan’s military readiness.
“Taiwan is suffering a serious and\h
worsening decay in the readiness\h\h
and training of its troops,\h
particularly its army units.”
Much of it is because Taiwan’s\h
mandatory military service\h\h
has dramatically decreased\h
from one year to four months.
But even within those four months,\h\h
some army conscripts say that they only fire 30\h
to 40 rounds with their rifles. That’s not a lot.
One army conscript said that he wasn’t even\h
taught how to clear his rifle if it jammed.
Not even a fraction of conscripts\h\h
get the chance to practice shooting\h
anti-tank missiles and grenade launchers.
So, they miss all the fun parts.
This is a problem because a military is\h
only as good as its soldiers. What good\h\h
is buying weapons if your soldiers\h
aren’t trained to use them properly?
The Tsai administration is trying to correct\h
these issues with a mobilization office.
Its goal is to better strengthen\h
and coordinate Taiwan’s reserve\h\h
forces so that reserve soldiers play a greater\h
role and support active-duty service members.
The administration will also\h
extend post-service training\h\h
for reservists from 8 years to 15 years in 2022.
But are these reforms enough?
I’ll get to that after the break.
Welcome back.
Taiwan’s a democracy, and as a democracy,\h
you don’t want to upset people — especially\h\h
young voters — with something like\h
mandatory military conscription.
But you know what’s easy to do? Rely\h
on America. But like I said earlier in\h\h
this episode, there’s no guarantee\h
that America will come through.\h
Although if it doesn’t, that would be a huge blow\h
to America’s standing in the world, not to mention\h\h
our ability to counter the Chinese Communist\h
Party. But that’s a whole nother episode.\h
The biggest problem for Taiwan, is that\h
relying on the US might be making Taiwan soft.
Retired US Marine Corp colonel Grant Newsham says\h
that Taiwan’s military has been whittled down\h\h
because it is acting as if defending the\h
country is someone else’s responsibility.
There is also a concern\h\h
the Taiwanese might not have the will to\h
defend against and resist the mainland.
This is a problem because, “as the president\h
of the U.S.-Taiwan Business Council puts it,\h\h
the problem of Taiwan's defense comes down to\h
‘the space between how young Taiwan citizens\h\h
feel about the island's sovereignty and\h
what they're prepared to do about it.’”
So how do they feel?
Polls show mixed messages. According to one\h
poll, “If war were to break out between Taiwan\h\h
and China, 40.9 percent of those surveyed said\h
that they are willing to fight or would not\h\h
object to their family's participation,\h
while 49.1 percent said the opposite.”
So the majority of Taiwanese are not willing\h
to fight against the Chinese regime.\h
But another poll shows that 96 percent of 18\h
and 19-year-olds would be willing to fight.
Although that percentage dropped to 26 percent\h\h
for people in their 20s. The age that would\h
likely be sent first to the front lines.\h
But public sentiment in Taiwan is likely\h
to change as the Chinese Communist Party\h\h
gets more aggressive. Hong Kong has already\h
been a huge wake-up call to many Taiwanese.\h
When faced with an existential\h
crisis, a smaller force like Taiwan\h\h
can beat a much larger foe like\h
China if it has enough resolve.
And Taiwan’s government is proactively\h
trying to solve their military weaknesses.\h\h
They just need enough time.\h
So let’s hope that this retired Japanese general\h
is wrong and China doesn’t invade Taiwan by 2025.
And this episode is sponsored by Surfshark.
Whenever you go online, you should be\h
using a VPN like Surfshark to protect\h\h
your identity. Everything you do online is being\h
tracked and logged—by the websites you visit\h\h
and your internet service provider.\h
And in many cases, by the government.
And if you’re in an authoritarian country like\h\h
China this kind of tracking can put you\h
at risk of surveillance and even arrest.
So I recommend you use Surfshark\h
to protect yourself online.
When you use Surfshark’s CleanWeb mode,\h
you’ll be protected from trackers,\h\h
plus a lot of ads and malware.
With one account,\h\h
you can connect as many devices as you want.\h
Try it out with a 30-day money back guarantee.
And Surfshark has a special discount for China\h
Uncensored fans. Go to surfshark.com/uncensored\h\h
and use the code UNCENSORED to get our special\h
deal that includes 3 extra months for FREE.
Click the link below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell. See you next time.