On this episode of China Uncensored,
is it getting cold in here?
Or is it just your cold war mentality?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
China reacts to “the biggest,
best State of the Union, ever.”
It was an hour and 20 minutes long,
way longer than a typical tweet.
Of course, you’re just watching to see
if your name gets dropped.
And China’s did.
Right alongside Russia.
And terrorist groups.
“Around the world,
we face rogue regimes,
terrorist groups,
and rivals like China and Russia
that challenge our interests,
our economy,
and our values.”
Now why do you have to be like that?
China’s fine.
It won’t try to block America’s new moment,
as state-run Xinhua says.
But also, if the US doesn’t stop
this kind of Cold War mentality,
there’s going to be problems.
“We hope the US can abandon Cold War mentality
and outdated zero-sum game ideas,
treat China and US-China relations properly.”
Yes, treat US-China relations properly.
Like, stop talking about protecting
US intellectual property from theft.
“And we will protect American workers
and American intellectual property,
through strong enforcement of our trade rules.”
Because we all know who Trump’s talking
about—
without naming names.
It’s about stopping the Chinese Communist
Party
from stealing an estimated $5 trillion dollars
a year
in American innovation.
That is such a Cold War mentality.
And of course,
no speech in front of a crowd by Trump would
be complete
without a reference to Rocket Man.
“We need only look at the depraved character
of the North Korean regime
to understand the nature of the nuclear threat
it could pose to America and to our allies.”
Of course the Chinese regime
might agree with President Trump
on that one.
Let’s just say China is not known
for its environment of open debate.
But academics have been given a free pass
to debate what to do about North Korea.
Of course that courtesy has not been
extended to the general public.
And its seems like President Trump
may have successfully driven a wedge between
the former best Communist neighbors.
According to this South Korean newspaper,
North Korea has banned Chinese retail products.
I guess beggars can be choosers.
So what’s your reaction to China’s reaction
to President Trump’s State of the Union
address?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode
of China Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Tired of that Cold War Mentality?
Then head on over to ChinaUncensored.tv.
There you can watch full half hour episodes
of China Uncensored you won’t see on YouTube.
Armed with that kind of knowledge,
you can make this cold war go hot.