On this episode of China Uncensored,
the US and China are getting along again!
And we have This guy to thank.
Hi, welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Something pretty incredible has happened,
folks.
The United Nations Security Council
all agreed on something!
And actually got something done!
That means the United States, Russia, and
China
found something they all had in common—
besides that they’re each the best
and greatest country in the world.
Last Saturday, the UN Security Council
unanimously voted for tough new sanctions
against North Korea.
It’s part of ongoing efforts to stop
North Korea from making nuclear weapons.
Not only is this newsworthy.
It’s Twitter worthy.
Yes, China and Russia voted with us
on these sanctions.
And they cover more than $1 billion dollars
in exports—
including coal, iron, lead, and seafood.
Meaning North Korea can’t sell those things
abroad.
Of course, that just means all that seafood
stays in North Korea,
which Kim Jong-un is happy about
because he’s on a strict seafood diet:
When he sees food, he eats it.
The sanctions also prohibit expanding
the use of North Korean laborers abroad,
along with new joint ventures or new investment
in current joint ventures.
Though if you think North Korea is a good
investment,
you might want to get a new financial advisor.
In practical terms, the sanctions mainly affect
how Russia and China deal with North Korea.
Those two countries are basically the only
major powers
doing business with the Kim regime.
China makes up about 90% of all North Korean
trade.
According to Bloomberg,
the US and China had been negotiating
the sanctions for a month.
Then, a “leak” last week said US President
Trump
wanted to go after China on trade
for failing to rein in North Korea.
And he even got support from Democrats on
it.
A rare bipartisan win!
But days later, news broke that the US
was going to delay the trade battle
to guarantee China’s support for the the
UN vote on North Korea sanctions.
Which shows how important the North Korea
situation
is to the US government.
This is a win-win.
The US gets cooperation from China on North
Korea
without starting a trade war.
And even though China will take
the brunt of the loss in terms of trade,
it’s great PR.
It makes it seem like China
is part of the solution,
not part of the problem.
It also prevents the US from putting more
sanctions
on Chinese companies with dubious ties
to North Korea.
For now at least.
North Korea for its part has not taken the
sanctions well.
As their perpetually angry state-run news
anchor said,
"We denounce and totally reject the United
Nations
Security Council Resolution on our country
which the United States and hostile forces
have fabricated to infringe on our sovereignty."
Then North Korea threatened ultimate measures.
Saying that the entire United States
was in reach of their nuclear weapons.
"There is no bigger mistake than the United
States
believing that its land is safe across the
ocean."
After the sanctions announcement,
China and North Korea’s foreign ministers
met on the sidelines of an ASEAN summit.
“Chinese foreign minister Wang Li
told reporters he had urged the North Koreans
to calmly handle the resolutions and,
quote, ‘not do anything unbeneficial
towards the international community.’”
Yes, we wouldn’t want anything unbeneficial
happening.
But there’s a problem here.
I mean, besides the rogue regime
threatening to nuke the world.
The problem is that China and the United States
see that problem in fundamentally different
ways.
“China says it’s confident new North Korean
sanctions
will bring the rogue regime back to the negotiating
table.”
The negotiating table?
The United States is not going to the negotiating
table
with an authoritarian regime with an obscene
human rights record that consistently
shows itself to be a belligerent threat
to other countries.
Unless it’s China.
Or Russia.
Or North Korea ten years ago.
The point is, the US doesn’t want North
Korea
to think it can get what it wants
through bombastic threats.
Secretary of State Rex Tillerson has said
the US
won’t sit down for talks with North Korea
until it stops its nuclear and ballistic missile
test
for an undisclosed,
but significant amount of time.
The Chinese regime sees it differently.
They see the United States as provoking North
Korea.
My favorite state-run media the Global Times
calls it US moral arrogance.
Both sides just need to have a heart-to-heart
discussion.
“Of course we also urge other parties,
especially the U.S. and South Korea,
not to increase the tension.
The situation on the Korean peninsula
is at a critical point of crisis,
at the same time it is a turning point
to make a decision to resume talks.”
Maybe not so ironically,
this is the same line North Korea takes.
Well, the “US is to blame” part.
Not the “let’s have a heart-to-heart discussion”
part.
"We want to make it clear
that the worsening situation on the Korean
peninsula,
as well as the nuclear issues,
were caused by the United States."
But with these sanctions in place,
what could realistically be done to
de-escalate the situation?
Well, China suggests the US
could get rid of the THAAD missile defense
system
protecting South Korea for a Northern attack.
I mean that’s totally reasonable right?
It absolutely wouldn’t have anything to
do with
China being worried THAAD
could threaten Chinese missile strikes
in the future.
Especially if say, the United States
does strike the North Korean regime
and suddenly there are US troops on China’s
borders.
But don’t worry,
I’m sure the US won’t strike North Korea.
“North Korea best not make any more
threats to the United States.
They will be met with fire and fury,
like the world has never seen.”
Don’t worry though.
According to Secretary of State Rex Tillerson,
that was just President Trump speaking
to North Korea in language
that Kim Jong-un can understand.
And North Korea proved Kim understood that
language
by saying that they would attack the US territory
of Guam
with “enveloping fire” by launching missiles.
You guys, they’re speaking the same language.
They’re having a heart-to-heart talk!
Seriously though, the most recent UN sanctions
are a good start to dealing with North Korea’s
nuclear threats--
an increasingly complicated issue
that makes everyone look back fondly
on the simple days when Kim Jong-il
would just stand around looking at stuff.
That’s another thing that the US,
China, and Russia can all agree on.
Coming up after the break,
the Chinese Communist Party has come up with
a novel way to eliminate poverty.
You know, maybe that movie Red Dawn
can still happen.
In case it does,
you’ll want to see every episode of China
Uncensored
as soon as possible.
This segment was part of our full half hour
episode
that you could have seen on Friday.
Go to China Uncensored dot TV
to catch full length episodes every Friday.