On this episode of China Uncensored,
China’s Xi Jinping has been named “core
leader.”
And with great power,
comes GREAT POWER!!!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
You might think that if you’re already
the leader of the unfree world
and oversee the biggest country on Earth,
with the biggest military,
there’s not much room for job advancement.
But you’d be wrong.
Because last week,
the guy who already holds the titles
of General Secretary of the Communist Party,
Commander-in-Chief of the People’s Liberation
Army,
and President of the PRC
just got a promotion.
Yes,
Xi Jinping is now China’s “core leader.”
Thanks Chris Buckley.
I love a good "core" pun.
By the way,
that's the most human looking photo of Xi
Jinping
I've ever seen.
He actually looks like he might be enjoying
that apple.
Anyway,
back to the core issue here.
This is big.
I can’t stress that enough.
Core leader is a term first used by Deng Xiaoping
to describe himself, and Mao Zedong.
Xi has entered the pantheon
of the Communist Party's Olympus.
This comes after years of Xi Jinping
purging his political rivals—
members of a faction tied mainly to
former Chinese Leader and underworld amphibian,
Jiang Zemin.
When Xi first came to power in 2013,
one of the first things he said he wanted
to do
was eliminate labor camps.
He was blocked.
Labor camps were a huge source of money and
power
for Zhou Yongkang,
Jiang's protégé and one of Xi’s biggest
opponents.
But after months purging officials in the
oil industry
with ties to Zhou,
before the year was out,
Xi was able to close labor camps down and
begin
an investigation into Zhou
that would lead to his eventual downfall.
And even that only happened last year.
It’s been a slow grind,
but now that Xi is the core leader,
he’s basically filled his special bar.
Now, he can finally take down the biggest
tiger of them all—
Jiang Zemin.
You see,
Jiang Zemin had also been named a core leader
by Deng Xiaoping.
Sorry Hu Jintao,
always the bridesmaid,
never the bride.
But Jiang's situation was different than Mao or Deng.
Deng Xiaoping named Jiang a “core leader”
because of how unstable the Party had become
following the Tiananmen Square Massacre.
If it wasn’t clear that Deng fully supported
Jiang,
other political opportunists would have tried
to overthrow him.
And even still, there were attempts.
Xi, on the other hand,
took the title himself after slowly taking
out his opposition.
This was all carefully planned.
In fact,
references to Xi being called the core leader
by lower level officials
started appearing in state-run media
back in January.
And now that he’s a core leader,
he’s in a position to take out the previous
core leader.
But when people start putting your face on
souvenirs
next to Mao Zedong,
it means you’re both very powerful,
and at huge risk of being taken down.
You see,
in 1980,
a few years after Mao died,
the Communist Party created the
Rules on Intra-party Political Life.
It was set up to prevent the kind of personality cult
Mao created, that plunged China into
the chaos of the Cultural Revolution.
The last guy accused of starting a personality
cult
was Bo Xilai.
Here he is
on a recent 8-part reality show of top officials
purged in Xi Jinping’s anti-corruption campaign.
Bo Xilai and his heavy-jowled mentor, Zhou
Yongkang
supposedly tried to stage a coup against Xi.
They obviously did not succeed.
Well now Xi has made it to core leader.
So, does he have the power he’s been trying
to amass
since the beginning?
Not quite.
The core leader announcement also stressed
“collective leadership”,
i.e. that collective leadership
“must always be followed
and should not be violated by any organization
or individual
under any circumstance
or for any reason.”
Collective leadership was also the system
in place
when Hu Jintao was Party head.
It meant that China’s top leaders—
the Politburo Standing Committee members—
had a lot individual say in how things were
run.
And since under Hu Jintao,
most of those guys were loyal to Jiang Zemin,
Hu couldn’t just do whatever he wanted.
Currently,
only three Standing Committee members
are still loyal to Jiang,
and they’re about to get force-retired
at next year’s National People’s Congress.
At that point,
Xi will get to hand pick the collective leadership.
In other words,
there’s still more power Xi can grab.
And if he gets it, then what?
Well, he may use it to stay in power
beyond the year 2022,
when, according to supposed precedent,
he would to step down
because he will have served two five-year
terms.
But since literally no Chinese Communist leader
in history,
except Hu Jintao,
has followed this precedent,
there’s really no precedent.
And Xi will probably do whatever he can
to stay in power.
So it ain’t over till the fat leader sings.
But all of this is basically following
what I predicted back in 2013:
Xi tries to play the role of the great reformer.
But he discovers,
oh the Communist Party is too corrupt to save—
in which case China would need a new system.
You know, not quite a president, or a dictator.
More of a presitator.
And with great power, comes...GREAT POWER!!!
So what do you think?
Is this the beginning of the end for the Communist Party?
And if so,
do you think Xi would hire me to head
the new English language Xinhua News?
Leave your comments below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.