A Chinese warship
Is tracked by Japan and Taiwan
Is a new alliance forming?
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
This episode has been sponsored\h
by Surfshark—because you should\h\h
be protecting your identity whenever you\h
go online by using a VPN like Surfshark.
The Chinese Communist Party is engaged\h
in territorial disputes with basically\h\h
all of its neighbors. The\h
problem for China is, sometimes,\h\h
when you bully people too much, they\h
eventually start to team up. Against you.
And that may be what’s\h
happening with Taiwan and Japan.
It seems like Taiwan and Japan\h
teamed up to track a Chinese warship.
Both sides are being pretty quiet\h
about it, but here’s what we know.
According to a Japanese Defense Ministry\h
announcement, a Chinese warship, the Binzhou,\h\h
was caught in the East China Sea. That’s where\h
China and Japan have a territorial dispute\h\h
over some uninhabited islands. It sailed\h
through what's called the Miyako Strait.
The Binzhou sailed through the narrow\h
waters between Taiwan and Japan’s\h\h
Westernmost inhabited island, Yonaguni.\h
That’s only 70 miles from Taiwan’s coast.
Three Japanese ships tracked it. But on\h
May 1, this satellite image was released.\h\h
It shows that a Taiwanese warship was\h
also there, tracking the Chinese ship.
“Taipei’s Apple Daily described it as\h
the first joint surveillance operation\h\h
between Taiwan and Japan.”
However, Taiwan’s defense ministry didn’t\h
confirm that. It just said they track any\h\h
Chinese warship sailing through designated\h
areas. And remember, it was close to Taiwan.
A Taiwan defense official said, the\h
Binzhou’s “crew was likely on a training and\h\h
intelligence-gathering mission,” and “‘did not\h
pose a serious threat’ to Taiwan’s security.’”
I mean, not a serious threat, other than\h
the fact China has promised to conquer\h\h
Taiwan. Which is what all China’s training\h
and intelligence-gathering missions are for.
And China’s People’s Liberation\h
Army didn’t stop there.
While the Binzhou warship was sailing between\h
Taiwan and Japan, five Chinese fighter jets\h\h
flew into Taiwan’s air defense identification\h
zone—this time between Taiwan and the Philippines.
“According to Taipei's Defense Ministry,\h\h
a Chinese Y-8 anti-submarine warfare\h
aircraft crossed the Bashi Channel.”
The Bashi Channel the Chinese aircraft flew over,\h
and the Miyako Strait the Binzhou sailed through,\h\h
are both very important strategic locations.
They’re among the few waterways the Chinese\h
military has of exiting the first island chain.\h\h
They can be used to give or cut off access\h
between the South China Sea and the Pacific.
In other words, these are territorial\h
waters the Chinese Communist Party\h\h
must take in order to secure a grip on the\h
region. So the Communist Party is being\h\h
very clear about its long-term goals. Which are\h
obviously concerning to both Japan and Taiwan.
And while the two countries don’t\h
have official diplomatic relations,\h\h
there are signs that ties are warming.
Yes, despite Japan having\h
occupied Taiwan for 50 years,\h\h
they can still be friends. And\h
for that, you can thank China.
And this episode is sponsored by Surfshark.
Whenever you go online, you should be\h
using a VPN like Surfshark to protect\h\h
your identity. Everything you do online is being\h
tracked and logged—by the websites you visit\h\h
and your internet service provider.\h
And in many cases, by the government.
And if you’re in an\h
authoritarian country like China\h\h
this kind of tracking can put you at\h
risk of surveillance and even arrest.
So I recommend you use Surfshark\h
to protect yourself online.
When you use Surfshark’s CleanWeb mode,\h\h
you’ll be protected from trackers,\h
plus a lot of ads and malware.
With one account, you can connect\h
as many devices as you want.\h\h
Try it out with a 30-day money back guarantee.
And Surfshark has a special discount for China\h
Uncensored fans. Go to surfshark.com/uncensored\h\h
and use the code UNCENSORED to get our special\h
deal that includes 3 extra months for FREE.
Click the link below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell. See you next time.