bjbj,(,( China is a Twit About Twitter Hi,
welcome to China Uncensored, I m Chris Chappell.
You know there s a funny habit oppressive
regimes always seem to share, they tend to
indulge in the same things they forbid the
people from having. And sometimes, it backfires.
Especially when it has to do with computers.
Because computers are hard. That s what someone
at China s state-run Xinhua news agency found
out when he tried to post a Tweet. You see
China has some pretty strict Internet censorship.
That s why you can t get on facebook in China.
You might see something subversive. But you
re also not allowed to get on Twitter. Which
might make you think why the state-run Xinhua
news agency even has a Twitter account to
begin with. But then really, who told you
to think? So here s a tweet by a twit at Xinhua.
He s answering a question asking why the account
hasn t been active. And WHOEVER ASKED THAT
QUESTION BETTER NOT HAVE BEEN IN CHINA! Basically
the old account manager quit and didn t tell
anyone how to get around the Internet blockade.
That was the first post since 2011. But that
hasn t stopped Xinhua from setting up a fully
functional English language twitter account.
So if they only have a functioning English
account, and you aren t allowed to go on Twitter
in China, who are they really talking to?
Over the past few years, China has pumped
billions of dollars into foreign language
media campaigns. For example, A 40 BY 60 FOOT
LED 24 hours a day 7 DAY A WEEK 365 DAY A
YEAR AD FOR XINHUA IN THE CENTER OF NEW YORKs
TIMES SQUARE. And so while the rest of the
world is talking about China s rampant corruption,
political infighting, and atrocious human
rights record, if you go to the official source
for China news, you get stories like this
about Chinese leader Xi Jinping. He also has
dreamy eyes. So if you want real Chinese news
in 160 characters or less, forget Xinhua,
check out my twitter account. Or if you still
want fake China news, just go to the Relevant
Organs. They re fake China news is way better
than Xinhua s fake China news. Thanks for
watching this episode of China Uncensored.
Once again I m Chris Chappell, see you next
time. Dreamy eyes Chinese hasn t been working
since 2011, but the English Xinhua twitter
is fully operational. The push for soft power
In this Chinese language Xinhua Tweet, this
message a response to a question asking why
the account has not been active says, quote,
it can t be helped, the previous account manager
didn t tell us how to scale the wall before
he left, I am new here. JUST SO LONG AS YOU
DON T DO IT CHINA! h1K) gdNF gdNF [Content_Types].xml
#!MB ;c=1 _rels/.rels theme/theme/themeManager.xml
sQ\}# theme/theme/theme1.xml G$$DA : BR \{i5@R
V*[_X ,l\Y Ssd+r] 5\|E Vky- V4Ej 6NGU s?^V
* 7;wP EBU` 5VD
GGHPXNT, /M,W m2iU [[v _Xtl theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.rels
6?$Q K(M&$R(.1 [Content_Types].xmlPK _rels/.relsPK
theme/theme/themeManager.xmlPK theme/theme/theme1.xmlPK
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.relsPK
<a:clrMap xmlns:a="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/main"
bg1="lt1" tx1="dk1" bg2="lt2" tx2="dk2" accent1="accent1"
accent2="accent2" accent3="accent3" accent4="accent4"
accent5="accent5" accent6="accent6" hlink="hlink"
folHlink="folHlink"/> Chris Normal.dotm Chris
Microsoft Macintosh Word PICT" kZg9^ kZkZ^
o\{o\{c %kZkZc g9g9^ g9g9kZg9g9c g9g9c g9g9w
=g9o\{c o\{kZkZo\{g9o\{o\{kZo\{o\{kZkZg9kZkZs kZkZg9s
o\{kZkZw kZo\{o\{kZkZc o\{o\{s o\{g9kZw kZo\{s o\{kZkZo\{s
kZkZo\{o\{g9kZo\{g9g9 g9kZg9o\{s o\{kZg9s g9kZ\
kZg9c o\{g9c kZNsV %g9c kZo\{w kZg9kZs o\{kZs
g9o\{o\{g9 o\{o\{s o\{kZs o\{kZg9c kZg9c g9o\{kZkZg9^
g9g9kZg9c kZg9s g9g9o\{g9g9c g9kZg9g9kZo\{kZg9c
g9kZc 1kZZ o\{kZkZ^ !kZg9Z kZkZV g9g9 g9kZkZw
o\{o\{s o\{o\{s o\{-kZo\{w o\{g9\{ o\{o\{g9o\{o\{g9kZo\
kZo\{ g9kZs g9g9c kZkZo\{g9s kZkZs o\{o\{ o\{o\{g9g9o\{s
g9g9R g9g9c kZg9s g9kZ^ *g9c o\{kZo\{Z kZo\{^
kZNsV ,g9o\{kZo\{kZo\{kZ\{ o\{kZo\{o\{kZkZo\{w kZo\{g9s
kZo\{kZkZo\{o\{s kZkZo\{w kZg9kZ o\{o\{c kZkZo\{w
g9kZkZo\{s kZg9g9 o\{o\{g9^ g9o\{ o\{g9 o\{kZkZg9s
g9kZkZs o\{g9s o\{g9kZkZg9kZg9kZw kZkZg9kZkZs
g9g9c o\{o\{Z g9g9V g9g9^ kZo\{V kZg9g9V g9 Z
kZo\{g9^ kZkZ^ o\{o\{g9^ o\{o\{ Dg9R Nsg9Z g9g9JRg9JRV
NskZR g9g9V o\{NsV g9g9kZ g9g9Z g9o\{w o\{o\
g9o\{kZkZg9c g9g9^ o\{kZkZs g9g9 kZ%V g9kZg9c
kZo\{c g9g9Z g9o\{o\{g9kZc g9kZw kZkZ^ g9g9w
kZo\{o\{s o\{o\{w kZo\{kZo\{w o\{o\{kZ g9o\{c g9g9R
3kZV o\{o\{ o\{o\{ 4kZc g9g9o\{c g9g9Z kZg9Z g9kZ^
kZg9c kZkZ^ o\{o\{w g9o\{g9g9s kZo\{w o\{o\{w o\{kZ
g9g9c o\{o\{g9c g9g9s g9g9s o\{g9c <o\{o\{g9kZkZw
o\{g9kZs g9kZs g9kZg9s o\{kZg9s kZkZc o\{g9o\{s
kZo\{s kZkZo\{o\{g9o\{g9s kZkZg9kZ kZo\{c g9g9\{
g9kZ o\{kZw g9kZ ;g9c kZkZZ kZkZg9^ o\{g9g9Z
g9g9kZc g9g9kZkZg9^ o\{o\{w g9o\{ o\{g9w o\{g9c
kZo\{o\{^ kZo\{ kZkZo\{kZo\{o\{s kZo\{o\{kZs kZg9s
o\{o\{w kZkZs g9g9kZg9g9kZkZo\{kZg9V g9g9o\{g9
g9g9kZs o\{g9o\{o\{kZo\{o\{c g9kZo\{g9o\{V o\{o\{kZs
g9kZs kZg9o\{c o\{o\{w kZc o\{g9^ kZg9^ g9kZ o\{g9^
g9g9^ g9g9V g9kZZ g9g9^ kZg9^ g9kZc g9kZo\
o\{g9g9o\{s o\{o\{s kZo\{g9w o\{o\{kZw kZo\{s o\{o\{s
o\{kZ kZkZ o\{kZV kZg9Z kZkZV kZg9V Title Microsoft
Word 97-2004 Document NB6W Word.Document.8