On this episode of China Uncensored,
Santa has clearly done some
outsourcing to China.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored. I'm your
host, Chris Chappell.
Merry Christmas.
And a very merry Christmas to the factory
workers in Yiwu,
a town in eastern China's Zhejiang province.
Because they've been working on Christmas
since January.
The US imported more than a half a billion
dollars’ worth
of Christmas decorations from Yiwu just in
2015.
It's is such an important exporter of cheap
products to Europe
that last year, China opened an 8,000-mile
rail line to Spain
that starts in Yiwu.
Now you might think it's weird that a single
town makes so much of a specific product,
but in fact, that's a thing in China.
For example, in the city of Songxia,
there are twelve hundred factories dedicated
just to making umbrellas—
1.3 billion dollars worth each year.
Qiaotou makes 60 percent of the world's buttons.
And Datang cranks out 8 billion pairs of socks
every year.
Presumably to feed George Clooney's sock habit.
And in Yiwu, they make 60 percent of the world's
Christmas decorations.
Peak season is July and August.
So it gets pretty hot in factories like this
one.
Somehow it doesn't seem like the healthiest
place to work.
And it's just one of more than 700 factories
in Yiwu.
Those photos were from Sina.com.
But for a happier look, here are some photos
from state-run Xinhua News.
Wait, that one's creepy.
Oh my gosh, are they building a clone army
of Santas?
Jango Fett, you've met your match.
But anyway, what's really amazing
is not just that China is the world's Christmas
factory,
but that Chinese people celebrate it too.
It's still a fairly new holiday in China.
Remember, less than 40 years ago,
the Communist Party banned Western beliefs
and traditions,
calling them "mental poison."
And even today, the Chinese Christian church
is run by the Communist Party.
So unsurprisingly, Christmas is not a particularly
religious holiday in China.
But it has recently become China's second-biggest
holiday, after Chinese New Year.
Like in America, it's a time for crazy amounts
of shopping.
But instead of Christmas Eve being family
time, it's more like
go-out-and-sing-karaoke-with-your-friends-and-drink-beer time.
Also, Santa playing the saxophone is a thing.
It's deeply disturbing—yet somehow I can't
get enough.
Anyway, as you know from my video last Christmas,
I try to avoid buying Christmas stuff made
in China.
But with most of the world's Christmas decorations
being made there,
and not in the North Pole, as some parental
figures tole me,
I want to give a shout-out to the hundreds
of thousands of people in China
who make Christmas come true.
And a Merry Christmas,
and, you know, other holidays,
to China Uncensored fans like you who've supported
me this year.
I'm off for a week, but I'll see you again
before New Years'.
I'm Chris Chappell. Thanks for watching.
The world enters what scientists call “the
post-antibiotic era.”
The BBC says this “could plunge medicine
back into the dark ages.”
If you've been watching this show for a while,
you know that China has plans for world domination.