On this episode of China Uncensored,
Teresa May I?
Start a Golden Era of UK China relations?
China’s belt and road
will squeeze you,
and then run you over.
And finally, China’s building weapons
that could shoot down satellites.
Good thing I’m also on cable.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
In our top story,
according to my favorite Chinese state run
media,
Chinese civilization isn’t just ancient
anymore.
It’s extra ancient!
And that’s been proven.
You know what that means:
More things will be part of Chinese territory
since ancient times.
Like all of world history.
And while China may love Uncle Trump,
He’s taking a backseat right now to
British Prime Minister Theresa May,
also known as “Auntie May.”
“‘Auntie May’ is a warm expression,
just like we call Xi Jinping ‘Uncle Xi’”
to show our fondness.
Whoa, that kid’s got it mixed up.
Trump is the Uncle.
Xi is the Dada.
So: Auntie Theresa May,
Uncle Donald Trump,
and Daddy Xi Jinping.
That’s a heck of a family reunion.
No politics at the dinner table, everyone.
Anyway, Prime Minister May made a
three-day trip to China this week.
She said she “will intensify
the golden era in UK-China relations.”
Golden Era is of course referencing
what China was calling a Golden Era
between China and the UK back in 2015.
That’s when Chinese leader Xi Jinping
visited the UK,
and knocked back a few pints
with then Prime Minister David Cameron,
and—in the highlight of his trip—
took a selfie with famous soccer player
Sergio Agüero.
Of course, that was years ago,
and with the old prime minister before Brexit.
But we can still have a golden era, right?
Right?
Well, the Chinese regime knows it might have
an advantage over the UK now.
As state-run newspaper Xinhua puts it,
“To mitigate the impact of a potential Brexit
cliff edge,
Britain is under immense pressure to consolidate
bilateral trade relations beyond Europe.”
By “beyond Europe”, they mean “with
China.”
But don’t worry.
That wouldn’t mean Prime Minister May
is going to sell out human rights for economic
gain.
Especially when it comes to raising concerns
about the erosion of freedoms
in the former British colony,
Hong Kong.
Wait, what’s that Shelley?
Oh, she actually did sell out.
And Chinese state-run media praised her for
it.
Pro-tip: If the Communist Party’s
state-run media is praising you,
you’ve probably done something horribly,
horribly wrong.
So what does all this mean for Hong Kong?
Well, it means freedom there isn’t free.
In fact, it’s priceless,
because the Chinese Communist Party
simply won’t allow it.
This is Agnes Chow.
She’s famous for her role
in the 2014 Umbrella Movement,
a several-months-long protest against Beijing
for going back on its promise of
universal suffrage for Hong Kong.
And now she’s been disqualified from running
for Hong Kong’s legislative council.
The Hong Kong government said
she was disqualified because her political
party,
Demosisto, advocated for self-determination,
which the government said was against
Hong Kong’s constitution,
the Basic Law.
But self-determination isn’t the same as
saying
Hong Kong should be independent from China.
It just means that Hong Kongers
should be able to choose their own future.
Therefore, it shouldn’t violate the Basic
Law.
But surely, Agnes was only disqualified
because the Hong Kong government
thinks someone with her point of view
could never win;
so really they’re just doing her a favor
by saving her the trouble of running a campaign.
It has nothing to do with increasing pressure
from the CCP to undermine Hong Kong’s elections.
But this does follow the resentencing
of another Umbrella Movement leader,
Joshua Wong...
and the disqualification of other
democratically elected legislators
Beijing doesn’t like.
So maybe there’s a larger thing going on
here.
Chow was running to replace Nathan Law’s
seat in the Legislative Council.
He had lost his seat for for quoting Gandhi
while taking his oath of office.
Law was also from the Demosisto party.
But he was allowed to run for office
a year and a half ago.
Strange how supporting self-determination
wasn’t an issue then.
About 2,000 people showed up Sunday
to protest Chow’s disqualification.
And according to a new Pentagon report,
China and Russia are developing weapons
that could shoot down US satellites by 2020.
US Defence Secretary Jim Mattis
has called China and Russia a bigger threat
than Islamic terrorism,
a statement backed by Australia.
“Australia has backed
a new United States defense strategy
naming Russia and China a greater threat
to national security than Islamic terrorism.”
I don’t know though.
I hear ISIS is working on some pretty impressive
anti-satellite technology.
Hey, remember that song
about China’s Belt and Road Initiative
from state-run media?
“The future’s coming now.
Oh oh oh oh.
The Belt and Road is how.
Oh oh oh oh.”
Just wanted to get that ear worm
stuck in your head again.
You’re welcome.
So despite all the talk about joint prosperity
and the like the Belt and Road
most definitely will bring—
turns out,
that might not be the case.
According to this report from a US think tank,
pretty much all the contractors hired
for the Belt and Road’s ambitious construction
projects
are Chinese.
By comparison,
when multilateral development banks
dole out contracts,
most contracts go to locals.
So the Belt and Road promises
economic development,
but then makes those countries borrow money
from China to pay Chinese contractors
to do most of the work.
That can lead to economic ruin instead.
That’s a problem for African countries like
Uganda.
“Uganda says this road
is the jewel in the crown of an infrastructure
project
to drive economic growth.
Critics say it will lead to more debt.
China lent Uganda $350 million—
about 60 percent of the cost—
towards building the 30-mile road.”
Also, some of the buildings the Chinese regime
has been building in Africa,
like the African Union building,
may be have been bugged.
Now sure, that sounds bad.
But have you considered this?
“We'll share the goodness now
Oh oh oh oh.
The Belt and Road is how
Oh oh oh oh.”
That’s the trouble with cheesy propaganda.
You just can’t stop listening to it.
And another foreign company
is in trouble with the Chinese regime
over the status of Taiwan.
Japanese retailer Muji
has been ordered to destroy a furniture catalog...
...because it had a map suggesting
Taiwan is a separate country.
The map also didn’t show a string of islands
both China and Japan claim.
Japan has lodged a protest over China
bossing around a Japanese company.
But I mean,
I don’t think China was too out of line
here.
I’d also want to destroy that furniture
catalog.
Not because of how Taiwan was labeled,
but because all Muji’s furniture
is just overpriced IKEA knockoffs.
And a Chinese national was spotted
illegally crossing the border into Laos—
according to this CCTV footage on CCTV.
They eventually caught him,
interrogated him,
and then forced him to join
China’s national basketball team.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Want to see more China Uncensored?
Head over to ChinaUncensored.tv,
where you can see full half hour
episodes of the show for free.
That’s ChinaUncensored.tv.