Jackie Chan
Loves the Chinese Communist Party
He says wants to become a Chinese Communist
Party member!
But does the Party want him?
Welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
World-famous martial artist and actor Jackie
Chan is making a desperate plea to the Chinese
Communist Party.
“I’m honoured to be a Chinese person.
But I’m also envious of you Chinese Communist
Party members.
I just feel like the CCP is truly too great.
For every promise that the CCP makes, it doesn’t
even take a century, but only decades to become
reality.
I want to be a Chinese Communist Party member.
Thank you all.”
[applause]
Yes, he wants to be a Chinese Communist Party
member.
Please, oh please, let him in!
And while Jackie Chan’s bootlicking would
embarrass even Smithers , he may not even
be good enough for the CCP.
Which I’ll get to later.
But first, I’d like to say that Jackie Chan
used to be cool.
Here he is singing at the Concert for Democracy
in China.
It was held in Hong Kong—his hometown—to
support the Tiananmen Square student protesters
in Beijing.
That was just one week before the tanks rolled
in.
And here Chan is in Taiwan in 1992, receiving
one of the ten Outstanding Chinese Youth Special
Awards, and shaking hands with Taiwan’s
first democratically elected president, Lee
Tung-hui .
It doesn’t seem like Jackie Chan would’ve
been the type to support the Chinese Communist
Party.
But that all started to change after the 1997
transfer of Hong Kong to Chinese rule.
Then, Chan seemed to transform himself from
a proud Hong Konger, into a proud Chinese
nationalist.
And in that weird brainwashed way, where he
conflates being ethnically Chinese with loving
the Chinese Communist Party.
This next clip is from 2009, when Jackie Chan
was invited to speak at a cross-strait symposium
as Hong Kong’s tourism ambassador.
“Is having freedom good?
Or is not having freedom good?
Really, I get those confused.
Too much freedom and you become like what
Hong Kong is today: chaotic.
Not to mention they’re becoming like Taiwan:
Also chaotic.
Uh, I’ve slowly begun to think that us Chinese
people need to be controlled.”
According to Chan, both Hong Kong and Taiwan
are just too free.
Like pets without a leash!
They’re in desperate need of control.
They need the warm, loving iron fist of the
Chinese Communist Party!
By the way, Chan’s whole thing about countries
with too much freedom being “chaotic”
is straight out of Communist Party propaganda.
In 2013, Chan was appointed to join the Chinese
People’s Political Consultative Conference.
Appointments are often used as a way to boost
celebrities’ egos while making the Party
look like it's open to outside ideas.
Hint: It’s not.
Unlike America.
A place where a celebrity can push for criminal
justice reform.
And actually get it done.
In China, it’s the opposite.
The Communist Party gives people high-up positions
as a way to control them.
And the Party is not open to constructive
criticism.
This year, Jackie Chan was also given membership
to Hong Kong’s newly reformed Election Committee—where
a group of unelected people get to participate
in a rigged election to determine the next
leader of Hong Kong.
Chan is also a Vice Chairman of the China
Film Association, which refers to itself as
“an important force for the prosperity and
development of socialist literature and art
and the construction of a strong socialist
cultural country.”
And by development and construction, they
mean endorsing censorship.
Here’s an interview Jackie Chan did with
CGTN in August 2019—as the anti-Chinese
Communist Party protests were raging in Hong
Kong.
0:38 I have visited many countries, and I
can say, our country has been rapidly developing
in recent years.
I feel pride in being Chinese wherever I go,
and the ‘Five-starred Red Flag’ is respected
everywhere around the world.
1:06 Hong Kong and China are my birthplaces
and my home.
China is my country, I love my country, I
love my home.
So what was Chan doing in June of that year
when the Hong Kong protests were happening?
He was drinking tea in Taiwan, promoting his
new album.
And he claimed he did not know anything about
the Hong Kong protests while he was there.
But what Jackie Chan seems to have forgotten
is that his success as a movie star is not
thanks to the Chinese Communist Party.
It’s thanks to Hong Kong’s freedoms.
I’ll explain after the break.
Welcome back.
Jackie Chan was born in Hong Kong—back when
it was a British territory.
And that’s where his career took off.
Hong Kong’s political and economic freedom
made it one of the world’s most flourishing
filmmaking industries—especially for martial
arts films.
For decades, Hong Kong was the world’s second
largest motion picture exporter.
Jackie Chan began his career in Hong Kong
films in the 60s and 70s.
In 1980, he starred in his first Hollywood
film.
That movie may have been dumb, but it was
his big break.
After that Chan’s career took off—thanks
to the freedoms of Hong Kong, and eventually
America.
And at the time, the film industry in China
was just pushing out boring propaganda films.
Unlike now, when some of them are interesting
propaganda films.
This article from 1991 says: “From the point
of view of the studios, an important advantage
of [China’s] political films is that no
matter how awful they are, they make money
because the great majority of tickets are
bought in bulk by offices and factories.
Employees are encouraged to see the films
during normal work hours.”
So while Jackie Chan was filming classics
like the thrilling “Police Story” and
the jam-packed “Drunken Master” mainland
China was pouring all its money into films
about the Communist Party like the “Creation
of a World”, and “Mao Zedong and His Son”.
So why on earth would Jackie Chan want to
join the Chinese Communist Party?
I don’t know.
But it does seem the Chinese Communist Party
hesitates to have Jackie Chan join.
I mean, he might not be good for the Party’s
image.
Which is sad, because their bar is real low.
On the business end, Chan is what Chinese
people call a broom star an old term for a
comet.
It means that Chan is bad luck.
Whatever product he endorses, ends up failing
miserably.
He’s promoted Chinese computer brand Xiaobawang
, and also the VCD player brand Aiduo . Never
heard of those?
That’s because Xiaobawang filed for bankruptcy,
and Aiduo’s boss was put in prison for embezzlement.
But maybe that’s just a coincidence.
Those Chinese manufacturers would have fallen
on their own.
Jackie Chan even said it himself.
When I buy a television, I definitely go for
the Japanese TV…
China’s TV’s will explode!
Chinese products are just not trustworthy.
Whoops.
That won’t get you in to the Communist Party,
Jackie.
Chan also ran promotions for BaWang shampoo,
which later was found to have carcinogens.
Chan was also the spokesperson for Yujia real
estate.
But in September 2020, two of his Beijing
luxury condos developed by Yujia were seized
and auctioned because Yujia hadn’t paid
its debts.
Plus, the boy band Jackie Chan manages is
a total flop.
So needless to say, Jackie Chan isn’t very
good at non-movie stuff.
But the biggest backlash from critics of Chan’s
wish to join the Chinese Communist Party cite
his embarrassing personal life.
“Many have said on social media that he
has cheated on his wife and that his son has
used drugs, both of which would disqualify
him from [Party] membership.”
If adultery and drug use actually disqualified
people from the Chinese Communist Party...there
would be a lot fewer Chinese officials.
Anyway, one of the biggest scandals with Jackie
Chan is his extramarital affair with Hong
Kong actress Elaine Ng.
They had a daughter together, but Elaine had
to raise her all by herself.
Chan allegedly refused to pay child support
at the time.
The other scandal happened in 2014, police
raided Chan’s home—the same one that later
got seized and auctioned.
Jackie’s legitimate son, Jaycee Chan, was
found with 100 grams of marijuana.
The penalty for drugs in China is severe.
Jaycee pleaded guilty for sheltering others
to use drugs and ended up spending six months
in jail.
And Jackie Chan didn’t even show up at his
son’s trial.
I understand why Jackie Chan was embarrassed.
After all, the Chinese government had appointed
Chan as their “Anti-drug ambassador” back
in 2009.
Clearly, that was another non-movie thing
he wasn’t good at.
But weirdly, even after all of that, Chan
still manages to be a Chinese icon.
He even took center stage at the 100 anniversary
of the CCP.
.
A dark past of corruption and failure, but
he still looks good when he performs?
Maybe he is a good fit for the Chinese Communist
Party!
And now it’s time to answer a question from
a member of the China Uncensored 50 Cent Army,
fans who support us and our efforts to expose
the truth about the Chinese Communist Party,
by contributing through crowd funding website
Patreon.
jessie santiago asks, “Is the US and the
rest of the world paying attention?
Is the US taking steps?”
That question in response to my recent episode
China’s First Space Walk Hides a Dark Secret
.
Basically, the Chinese space program is run
by the People’s Liberation Army.
That’s right, not a civilian organization
like NASA.
Not even a private company run by an evil
super villain like SpaceX.
.
The Communist Party’s military.
That’s a huge danger to democracies around
the world.
“Advanced weapons at China’s military
bases can fire warheads that smash satellites
and can shoot laser beams that have a potential
to blind arrays of delicate sensors.”
And so the question was, is the US paying
attention?
Well, some in the intelligence and military
sectors have been sounding alarm bells for
years.
Not too much was done.
But the Trump Administration’s Space Force
was partly an attempt to turn things around.
The Space Force currently has bipartisan support
in Congress and in all likelihood, the Biden
Administration will continue it.
Last year, the Space Force unveiled its first
weapon, a satellite jammer.
So in many ways, space warfare has already
begun.
But the US is only just beginning to play
catch up.
Thanks for your question and your support
Jessie.
And a big thank you to everyone who supports
China Uncensored on Patreon.
We could not do this show without you.
So thank you for joining us in the fight to
expose the Chinese Communist Party to the
world.
If you’re interested in joining, head over
to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
You’ll get a bunch of cool perks, including
the chance to have me answer your question
on the show!
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next
time.