On this episode of China Uncensored,
don’t partake in the forbidden fruit.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Doing business in China.
It’s a foolproof way to make huge profits.
Say you’re a company like,
oh, I don’t know, Apple.
You have a great, innovative, original product
that surely the 1.3 billion people in China
would love.
Now conditions apply
any time a Western company wants to do business
in China,
but it’s totally worth it, right?
Well, it turns out,
it’s a business plan that makes about as
much sense as this:
“You see, Phase 1: collect underpants.
Phase 2...
Phase 3: Profit.”
And Apple might be discovering that
getting to Phase 3 is harder than it thought.
“This soap opera between the Chinese government
and Apple just continues…
Unfortunately, [there’s] huge opportunity
still in China,
and you just gotta kinda deal with the
bumps in the road with these types of announcements.”
Well, “bumps in the road” might not be
quite the right analogy.
It’s more like the Chinese government
is a giant gorilla throwing barrels at you.
And get a load of this barrel.
This is the Chinese smartphone, 100C.
Not the iPhone, as you might have first thought.
It’s a company so small,
it doesn’t even appear to have its own website.
And it just sued Apple in a Beijing court
for stealing its design.
Apple immediately appealed the decision, of
course.
So for now, the iPhone is still on sale,
and a final ruling could take a full year.
Now you might be wondering,
a no-name phone company sues Apple for stealing
its design,
when clearly it’s the other way around.
In what world does that happen?
China.
“It seems to me there could be some
backdoor political cronyism happening here.”
Because no matter how much money Apple invests
in Chinese companies,
or how willing it is to comply with Chinese
censorship,
the Chinese government has the same plan for
Apple
as it does for every Western company:
Lure them in with profits,
steal their intellectual property,
and make homegrown Chinese knockoffs to eventually
replace the original.
But they’ve been particularly harsh with
Apple.
“It reflects the challenges that I think
a lot of Western companies face when they
go to China.”
Chinese courts don’t really care about copyright.
If you don’t believe me,
check out this photo of my new iPhone.
No, that’s the 100C again.
No, that’s an actual iPhone.
I mean this,
my Chinese-made “iPhone” leather carrying
case!
In May, Apple lost the appeal
to stop a Chinese leather goods maker
from putting the brand label “iPhone”
on things
that are clearly not iPhones.
And just a few days before,
the Chinese regime had forced Apple to shut
down
iBooks and the iTunes movie feature,
just seven months after it had been launched.
This has been happening for a while.
This is from March 2013.
It’s a CCTV yearly exposé on scams,
defective products, and lousy customer service.
It also had some pretty rad song and dance
numbers.
And Apple was slammed for treating Chinese
consumers
differently from its other consumers around
the world.
The backlash was so intense,
Tim Cook had to issue a formal apology.
There’s even evidence that CCTV hired celebrities
to post negative comments about Apple.
Now this lawsuit in and of itself probably
won’t hurt Apple much.
By the time the court case is finished,
Apple will be onto the iPhone 7 and it will
be a moot point.
The real problem is that Chinese law,
and China’s courts,
are pretty much like the Wild West.
“Rules? In a knife fight?
No rules!”
And the hits Apple is taking in China has
some investors scared.
This one sold off $5 billion in Apple stock.
Yes, you heard me right: $5 billion.
Due in part to Chinese competitors and knockoffs,
Apple had a 26% year-on-year drop in iPhone
sales in China.
So what do you think of the hits Apple is
taking in China?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.