On this episode of China Uncensored,
China's growing interest
in “green” energy:
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
Bad news, everyone!
“Our world is in peril.”
That’s right.
Air pollution,
greenhouse gases,
fidget spinners—
the world is out of control, people!
Our planet,
voiced by Whoopi Goldberg,
is dying!
And now that President Donald Trump
has withdrawn the US
from the Paris climate agreement,
who can the world turn to for help?
One moment.
Moving on.
It's true that many are now looking to China
to be a global leader
when it comes to climate change.
Even some US politicians
plan to team up with China.
Like California Governor Jerry Brown,
who recently meet with Chinese officials
and green energy companies in Beijing.
"California is all in,
100 percent in meeting
the Paris Agreement—
in fact, going beyond.
We only make,
we only do that
if we are going to work with China,
Chinese provinces
to get the job done."
Yes, the Chinese government
has pledged to combat pollution.
China’s premier Li Keqiang has even promised
the return of blue skies.
Li also pledged
that upon the blue sky's return,
that he would ask it
to please tell us why
it had to hide away for so long,
so long,
where did we go wrong?
I didn’t realize Premier Li
was such a big E.L.O. fan.
But love is like oxygen.
You get too much,
you get too high.
Not enough…
then you’re probably living in Beijing.
So does this mean China is poised to become
a world leader in combating climate change?
Well, it turns out,
being a world leader in combating climate
change
is easier said than done.
Especially when parts of your country
look like a permanent Instagram filter.
I think this one's called
“Terracotta Worrier.”
Even though some Western media
and elected officials might be saying
China should replace the US on climate change,
that doesn’t mean the Chinese regime
is too keen on that.
According to my favorite Chinese state-run
media,
“Taking on global leadership
is too much, too soon for China.”
Here’s an example.
A recent inspection in one region of China
showed that a shocking 70% of companies there
were violating pollution regulations.
It’s a bit of a hiccup.
Or a gasping,
sputtering cough as it were.
Over the course of several months,
the Chinese Ministry of Environmental Protection
investigated some of China’s
most polluted cities
in the mega urban sprawl of Jing-jin-ji,
a combination of Hebei,
Beijing, and Tianjin.
Jing-Jin-ji.
It just rolls off the tongue.
Anyway, the ministry looked at
a variety of industries
and found that 14,000 out of 20,000 companies
were producing more emissions
than allowed,
or operating without pollution-control equipment.
But just because inspections
showed there was a problem
doesn’t mean the Chinese Communist Party
is going to effectively stop the problem.
Look, Chinese leaders
would love to have less pollution.
After all,
it literally makes China look bad.
I think this filter's called "Cobalt Monoxide."
But it’s complicated.
The Chinese economy
is heavily dependent on manufacturing,
which creates tons of pollution.
And the Party isn’t willing
to sacrifice China’s economy
to save the planet.
The promise of economic prosperity
is the main thing keeping the Communist Party
in power right now.
But pollution is also a potential threat
to the Party’s power.
Pollution is one of the few issues
the Chinese mainstream middle class will protest.
En masse,
like this one in Jiangsu
back in 2012.
And in Dalian,
after tens of thousands of white collar workers
protested in 2011,
they successfully forced
a chemical plant to relocate.
Anti-pollution protests
are one of the only kinds of protest
that can have an effect in China.
And that's because these protests
are generally directed at local companies
or local government officials—
and not at the Party Central.
At least, for the time being.
You see, the Chinese Communist Party
has set up a system
where the central government
solves pollution problems
by issuing guidelines and targets
and then leaves it up to local officials
to implement the guidelines
and reach the targets.
On one hand,
this enables the Party
to blame local officials
when things go wrong.
But on the other hand,
this system is not necessarily effective
when dealing with pollution.
Because local officials don’t always
come up with pollution solutions
that are...not stupid.
Like how, to keep skies blue,
local officials in Beijing
banned outdoor barbecuing.
Repeatedly.
And in Xi’an,
officials just stuffed cotton gauze
into the air monitoring equipment.
Hey, the numbers don't lie.
Except they really, really do.
And in this lovely city in China’s Hebei
province,
villagers protested against a chemical plant
they alleged was giving them cancer.
So officials had a great solution.
"They blocked the doors to our village houses
to stop us going out and blocking the road.
Some would take you away,
some would beat you,
some hit you so badly
you'd end up in hospital."
As you can see,
Chinese officials really beat the problem.
What’s that, Shelley?
OK, too soon.
But China is changing, you say!
They’re investing billions of dollars
in renewable energy.
That’s true.
But there are still many state-owned enterprises
in the power, steel, and cement sectors
that rely on coal.
And they have tremendous power
to block limits on coal emissions
that could hurt their bottom line.
According to the US Energy Information Administration,
China burns almost as much coal
as the rest of the world combined.
This was Beijing at the end of last year.
I think they're calling this filter,
“Orange Is the New Blue.”
But, according to the Paris Agreement
that China just signed,
all that’s going to change.
Just kidding.
It allows China to actually increase emissions
until 2030.
But don’t worry,
that’s when the Chinese regime promises
CO2 emissions will peak.
“I’m totally going to quit smoking,
Just gimme, like,
twelve more years.”
Now to be fair,
over the past two years,
China has stopped the construction
of 103 new coal power plants.
And over the past several years,
coal consumption has already been decreasing.
But according to this article,
that’s “largely because of slowing economic
growth.”
And while the Chinese regime canceled construction
of a bunch of coal plants,
there are “46 coal-to-chemical plants in operation,
and another 22 under construction.”
But there's still plenty of time
for China to actually meet its targets
from the Paris Agreement.
As long as local officials
have a steady supply of cotton gauze.
And on top of that,
China is also helping other countries pollute—
through its One Belt, One Road project.
Basically, China is helping developing nations
build coal-fired power plants.
According to National Geographic,
a state-owned Chinese company
is currently building a $2 billion
coal power plant in Kenya.
And in Africa overall,
more than 100 new coal plants
are in development,
and about half are being funded by China.
This is not to say Chinese officials
don’t care about pollution.
Many of them genuinely do.
It’s just that this kind of green
always comes first.
So what do you think of
China’s ability to fight pollution?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode
of China Uncensored.
Once again, I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
See you next time.