On this episode of China Uncensored,
China wants to use drones to hunt Tibetans.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I'm your host Chris Chappell.
Is it a dystopian sci-fi future?
Or just China today?
Yes, China is working on a rating system for
every citizen.
Yes, China wants to go to the Moon to mine
Helium 3.
Yes, China is planning to build orbital space
lasers.
And now this.
Wait, sorry. That's from Star Wars.
But, sadly, it's not far from reality.
Because the Chinese regime has set up a new
frontier monitoring system in Tibet.
A system that will track people using radar
and drones,
according to a November 6th report in China
Daily.
Unlike in America, where border patrol tries
to keep people out...
...in China, border patrol tries to keep citizens
from leaving.
Now I'm not sure why anyone would want to
leave Tibet.
I mean, sure the Chinese Communist Party under
Mao Zedong killed an estimated 1.2 million
Tibetans,
and destroyed 6,000 Tibetan monasteries.
But that was a long time ago!
It's not like there's cultural genocide happening
now.
Oh.
But according to state-run media,
Tibet has a growing economy...
...and is full of happy faces!
In fact, Lhasa tops CCTV's list of the happiest
place in China!
So it's hard to imagine that anyone would
want to leave.
And yet, for some reason, several thousand
Tibetans flee Tibet every year.
Tibetan refugees attempt a dangerous trek
across the Himalayas in hopes of making it
to India or Nepal.
I can't stress how dangerous this is.
Because in addition to avoiding dangerous
mountain conditions,
they also have to avoid Chinese soldiers.
For example, a group of Western mountain climbers
caught this footage near the Nepalese border
in 2008.
Dozens of Tibetan refugees are walking in
line through the mountains of snow trying
to reach India and see the Dalai Lama, their
spiritual leader
Everybody can see the Chinese soldier standing
in shooting position
He opens fire.
The bullets hit human flesh.
They're shooting them like dogs.
Whoa. Did you see that?
No, of course you didn't.
Because according Chinese state-run media
Xinhua,
the Tibetans had attacked the People's Armed
Police.
And so the soldiers were forced to defend
themselves.
As you can see from the footage.
That was in 2008.
But now, no longer will the brave Chinese
border soldiers have to hunt Tibetans alone,
purely out of a sense of responsibility.
Because now, China has drones.
Here's how it will work.
The Chinese drones will provide "round-the-clock,
all-weather surveillance of illegal cross-border
movements.
People trying to cross the border will be
detected by the system,
which then automatically notifies soldiers."
And then the soldiers...
"He opens fire. The bullets hit human flesh."
And in case that doesn't work,
the new monitoring system also includes acoustic
weapons.
Now I think I've heard something about how
loud sounds on snowy mountains are a good
idea.
But acoustic weapons are also capable of anything
from causing nausea and disorientation,
to actually being able to kill.
So I guess they'll be playing Miley Cyrus?
And this whole using-drones-to-hunt-people
thing isn't just for Tibet.
It's also being set up in Xinjiang, home to
the Uighur Muslims
who are equally disenfranchised,
but get way less media attention.
Maybe because they don't have a Dalai Lama.
Check out this video from Seeker Daily.
"Although the Chinese government stresses
that it respects Islamic traditions,
incidents like this suggest otherwise."
So what do you think of the Chinese regime's
new monitoring system aimed at stopping refugees...
from attacking poor defenseless Chinese soldiers?
Leave your comments below,
and please share this video with people you
know.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell.
See you next time.