On this episode of China Uncensored,
International Women's Day in China.
Like Black History Month.
But only a day.
And way less respectful.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I'm your host, Chris Chappell.
You know, a lot of people say,
Chris, why are you always criticizing the
CCP?
How come you never talk about all the good
things the Communist Party has done?
Well today, that changes.
Because I'm going to talk about International
Women's Day.
The first International Women's Day was celebrated
in 1909
and was organized by The Socialist Party of
America.
But it didn't really become big until 1922,
when the Soviet Union made it official.
And until the 1970s,
it was pretty much something only celebrated
by communist and socialist countries,
until the United Nations decided to join in.
According to the UN,
International Women's Day is a time
"to reflect on progress made,
to call for change
and to celebrate acts of courage and determination
by ordinary women."
Now that's inspiring.
The Chinese Communist Party made March 8 an
official holiday in 1949.
Women get to take a half day off work.
And for more on how they celebrate,
we go to China Uncensored's international
woman, Shelley Zhang.
Hello, Chris!
Wow. What's with all the bags?
I'm celebrating International Women's Day.
With Chinese characteristics.
So women in China celebrate by going...
Sha ping! Nothing says honoring women like
50% off the original price.
Isn’t that...kind of a shallow way to celebrate
an important holiday?
Is celebrating President’s Day with mattress
sales?
Fair point. But that's not all China does
for International Women's Day, right?
Don't be silly Chris!
There's also...fashion shows!
Really.
Yes, like this one from southern China.
Or this one, held in the Great Hall of the
People
as part of a celebration hosted by the All
China Women's Federation.
The All-China Women's Federation.
Isn't that the women's rights organization
set up by the Chinese Communist Party?
I assume they talked about policy changes
to improve women's lives...
Actually, no.
They had a couple of dance numbers,
and some acrobats performed.
But it was a celebration!
Not a policy meeting...
Were there any other, uh, notable, International
Women's Day events?
Sure! I wouldn't want you to think that men
weren't involved, Chris.
In fact, look at these guys, who turned themselves
into punching bags so their wives could take
out their aggression.
And these men, who decided to literally walk
a mile in women's shoes,
and dresses, up a mountain.
They even stuffed their bras like 12-year-old
girls.
That's dedication.
And you're...ok with this.
It's kind of hard to see how that directly
relates to improving the lives of women,
but it's a...C+ kind of for effort?
Anyway, the point is, men in China also care
about International Women's Day.
Wait...what was that last image?
Um, nothing.
Was that...what I think it was?
So a mall in southern China had a competition
to find the fastest person to undo women's
bras one-handed.
For International Women's Day?
Yes.
Shelley, are you ok?
Shouldn't you be mad about this?
Hey, a woman won it!
Look, you're right, I hate this.
There's one entire day that's supposed to
be about women,
and we have guys literally dressing up like
clowns in high heels,
or taking off women's bras.
It's just too much sometimes!
I wanted to find a silver lining!
I even defended the All-China Women's Federation!
Weren't they the ones calling educated, unmarried
women over 27 "leftover women"?
Yeah. And they also said women shouldn't "make
a fuss" if their husbands have affairs.
I expected the Party to have a better track
record on women's rights.
After all, Mao said that women hold up half
the sky.
Yes he did, as mentioned in every article
that talks about women in China.
But while in the early days,
the Party did do things like abolish foot
binding,
Party leaders almost immediately started backtracking
on their statements about women being equal
because the Chinese men who they were trying
to recruit didn't like it.
And they cared more about having men to fight
for the Party.
I guess years of the one-child policy that
led to female infanticide and forced abortions
were also not good for women.
No. And while the state-run People's Daily
may say that women are irreplaceable in
"constructing socialist core values,"
it's only ok as long as they don't speak up.
Like last year, when five women were jailed
for planning an International Women's Day
protest against sexual harassment.
But surely there has to be something good
here?
Ok, here's something.
This year at the Two Sessions
China's annual legislative meetings,
they replaced some of the attractive female tea servers
with men.
Doesn't that just take jobs away from women?
Yes it does.
But at least it means that fewer women
have to get ogled by Party elders.
At least there's that.
Thanks, Shelley.
And thank you for watching.
Be sure to subscribe to China Uncensored for
more episodes.
Once again, I'm Chris Chappell. See you next
time.