China bans Taiwanese pineapples
In response, everyone is
buying *more* pineapples
Welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m Chris Chappell.
Tensions are at an all time high
between China and Taiwan.
Especially after the Chinese
Communist Party took over
Hong Kong,
and showed the people of Taiwan
what “unification” looks like.
The Communist Party has been
ramping up military pressure on
Taiwan in recent months.
And then, out of nowhere, China
put a ban on the import
of Taiwanese pineapples.
The announcement came only a
few days before the ban—
very short notice.
Chinese authorities claim it’s
an emergency issue of
biosecurity.
This ban was put in place
even though
“All 600-plus batches of
pineapples
exported to China over the
previous four months had
been approved.”
But China’s spokesperson said,
“Customs of the mainland have in
various instances found pests in
pineapples imported from Taiwan,
which would have posed a serious
threat to the mainland’s
agriculture and ecological
security had they
not been intercepted.”
“The temporary ban is a
scientific biosecurity measure
and is in line with the
mainland’s laws, regulations
and standards.”
And no country has higher
standards for food safety
than China.
The problem is, mainland China
makes up 90% of Taiwan’s
pineapple export market.
It’s worth around 50 million
US dollars a year.
So the sudden ban was a huge
blow to Taiwan’s pineapple
farmers.
So how did Taiwanese
people respond?
By going bananas for pineapples!
They bought up the entire year’s
worth of pineapple exports in
just four days.
People began posting photos
online of huge pineapple buys.
Cooking shows have started
featuring creative pineapple
dishes.
Also, bakeries.
And noodle shops.
And burger joints.
And ooh, pineapple
shrimp pad thai.
You know what they say,
"A pineapple a day
keeps the doctor away!"
As long as you don’t poke
yourself in the eye.
That’s, um, never happened
to me.
This photo caption says
“Today’s work buddy, the
Taiwanese Pineapple!”
And unlike most of my friends,
my pineapple buddy won’t
abandon me.
Where was I? Oh right.
"Support Taiwan,
Buy Pineapples."
I mean, who wouldn't want to
buy pineapples?
So pineapples have become
all the rage in Taiwan.
Overseas, too.
Japan ordered 6,000 tons—and
that wasn’t enough.
This is a Japanese supermarket.
All the Taiwanese pineapples are
sold out.
I guess no one wants
to buy Dole.
Taiwan’s representative in the
US is promoting Taiwan’s
pineapples, too.
And the American Institute in
Taiwan,
which is the de facto US
embassy there,
shared a photo of director Brent
Christensen
with creative pineapple decor
around the office.
The caption says,
“Have you pineappled today?”
You know it’s a hot trend when
people start using it as a verb.
Don't believe me?
Just Google it.
And the de facto Canadian
embassy, the Canadian Trade
Office in Taipei,
Separately shared a photo of
themselves enjoying
pineapple pizza.
To which I have to say:
Pineapple on pizza?!
Not cool, Canada.
Way to ruin it. Like you
ruin everything.
Anyway, the Chinese Communist
Party’s efforts to punish Taiwan
backfired.
People inside and outside Taiwan
banded together.
And now pineapples have become a
symbol for standing up to the
Chinese Communist Party.
A sweet ending.
This Taiwan pineapple buying
spree is a bit like what
happened last year with
Australian wine.
After the Australian government
called for an independent
investigation into the origin of
the coronavirus,
The Chinese regime blocked or pu
tariffs on a wide range of
Australian imports to China.
That included a 200% tariff
on wine.
Chinese state-run media called
it not a punishment, but simply
an anti-dumping measure.
Also, the Australian government
had better “grow up or
face more pain.”
Yeah, totally not political.
In response, there was a global
call to buy Australian wine.
Politicians encouraged
people to buy Aussie wine.
And even the White House
featured Australian wine at
a holiday reception.
Andreas Fulda, an International
Affairs Expert,
And author of a
book about democracy in
China, said.
“The danger of this [to China] i
You can’t simultaneously say Chi
a peaceful country that never
picks fights with people,
And then simultaneously say.
If Australia doesn’t change its
political system, legal system,
foreign policy, education system
and everything else,
We'll never normalize relations.
I think this wolf warrior
diplomacy is inherently
self-defeating."
And yes, he bought some
Australian wine, too.
The Chinese Communist Party’s
attempts at coercion may work on
people in China who are too
terrified to respond.
But outside China, people
stand up and fight back.
And the rest of the world gets
to enjoy more delicious
pineapple.
Can the Communist Party ban
Taiwanese bubble tea next?
I could really use some
more bubble tea.
And you can even put it on a
pizza. Canada.
And now it’s time for me to
answer a question from you, a
viewer who supports China
Uncensored on Patreon.
John Shultz says:
Good question, John.
You’re right.
Whenever a zoo anywhere in the
world gets Chinese pandas,
The deal is that the pandas
still belong to the Chinese
government.
Zoos have to “shell out
up to $1 million a year
to rent just one.”
And “If any baby cubs are born,
they pay an additional $400,000
baby tax.”
And those baby pandas belong to
the Chinese government, so they
have to be “returned” to China
at some point.
Now your suggestion is:
The US and other countries could
just hold onto the pandas as
Remuneration for intellectual
property theft, and other things
the Chinese Communist
Party owes.
That's a great idea in
principle.
There's just one problem.
If we did that, we’d have to
KEEP THE STUPID PANDAS!
Thanks for your question, John.
Be like John and support
China Uncensored on Patreon.
Go to
Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored to
see how you can contribute a
dollar or more per episode
To help us keep this show going.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
Thanks for watching
China Uncensored.