On this episode of China Uncensored,
if China keeps taking bites out of Apple,
there won’t be anything left!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Apple is finally taking a hard line
with the Chinese Communist Party
over its draconian internet censorship.
Apple and its CEO Tim Cook
have always been champions
of freedom of expression.
I mean, a few months ago,
he even won a free expression award!
Apple always goes that extra mile
to support free expression.
Like being the Platinum Sponsor
of the Free Expression Award
that Tim Cook coincidentally happened to win.
And now Apple is putting the screws
on the Chinese regime.
The CCP demanded Apple remove
some of the apps in the App Store
that let Chinese users go around
Chinese internet censorship.
They’re called virtual private networks
or VPNs.
VPNs are the only way Chinese netizens
can access the internet the rest of the world
sees,
including things like Facebook,
Twitter, or YouTube.
So when the Chinese regime made that demand,
Tim Cook took a stand.
He said, “We’re hopeful that over time
the restrictions we’re seeing are lessened,
because innovation really requires
freedom to collaborate and communicate.”
That was of course after he totally caved
and banned a bunch of VPNs
from the App Store,
just like the Communist Party wanted.
Very brave.
Just as brave as establishing
that new data center in Guizhou, China,
just like the Communist Party wanted.
That was in compliance with a new
cyber security law.
It will speed up Apple’s service
to Chinese customers,
as well as totally freak everyone out
because it means Chinese authorities
will also have access to data
from Apple customers in China.
Now Tim Cook has defended Apple’s actions,
following the same blueprint every company
operating in China uses.
The law is the law in China.
Our product does more good in China
than if we withdrew.
Vague, softly worded hopes
that the law will change someday.
Followed by complete subservience.
Just like the Communist Party wanted.
Look, when Steve Jobs said,
“Stay hungry, stay foolish,”
I don’t think he meant,
“Stay stupid.”
Because over the years,
Apple has been bending over backwards
to please the Chinese regime
in a desperate attempt to maintain
its market presence in China.
Almost 20% of Apple’s revenue
comes from China.
Which is too bad for Apple,
because man, the Chinese regime
is really trying to screw them.
From bizarre fines,
to smear campaigns on state-run media,
to awarding this Chinese leather goods company
the right to the iPhone trademark,
the Chinese Communist Party
is not making life easy for Apple.
And for all Apple’s efforts
to make the regime happy,
it’s not working out for them.
Apple’s earnings dropped for the
fifth straight quarter in a row.
And it’s thanks largely to losing out
to local competitors that have state support,
including some that stole technology
and designs from Apple.
Not that Apple isn’t getting its just deserts.
But Huawei has recently said
it plans to surpass Apple
at being the world’s number one
smartphone manufacturer.
As long as the world is fine with
the security concerns that come with Huawei.
And if anyone should be an expert
on invading people’s privacy,
it’s the former head of the NSA.
So what do you think of Apple’s willingness
to,
you know, comply with Chinese law?
Leave your comments below.
And coming up after the break,
China demonstrates its “peaceful rise.”
Want to watch more China Uncensored episodes
before they come out on YouTube?
Of course you do!
We put full half-hour episodes on our website
every Friday afternoon.
Click the link now to visit ChinaUncensored.tv.
See you there.