On this episode of China Uncensored,
we bless the rains down in Africa.
That is, if the Chinese Communist Party
doesn’t beat us to it!
Welcome back to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Did you know the United States
is the world’s biggest hegemon?
Yes, America’s colonial ambition knows no
bounds.
Just ask my favorite Chinese state-run media,
the Global Times!
“US monopolistic hegemony goes against
the will of the people.”
But, “Over-confident and Cold War-minded
US
is feeling that it is increasingly tough
to pursue global hegemony.”
Fortunately, a glorious red hero has emerged
to take the place of America’s imperialist
ambitions:
The Chinese Communist Party!
State-run Xinhua says,
“If globalization is led by countries in
the East,
like China,
it will be more respectful of the political
identity
and sovereignty of other countries.”
And the Chinese Communist Party
has already begun respecting
the political identity and sovereignty of
Africa.
To learn more, I sat down with Jeff Smith,
the founding director of Vanguard Africa,
an advocacy group for human rights
and democracy in Africa.
So Jeff, thank you for joining me.
You're an expert on Africa,
so you must be pretty happy with the way China
is liberating Africa from European colonialism.
I think it's, um, I think it's certainly a
mixed bag.
I think a lot of the attention lately
has been on China filling this,
what people describe as a void with US leadership
under the current administration taking a
step back,
putting a positive spin and so far as the
infrastructure
that the Chinese government has been involved
in across
the continent building schools and roads,
but what gets left out of that conversation
quite a bit is the really disastrous effects
that it's had on,
um, the state of democracy and in a certain
few countries,
but I think across the continent writ large,
um, and you know,
along with that as well,
the declining respect for civil liberties
and political rights,
uh, due to their political and social influence
on some of these countries.
Um, so yeah, it's a very complicated,
increasingly worrying situation
for pro democracy advocates like myself.
Well, I bet the African dictators,
China's helping prop up, I bet they love it.
They do. I mean, they embrace it.
Um, it's often seen as, you know, Chinese
support,
whether it's through a, you know, military
support or,
or trade or direct bilateral support.
It's often seen as coming with, you know,
what many people describe as "no strings attached."
Uh, so the Communist Party in China doesn't
really care so much
as evidenced by their own track record at
home about respect
for basic human rights and democratic ideals
and the principles of human dignity.
And is that different from investment from
the West?
Uh, in some cases, yes. I think there is valid
criticism of um,
you know, so called Western involvement in
some of these environments,
particularly the way our government views
Africa,
which has traditionally been through military
security lens.
But the, the deleterious effects that China's
involvement has had,
in my opinion, severely outweighs these other
issues,
particularly if you look in areas of, um,
you know, uh,
you know, investment in some of Africa's,
you know, military,
their security forces, their collaboration
and at times,
direct involvement in censorship of both online
discussion
and public discussion, the massive investment
in censorship technology.
Particularly, we're seeing this in east Africa
a lot, very recently.
They've been holding what they call media
roundtables.
It just recently happened in Tanzania where
they're talking about
how to censor their populations, how to block
social media,
how to really stifle discussion online.
Um, and lo and behold, you know, thereafter
the country,
Tanzania in this case, will pass a raft of
draconian laws.
For instance, just this past month, passing
legislation
that requires all online bloggers to post
over a $900 fee
just to have their blogs online. When, if
you look at that figure,
it may not seem like much to those of us
sitting here in the United States,
but that's oftentimes what many Tanzanians
will make in a year.
Uh, so it's really had a profoundly negative
effect across the board.
Well it's great that China can use all of
the experience
it's developed over the years and export that.
Exactly. No, they have exploited draconian
measures that have
really stifled civil liberties and political
rights, across the board.
But I think it's been particularly prevalent
in certain countries.
I think you've seen it a bit more particularly
and unsurprisingly
in countries where you've had one ruling party
since independence—
in the case of Tanzania, one ruling party,
it's actually the longest ruling party in
all of Africa.
So it's, you know, it's a natural fit there
if you will.
Well, don't take this the wrong way,
but tell me about Djibouti.
Djibouti is a very small country, less than
a 2 million people,
in what is called the eastern Horn of Africa
or the Horn of Africa.
It's really a geostrategic goldmine given
its location on the Red Sea,
So the size of Djibouti doesn't matter.
The size of Djibouti does not matter.
It does matter in so far as the size and scope
of the
increasing military bases that are occupying
essentially Djibouti.
It's actually where the US has their lone
military base in Africa,
Camp Lemonnier.
And China has its first overseas base.
China has its first overseas base,
so they've been flexing their muscles quite
a bit in Djibouti
but also in the region.
But in Djibouti as well, you have other competing
powers
where you have Russia, you have Italy, you
have Japan
all jockeying for position on that very strategic,
small strip of land.
So China has been investing in Africa for
a long time, for years.
How have things changed under Xi Jinping and
the One Belt,
One Road Initiative or Belt and Road Initiative?
I mean, I think you've seen, to my mind
just a continuation of standard Chinese Communist
Party
policy and an ideology really, again,
a lack of respect for, you know,
democratic basic democratic principles.
I also don't think it's a coincidence that—
I don't think you can draw a direct line,
but for the past 12 years in a row,
there's been overall declines in respect for
civil liberties
and political rights throughout the entire
continent.
I don't think it's a surprise or a coincidence
that during that
same time span you've seen China dramatically
increase its
investment in, and times cooperation, as I
mentioned earlier,
with military and security forces, across
the continent.
So I don't think you can draw a causal line,
but I think the correlation is rather rather
stunning.
Secondly, related to that, there's been academic
studies
that have shown that the more China invests
in a country,
particularly in the security forces, unsurprisingly,
human rights abuses go up and that's been
documented repeatedly.
Um, so again, \hthat's, that's cause for concern
as well for all of us
were concerned about, you know,
these sorts of issues and the overall democratic
backsliding
that we're seeing across the continent.
Well, don't you think it's a bit hypocritical
of the West
to criticize what China's doing in Africa
considering,
you know, slavery?
Yeah, no, I take that point.
I think that's something that certainly needs
to be taken into consideration.
The United States certainly has a checkered
past on human rights...
England, too.
...particularly in Africa.
But I think if you look at the general trajectory,
I don't think one could ever make the argument
that, well,
let's put it this way.
I don't think there's ever been a country
in the history of the earth
that has contributed more to human freedom
than the United States.
Despite the myriad mistakes that have been
made in the past.
I don't think it's anything compared to the
negative influence
that China has had, whereas the US government
invests
under both Democratic and Republican administrations
hundreds of millions of dollars every year
to democracy and governance
to, to human rights, to supporting local civil
society groups.
That type of investment over the course of
human history is unmatched.
The counter to that is, I think the investments
that China
has made in some of the world's worst autocratic
leaders,
not just in Africa but worldwide, is also
unmatched.
So it is really a great power struggle playing
out right now.
And I think unfortunately where we are now
in the US,
we've sort of taken a few steps back
and we're allowing China to fill that void.
Often the criticism is that, you know,
the no strings attached approach that China
takes
is a benefit to them,
and it's a negative for the United States.
I see the opposite.
I think the fact that our government has traditionally
stood
on the side of the democratic underdog,
on the side of pro democracy advocates in
Africa and elsewhere,
it should be seen as a positive.
That should be seen as a strength.
And I think that should be advanced and not
retreated.
So why should Americans care about
Chinese investment in Africa?
I think it goes to the larger point of this
larger
democratic backsliding we're seeing,
and it allows a highly abusive leaders to
kill torture,
to disappear their citizens with impunity.
We've seen this over and over again.
You know, let's just take one example.
There are upcoming elections
about a month from now in Zimbabwe.
China has built to their military college.
They have built the ruling party's—
or I should say they have built
the national assembly in the country,
which is dominated by the ruling party, again,
the same ruling party that has ruled the country
since independence in 1980.
Again, a natural attraction there for one
party rule.
So you see that playing out on a daily basis.
And you also see in Zimbabwe and elsewhere,
these leaders who've been in power for decades
at a time
adopting some of the same tactics that you've
seen in China,
whereas before, until recently, you know,
it was brute violence that kept them in power.
It was baton wielding security forces.
It was opening fire on protestors and killing
them.
Now they become more clever because of the
role of social media,
because of the role of the international media,
because of shows
like yours who sort of, you know,
highlight and keep a sustained spotlight on
some of these situations.
They've become more clever.
They've used more subtle forms of voter suppression.
They've used more subtle forms of intimidation
to keep people in line,
including censorship that we were talking
about before.
So I think overall it's just been a very concerning,
um,
decline in respect for basic basic human rights.
And I think it's evident to anyone who's paying
attention.
Chinese investment though,
does it have any benefit for the locals?
Like pumping up the local economy?
Sure, yeah.
I think it always is important to sort of
check ourselves
and notice the positive.
Being a human rights activist and being involved
in a pro democracy field,
we often look at the negative and how we can
help
work with local partners to counteract that.
But I think it is also important to recognize
some of the
positive contributions that Chinese investment
has made.
I think we noted at the top the investments
that they've made
in building local infrastructure, building
dams, building bridges,
and building the African Union for instance,
which was then bugged to then spy on African
leaders...
So maybe not so great, that one.
...but I think it is important to note
some of those positive achievements.
However many of the complaints you'll hear
from local citizens in Zimbabwe
where I've traveled extensively
and throughout southern Africa in particular,
is when Chinese investment comes in,
or Chinese companies come in,
locals often don't benefit from that.
They bring in Chinese workers.
They don't hire local workers.
They bring in shoddy infrastructural, um...
The buildings might not be great quality.
Exactly, so just last night, a copper mine
in Zambia,
allegedly reportedly run by a Chinese company,
collapsed, killing 10 people,
which is not the first time that this has
happened in Zambia.
It's happened a lot.
It's happened many times and so there's
no account of no accountability.
These people are dying with no recourse to
justice because,
you know, it's a Chinese company and obviously
there's very little recourse for accountability
there.
So I think those are some of the problems
that they run into.
Also, you know, China's population is expanding.
They, you know, you'll hear
when you talked to many people on the ground,
and they'll say they need space.
They're buying up entire, you know, entire
swaths of land,
so people could come and move there.
There, there are these famous ghost towns
in Angola
where China has invested heavily in the oil
industry there.
And you have these entire towns,
these entire cities that are built for Chinese
workers.
Wow.
And it's staggering when you look at the size
and scope of this,
and ordinary average Angolans, the vast majority
of which are
living under the poverty line, will never
have the chance of,
you know, having the opportunity to live in
a neighborhood like that.
Whereas, you know, a Chinese companies are
importing
their own citizens to work local industries.
And I think that, um, that really has harmful
effects.
I've heard a lot of criticism that this is
essentially
a Chinese form of colonialism.
Do think there's any merit to that?
I'm biased. So, you know, I think there is
some merit to that,
but if you talk to—again,
and you notice that the hypocrisy of the United
States
and, you know, we weren't a colonial power
by any means,
but you mentioned England, and in some, some
others,
there really is still in some segments of
these populations a
n animosity towards the west—
and rightfully so—
towards the United States and in some of the,
you know,
more negative instances of us supporting dictators
just like China does today in Africa.
So there's sort of like that prevailing hostility
towards
what is perceived as the west, and anything
that comes from
say Russia or China or North Korea—
in some instances where the North Korean regime
is investing heavily in so called cyber security
and threat detection in Zimbabwe and elsewhere—
there's less of an apprehension to allow them
in
because there's no colonial history there.
But I think it's absolutely right to call
it
on a modern form of colonialism.
And many people may see it differently.
But, but I would certainly,
I would certainly agree with that.
So where do you see the situation in the next
50 years?
I mean, I'm an idealist, I'm an idealist without
illusions,
but I would hope that the US recognizes—
whether it's a Republican president
and whether it's a Democratic president—
Or some "third party"...
Or some third party—who knows?—
that in so many ways,
Africa really is the future.
If you look at the youth population that is
coming up.
And I think that's where the one hope lies,
is they become more emboldened, I think, you
know,
with the explosion of social media and different
outlets
for mobilizing and for communicating and for
building
solidarity across borders, whether they're
regional or international.
I think that's where the hope lies and if
you look at just to the,
not only the human potential on the continent,
which I think is first and foremost, but also
again,
the natural resource wealth that this continent
has is just tremendous.
And I just don't think, number one, it's going
to benefit local populations.
It's going to benefit individuals, it's going
to benefit
highly abusive autocratic leaders.
And it's going to benefit in many ways that
the Chinese government,
because they're partnering directly with,
with these abusive leaders.
So I would like to think that we could, you
know,
get back on track and power local people,
allow them to take control of their own destiny.
Have the US government play more proactive
and positive role
in developing that democratic culture.
But right now I'm feeling a bit pessimistic
and I think we can get there,
but I think it'll certainly take some time,
but it's, you know,
we have to start talking about these issues.
We're just not, we're not even having that
discussion
here in Washington right now.
We're not even talking about the future of
Africa.
We're talking about—when it is talked about,
it's talked about under the guise of stability.
And what that often means is keeping the men
who've been in power for 20, 30, 40 years
in power
and not messing with the status quo,
which is what China wants.
So I think we need to,
we need to get over that hurdle.
Well, fortunately I can guarantee you
there'll be some lively conversation happening
in the comments section below this video.
Uh, one final question.
The most important question really:
in the Toto song "Africa",
is it "bless the rains in Africa"
or "miss the rains down in Africa"?
So it's definitely, I think it's "bless."
That's correct. I only just found that out.
Yeah. Yeah. I mean,
and that just sounds better, right?
Bless the rains?
It's better to bless something than to miss
something.
I guess, but I mean, who is this, who is "Toto"
to have the ability to bless the rains in
Africa?
Oh, I think it speaks to all of us, though.
It speaks to our, you know,
it speaks to our humanity.
So really that's...
Blessing the rains.
...that's the essence of everything.
Rain brings life. Yeah.
And that is what the West can bring to Africa,
versus China.
We can bless the rains in Africa.
I would hope so. In the ideal scenario, yes.
But to your point, I think it is very important
that we do
have to recognize the mistakes that our government
has made for a long time.
But with that said,
I think there's so much more positive that
has been done,
and unfortunately that gets sort of pushed
by the wayside.
But I think if we all come together and recognize
that
human solidarity knows no bounds,
and we're all in this together,
I think we can really make a positive impact.
So that's my idealism coming out,
but I really do truly profoundly believe that.
Well, I think that's the message
Toto was trying to leave us.
I think so, too.
So they were the trailblazers way back.
Absolutely.
Way back in the day.
Well thank you so much for joining me today,
Jeff.
Of course. I appreciate it.
Did you like this interview?
Help us do more!
...Assuming your answer was,
“Yes, I did like this interview.”
Your support helps us travel
and interview more people like Jeff.
So click this orange button to contribute
a dollar or more per episode
on the crowdfunding website Patreon.