On this episode of China Uncensored,
could this be China’s new weapon for the
South China Sea?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
War between the US and China.
It would “destructive, “prolonged,”
and “ruinous.”
Those were the findings of this recent report
by the Rand corporation.
Even though the Chinese People’s Liberation
Army
is far behind the US army in terms of technology
and war capability,
“by 2025, that gap could be much smaller.”
One piece of the gap that China would need
to fill is aircraft carriers.
The United States currently has 10 functional
aircraft carriers.
China has one.
And it wasn’t even made in China.
It was built in Ukraine before the fall of
the Soviet Union.
It was sold to China as scrap.
The Chinese buyer said he was going to turn
it into a casino.
But then, shockingly,
the Chinese government got ahold of it
and kept it as an aircraft carrier.
After nearly two decades of refurbishing,
it set sail in 2012.
It’s called the Liaoning.
And it’s not even that functional.
But now, these photos have surfaced,
showing China has almost completed a new aircraft
carrier.
And this one is made in China.
Chinese military sources say it will still
be several years
before construction is complete and
crews trained to make it fully operational.
Hopefully it will be more operational than
my Polystation.
Now a country having its own aircraft carrier
is a rite of passage of sorts.
Also helpful for protecting its military interests
overseas.
Only 13 countries in the world have them.
And even though Douglas MacArthur described
Taiwan
as “the unsinkable aircraft carrier,”
at best that just makes it another US one.
But there are some pretty big differences
between even this newest under-construction
Chinese aircraft carrier
and the US ones.
For one, China’s is much smaller,
displacing only 60-70,000 tons.
Compare that to some of the bigger US ones
that displace 100,000 tons.
Also, both the Liaoning and this new one use
a ski ramp.
And while that’s fun for a weekend at the
Poconos,
it’s less useful for war.
Basically, jets get the lift they need to
take off by going really fast
and the ramp adds the extra little something
to get them in the air.
The US uses a catapult system.
No, a modern catapult system.
It hooks onto the front of the plane and throws
it into the air.
This means heavier or slower aircraft can
still launch.
But China, using the ski jump, wouldn’t
be able to launch turboprop planes,
for example cargo aircraft like the US C-2
Greyhound or early warning aircraft
like the E-2D Hawkeye.
So that means Chinese supplies won’t be
so fresh off the boat.
That’s why a recent report by the Pentagon’s
Defense Intelligence Agency said,
“The aircraft carriers that [China is] building
will not have the same blue open ocean capability
that our aircraft carriers have.
Nor will it be able to execute air operations
the way we use our carriers.”
But directly competing with the US is probably
not China’s goal.
Since that whole, war between the US and China
would be
“destructive, “prolonged,” and “ruinous,”
thing.
A Chinese aircraft carrier doesn’t need
to be very powerful
or even go very far to achieve the Chinese
government’s goals.
That’s because “There are strong indications
that the new carrier
will be placed at a military port on Hainan
Island,
which faces the South China Sea.”
So as early as 2020,
we might be seeing a Chinese-made aircraft
carrier
sailing in those disputed waters.
And that’s not all.
According to this article,
“Some experts believe that the People's
Liberation Army
plans to have four to six aircraft carrier
groups in the near future.”
So who knows?
Maybe by 2025 we really can be on the brink
for a good old fashioned
“destructive, “prolonged,” and “ruinous,”
war!
So what do you think of China’s new addition
to their navy?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.