How big a threat is China?
That’s the question on people’s minds
in Taiwan...
As they vote for their new leaders.
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
I’m in Taipei, the capital of the country/region
of Taiwan.
Three days from now,
Taiwan will vote for its new president and
legislature.
There are election banners everywhere,
and you can feel the excitement in the air.
One candidate even gave me a bar of soap.
I guess he’s really trying to clean up politics.
But there’s still one messy issue that’s
on every voter’s mind: China.
I sat down with Taiwan politics expert Lev
Nachman to find out more.
Thanks for joining me.
Thanks so much for having me.
So the Chinese Communist Party has vowed to
take over Taiwan
with military force if necessary.
How does that looming shadow sort of affect
Taiwanese politics?
So in Taiwan, when we think about a left-right
spectrum
in the way that we think left-right in say
America, it's very different here.
So in America, we think more along the lines
of tax,
wealth redistribution, welfare, even social
issues
like how you feel about things like same sex
marriage, et cetera.
In Taiwan, left-right is instead defined by
independence versus unification.
So how Taiwanese people feel about whether
Taiwan ought to become
more sovereign and maybe its own independent
state or less sovereign
and slowly create ties and become a part of
the PRC.
So for Americans who don't really know Taiwanese
politics,
what are the main parties and what are their
views?
So the two biggest parties in Taiwan
are the Democratic Progressive Party,
the DPP and the Chinese Nationalist Party,
the KMT.
Now, Taiwan was under martial law for 37 years.
During that time that came, the KMT was the
only party in Taiwan.
It controlled all aspects of life and other
parties were illegal.
But through a very long struggle of democratization,
eventually a group was able to actually consolidate
their kind of pro-democracy,
[inaudible] KMT political circles and form
what is now known as the DPP,
the Democratic Progressive Party.
Now the DPP is vaguely pro-Taiwan sovereignty.
A lot of people described the DPP as a pro-independence
party,
but in fact the DPP has not been pro-independence
for quite some time,
especially since around the year 2000 the
DPP
has been adamantly pro status quo.
So which is actually why the current president
Tsai Ing-wen
was so controversial,
because she was pushing it further than the
status quo.
No, she actually is explicitly pro status
quo
and a lot of deeper green Taiwanese political
parties don't like her
because she's so pro status quo.
But I thought she wasn't,
she wasn't using the one China policy in speeches.
And I thought that got people's-
No, that doesn't really have a big impact
on
whether or not they're pro status quo or not.
So pro status quo means that they don't want
to change how things are now.
Okay.
Now whether or not she endorses the '92 consensus,
China's one China versus the America's one
China,
these are kind of separate issues from whether
or not
she's actually pushing any sort of actual
change, which she hasn't.
She even just this last week has had to actually
emphasized to the T
that she is a ROC leader, specifically inciting
[inaudible]
as not any sort of pro-Taiwan independence
leaning anything,
which is why when a lot of people say that
Tsai Ing-wen herself
is pro-independence, it's just kind of not
true,
because nothing about her speech or the policy
she's pushes
is really indicative that she's pro-independence.
She's just very pro status quo and that's
not a good thing or a bad thing.
It's just more of a reflection
of how she actually falls within Taiwan's
spectrum.
Now the KMT falls on the more pro-unification
side.
Now, of course, the KMT doesn't just say we're
pro-unification.
Instead, what they do is their strategy
is to try to sell closer ties with China
to the Taiwanese public.
So a lot of their strategy is saying
we can become a more successful Taiwan
if we increase our ties with China.
And of course, they rely on a lot of much
more
kind of essentialist cultural traits
by saying we were both speak Chinese,
we both come from the same ancestors,
therefore we should align with them.
But for a lot of people in Taiwan,
those kinds of appeals don't work anymore,
because Taiwan has politically and culturally
developed
so separately from the PRC for a very, very
long time.
So what is the feeling in Taiwan with this
sort of independence
or unification stance?
Because I would think a lot of...
I don't understand why there’d be people
talking about unification.
So an important, and this gets very complicated,
so within these camps of independence unification,
there is no black and white.
One thing is independence and one thing is
unification.
So within the independence camp,
what independence means is hotly contested.
Okay.
Within the unification camp,
what unification means is also contested.
So when we ask these kinds of survey questions,
are you pro-independence or pro-unification?
If that's all the question asked, that's not
a very good question.
What's a better question is, should Taiwan
pursue more independence
if there is no chance of war with the PRC?
Because when you ask that question, independence
goes up,
are you pro-independence?
If war with the PRC is likely, then it goes
down.
Are you pro-unification if all of China were
to democratize?
Now, it might seem overstated, but if,
if you're okay with unification if China's
also democratic
and those numbers also change.
So one of the ways the Chinese Communist Party
has presented a possible unification scenario
is the one country, two systems.
Sorry all they have in Hong Kong, which is
going very well.
But so a lot of people have been saying since
people in Taiwan,
I've seen how that has gone down in Hong Kong
that's had a big influence in Taiwanese politics.
Do you think there might be something else
going on?
What's going on?
So the way that Hong Kong has impacted Taiwan's
election,
it most certainly has had an impact,
but it has by no means really defined this
election
the way that many people might think.
So what Hong Kong presents to Taiwan is kind
of the same issue
that Taiwan always talks about.
So in Taiwan, every election, the issue of
independence,
unification is the most important political
issue.
That's what people vote on.
That's how people evaluate their candidates
and evaluate their parties.
So in a world where the Hong Kong protests
never occurred,
Taiwan would still be talking about unification,
independence, sovereignty, one country, two
systems just as much.
But what Hong Kong does offer to Taiwan is
a very tangible way of looking at unification.
So we always think about unification, one
country, two systems
in this very abstract way.
And what Hong Kong gives Taiwan is a very
concrete way
to say that's unification and that's why we
shouldn't be for it.
Now, that appeal is very powerful, but for
green voters.
Meaning green, meaning pro-DPP pro-Taiwan
sovereignty voters.
So if you're pro-KMT or you're pro-China,
Hong Kong probably isn't going to have that
big of an effect
on how you're going to vote.
Really when the DPP uses Hong Kong
within their rhetorical strategy,
it's a matter of appealing to young people,
but it's also a matter of trying to get their
base of support
to go out to vote, more than it is trying
to convince,
say moderate or pan-Blue voters to instead
vote for them.
So how are these elections different than
the elections
several years ago in 2016?
So a number of big differences.
So the 2014 Sunflower Movement created this
very dynamic moment
in Taiwanese contemporary history
in which a lot of new political parties
formed out of social activism,
formed and entered formal politics in 2016,
in the last election.
In 2016, there was a lot of hype around these
new young progressive pro-Taiwan parties.
Because of the Sunflower Movement
and eight years of a very unsuccessful Ma
Ying-jeou term president,
presidential term.
The kind of sentiment towards the KMT was
at an all time low,
meaning that people were not excited to vote
for the KMT in the last election.
And if you look at the results the KMT lost
heart,
the DPP won overwhelmingly.
A lot of these smaller parties had that space
to grow in the last election,
because people were so confident that the
DPP was going to win.
A lot of voters voted for smaller parties
instead.
Four years later, we have the rise of Han
Kuo-yu.
We have the KMT actually regaining a lot of
their popularity.
They're not nearly as unpopular this year
as they were four years ago
and a lot of this kind of common hype around
progressive Taiwanese parties
is just not there and the way that it was
four years ago.
Part of that is due to how these smaller parties
have performed.
But a larger part is how the DPP has performed
the last four years.
So the DPP has had a majority in Taiwan's
legislature,
they've had the presidency,
but a lot of their policies have kind of been
very lukewarm.
People aren't really excited about
how they've performed the last four years
and that's hurt their popularity.
So this year people are kind of just much
more scared that the KMT
will actually do well.
And four years ago people kind of knew they
weren't going to do well,
which kind of creates this bigger sense of
dread
around the future of Taiwanese politics.
There's a very popular phrase in Mandarin
that's been going around called "Wang guo
gan", meaning,
and I think the formal English translation
was like a sense of doom,
of impending doom about the country.
But that's kind of how a lot of young people
have felt about this upcoming election,
because of the KMT's kind of a return to popularity.
Well, so what's making people go back to the
KMT?
So in 2016, the KMT ran a very bad campaign.
So the best example is that
they switched out their presidential candidate
two months before the election.
That's bad.
That was bad, because it showed one
a total lack of support in their candidate.
It kind of seemed that they were kind of throwing
in the towel
two months early.
They switched as a kind of a hail Mary way
to kind of
consolidate support within the party.
Not only that, but Ma Ying-jeou was not a
particularly
strong president in his later years
that a lot of people were just generally unhappy
with the KMT.
So a lot of people either didn't vote last...
A lot of KMT supporters here, they didn't
vote last election
or they voted for the DPP instead.
And a lot of that kind of common sentiment
just isn't around anymore.
Meanwhile, a lot of KMT voters have really
mobilized
and rallied around Han Kuo-yu in a way that
I think
we didn't necessarily expect in the last year.
But the KMT is also, when a party is an opposition,
it's easier for them to regain their support.
Parties that are in power almost overwhelmingly
will be more criticized and have lower levels
of support
than when they were in opposition.
So it was also just kind of a natural rebalancing.
So when the KMT was in power, they were unpopular,
when they're in opposition, their popularity
comes back up.
Yeah.
Well I know in this election,
it seems to me China is the key issue in a
lot of this.
But it seems this year I guess,
you would call it the kind of pro-Beijing
KMT
has been focusing on calling Tsai Ing-wen
gay.
Now I'm just a simple American,
but I probably don't understand Taiwanese
politics.
But why is that?
So it's important to note that
a lot of anti-same-sex sentiment within Taiwan
does not neatly map onto this pro-unification,
pro-independent spectrum.
And this is the difference between the American
left and right.
Exactly.
So although the KMT tends to be more anti-same-sex
equality than the DPP,
a lot of the DPP is actually very against
same-sex marriage.
In fact, one of the most adamant
anti-same-sex marriage groups is our deep
green.
In a lot of anti-Tsai Ing-wen rhetoric
that's come out from Taiwanese groups
actually comes from deep green groups, not
from the KMT.
So you might also be familiar with the Tsai
Ing-wen PhD scandal.
There's a very big push to try to say that
Tsai Ing-wen's PhD
was fake and that she never actually graduated
from the London School of Economics.
Now the London School of Economics,
he wrote a letter saying,
"No, her PhD is real,"
but there's this massive conspiracy theory
within Taiwan that it's all fake.
Wow.
And this did not come from the KMT.
This came from deep green parties who do not
like Tsai Ing-wen
and do not want her to be leading the DPP.
Wow. [inaudible]
Well, so clearly China wants something out
of this election in Taiwan.
What is that and how are they going to go
about getting it?
So there's something very interesting about
this election,
unlike previous elections as well, is the
role that CCP has played.
So typically the CCP will in a very politically
correct for the PRC kind of way,
tacitly endorse whoever the KMT is running.
They have not done that with Han Kuo-yu.
Now this says a couple of things.
Either they don't have a lot of faith in Han
Kuo-yu,
which I think is partially true.
Han has shown that he's very difficult to
control for the KMT
and that the PRC might see that and say,
"Well, we're not really sure we want to throw
our cards behind this guy."
At the same time, the PRC doesn't really need
to formally
say anything about the KMT nearly as much
anymore,
because they found so many other avenues
with which to disrupt Taiwan's democratic
practices.
So we've seen a lot of stories about disinformation
campaigns
coming from the PRC,
fake news being started and pushed by farms
in the PRC.
And a lot of these reports show that the PRC
is actually using
a number of different strategies to try to
influence Taiwan's democracy
rather than just saying we support whoever
the KMT is running.
And what should we be looking for in the election
results?
So when we think about this, suppose that
rise of populism in Taiwan.
As of now according to polls and polling data
is of course just poll.
So election, it could be very different.
It seems like Tsai Ing-wen is going to win.
But it's not just a matter of whether or not
she wins.
We should pay attention to how much Han Kuo-yu
loses by.
Because if Han Kuo-yu only loses by like 5%
then that sort of signals that his populist
appeal
was still very successful and that the odds
of him
just kind of disappearing to the sideline
are not very likely.
He's probably going to try to consolidate
his support after the election,
even if it's a small loss.
Now, if he loses by a lot, well then maybe
his populous appeal
wasn't as strong as we thought it was and
maybe Taiwan
may be one of the few democracies to overcome
this challenge of populism.
So we'll have to wait and find out on election
day
just by exactly how successful Han's appeals
have been.
And at the same time,
I'm very curious about what voter turnout
will be.
So the DPP [inaudible] has invested so much
of their time
to try to frame Hong Kong as part of its sovereignty
issue.
So appealing to young people through the lens
of Hong Kong.
A lot of these mobilization campaigns
have been geared towards trying to get young
people
to come out to vote.
And I'm very curious what exactly
the young person voter turnout rate will be.
So like all democracies,
young people vote the least in Taiwan as well.
Now that being said, I think the young person
vote,
the younger voting cohort rate in Taiwan was
60%
which for Americans that's the low rate.
Like whoa.
But for people in like the 80 plus age range,
it's over 80% voter turnout.
Wow.
So people here really love to vote, which
is great.
But older cohorts tend to vote way more than
younger cohorts.
And for anyone who's familiar with how younger
Taiwanese people
feel about their politics or political choices,
they overwhelmingly do not like the KMT.
Now that's not a tacit endorsement of the
DPP.
A lot of young people aren't crazy about the
But they most certainly don't like the KMT.
So if more young people voted,
then the results of the election would be
drastically different.
And so I'm very curious how successful
the DPP's appeals to young voters
will actually be come election day.
And what about the outcomes for the legislature?
So the legislature is a bit complicated.
So, Taiwan has what's called a mixed electoral
system.
So there's single member districts.
So you vote for the person from your district,
but you also vote for whatever party you like
most.
There's a party list.
So it's kind of a mix of how Germany does
their politics
with how the U.S. does their politics.
And currently there's a lot of different polls
that show
how people are going to vote for which party.
Right now it looks like the KMT is going to
get about 20% of the party votes
and the DPP about 30%,
with still about 20 to 30% of the people undecided.
So that's going to be a big mystery.
And then you have these smaller parties,
about five small parties that are all competing
for whatever limited space that they can get.
Now within the single member districts,
this is much more complicated and really varies
by area.
Of course, there's a lot more contested seats
than there were last time.
I know another big difference between last
time and this time is the DPP
won a lot of seats that the KMT normally wins,
because the KMT was so unpopular.
But four years later,
because the KMT is not as unpopular as it
was before,
a lot of these seats that the DPP won last
time
will not be as easily held this election.
So these are all things to also be looking
for.
All right, well thank you so much for joining
me.
Oh, thank you so much.