Nothing’s Racier Than Democracy
At least to the Chinese Communist Party
That's why they’ve taken to PornHub
To spread disinformation about Hong Kong.
Welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m Chris Chappell.
I’m sorry to say, the Chinese Communist
Party may have just won
the propaganda war against Hong Kong protesters.
By using...PornHub.
Protests have rocked Hong Kong for 5 months.
Protesters are fighting against the Chinese
Communist Party’s
efforts to take away Hong Kong freedoms.
Wow, an underdog fight for liberty.
A compelling story.
Which is why the Chinese Communist Party
is trying to twist the narrative.
State-run media says the protesters are rioters,
and probably terrorists.
But not a lot of people read
the English version of Chinese state-run media.
They’re into a different type of pornography.
Since the protests began in June,
China used Twitter Porn Bots to spam disinformation
about the Hong Kong Protests.
Yes, because people who follow porn accounts
on Twitter
are the target market for disinformation.
Facebook and YouTube were also used in similar
ways.
But eventually, Twitter, Facebook, and YouTube
all took action
to stop the spread of this Chinese propaganda.
So obviously, with no other option left,
the Chinese Communist Party turned...to PornHub.
This Chinese social commentator with 3 million
followers
said she switched to posting on PornHub
after YouTube shut down their accounts.
Here’s a new channel on PornHub
called Chinese Communist Youth League Central.
Probably no official tie to the Communist
Youth League.
They have over 9000 views and 32 subscribers.
I think you’re using PornHub wrong.
There are others.
Like this video called Rioters (Cockroach)
in Hong Kong.
It’s a very disturbing video of a man getting
into
an argument with protesters
before someone lights him on fire.
The user said,
“Chinese people are at risk of being burned
alive
if they dare to disagree with the fascist
right-wingers in Hong Kong.”
Just the kind of content people are looking
for on PORNHUB!!!
So Chinese Communist Propaganda
can really turn up everywhere.
Have fun out there, kids.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.