More Americans view China as an enemy
As the CCP prepares for war
Plus an odd affection for Trump in China.
That and more on this week’s China news headlines
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.\h
After decades of the Chinese Communist\h
Party’s unrestricted warfare against the US,\h\h
a lot of Americans have come\h
to view China as the enemy.
That’s according to this new\h
poll by the Pew Research Center.
“Roughly nine-in-ten U.S. adults consider China\h
a competitor or enemy, rather than a partner.”
However, while 53% of conservatives\h
describe China specifically as an enemy,\h\h
only 20% of liberals say the same.
“Concerns about China’s aggressive\h
behavior are not new—U.S.\h\h
military and intelligence officials repeatedly\h
warned about Chinese military investment,\h\h
disinformation, and espionage\h
and cyber operations.”
I think someone else has been warning Americans\h
about the Chinese Communist Party, too.\h\h
Yeah, someone.\h
This week, Admiral Philip Davidson,\h
commander of U.S. Indo-Pacific Command,\h\h
testified before members of the\h
Senate Armed Services Committee.\h
He said China plans to overtake\h
the US on the world stage.
Well all the world’s a stage.\h
Someone's gotta be the villain.\h
And China is putting big money behind that.\h\h
According to Chinese state-run media,\h
China is ramping up military funding.
This was a big topic at the recent meeting of\h
top Communist officials, called the Two Sessions.\h\h
Premier Li Keqiang said\h
“[We should] comprehensively\h\h
strengthen the military exercises\h
and fully prepare for war.”
Do they have a particular target in mind?\h
Well it just so happens they\h
do. Admiral Philip Davidson\h\h
also said he expects China\h
to invade Taiwan by 2027.
Now China says the US admiral is only\h
hyping up the threat of a Taiwan invasion.
After all, the Chinese Communist Party has\h
been promising to invade Taiwan for decades.\h\h
Let’s just hope this is one\h
of those promises they break.
But Chinese officials are\h
also telling President Biden\h\h
to stop the dangerous\h
practice of supporting Taiwan.
It is dangerous. Dangerous for the CCP.\h
They don’t want to fight the US military.\h
Speaking of US action against\h
China, Biden’s Commerce Chief,\h\h
Gina Raimondo, has said Trump’s steel\h
and aluminum tariffs were effective.
President Biden has never been clear about what he\h
intends to do with the Trump-era tariffs on China.\h\h
But this might be a sign tariffs will continue.
That being said, a lot of\h
Trump policies have been frozen\h\h
as the Biden administration reviews them.\h
For instance, the WeChat ban. In February,\h\h
Biden temporarily paused the ban so\h
his administration could review it.\h
But it has now come out that\h
Commerce Secretary Raimondo\h\h
and her husband own a stake\h
in WeChat’s parent company.
That parent company is Tencent, one of\h
several Chinese tech companies the US\h\h
considers a national security threat\h
and potential vector for espionage.
How could she do that?! Well, the same way\h
most Americans are invested in potentially\h\h
dangerous Chinese companies. Through\h
Emerging Market Funds. She and her husband\h\h
“jointly own shares of two emerging\h
markets exchange-traded funds,\h\h
which are composed of several foreign\h
stocks including Tencent Holdings.”
Of course, as Commerce Secretary, I hope\h
Raimondo learns about all the ways Americans\h\h
end up supporting an authoritarian regime that\h
kills their own citizens for their organs.
And after the break, China’s\h
National People’s Congress\h\h
has approved new rules to make sure Hong Kong’s\h
democracy is firmly within their control.
Welcome back
This week, China’s National\h
People’s Congress approved\h\h
sweeping changes to Hong Kong’s electoral system.
What are the changes?\h
One change is about how Hong Kong’s\h
Chief Executive gets selected.\h\h
The Chief Executive is like a governor.
In the past, there’s been a 1,200 member\h
committee that elects the Chief Executive.\h\h
It’s made up of four equally sized sectors. The\h
fourth sector includes elected members of Hong\h\h
Kong’s legislative council and district councils,\h
plus some unelected members from mainland China.
But that’s not enough for the CCP.\h
Under the new rules passed this week,\h\h
the election committee will be expanded by\h
adding a new group of 300 communist officials.
So with the election committee\h
increased from 1,200 members\h\h
to 1,500 members, I think it’s safe to\h
say: Hong Kong is now 25% more democratic.\h
And in case that doesn’t pack the\h
Hong Kong government with enough\h\h
pro-Beijing officials, they’re also\h
expanding Hong Kong’s Legislative Council.\h\h
In the past it had 70 seats, 35 of\h
which are elected by the people.\h
Now the Chinese government will be adding\h
20 more seats, and filling them with its\h\h
own people. So elected representatives\h
will now always be in the minority.
And in case *that* doesn’t pack the Hong Kong\h
government with enough pro-Beijing officials,\h\h
a new vetting committee\h
will be established to block\h\h
any of those potential candidates\h
not deemed sufficiently “patriotic.”
This is what Chinese officials call\h
“democracy with Hong Kong characteristics.”
Yeah, that’s not a joke. And according to\h
this report, members of the NPC “applauded\h\h
for the longest period after the Hong\h
Kong electoral proposal was passed.”
I feel like there’s some kind\h
of quote about liberty dying\h\h
and thunderous applause that might apply here.
On the plus side, State\h
Department Spokesman Ned Price\h\h
says the US condemns China’s actions in\h
Hong Kong. And the US is also working to\h\h
galvanize action over the CCP’s abuses\h
of ethnic minorities in Xinjiang.\h
Price said, “I don’t think anyone is satisfied\h
yet, with the international response to what\h\h
has taken place in Xinjiang. And that’s precisely\h
why we are, in many ways, galvanizing the world,\h\h
galvanizing collective action, to make clear\h
that these sort of abuses against human rights\h\h
in Xinjiang and elsewhere will not be tolerated.”
Wait, what actions has the Biden Administration\h
taken? Who’s being galvanized? They’re still\h\h
“reviewing” whether to call what’s\h
happening in Xinjiang a genocide.
Hopefully they’ll get to that in the US’s\h
upcoming high level meeting with China.
And I’ll get to that meeting, after the break.
Welcome back.
Next Thursday, top Biden officials will meet with\h
their Chinese counterparts for the first time.
And they’re meeting in Alaska, for some reason.\h
According to a senior administration\h
official, they will discuss everything\h\h
from Covid-19 to climate change, Hong Kong,\h
Taiwan, and China’s trade war with Australia.\h
“The U.S. will also discuss Chinese practices\h
seen as damaging to American workers and farmers,\h\h
as well as intellectual property theft,\h
forced technology transfer and human rights”
Ok, holding the meeting in\h
Alaska makes more sense now.\h\h
Because both sides will be\h
expecting a chilly reception.\h
A bipartisan group of US lawmakers have introduced\h
a bill to fight forced organ harvesting.
It’s called the Stop Forced Organ Harvesting Act,\h\h
otherwise known as the I CAN’T\h
BELIEVE WE HAVE TO SAY THIS act.
According to the bill’s sponsor, Representative\h
Chris Smith, “We must do more to put an end to\h\h
the horrific abuse by international human\h
trafficking gangs, terrorist organizations,\h\h
and even some governments—China’s\h
Communist regime in particular—who\h\h
kill innocent people and sell\h
their organs for profit.”
Specifically calling out the Chinese Communist\h
Party for organ harvesting is a huge move.\h
One of the victims of forced organ harvesting\h
in China are the Ugyhur Muslims. The CCP denies\h\h
there’s any genocide happening in Xinjiang\h
and has welcomed investigations. Well, the\h\h
first independent report has come out and it says\h
Beijing is intent to destroy the Uyghur people.
In fact, according to the report, “The Chinese\h
government’s alleged actions in Xinjiang\h\h
have violated every single provision in\h
the United Nations’ Genocide Convention.”
You hear that Joe?
And finally, this image has gone viral in China.
The listing says it was made\h
by a Chinese furniture company.\h\h
The listing says you should buy this\h
statue to “Make your company great again!”
And it features “Trump, who knows\h
Buddhism better than anyone.”
“I’m so enlightened. I’m the most\h
enlightened being. So much humility.”
What I get from this though, is that inner\h
peace comes from being banned on social media.
And now it’s time for me to answer a\h
question from a member of the China\h\h
Uncensored 50 cent army, fans\h
who support the show on Patreon.
Today’s question comes from:
Jason. “Does bear spray work on tiny Pandas?\h
Please there must be something i can do to\h\h
protect myself! Can pandas swim? I know!\h
I will move my entire house onto a boat,\h\h
that will show those tiny pandas who's the boss.”
Your fears are entirely justified, Jason.\h
But I’m sorry to say, according to the WWF,\h\h
which I believe is the World Wrestling\h
Federation, “They can also swim and,\h\h
unlike most other bears, do not hibernate\h
for months at [a] time during winter.”
Which means they will never rest until they’ve\h
killed you and everyone you ever cared about. A\h\h
house boat isn’t going to cut it. Fortunately\h
Pandas are very dumb. I mean, look at them.
They can easily be fooled and tricked.\h
I recommend booby trapping your house,\h\h
with a large pile of bamboo. Then the\h
pandas will get distracted and start eating.\h\h
And since they spend like 14 hours a day eating\h
bamboo, you can use that time to run away.\h
Thanks for your question Jason.
And thank you for watching. I’m\h
Chris Chappell. See you next time.