On this episode of China Uncensored,
don’t worry!
The Chinese military has you covered.
Welcome back to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
PLARF.
No, I’m not celebrating 25 years of Pinky
and the Brain.
I’m talking about the Chinese Communist
Party’s
People’s Liberation Army Rocket Force.
New satellite photos have emerged of a PLARF
base
in China’s Sichuan Province.
And what does the People’s Liberation Army
Rocket Force
plan to do tonight?
The same thing it does every night:
Try to take over the world!
Well, not the world.
But possibly part of India.
China’s Sichuan Province is of course a
short distance
from the Arunachal Pradesh,
territory disputed by both India and the Chinese
Regime.
According to The Print, this new Chinese base
could potentially
“support a brigade-sized intercontinental
ballistic missile formation”
capable of covering “all of India,
the Indian Ocean Region as well as large parts
of continental America.”
Reports of the new base come just a few months
after the tenth successful test
of China’s latest and most powerful ICBM,
the DF-41.
According to video from state-run People’s
Daily,
the DF-41 is capable of carrying up to 10
nuclear warheads,
with a range of about 7500 miles.
With that kind of range, a DF-41 launched
from Sichuan
is capable of traveling around the globe—
or across the flat Earth disk,
if that’s your thing—
to strike the continental United States.
Also, it can hit India.
Which is way closer.
But India isn’t exactly a sitting duck.
Or...sitting cow.
Or elephant.
Whatever the appropriate sitting animal is
in this scenario.
Earlier this year, India tested its own nuclear
capable missile
that could hit anywhere in China.
Then in March,
China sold Pakistan, “a powerful tracking
system
in an unprecedented deal that could speed
up
the Pakistani military’s development
of multi-warhead missiles.”
Which was then later followed by China’s
DF-41 test
and news of the new missile garrison.
And this is just the latest development in
a long history
of bad nuclear family relations.
China and India have the two largest populations
in Asia,
and the nations often compete for the same
sphere of influence.
Plus they both have nukes.
But really, is that any reason they couldn’t
still be friends?
After all, China’s foreign minister says
that
India’s Elephant and China’s dragon
should dance instead of fight.
How would that work?
Would it look something like this?
Unfortunately, in the past,
India and China have been more interested
in fighting than dancing.
China and India fought a brief but bloody
war in 1962
over disputed territory.
And they still periodically have confrontations
over the same territory.
Like the longer, but fortunately not bloody,
confrontation last summer.
“Its personnel were caught on camera
jostling with Indian troops—
some time in second week of June
across the LAC in Sikkim.”
That standoff lasted over 70 days.
And in that entire time,
no one thought to have a dance.
Really.
But the Chinese Communist Party has been patiently
working
to weaken and surround India.
“China is allegedly the principal opponent
to India’s bid
for the United Nations Security Council membership
and it has also been opposing India’s entry
at the Nuclear Suppliers Group.”
India wants a voice in that influential nuclear
group.
According to the Arms Control Association,
India has around 140 nukes.
For its part,
India is one of the rare countries in the
region
that doesn’t support China’s Belt and
Road Initiative.
That’s where the Chinese regime builds infrastructure
in other countries,
gets them in debt,
and then occasionally forces them to establish
potential Chinese military bases.
That’s called the String of Pearls theory.
And look!
It just so happens they all surround the Indian
Ocean.
But it’s not like the Chinese Communist
Party is going to try
to make a move on the Indian Ocean, right?
I mean, the China Ocean has a ring to it.
Well, not so much a ring, as a string...of
pearls.
Maybe we’ve been looking at this problem
all wrong.
Why should India and China have
to choose between dancing and fighting?
When they could dance and fight at the same
time?
Now that’s a dance off!
Then again, with India and China both able
to cover each other in nuclear missiles,
the fate of the world should probably depend
on
more than just great choreography.
I think I’m ready for new world leadership.
So what do you think of China’s new missile
base?
What is the risk to India?
Leave your comments below.
And before you go,
it’s time to answer a question from a fan
who supports China Uncensored
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
Jonathan Swanberg asks,
“With the United States announcing
its United States Space Force,
do you think China will follow suit?
I mean they already have a freakin laser in
the works...
Is this just wishful thinking for someone
who wants to join the space Marines?
Good question.
Back in 2014,
there were rumors that the Chinese military
was going to establish a space force,
but those rumors were never confirmed.
But regardless,
the Chinese space program
is already a branch of the military—
the Chinese Communist Party’s military.
And they’re already weaponizing space,
like with freakin’ lasers, as you pointed
out.
And I assume they believe Mars has belonged
to China
since ancient times.
Because it’s called the Red Planet!
Anyway, in my view,
the US sees the Chinese regime’s space plans
as a real threat,
and is responding to that by establishing
the US Space Force.
But Jonathan, trust me,
you don’t know want to join the space marines.
It’s not gonna be pretty once you have to
fight the aliens.
Thanks for your question Jonathan.
Remember, China Uncensored is made possible
by the support from you,
my amazing fans.
So if you can, consider supporting China Uncensored
through our Patreon website.
You’ll have a chance to get your questions
answered on the show,
and get some neat stuff for your support.
Once again,
thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Want to learn more about China?
Go to ChinaUncensored.tv.
We have full half-hour episodes there every
Friday.
You can also watch our TV show
on the China Uncensored app
on Apple TV, Roku, and Amazon FireTV.