On this episode of China Uncensored,
I will not sanction these sanctions.
China defends good buddy Pakistan
from mean old Trump.
And who else but a Chinese human rights lawyer
would be guilty of subverting state power?
This is China Uncensored.
Welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
On Wednesday, a huge typhoon struck southern China,
including Hong Kong and Macau.
Ten people were killed.
Hong Kong authorities did their best
to make sure their residents were safe,
telling them not to go outside and...
exercise?!
Or go swimming?!
What are you doing?!
Get out of the water!!
The nearby gambling hub of Macau
fared less well than Hong Kong.
Streets were flooded,
and a lot of buildings lost power.
Fortunately, that meant the casinos
had to shut down,
saving thousands of gamblers
from losing a ton of money.
We’re going to talk more about
Hong Kong and Macau later in the show.
But in the meantime,
the Chinese Communist Party wants you
to know how they feel.
That’s why they invented the phrase,
“hurt the feelings of the Chinese people.”
So the rest of the world
would better understand when they’ve said
or done something they weren’t supposed
to.
According to one Chinese blogger,
state-run People’s Daily,
“has used the phrase in reference
to 19 different countries and organizations,
ranging from the United States
to the Nobel Committee
and to NATO.”
What’s that, Shelley?
That was back in 2008?
Well, who knows how many more countries and
organizations
have hurt the feelings of the Chinese people
since then.
And you should be very concerned
about the feelings of the Chinese people.
Why just this week,
a professor at the University of Sydney
found that out the hard way.
He dared to make a bold statement
that China has no right to disputed territory
that both China and India claim.
OK, it wasn’t so much of a statement.
It was more like he showed a map.
And it wasn’t so much a map
of the disputed territory per se,
it was a world map.
And it wasn’t his world map.
It was just the first one that shows up
when you Google “world map,”
and he put it on a PowerPoint slide.
And it wasn’t for a geography class or anything.
It was just for an IT class.
And it was 18 months ago.
But if you zoom way, way in,
you can see that the blurry borders
show India’s claim,
not China’s.
So Chinese students in his class
began denouncing him on WeChat,
and it became a big thing because,
you know,
he hurt the feelings of the Chinese people.
So this week
he was forced to publicly apologize.
I wonder if students suspected him
of using an anti-China map
because his name is Khimji Vaghjiani
and he looks like this.
Nah.
Moving on.
With so much focus on feelings,
it’s no wonder that most of the
China news this week involved
the Chinese regime telling the rest of the
world
how it felt about something else.
For instance:
the US putting sanctions on Chinese companies
and individuals supporting Kim Jong-Un’s
fantasyland paradise.
China was not happy about
what it called the US’s “mistake.”
“What the United States has done
is not helpful to the resolution
of the issue and is not beneficial
to mutual trust and cooperation
between China and the United States
on this matter.
We ask the United States
to immediately stop its mistake.”
The sanctions are the second round since June.
They target Chinese companies
that work with North Korea,
including three that imported its coal,
and another one that helped finance
its ballistic missiles program.
And speaking of North Korea’s
ballistic missiles program,
China was not happy about the latest
US-South Korea military drills.
You know, the ones where they prepare
for Kim Jong-un following through
on his threats to nuke South Korea
and the US.
“We think that South Korea and the United
States
holding joint drills is not beneficial
to easing current tensions nor the efforts
by all sides to promote talks."
That’s a bit of an overreaction.
Considering they were the least aggressive—
and quite possibly lamest—
joint military drills ever.
They were just sitting around
simulating drills on computers
at the Korea Battle Simulation Center.
Meanwhile, in Virginia on Monday,
President Trump outlined his new Middle East
Strategy.
And then he dropped this bomb.
A figurative bomb.
Probably need to be clear about that.
“We can no longer be silent about
Pakistan's safe havens for terrorist organizations,
the Taliban,
and other groups that pose a threat
to the region and beyond.”
Hmm, I wonder if this hurt the feelings
of Pakistan’s biggest ally and trading partner,
China.
Let’s check in again
with the Chinese Foreign Ministry.
“Pakistan is on the front line
in the struggle against terrorism.
It has actively made efforts
and great sacrifices
to combat terrorism for years
and has made important contributions
to safeguarding regional
and global peace and stability.”
I’m sure India might disagree,
but China and India aren’t exactly seeing
eye to eye right now—
considering their most recent bilateral meeting
included border soldiers
throwing rocks at each other.
To be clear,
that’s the same dispute that we talked about
last week,
but now there’s video!
So as you can see,
they are definitely throwing rocks at each
other...
or playing capture the flag.
Really, it could be either one.
But feelings were probably hurt on both sides.
And speaking of feelings,
have you been wondering how the Chinese regime
feels about the US State Department’s
latest International Religious Freedom Report?
It slammed China with harsh language,
calling China one of 7 countries
“of particular concern”.
Other countries include North Korea and Iran.
Well, China is back with some harsh words
for the US.
“Everyone has seen that the facts
prove the United States is not totally perfect.”
She was referring to what happened
in Charlottesville,
Because a handful of idiots shouting
“Jews will not replace us”
and ruining tiki torches for everyone
is exactly equivalent to the ruling Chinese
regime
killing tens of thousands of religious believers
and then selling their organs
on the black market.
The point is,
China has great religious freedom.
“The Chinese government fully respects
and protects people’s religious freedom
according to the law.
People from all ethnic groups and regions
fully possess religious freedom
according to the law.”
Speaking of rule of law in China,
a prominent human rights lawyer
just confessed on state-run television
to subverting state power.
I fully realize that my actions of inciting subversion of state power and overthrowing
the socialist system violate the law and constitute crimes.
In the past,
Jiang Tianyong had accused the Chinese regime
of torturing another prominent human rights
lawyer.
It was a brave thing to do.
Like a lamb calling out a wolf
for eating other lambs.
He also defended blind human rights activist
Chen Guangcheng and Falun Gong practitioners.
This guy had some real guts, is what I’m
saying.
But then he was secretly detained
and probably tortured for 10 months.
And now he’s a reformed man!
This week, he clarified on state-run media
that all the things he said about the Chinese
regime
torturing that other human rights lawyer
were just lies—
and he made them up to curry favor
with foreign media.
You see, he was deceived
after being indoctrinated by the
“bourgeois Western constitutional system.”
Those were words he spoke during the trial
that were totally not scripted at all.
He deeply regrets his actions.
So who else do you think is guilty
of so-called “hurting the feelings of the
Chinese people”?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Hey, you know what would really hurt my feelings?
If you don’t go check out ChinaUncensored.tv.
That’s where we upload full half hour episodes
of China Uncensored for free every Friday.
You would have seen this episode
and so much more.
ChinaUncensored.tv.