The Chinese Communist Party
Controls the coronavirus narrative
They even control
“The Science” around
the world
Welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
From the beginning of the coronavirus outbreak,
the Chinese Communist Party has been involved
in a massive cover-up.
The Party silenced doctors who tried to warn
others about the virus.
They lied about human-to-human transmission
of the virus.
They pressured the World Health Organization
to repeat those lies.
That’s why I’ve been calling the coronavirus
the CCP virus.
Because no matter where the virus came from,
the Chinese Communist Party is still responsible
for the cover-up that led to a global pandemic.
But now that the Wuhan lab-leak theory is
suddenly credible, more media have been doing...actual
reporting.
Which means they’re almost catching up to
the group of amateur Twitter sleuths who broke
this story last year.
So evidence that the CCP virus leaked from
a lab in Wuhan is piling up.
And people are paying attention.
The Chinese Communist Party hates this.
Their response to this has been to repeatedly
imply that the coronavirus actually comes
from the US military biolab at Fort Detrick.
With headlines like “Who lives a lie gets
challenged by the truth.”
Proving once again the Communist Party lives
in an irony-free zone.
I’ve talked about how the US media outright
dismissed the lab leak hypothesis as a conspiracy
theory, which made them a mouthpiece for Chinese
communist propaganda.
That’s on my other channel America Uncovered.
But this denial and censorship isn’t just
the media’s fault.
For the last year, we’ve been told to “follow
the science” when it comes to the virus.
But it’s clear now the Chinese regime has
been able to manipulate, co-opt, and censor
“the science” from the very beginning.
Some of it was obvious.
Like when Chinese police silenced Dr. Li Wenliang
for trying to warn other doctors about the
CCP virus.
Another early example: A group of Chinese
researchers shared the genome of the CCP virus
on January 11, 2020.
This was hailed as a sign China was being
more open about the virus outbreak.
It turns out, not so much.
The lab that released the genome was shut
down for “rectification” the next day.
The researchers had already sequenced the
genome on January 5, two days before China’s
official announcement that the mysterious
pneumonia cases in Wuhan were caused by a
coronavirus.
“The team made the finding public on January
11 after it saw that the authorities had taken
no obvious action to warn the public about
the coronavirus.”
And then they were closed down.
But months later, the head of that lab, Zhang
Yongzhen, denied that his lab suffered any
prolonged closure.
Was he telling the truth?
It’s hard to say.
Chinese scientists work under an authoritarian
regime.
If he’s talking to TIME magazine, Zhang
isn’t going to say, “Yeah the government
totally closed me down.”
Even if it did.
But it turns out, Zhang’s lab was not the
first one to sequence the virus genome.
Several other labs had sequenced it in late
December and early January.
Then they were ordered by health officials
to stop testing and destroy the samples.
“On Jan. 3, China’s National Health Commission
(NHC), the nation’s top health authority,
ordered institutions not to publish any information
related to the unknown disease, and ordered
labs to transfer any samples they had to designated
testing institutions, or to destroy them.”
Even the Wuhan Institute of Virology was ordered
to destroy their samples.
So given the global gag order, Zhang’s lab
would definitely have been in trouble for
publishing the genome without official approval.
So the Chinese Communist Party has definitely
censored scientists in China.
That’s terrible, but not surprising.
But the Chinese regime has also censored scientists
in the West.
They've done this through manipulating Western
scientific journals to silence any discussion
about the lab leak hypothesis.
I’ll tell you how after the break.
Welcome back.
We’re talking about the CCP virus, so you
probably didn’t see an ad there, did you?
One of the main ways the Communist Party spreads
its message is to co-opt outsiders and get
them to repeat the Party line.
In the case of the CCP virus, one of the loudest
voices has been Dr. Peter Daszak.
Daszak worked directly with the Wuhan Institute
of Virology.
But he organized a letter published in the
Lancet.
That’s a prestigious medical journal.
His letter called the lab leak hypothesis
a conspiracy theory.
Of course, at first people didn’t realize
that Daszak’s non-profit was working with
the Wuhan Institute of Virology on bat coronaviruses,
because Daszak didn’t disclose that giant
conflict of interest.
In fact, he outright lied and said “We declare
no competing interests.”
And then he talked to anyone who would interview
him about how the idea that the CCP virus
could have possibly leaked from a lab was
an absurd and harmful conspiracy theory.
Daszak also traveled to China as part of the
WHO team to investigate the origins of the
coronavirus.
He was the only American allowed on the team.
Sure, he’s worked with the lab that should
be investigated, but that just means he’s
an expert, right?
Speaking of conspiracy theories, Daszak even
gave an interview to my favorite Chinese state-run
media, the Global Times.
He validated their propaganda that the CCP
virus did not come from China.
Last year, after the Trump administration
shut down funding to Daszak’s non-profit,
Nature magazine even did a sympathetic interview
with Daszak.
Of course, when Daszak was describing the
research they did in Wuhan that the US government
should definitely be funding, he conveniently
left out the part about how the Wuhan Institute
of Virology was doing gain of function research
to make coronaviruses more dangerous to humans.
We know they were doing this based on research
grants Daszak got from the US National Institutes
of Health.
But now that Daszak’s conflicts of interests
have been exposed, he’s left a UN-backed
commission to look into the origins of Covid.
That commission was organized by the Lancet,
the same medical journal that published Daszak’s
letter condemning the lab leak hypothesis,
the one where he falsely declared no competing
interests.
I bet the Lancet is embarrassed now.
They should probably issue a correction on
that letter.
Instead, the Lancet published Daszak’s updated
disclosure statement.
Where he said he never received funding from
the People’s Republic of China.
Ok, that’s *technically* true.
You never directly got money from China.
But you did research with a lab that’s directly
funded and managed by the Chinese government.
One that also works with the Chinese military.
And your access to that work depends on the
Chinese Communist Party.
Maybe that’s worth pointing out.
But the Lancet letter wasn’t the only one
that convinced everyone to stop looking at
the lab leak hypothesis.
There was also this letter published in Nature
Medicine.
It was held up as definitive scientific proof
that the CCP virus came from nature and not
a lab leak.
One of the scientists who wrote that letter
received China’s top science award for foreigners.
And another is a guest professor at China’s
CDC and a visiting professor at Fudan University.
So those are both big conflicts of interest.
But there’s an even bigger problem with
the Nature Medicine journal—the problem
of where the journal gets its money.
More after the break.
Welcome back.
In 2015, Nature Medicine published this research
article on bat coronaviruses.
One of the authors was Dr. Shi Zhengli , who
works on bat coronaviruses at the Wuhan Institute
of Virology.
And it involved doing gain of function research
on bat coronaviruses.
Which led to Nature Medicine leaving this
Editor’s Note on the article to “debunk”
the idea of a CCP virus lab leak.
Maybe it’s time to update that editor’s
note.
Shi Zhengli also published a paper in Nature
that was the first analysis of the CCP virus.
In that paper, she introduced a virus called
RaTG13, which was the closest relative to
the CCP virus.
She said it was found in nature.
So if the closest relative to the CCP Virus
was found in nature, then *surely* the CCP
virus itself must also have a natural origin,
right?
But Dr. Shi *hid* the fact that she was the
one who discovered RaTG13, and took it into
her lab, and did experiments on it.
And it’s *possible* she used gain of function
research to turn RaTG13 into the CCP Virus.
But it took Nature nine months to even acknowledge
that she was the one who discovered RaTG13.
Shi Zhengli has been hiding a lot more stuff
when it comes to the CCP virus.
I don’t have time to get into it all here,
but let me know if you’d like me to do an
episode on it.
And Shi isn’t the only Chinese scientist
who used Western journals to dismiss the possibility
of a lab leak.
Chinese officials claimed the CCP virus outbreak
was from an animal at the Wuhan wet market.
And then, Chinese scientists suddenly started
submitting papers in Western journals pointing
to a similar virus that was in pangolins.
Nature published two of these Chinese papers—and
that made the theory seem credible.
Even though...it turns out, pangolins weren’t
sold at that wet market.
But Nature never pointed out the problems
with the pangolin studies.
Here’s where it gets interesting.
Nature has a financial relationship with the
Chinese Communist Party.
Here’s how it works:
Nature’s parent company is Springer Nature.
It turns out that China is “becoming the
biggest national sponsor of open access journals
published by both Springer Nature and Elsevier
(El-zuh-veer), owner of The Lancet.”
Oh the Lancet too?
The one Daszak wrote for.
Good to know.
So what does all this Chinese Communist Party
money go to?
They’re paying these publishing companies
to publish Chinese “scientific” journals
that the Communist Party funded.
Those journals include China Science Materials,
which is edited by the state-run China Academy
of Sciences.
And the Chinese Journal of Catalysis, which
is also run by several Chinese state scientific
bodies.
Springer Nature and Elsevier get millions
of dollars, and China’s scientific journals
seem more prestigious.
Springer Nature’s sponsorship agreements
alone could be worth 10 million dollars.
That’s 10 million reasons to not publish
papers that challenge the Communist Party’s
coronavirus claims.
And Springer Nature *has* censored articles
in the past.
Back in 2017, at the Chinese Communist Party’s
request, Springer Nature censored hundreds
of journal articles on sensitive topics.
Topics that Springer Nature censored included
Taiwan, Tibet, and human rights.
Those articles were censored in China.
But it’s not a leap to think Springer Nature
would be worried about angering the Chinese
regime outside China now about the origins
of the CCP Virus—since millions of dollars
may depend on it.
So when we in America were told to “follow
the science” over the past year, we were
actually following scientists and journals
that have huge conflicts of interest—including
funding from communist China.
And now it’s time to answer a question from
a member of the China Uncensored 50 Cent Army,
fans who support us and our efforts to expose
the truth about the Chinese Communist Party,
by contributing through crowd funding website
Patreon.
Black Label asks, “Given the massive Sinkholes,
the shaking building and the collapse of bridges,
and the recent fear of the Taishan nuclear
plant going up Chernobyl style...would China
fall first from an infrastructure standpoint,
before any military action would happen?
That's a really interesting question Black
Label.
So first of all, considering all the corruption
in construction and manufacturing you just
mentioned, you gotta wonder how capable the
Chinese Communst Party’s military actually
is.
But I think you’re right—internal corruption
is a major risk to the Chinese Communist Party.
That’s something even former Communist leaders
have talked about.
A lot of construction is also rushed through
to artificially boost GDP numbers.
It’s not tied to any kind of market principles.
On top of that, China is running out of US
dollars.
That will have a major impact on the economy
and any future infrastructure works.
So I think you’re right, war with the Chinese
Communist Party may never happen.
Internal corruption could be the catalyst
that triggers the collapse of the Party.
Thanks for your question and your support
Black Label.
And a big thank you to everyone who supports
China Uncensored on Patreon.
We could not do this show without you.
So thank you for joining us in the fight to
expose the Chinese Communist Party to the
world.
If you’re interested in joining, head over
to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
You’ll get a bunch of cool perks, including
the chance to have me answer your question
on the show!
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next
time.