Emotion recognition spytech.
It’s China’s newest mass surveillance
craze
But there’s a big problem
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I'm Chris Chappell.
Forget facial recognition,
eye tracking,
and crowd analysis.
China’s hottest new surveillance craze
is emotion recognition.
Emotion recognition:
the thing all my ex girlfriends wish I had.
Here’s how the computerized version works.
The idea is that software algorithms can tell
how
you’re feeling by analyzing real time video
of your face.
For a long time,
China’s internal security
has used facial recognition software
that analyzes your facial dimensions,
hair color and skin color.
And they’ve discovered that that most crimes
in China
are committed by people with...black... hair.
Arrest all the Party officials!
Haha, you’ll have to wait till after the
revolution.
But soon China’s 200 million surveillance
cameras
could start recording and analyzing people’s
emotions
to figure out if they’re likely to commit
a crime.
If the system spots certain indicators—
say you’ve had a bad day and are scowling
on your way home from the office—
up goes a red flag
and a possible police interception.
The trouble is,
experts say emotion recognition technology
is actually “pretty bogus.”
This recent study found that
while facial expression recognition systems
are up to 97% accurate in the lab,
that accuracy rate drops to around 50%
in the real-world.
But never mind that it’s only right half
the time.
The Communist Party has no qualms
about arresting innocent people.
And the Party has already begun
experimenting with emotion recognition
to target China’s most vulnerable population.
A Financial Times reporter
went to a spytech expo in Shenzhen.
She tweeted that a “policing expert and
party cadre
from Xinjiang’s public security bureau”
told her they’re already using emotion recognition
to target people there.
Xinjiang is in western China.
It’s the testing ground for the latest in
spytech.
That’s where the Communist Party
is putting people in concentration camps.
“The Chinese Communist Party is detaining
and abusing more than 1 million Uighur Muslims
in internment camps in Xinjiang,
the western region of China.
The pages of George Orwell’s 1984
are coming to life there.”
It’s 1984, with 2019 technology.
But experts say it’s still early days.
More testing needs to be done
In emotion recognition technology
is adopted widely across China.
But in Xinjiang, better safe than sorry.
If you’re having a bad day...
Smile!
Because anything less can get you into a lot
of trouble.
So what do you think about China’s security
using emotion recognition to target its citizens?
Leave your comments below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.