Do we have proof the coronavirus was engineered?
The US Air Force prepares for war with China.
And why street names in Hungary are infuriating
China.
That and more on this week’s China News
headlines.
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
For over a year, anyone who suggested the
coronavirus leaked from a Chinese lab, let
alone was bioengineered in a Chinese lab,
was labeled a right wing conspiracy nut.
Listen to the science, you morons.
Well, now the science suggests the coronavirus
is a bioengineered virus that leaked from
a Chinese lab.
Surprise!
Without getting too much into the science,
“The Covid-19 pathogen has a genetic footprint
that has never been observed in a natural
coronavirus.”
It does have a genetic code seen in coronavirus
engineered in labs.
Specifically after gain of function research—that
is, research designed to make viruses more
deadly and contagious.
Even more damning, when the Chinese lab “published
a paper in February 2020 with the virus’s
partial genome, they omitted any mention of
the special sequence that supercharges the
virus.”
Now this special genetic sequence that points
to lab engineering was easy to see.
In fact, scientists in this report from February
2020 noticed it.
The paper says a special protein marker “may
provide a gain-of-function” capability to
the virus, “for efficient spreading” to
humans.
Again, that was in February 2020.
Before we even began locking down in the United
States.
And yet despite the obvious signs of engineering,
and despite Dr. Anthony Faucisigning off on
US funding for coronavirus research that took
place at the Wuhan Institute of Virology,
Fauci dismissed the lab leak theory for months.
Which is why you have fact checks like this
one from last year saying the lab leak was
doubtful.
It now says, “This fact check has been updated.”
Or this one that now says
“scientific consensus has shifted”.
How about that?
In fact, a report prepared for the US government
by the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory
found it plausible that Covid leaked from
a Wuhan lab.
“Lawrence Livermore has considerable expertise
on biological issues.”
That report was prepared in May 2020, but
it remains classified.
But even knowing about the existence of this
report is further evidence of the lab leak
hypothesis.
It’s amazing what the media can find out
when they actually...report on things.
And here’s a fun fact, “A Chinese Communist
Party military scientist who got funding from
the National Institutes of Health filed a
patent for a COVID-19 vaccine in February
last year.”
So...a Chinese military scientist could have
had a vaccine only a month after the Chinese
Communist Party admitted there was human-to-human
transmission?
Good to know.
And after a genetically engineered Chinese
supervirus that was partly funded by the US
killed millions...why did top US scientists,
officials, and the media ruthlessly attack
anyone even suggesting it came from a lab?
Somehow, I think we need more of an explanation
than—it was Trump’s fault.
Don’t worry, the WHO says they can’t force
China to give more information on the origin
of the coronavirus.
I’m so glad Biden stopped us from withdrawing
from the WHO.
Earlier this week I did a deep dive on how
US media discredited the Wuhan lab leak story
on our other channel, America Uncovered.
Check it out, link is below.
And after the break, the US is preparing for
war with China.
Welcome back.
The US is preparing for war with China.
The Air Force is fanning out jets across the
Pacific.
You see, most US warplanes have been stationed
in either Japan or Guam.
So China built up over a thousand ballistic
missiles capable of wiping out those bases
in the event of war.
So, the US Air Force is spreading out hundreds
of warplanes across potentially dozens of
smaller bases—thus diluting the striking
power of China’s rocket force.
However, the US isn’t prepared for China’s
contingency plan.
To use China’s team rocket force to steal
America’s pokemon.
Gotta catch ‘em all.
Last week was the anniversary of the Tiananmen
Square Massacre.
And Western tech companies had the chance
to prove they’re on the side of Chinese
dictators.
According to exiled Hong Kong activist Nathan
Law, the Israel based company Wix shut down
a Hong Kong democracy website.
That was after Hong Kong police asked them
to.
Don’t worry, Wix said it was a mistake.
Get ready to hear a lot of that.
Microsoft’s Bing search engine came up with
no results found for Tank Man.
They said it was human error.
Tiananmen Survivor Zhou Fengsuo , whom we’ve
had on the show before, said a live stream
commemorating the massacre couldn't be viewed
on YouTube.
“YouTube replied to Zhou citing a possible
technical reason for the video issue.”
Zhou also said Facebook cut off a live stream
of a Tiananmen commemoration calling it spam.
It was a technical error.
Look, the only technical error was normalizing
trade with China.
Which is apparently something Florida Governor
Ron DeSantis is trying to fight.
Here he is at a press conference this week.
If you look right now, there is no single
entity that exercises a more pervasive nefarious
influence across a wide range of American
industries and institutions than the Communist
Party of China
DeSantis signed two new bills aimed at countering
China.
One of the new laws bans trade secret theft
and trafficking and increases penalties for
such crimes.
Those that steal for foreign regimes will
face even higher penalties.
The other bill “aims to cut the Chinese
Communist Party’s access to higher academic
institutions...by prohibiting [them] from
entering into agreements with the Chinese
regime or companies with close state ties.”
The bills target several different countries,
such as Cuba and Venezuela, but China is the
main focus.
Unfortunately for Ron DeSantis, he’s a state
governor, not the US president.
He can’t actually set national policy.
But he gets an A for effort.
Plus an F for Florida.
Unfortunately, the Chinese government knows
how to play that game too—and they can do
it at a national level.
I’ll tell you more after the break.
Welcome back.
China is moving forward with a new law aimed
at countering US sanctions.
China doesn’t like the US sanctioning Communist
officials for genociding the Uyghurs, or blocking
China from getting certain sensitive technologies.
That’s why China has been drafting new laws
that “would allow China’s courts to punish
global companies for complying with foreign
sanctions”.
Oh no, if they punish US companies too much,
they’ll pull out of China.
Then they won’t be cheated, having their
technology stolen and their global market
share taken by cheaper Chinese knockoffs.
They might even have to bring manufacturing
jobs back to America.
Tragedy.
And it turns out, China’s strategy to punish
foreign companies and officials has already
backfired in Europe.
Back in March, China sanctioned EU officials
for sanctioning Chinese officials.
And that killed a major investment deal between
China and the EU.
And speaking of reasons not to do business
with the Chinese Communist Party, did I mention
the genocide in Xinjiang?
Even though China is facing a population crisis
because of hundreds of millions of forced
abortions during the One Child Policy...
that doesn’t mean trying forced abortions
in Xinjiang won’t be a good idea!
New “Chinese birth control policies could
cut between 2.6 to 4.5 million births of the
Uyghur and other ethnic minorities in southern
Xinjiang within 20 years.”
And a proposed Chinese funded university in
Hungary really backfired for the Chinese regime.
First, thousands protested against it.
Then the mayor of Budapest decided to do some
inventive street renaming in the capital.
“One street will be named after the Dalai
Lama.”
“Another will be called ‘Uyghur Martyrs’
Road.’”
“A third will be called ‘Free Hong Kong
And “A fourth street will be renamed after
a Chinese Catholic bishop who was jailed.”
Which tells us something very interesting.
The global elite may like the Chinese Communist
Party.
But your average people, and often your local
politicians, really don’t.
And now it’s time to answer a question from
a member of the China Uncensored 50 Cent Army,
fans who support us and our efforts to expose
the truth about the Chinese Communist Party,
by contributing through crowd funding website
Patreon.
oliviero gubelmann asks, “Hi Chris , would
you consider writing a book about all ccp’s
dark secret and history of mad ideas and policy?”
I’m glad you asked Oliviero!
I was actually talking with Matt and Shelley
about this the other day.
We’ve been making this show for almost 9
years now.
And we’ve learned a lot about the Chinese
Communist Party and its actions against democracies
around the world.
So I had the idea—what if we wrote a book?
It could be a digital book, that would be
pretty simple to do.
But I guess that all depends on you.
Those of you watching, would you also be interested
in buying a book we write?
Would you want it to have some humor?
Tell me in the comments below what kind of
book you’d like to see.
Thanks for bringing it up Oliviero and thanks
for your support.
And a big thank you to everyone who supports
China Uncensored on Patreon.
We could not do this show without you.
So thank you for joining us in the fight to
expose the Chinese Communist Party to the
world.
If you’re interested in joining, head over
to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
You’ll get a bunch of cool perks, including
the chance to have me answer your question
on the show!
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next
time.