On this episode of China Uncensored,
can you hug your children with nuclear arms?
Kim Jong-un is certainly going to try!
China is exploding...
over US weapons sales to Taiwan.
And what do a mistress,
a spymaster,
and a Chinese billionaire have in common?
I’m not sure,
but it sounds like a party.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
For all my fellow Americans out there,
I hope you all had a wonderful Independence
Day.
And a special shout out as well
to all my friends in the UK;
we couldn’t have done it without you.
This Fourth of July was special,
not just because of this sick American flag
cake
Shelley made…
but because this year’s celebrations
were made in China.
As is apparently every Fourth of July these
days.
“93 percent of fireworks used in the United
States
are made in China,”
according to a 2013 report
by the American Pyrotechnics Association,
right before it caught on fire.
That’s almost 300 million dollars
in fireworks last year.
Which makes sense,
because after all,
China invented fireworks in the 7th century.
But Chinese manufacturing has taken things
to a whole new level.
In China,
there’s a town that makes the world’s
jeans.
A town that makes Christmas.
Even a village that makes Van Goghs.
And most of the world’s fireworks
are made here in Liling,
Hunan Province.It’s one of the most dangerous
industries in China.
Poor safety standards often lead to disasters,
like this explosion in 2014
that killed 13 people and injured dozens more.
The good news though is that industries in
China
are beefing up their safety standards,
like for example,
when electronics maker Foxconn
installed these suicide nets.
But I don’t mean to grill China.
Because you’re probably already doing that
yourself.
According to Consumer Reports,
“Most gas grills are made in China.”
And this Fourth of July,
Americans spent 5.3 million dollars
on American flags made in China.
But America didn’t pay for everything
this fourth of July.
Some things were gifts!
Like this,
an Intercontinental Ballistic Missile
launched by our friends in North Korea.
Rotund North Korean leader, Kim Jong-un
said it was a “gift” to “American bastards.”
Well that was very thoughtful of him,
but unfortunately
America already has an ICMB.
Actually 450 of them.
“Oh wow.
I totally don’t have any of these.
Thank you so much.”
Meanwhile, South Korea responded to the missile
launch
with this video simulating
how they could strike back at North Korea.
For example,
say North Korea were a star on a giant rock.
They could totally blow it up.
China, on the other hand,
is not having much luck
with explosive projectiles.
This is the Long March 5,
China’s most powerful rocket.
They launched it on July 2.
And completely not living up to its name,
it failed soon after takeoff.
State-run media said the failure
was caused by an “anomaly,”
but was vague on details.
I’m going to guess the anomaly was...
it turned into a giant fireball.
Don’t worry, it was unmanned.
But the failure throws into questions
many of the space plans China
has proposed for the coming months,
including an unmanned trip to the moon
scheduled for November.
Maybe they can just go halfway and come back.
Speaking of Independence Day,
on July 1, Hong Kong celebrated
the 20th anniversary of its own liberation
from Great Britain,
with a fun-filled military parade
led by their Chinese overlords.
This woman says she feels a lot safer
knowing that the People’s Liberation Army
is here to enforce Hong Kong’s liberation.
I’d feel safer, too,
with eight to ten thousand PLA troops
on the ground, ready for action.
By the way,
you know that Sino-British Joint Declaration
that established the One Country,
Two systems policy,
the one that allows Hong Kong
to keep freedoms impossible in mainland China?
Well on June 30th,
my favorite Chinese spokesman Lu Kang
had this to say.
"The Sino-British joint declaration,
as a historical document,
no longer has any practical significance.”
Just like how the Chinese Constitution,
which guarantees freedom of speech and religion,
also has no practical significance.
In other news,
the US sailed a Navy destroyer
through the South China Sea.
China is calling it a provocative act.
To which President Trump responded,
“Destroyer?
I hardly know her.”
This is the second freedom-of-navigation exercise
completed under Trump’s administration.
This time by the USS Stethem.
To which President Trump responded,
“Stethem!
Damn near killed ’em.”
The Defense Department said the exercise
was to challenge the territorial claims of
China,
Vietnam and Taiwan.
To which President Trump responded,
“TAI-won?
I…”
Ok, we’re done with this joke.
And finally,
a Chinese company has dropped its plans
to create genetically engineered miniature
pigs.
I didn’t know they had plans
to make them in the first place,
but I guess it’s a brave new world.
A company called BGI had announced plans
to alter the DNA of Bama pigs
to make them in custom sizes and colors.
That was followed by strenuous objections
from animal rights groups,
which pointed out that pigs
should only come in custom sizes and colors
after they’re dead.
So it looks like next year,
we’ll all have to load up some non-GMO pork
on our Chinese-made gas grills
and watch Chinese-made fireworks
as we celebrate America’s birthday.
Which reminds me,
Shelley, I’m going to need some more of
that flag cake.
We’ll be right back.
So what size and color pig would you want?
Now maybe that’s the kind of merchandise
we should be selling on the website!
Speaking of the website,
if you go to China Uncensored dot TV,
you can watch our new full-length episodes.
Each episode has segments
we won’t be putting on YouTube until next
week.
You can also watch full-length episodes
on the China Uncensored app for Apple TV,
FireTV, and Roku.
So click the link to go to ChinaUncensored.tv.