On this episode of China Uncensored,
gun control?
To the Chinese regime,
that means using both hands...
to give guns to some of the world’s
worst violators of human rights.
Welcome back to China Uncensored,
I’m Chris Chappell.
Check out these guns!
Sorry, these guns.
They’re part of 22 million dollars worth
of guns and ammunition
the Chinese regime has just donated to the
Philippines.
The donation includes 3,000 assault rifles,
3 million rounds of assorted ammunition,
and 30 sniper scopes.
Look at those happy faces.
You can almost hear him going,
“pew pew pew!”
Though it’s less funny
when you consider that the president of the
Philippines
has bragged about personally using guns
to kill people.
Now you may think 22 million dollars in weapons
isn’t all that much,
since you couldn’t even buy
one antique Chinese bowl with that!
But it’s just the latest in around 300 million
dollars,
“in military and disaster relief assistance
in a little over a year.”
And you could buy a lot of those antique bowls
with 300 million dollars.
Well, seven of them.
Plus 800 of these antique spoons.
The Chinese ambassador to the Philippines
Zhao Jianhua said the weapons deal was a sign
that,
“China is a sincere friend
and sincere partner [to the Philippines],
and will remain so forever.”
So why, you ask,
is China so generous with its arms?
Well, it actually follows a strategy
the Chinese Communist Party is using around
the world.
Buying friends with the the most loving gift
of all:
deadly weapons.
Last year,
following concerns that Filipino President
Duterte’s
War on Drugs was devolving into
roving death squads killing loads of people
outside the law,
the United States blocked the sale
of 26,000 rifles.
But does the Chinese Communist Party care
whether the Philippines shoots
some piddly little drug dealers,
or people who may or may not be drug dealers?
Or users?
Or students?
No way!
That’s because
“China is vying to become Southeast Asia’s
primary weapons vendor.”
And the Chinese regime won’t have any strings
attached.
Strings like requiring the governments they
work with
to follow the rule of law or whatever.
The Pakistan government refuses to stop terrorists?
No problem!
The Chinese regime has sold their navy
$4 billion dollars worth of submarines.
The US condemns Myanmar for ethnic cleansing?
No worries,
“China is Myanmar’s biggest supplier of
weapons,
providing most of its fighter aircraft,
armoured vehicles,
guns and naval ships.”
In fact,
the top three buyers of Chinese weapons
are Pakistan, Bangladesh, and Myanmar.
Look, the Chinese regime just sells the weapons.
What other governments do with them
is their own business.
Guns don’t kill people.
Oppressive regimes kill people.
With Chinese guns.
And it’s not just in Southeast Asia.
It’s the Middle East,
Africa,
and Latin American as well.
Last year,
an Iraqi drone strike accidentally killed
anti-ISIS fighters.
It was a Chinese drone.
In July,
Venezuela’s national guard chief said they
were,
“‘saving lives’ by using riot-control
gear
supplied by China
when confronting anti-government protests.”
Let’s look at that.
Clearly,
a lot of life-saving going on here.
China has been selling a variety of weaponry
to Caribbean and Latin American nations, too.
And when it comes to drones,
China wants to be part of a potentially
10 billion dollar market.
It’s this kind of sell-to-anybody attitude
that has put China in a position to battle
it out
for the world’s third-largest arms dealer.
Of course,
as you can also see from this chart,
no one can come close to exporting as much
weapons
as the US and Russia.
But the US would never sell weapons
to countries with bad human rights records.
Maybe I should do America Uncensored.
But it’s still true that China
is a special kind of arms dealer.
China’s clients are countries,
“either too poor to buy Western or Russian
armaments,
or who are subjected to arms embargoes
(such as Venezuela).”
The US is at least more selective
about what countries it sells to,
and the stuff that’s made in America
is usually pretty good quality.
On the other hand,
most of what China sells is,
let’s just say it’s more on the
Robert Cop side of the spectrum.
Like that time China sold four brand new
attack helicopters to Cameroon.
And then “One of them crashed shortly after
delivery.”
Hmmm...
That’s not good.
Well, at least cheap Chinese weapons
have “become popular with warlords,
rebel groups
and militias around the world”.
Fortunately for the the buyers of Chinese
weapons,
the quality of made-in-China is getting better.
Like that CH-4 drone that
“experts believe...was engineered using
information
stolen from U.S. defense contractors.”
Intellectual property theft?
We should take it as a compliment that
America’s killing machines are so good,
China wants them too.
And as long as there are countries
who don’t mind pointing guns at their own
citizens,
the Chinese Communist Party will be there
to make sure they have the guns to do it.
And if no one wants to buy them,
China will donate them.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Guns, guns, guns!
Git yer Chinese guns!
Shaky human rights record?
Extrajudicial killings?
No credit,
no problem!
The Chinese military has all the best knock-off
designs.
Guaranteed not to fall apart some of the time.
Buy yer weapons from China now!
Visit ChinaUncensored.tv to find out how!