On this episode of China Uncensored,
how does North Korea keep building these nukes?!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
You know,
one of the best decisions I ever made
was moving from Los Angeles to New York.
Why?
Within a few years, North Korea might be able to
nuke the West Coast of the United States.
Probably by the end of the first term
of the person we’re electing this November,
they are going to have the ability
to put nuclear warheads on missiles
that can reach the West Coast of the United States.
Good to be nice and safe here in Manhattan.
What?!
Now I know how this guy feels…
“Some days you just can’t get rid of a
bomb!”
But this is a serious issue.
North Korea tested yet another nuclear device
this month.
He’s done it again.
Kim Jong-Un has carried out his second nuclear test
in 8 months.
This one the strongest ever.
The US also now assumes
North Korea has a rudimentary miniaturized nuclear warhead.
Hmm…
does my miniaturized nuclear device make me
look fat?
Now despite repeated attempts to pile sanction
upon sanction
and isolate North Korea,
the West has been able to do very little
to curb Kim Jung-Un’s Fat Man dreams.
North Korea is already isolated.
Only its ally China could really punish it
more.
Yes!
China will come to the rescue!
Right?
Right!
Chinese authorities are investigating a company for
“grave economic crimes.”
The conglomerate—
Hongxiang Industrial Development Company Ltd—
may have violated a ban by China’s own Ministry
of Commerce.
They were selling aluminum oxide to North
Korea.
Aluminium oxide to those of you folks outside
the US.
What’s the big deal about that?
Well, according to the United States Nuclear
Regulatory Commission,
it’s a key ingredient in uranium enrichment.
This is just one of several key nuclear ingredients
this Chinese company was shipping to North Korea.
Fortunately,
Chinese authorities are cracking down on this
greedy corporation
that would sacrifice global security for profit.
Except it turns out, that’s not at all what
happened.
You see,
when local police posted this message,
what they actually meant by “during their work,”
is that two officials from the US Department of Justice
told them what Hongxiang was doing
and that Chinese authorities had better do
something about it.
So I guess their work
is just doing what the US government tells
them.
Not that I... know...anything about that...
Anyway,
Chinese authorities made the move
only days before this report by a South Korean
think tank
and a Washington research group.
It specifically singled out Hongxiang.
So this makes it look like the Chinese regime
is actually doing something about a nuclear North Korea.
And it is.
It’s supporting a nuclear North Korea.
You see, China trades with North Korea.
A lot.
In fact,
China is North Korea’s biggest trading partner.
China and North Korea have been buddy-buddies
for a long time.
To be fair though,
the friendship has soured a bit in recent
years,
with Kim Jong-un being a smidge more volatile
than his father.
And this is also partly because
certain Chinese leaders who had close ties
with North Korea
have been purged.
Also, North Korea has been testing nukes
close to the Chinese border,
which is kind of annoying.
Speaking of close the Chinese border:
The City of Dandong.
It’s a major trading center with North Korea.
That’s the location of Hongxiang Industrial Development—
the company that just got busted.
Hongxiang itself has been trading with North
Korea
for a long time.
And it’s pretty hard to believe that the
Chinese regime
somehow didn’t know what they were really
up to
all these years.
I mean,
we’re talking about the regime behind the
world’s
most intrusive mass surveillance system,
with 30,000 internet police,
and with a Party Secretary in every big company.
And we’re expected to believe that,
somehow,
they had no idea what Hongxiang was doing
until the Americans told them?
The Chinese regime is absolutely keeping tabs
on Chinese companies’ trade with North Korea.
That’s what gives China its biggest bargaining
chip
with other countries.
That’s why each time the US starts freaking
out about nuclear testing
in the Evil Empire,
it has to be all like,
“Help me, China!
You’re my only hope!”
So back to Hongxiang Industrial Development.
Chairwoman Ma Xiaohong has called her company
a “golden bridge” between China and North
Korea.
Figuratively of course.
Otherwise starving North Koreans would melt
it down to buy food.
And Ma was in pretty good with the Chinese
regime.
She was a member of the Liaoning Province
People’s Congress.
The Ministry of Commerce even gave Hongxiang
a license
to import oil products.
Private Chinese business can only do that
with special permission.
So when the Ministry of Commerce banned aluminum
oxide sales
to North Korea,
but her well-connected conglomerate does it anyway,
that is not a surprise.
Neither was it a surprise to Ma when North
Korea first tested nuclear weapons
in 2006.
In fact,
Chinese authorities haven’t even made it
clear whether or not Ma herself
is under investigation.
But Ma might be in trouble anyway.
Earlier this month,
she, along with 451 others,
were stripped of their positions in the Liaoning
People’s Congress.
But that had nothing to do with selling uranium
enrichment components
to North Korea.
Apparently a lot of these Liaoning People’s
Congress members
got their positions through bribery.
Ma still got to keep her company though.
So at first glance,
it looks like the Chinese regime is taking
steps
to stop a nuclear madman from endangering
the world.
But really, it’s because the US forced their hand,
and the head of the company was in trouble
for something totally different anyway.
So what do you think of the Chinese regime’s
trade with North Korea?
Leave your comments below.
Did you find this episode controversial?
Then you might want to check out what that
could mean for this video.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time