George Herbert Walker Bush,
the 41st president of the United States
Has been laid to rest.
But his influence on US-China relations
is still being felt today.
Hi, welcome back to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
President George Bush, the original,
passed away in November at the age of 94.
He’s the first president I remember as a
kid.
In his years of service to the United States,
he accomplished a tremendous amount.
And as a final accomplishment,
at his funeral,
he got Trump and Obama to shake hands
and sit practically next to each other.
Hillary seems a little less than pleased.
I think she wanted Trump’s seat.
The funeral was touching,
especially the speech given by his son.
No, the one people liked.
I said Dad I love you and you've been a wonderful
father.
And the last words he would ever say on earth
were,
I love you too.
To us he was close to perfect,
but not totally perfect.
His short game was lousy.
Wow, I think that’s the first time I’ve
ever seen people
laughing with him.
But George Bush Senior was many things to
many people.
A patriot who fought for his country in World
War II.
The leader of the CIA at the end of the Cold
War.
A president in a time of transition.
For others...he was a reptilian alien
...who secretly tried to have Reagan assassinated.
So...you know, there’s a lot of views on
the guy.
But since this is China Uncensored,
and not America Uncovered,
I’ll stick to the impact he had on US-China
relations,
which was huge.
So huge that on the sidelines of the recent
G20 summit,
Chinese leader Xi Jinping said he was
“greatly saddened” by Bush’s passing,
saying he was “someone who made important
contributions
to the China-US friendship and relationship
during his lifetime.”
Xi apparently even, “asked Trump to convey
a message of condolence.”
And let me just say,
it was a great condolence.
Trump has the best words.
So how did George H.W. Bush become China’s
“old friend?”
Bush served as the second Special Envoy to
China between 1974 and 75.
He was basically an unofficial ambassador,
since there was no official China-US embassy
at the time.
According to CNN, he was known in Beijing
as the bicycle-riding envoy.
But after a year,
Bush left the position to lead the CIA.
And that’s a whole ’nother story.
But Bush saw Asia, and in particular China,
as pivotal for the US.
So when he became president,
he carried on building the relationships he
had in China.
Here he is having a grand old time
in Tiananmen Square in February 1989.
Ah, Tiananmen Square,
where absolutely nothing would go wrong four
months later.
“Soldiers fired automatic weapons into crowds
of civilians,
and the casualties were staggering.
The Chinese Red Cross says at least 2,600
people were killed.”
Oops.
But before that happened,
there were hopes Bush would stand up for human
rights
and political change in China.
Two months earlier,
at a banquet in China,
Bush had invited two of China’s most famous
political dissidents
Fang Lizhi and his wife Li Shuxian.
But then the June 4th Tiananmen Square Massacre
happened,
and it created a real pickle for President
Bush.
The Chinese Communist Party became
an international pariah overnight.
And on the surface,
Bush took a hard stance.
His administration put heavy economic sanctions
on China.
At a news conference,
Bush said he was moved,
not only by Tank Man,
but also by the often overlooked tank driver.
“Seeing the tank driver exercise restraint,
I'm convinced that the forces of democracy
are going to overcome these unfortunate events
in Tiananmen Square.”
Unfortunately that did not happen.
And Bush played a role in it not happening.
Because behind the scenes,
Bush sent a secret delegation to assure
the Communist leadership that, don’t worry,
the relationship would be fine.
Just a weeks after the massacre,
Bush sent National Security Adviser Brent
Scowcroft
and Deputy Secretary of State Lawrence S.
Eagleburger to China
to “keep open the lines of communication”.
I don’t know what’s more offensive:
the complete disregard for the lives of those
Chinese students,
or that there’s a guy named Eagleburger.
That’s like being named white rhino sandwich.
Anyway, according to this declassified US
State Department document,
Bush told the leadership in Beijing that he
“wants to manage short-term events in a
way
that will best assure a healthy relationship
over time.”
Basically he sent the message to the Communist
Party,
that no matter what a US President says in
public,
behind the scenes, he’ll be cooperative.
And that was a tradition future presidents
would follow.
Ultimately this caused a bit of a scandal
when it was discovered.
Bush defended his decision to the New York
Times
by saying China “is a billion-plus people.
They have a strategic position in the world
that is important to us...
I do not want to isolate the Chinese people.”
That was a policy that outlived Bush’s presidency—
that if the US keeps engaging with China,
things will get better.
But better doesn't always mean better for
everyone.
As China expert James Mann asked,
“Relationship...with which “China”?
Not with Chinese society as a whole, but with
the Party.
And not even with the official
Chinese Communist Party leadership of the
time,
headed by General Secretary Zhao Ziyang...
Back then, the United States found countless
ways
to show sympathy for reform elements
and dissidents in the Soviet Union—
but not in China.”
China scholar Perry Link told Hong Kong’s
Apple Daily,
“This constituted not only a lie to the
American people,
but also the greatest failure of American
policy toward China
after the 1989 Tiananmen Square Protests.”
Despite international sanctions, the relationship
between
the US and Chinese governments thawed very
quickly.
By May 1990, the US had renewed
China’s Most Favored Nation trading status.
In November 1991,
Secretary of State James Baker visited China.
Human Rights were not big on the list of discussion
topics.
And then in 1992,
just three years after the bloody, bloody
massacre,
Chinese Premier Li Peng visited the US
and relations were basically restored.
And in 1994, Bush met Jiang Zemin.
Jiang was the next leader of China.
Also, as it eventually turned out,
Jiang was the next mass murderer of China—
but that’s another episode.
Now I don’t want to give you the impression
Bush’s actions towards China were all bad.
Bush was largely responsible
for the Chinese Student Protection Act of
1992.
It began as an executive order he signed in
1990,
and essentially granted asylum for Chinese
students
in the United States after the Tiananmen Square
massacre.
In fact, the reason we have Shelley on our
team
is because her parents got that.
But even after Bush’s presidency ended in
1993,
he was still pretty China focused.
Here he is in 2002 again with everyone’s
least favorite battletoad,
Jiang Zemin.
This was just three years after Jiang began
the bloody purge against Falun Gong practitioners,
a purge that’s killed way more people than
in Tiananmen Square.
Then in 2008, Bush visited Beijing for the
Olympics.
He said, “China was an important ‘friend’
and ‘supporter’ of the US.”
This was after the Communist Party had just
forcibly evicted
one and a half million people for the Games.
But, I mean if we keep engaging with the Communist
Party,
sooner or later they’ll have to get better!
That was also the same year Bush released
his China diaries.
In the forward he summed up his views of China:
“I love the Chinese people.
One of my dreams for our world is that
these two powerful giants will continue working
toward
a full partnership and friendship
that will bring peace and prosperity to people
everywhere.”
That’s a nice sentiment.
It’s just too bad that,
like many US politicians,
Bush confused supporting the Chinese people,
with supporting the Chinese Communist Party.
So what do you think about the China legacy
left behind by George HW Bush?
Leave your comments below.
And before we wrap up, now is the time
when I answer a question from a fan
who supports China Uncensored
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
Joakim Idland asks,
“Are there other Chinese politicians
that have been connected to other cartoon
characters
other than Winnie the Pooh aka Xi Jinping?
Ah, yes.
For those of you not in the know,
Chinese leader Xi Jinping has been compared
to Winnie the Pooh.
And after this meeting with president Obama,
Chinese netizens began to notice some more
striking similarities.
And when Xi Jinping became president for life,
it happened again.
It became so much of a meme,
Winnie the Pooh has been occasionally banned
in China.
As for other Chinese officials,
while this is not a cartoon character, Jiang
Zemin,
in general, looks like a toad.
And that led to this giant inflatable toad
being censored.
Which is ridiculous.
The giant inflatable toad is much better looking.
Here at China Uncensored,
we’ve noticed a few more Chinese officials
who look like cartoons.
Like the perpetually sad Vice President Wang
Qishan
who looks like Eeyore.
And Zhou Yongkang,
who is a human version of the Thwomp
from Super Mario Brothers.
Chinese authorities are fully aware of
all the ways people make fun of them,
and they’re extremely sensitive.
And that’s why you probably won’t be seeing
Winnie the Pooh
at the Shanghai Disneyland.
Oh bother.
Thanks for you question.
And if you’d like to support China Uncensored,
and get a shot at having your questions answered,
consider supporting the show with a dollar
or more per episode
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
Link is below or on the endscreen.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.