On this episode of China Uncensored:
Are Chinese tourists invading South Korea?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I'm your host Chris Chappell.
Lunar New Year.
A time for Chinese citizens to celebrate family.
And China's transit system.
But there's a new New Year's tradition among
Chinese citizens with money.
Matt Gnaizda has more.
Chinese New Year.
For China's growing middle and upper class,
it's a two week break from the monotony of
white collar office jobs.
And there's a growing trend among these Chinese
to
not be in China.
One of the hottest new tourist destinations
this time of year
is South Korea.
And why are Chinese so fond of South Korea?
Why do you like Korea?
Korea...
I don’t especially like Korea.
The shopping is convenient,
but the food takes some getting used to.
I like this country.
It’s very civilized.
Why do you like it?
The culture attracted me.
People are very polite.
What else?
The shopping is pretty good.
The beauty products and makeup are really
good.
So, polite shopping is a huge draw.
But while everyone I talked to was nice,
Chinese tourists overall
don't exactly have a stellar reputation.
Last year, this video posted by a Thai celebrity
visiting South Korea went viral.
Everyone was lining fine
Then the Chinese got here
And LOOK
They don't know what
it means to have manner,
to form line, or to have curtesy! None!
Whether it's clumping in line,
spitting on the floor,
or urinating in public,
it's gotten so bad
that the Chinese government even published
a handbook
for Chinese tourists traveling abroad.
I mean look at these Chinese people at the
presidential palace in Seoul.
They…
Well, they seem pretty polite, actually.
But anyway, to get the real scoop, I decided
to ask some Koreans.
How is Chinese people's behavior when they're
here?
I think that problem will be
smaller and smaller,
day by day.
Most people's behavior is
very good and kind.
But I mean,
do they really want so many Chinese visitors?
I think Chinese tourists coming to Korea is
very, very good for Korean economic system.
They spend more money in Korea,
so it can be a help for the Korean economy.
I'm looking forward to them—
more Chinese tourists coming to Korea.
Wow.
These Koreans are the nicest, politest people.
Let’s ask an American instead.
I don't like to judge too much on people
until I've actually experienced them,
and talked with them, but.
Can't you just stereotype everyone together?
You can, but
a lot of them only applies
to a few people of that race.
This is getting ridiculous!
You're causing me a problem here.
Don't edit my words in bad ways!
You mean, like this?
I don't...like...tourists from China...
They...are...not...considerate in public places.
I would never do something like that.
But if Chinese tourists are not that bad after
all,
does that mean they’re the best tourists
in South Korea?
So which are the best tourists?
Best tourists?
Say Americans.
Americans.
And there you go.
Alright, thanks very much.
This is Matt Gnaizda, reporting from Seoul.