On this episode of China Uncensored:
The Chinese military has landed this bomber
plane
in the South China Sea.
And China’s neighbors are not happy.
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
The South China Sea.
More than 5 trillion dollars worth of trade
flows through here each year.
And underneath,
there’s an estimated 11 billion barrels
of oil to tap.
No wonder it’s a powder keg—
or oil barrel—
of competing territorial claims.
But not to worry,
because the People’s Liberation Army Air
Force
has just landed one of its state-of-the-art
nuclear-capable long-range bombers
on a disputed island deep in the South China
Sea.
China’s Ministry of Defense said they were
practicing
simulated air attacks.
Because practice makes perfect.
And with the move,
“Beijing’s annexation of the South China
Sea
appears complete,”
without firing a single shot.
At least according to News.com.au,
which is owned by News Corp.
They also say the move is
a “clear signal that Beijing considers
its ownership of the contested waterways
and illegally-reclaimed islands
complete and uncontested”.
Although I have to say...uncontested?
A lot of countries are still contesting
the Chinese regime’s claims.
Just not very effectively.
Anyway, last Friday the Chinese air force
released
this video of its newest heavy bomber
landing and taking off from Woody Island.
Woody Island is one of the natural islands
that make up the Paracel island chain.
It’s also... contested.
Both Taiwan and Vietnam lay claim to it,
but clearly,
it’s occupied and militarized
by the People’s Republic of China.
Openly turning Woody into a military outpost
for long-range bombers is an important step
in the Chinese Communist Party’s takeover
of the South China Sea.
See this nine-dash line?
The Communist Party says everything inside
it
belongs to them.
An international arbitration court disagrees,
but the Communist Party can just ignore
a court decision it doesn’t like.
They’ve built artificial islands on coral
reefs
and tidal rocky outcrops,
then turned these islands
into weaponized fortresses.
It’s just like playing Fortnite.
Well, minus the monsters.
Wait a second...I know what’s going on.
The whole reason the Communist Party
is militarizing the South China Sea
is to stop giant monsters from invading China!
It makes sense.
As we know from this historical documentary,
giant monsters once tried to invade China
from across the Great Wall
during the Song Dynasty.
True story.
But while giant monsters may be a serious
threat,
Xi Jinping had actually promised in 2015
that China would not militarize the islands.
But you can’t see his hands!
His fingers are definitely crossed.
Now, three years later,
the only thing missing from the Chinese military’s
total domination of the South China Sea,
in the words of US Admiral Philip Davidson,
is “deployed forces.”
But that may be approaching soon.
The Chinese military deployed their first
missiles
a few weeks ago in the South China Sea.
And now these warplanes on Woody Island
change everything.
I guess Missiles for Peace was so successful,
they decided to start Bombers for Peace too.
Don’t worry,
I’m sure they’re just defensive bombers.
But with facilities that can handle bomber
planes,
the Chinese military is now capable of challenging
any of its neighbors in the region.
And “any forces deployed to the islands
would easily overwhelm the military forces
of any other South China Sea-claimants.”
And the capability to launch long-range
military operations from Woody Island
means China’s military reach extends
way beyond the nine dash line.
How far?
China’s less advanced combat bombers
can reach all five Philippine military bases
where the US military has troops and facilities.
And China’s new top-of-the-line H-6K bomber
that just landed on Woody Island
has a range of more than 2,000 miles.
So the Chinese military now has most of Southeast
Asia
within combat flight range.
Defensive combat flight range, obviously.
And that’s just the beginning,
according to the Asia Maritime Transparency
Initiative.
They say the military base on Woody Island
is a blueprint for other land formations further
south.
In particular,
the islands China built on top of three contested
reefs:
the Subi Reef, Mischief Reef, and Fiery Cross
Reefs,
part of the Spratly Island archipelago.
Satellite images of the reefs
already show airfields and hangers
that “can accommodate bombers like the H-6
series.”
And from there,
China’s combat planes could potentially
reach
northern Australia and the US island of Guam.
That’s why the White House has some thoughts
about this.
“We’re well aware of China’s militarization
of the South China Sea.
We’ve raised concerns directly with the
Chinese about this.
And there will be near-term and long-term
consequences.”
But the “Chinese don’t fear they are provoking
a crisis,"
says Bonnie Glaser, director of the China
Power Project
at the Center for Strategic and International
Studies in Washington...
...because the US has already lost
its “capability to shape events” in the
South China Sea.
Since obviously we don’t want to have
a full-on war with China...
Right?
There’s just one hope, says Admiral Davidson:
Recovering a technological advantage.
“Hypersonic and directed energy weapons,
resilient space, cyber and network-capabilities,”
he says, “will be crucial to our ability
to fight and win.”
So if there’s a war,
it will be fought with hypersonic and energy
weapons.
Welcome to our dystopian future.
And until then,
the Chinese military will probably continue
to build up its own capacity.
And on that happy note,
it’s time for a question from one of our
fans
who supports China Uncensored
through our Patreon website.
Jonathan Swanberg asks:
“How afraid should you/we be
that China is focusing on creating AI
without the necessary oversight?
Like are we talking terminator level scared?”
Oh Jonathan,
we should be Terminator 2 level scared.
Because China doesn’t approach science
in the way most countries around the world
do.
Take the United States for example.
The public has a say.
There’s debate online and in the media.
That means moral considerations are taken
into account.
The Communist Party doesn’t work that way.
It doesn’t have to answer to anyone.
And what it does for the sake of short term
control
could have long term consequences.
Elon Musk has made the point that
any evil dictator will eventually die.
But AI could create an immortal dictator.
So, in the Communist Party’s rush to create
AI,
we may all end up slaves to the machines.
And really, would that be so bad?
Remember, you can leave your questions for
me, too.
Support China Uncensored with a dollar more
per episode
and join our exclusive 50-Cent Army.
And what do you think about
the Chinese military’s expansion in the
South China Sea
and its increasing global reach?
Leave your comments below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Thanks for watching.
China Uncensored is supported mainly through
contributions from viewers like you.
Without our viewer support,
we’d have to stop the show.
So click this orange button
and visit Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
You can contribute a dollar or more per episode.
You can also set a monthly limit if you need.
When you join,
we’ll give you some cool perks—
and you’ll be making a big difference for
us.