On this episode of China Uncensored,
China is years ahead of America.
And I don't mean its glistening skyscrapers
or high-speed rails.
I mean its plan to stop crime before it happens.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I'm your host, Chris Chappell.
Good news everyone!
In a world laboring under the shadow of terrorism,
China has the answer.
And don't worry, this is definitely not an
idea torn from the pages
of some Philip K. Dick dystopian sci-fi story.
To understand it,
let's take a look at a movie based on
a Philip K. Dick dystopian sci-fi story.
“Mr. Marks, by mandate of the District of
Columbia Precrime Division,
I'm placing you under arrest for the future
murder of Sarah Marks.”
In the movie Minority Report,
crime is stopped before it happens,
because it's predicted by three "precogs."
This is called "precrime."
"Precrime: it works.
It works.
"Precrime: it works!
On Tuesday, April 22,
vote yes on the national precrime initiative."
Obviously that's science fiction,
and not what's happening in China.
China wouldn't let people vote.
Seriously, they are planning to create precrime,
though.
China is already a surveillance state.
The Communist Party monitors every aspect
of every citizen's life.
Here's China Uncensored Precrime expert Harold
Finch on how it works.
“The government gave itself the power to
read every email,
listen to every cell phone,
but they needed something to sort through
it all,
something that could pick the terrorists out
of the general population before they could
act.”
Oh wait, sorry,
that's from the fictional TV drama Person
of Interest.
My mistake.
I'm really having a hard time separating
fictional plot devices from Communist Party
policy.
So you see, the Chinese government can already
gain access
to anyone's bank accounts and tap their phones.
They have an army of Internet watchdogs that
dog your every click.
They monitor people's online activity
and give them a score on their "trustworthiness"—
the "social credit" system.
Then there's the massive nationwide network
of surveillance cameras China calls Skynet.
Wait, that can't be right.
Skynet was the name of the AI computer network
in the Terminator movies—
the one that wiped out humanity.
What's that Shelley?
Ok, China is actually calling it Skynet.
Wow.
I think it might be time to cancel the Communist
Party's Netflix subscription.
Anyway, China is collecting huge amounts of
information on its citizens.
But they also need to sort through it
and figure out how to use it to prevent crime.
So can they?
Well, that's where the China Electronics Technology
comes in.
They're one of China's largest state-owned
defense contractors.
They've been given the job to, as Bloomberg
puts it,
“Develop software to collate data on jobs,
hobbies, consumption habits, and other
behavior of ordinary citizens to predict
terrorist acts before they occur.”
Is this even possible?
Well, a recent research paper by mathematicians
at
University College London suggests that with
enough data,
patterns of behavior emerge that you can use
to predict certain terrorist acts.
So anyone who engages in suspicious or dangerous
behavior,
such as using a VPN to jump the Great Firewall
of China,
and look up information on known terrorist
ringleader
the Dalai Lama,
might find themselves "invited to tea" with
authorities.
Did I mention is this is for fighting terrorism,
and absolutely not for clamping down on dissent?
The government would definitely not use it
to, say,
predict anti-government protests,
and send in the police before they begin.
Because China's constitution guarantees freedom
of
speech, and the press, and assembly.
Now a lot about this precrime program remains
unknown to the outside world,
and to the Chinese people—
including when it will be put in effect.
And while other countries are trying to create
similar programs,
China's program is likely to be more successful.
According to their definition of success,
at least.
That's because the Party doesn't have to worry
about pesky things like
rule of law, or public approval,
or people protesting massive surveillance.
And with so much data, it might actually be
possible
to have something that approaches pre-crime.
So what do you think about China's new system?
Leave your comments below.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell. See you next
time.
"Chris Chappell, you are under arrest for
the future subversion of state power!"
"Future subversion?"