Fighting evil by moonlight
Winning love by daylight
Never running from a real fight
Xi is the one named Sailor Moon!
Welcome back to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
China celebrated its third ever Space Day
on April 24.
And what better way to celebrate than with
this video
from The China National Space Administration.
It shows the history of the Chinese Communist
Party’s space program.
But more importantly,
it reveals the Party’s of plans for a moon
base!
...and potentially some kind of Earth destroying
laser.
OK, I’m not sure about that last one.
Anyway, there’s an ancient legend
about a Chinese princess named Chang’e
who lives on the moon in a lunar palace.
Until the evil Queen Beryl used the power
of the Negaforce
to destroy the Silver Millennium and kill
the moon princess,
who reincarnated on Earth...
What’s that, Shelley?
Yes, I know that’s the wrong moon princess.
But Sailor Moon is way more fun.
The point is, the Chinese Communist Party
is rebuilding
China’s ancient moon kingdom.
“China’s dream of residing in a lunar
palace
will soon become a reality.”
Although their “palace” might not be so
glamorous.
Back in July, they locked 4 students in a
capsule
similar to the one they plan to build on the
Moon.
“Cultivating plants using seeds and fertilizer
made from their own poop.”
That is less fun than astronaut ice cream.
Don’t worry.
The Chinese Communist Party
is not launching students to the moon
to survive off their own poop.
Matt Damon already did that on Mars.
No, the Communist Party’s plan is to send
containers of flower seeds and silkworm larva
in containers like this on a December trip
to the dark side of the moon.
But surely there’s no dark side
to China’s moon ambitions.
Except...well...
You know how the United States space program,
NASA,
is a civilian organization?
Well, China’s space program is a branch
of the Communist Party’s People’s Liberation
Army.
So China’s moonbase will actually be set
up
by the Chinese military.
That’s because to the Chinese Communist
Party,
space is the final frontier...
of war.
I’m not making this up.
That’s according to this report to the US
government.
Chinese military analysts view space
as the “ultimate high ground,”
and claim that “space warfare is inevitable.”
And for the Chinese military,
“seizing the initiative is to achieve space
supremacy.”
The report warns that the Chinese regime
is developing capabilities that “could also
be used
to attack U.S. bases and the bases of its
allies in Asia
as well as targets within the 50 states.”
Yeah, turns out, that’s no moon.
That’s a battle station.
The moon is a key part of China’s long-term
space warfare strategy.
Richard Fisher, senior fellow
with the International Assessment and Strategy
Center,
says “China wants to control the Earth–Moon
system.
By doing so, it can impose a toll on
the space economy ambitions of the West.”
A key part of that is helium-3.
And no, that’s not what Xi Jinping will
inhale
to sound like Sailor Moon.
Helium-3 is a key fuel for nuclear fusion
energy,
an almost unlimited source of non-polluting
energy.
And while there’s basically none of it on
Earth,
“Some estimates suggest there are at least
1.1 million metric tons of helium-3
on the lunar surface,
enough to power human energy needs
for up to 10,000 years.”
And there’s yet another reason
why the Chinese Communist Party
wants to set up shop on the moon.
According the legend,
the moon has already been Chinese territory
since ancient times.
Because Moon Princess.
But now, the Communist Party is looking put
that claim
on more solid footing.
According to a 1967 UN Treaty signed by over
100 countries,
including China,
no one is allowed to own the moon.
But the Chinese Communist Party
still wants a slice of the moon pie—
the same way they’ve been carving out
slices of the South China Sea,
and setting up military bases there,
even though the rest of the world
has been telling them they’re not allowed
to.
And for the Party,
“Sending a spacecraft to the Moon...
may provide a compelling case for recognition
if the Moon were ever to be carved up
into zones of research and economic development.”
So flowers and silkworms on the moon count
as territorial claims, right?
Of course, China isn’t the only country
going to the Moon.
And who is this mysterious rival?
Why, it’s US President Donald Trump!
And he wants to join Xi on the moon.
In the 2019 budget for NASA,
the president’s Space Policy Directive is
that
“the United States will lead the return
of humans to the Moon.”
It puts moon funding above even another space
station.
And Trump is the first president to ever
seriously talk about putting US troops in
space.
“My new national strategy for space recognizes
that space is a warfighting domain,
just like the land, air, and sea.
We may even have a Space Force.”
Make Space Great again.
Not that it ever wasn’t.
I assume Trump is also going to build a space
wall
to keep out those illegal aliens.
So the US is competing with a Communist superpower
to build rival moon bases.
The sixties are back, baby.
Hopefully they don’t bring back the constant
fear
of impending nuclear annihilation.
But in terms of this new space race,
the US is already winning...
at least when it comes to spending.
The US spends about 21 billion dollars a year
on NASA,
while China only spends 3 billion on its space
program.
Though the Chinese Communist Party
has gotten some hits in.
They were responsible for hacking
“NASA climate satellites in 2007 and 2008
but no permanent damage was reported”.
The thing is, space is already a part of modern
warfare.
GPS for soldiers and missiles, communications,
wireless Internet, even a lot of spying—
that all relies on satellites in space.
Destroy those satellites and you can cripple
a much larger army.
That’s something the Chinese regime understands.
It’s been decades since the the last space
race,
so a lot of this moonbase stuff
sounds more like science fiction.
But it might not be as far away as we think.
And this new space race
could make for some strange bedfellows.
So what do you think of China’s moon plans?
And will Tuxedo Trump and Sailor Xi
ever get over their differences?
Leave your fan fiction below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
You know what requires funding besides secret moon bases?
China Uncensored.
Thanks to YouTube demonetization,
we rely on support from viewers like you
to fund our operations.
If you'd like to learn how you can support the show,
Visit patreon.com/chinauncensored.