The Chinese economy is hurting badly
What does this mean for the rest of the world?
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I'm Chris Chappell.
Joining me today at the Oslo Freedom Forum
in New York
is economist and China expert,
Christopher Balding.
He taught in China for nine years, and now,
he's an associate professor at the Fulbright
University,
Vietnam in Ho Chi Minh City.
Thanks for joining.
Thanks for having me, Chris.
So, China just posted GDP figures for its
third quarter
and it's the lowest it's been in 27 years.
What does it mean that the official figures
are that low?
If the official figures are that low,
it means the reality is that much worse.
I think most economists, in reality,
are looking at a GDP growth figure, probably
half that.
Some are speculating it's even worse than
that.
Well, so what does that mean?
That basically means that China is growing
much slower
and we're actually seeing this across a range
of activities.
If you look at the consumer sector,
which China is touting as the great growth
hope,
actually we're seeing,
in a lot of areas of the consumer sector,
declining growth.
Car sales are down significantly,
phones are down significantly-
Are these Chinese-made cars and phones,
or imports of Ford and iPhone.
So, in the automotive sector,
China actually makes most of its own cars.
It imports relatively small amounts,
primarily of luxury vehicles,
but China actually produces
and consumes most of its own vehicles.
And so, with the depth of decline that we're
seeing
in consumer durables like washers and dryers,
refrigerators, air conditioners, cell phones,
automobiles,
and even the food staple, pork,
it's very, very difficult to see how, for
instance,
the consumer sector is growing strong enough
to drive
the Chinese economy towards a 6% real GDP
growth figure.
So, are these lower GDP numbers,
whatever they may actually be,
an effect of the trade war?
No, these are actually an impact from, really,
Chinese domestic policy over the years.
A couple of things that we're seeing, for
instance,
are really high debt figures in households
and corporate sector
are really restraining a lot of purchases
that people might be making.
Again, if we focus on the consumer sector,
Chinese households now actually have more
debt
than most developed countries like the United
States and Japan,
things like that, when compared against household
income numbers.
And, this is also impacting the corporate
sector.
We're seeing a very restrained investment
growth in China because,
even though credit is being pushed,
there's been so much previous investment of
things that have been built,
and now, there's over capacity in a lot of
industries,
in real estate, in other sectors.
And so, people are quite fearful to actually
go out
and invest if they don't believe it's a profitable
project.
So, this is not so much an effect
of anything the Trump administration is doing
as much as it is systemic problems with how
the Chinese communist party has been managing
the economy.
That's absolutely correct.
Probably the most that you could say about
the Trump impact,
if you will,
is that it would be the straw that breaks
the camel's back.
It's additional stress. It's absolutely not
the driver.
And again, just more sense and perspective
of what we're dealing with,
you'll frequently hear that the trade war
is driving this global slowdown in growth
or in trade.
And, actually, that's not correct because
this slowdown in growth,
slowdown in trade, is centered in China.
If we look at Chinese trade patterns
with all of its partners,
everywhere from Germany to Australia, Indonesia,
Thailand,
so we're looking, really, to a very broad
range of countries.
Trade with those countries is down across
the board,
and this isn't just inputs that might go into
an iPhone
that end up in the United States.
These are products that are going to end up
in China.
Iron ore exports from Australia to China are
very slow.
High quality machinery exports
from Japan and Germany to China are very slow.
So, we're not just looking at a narrow range
of goods
where there's a trade slowdown with China
and its partners,
but really, across the board,
across a wide, wide range of countries.
So, because of the systemic problems within
China
that's creating a slowdown in their economy,
which is creating a global economic slowdown.
Is that right?
I think that's much more accurate.
If you look at the countries that are really
experiencing some economic pressures, if you
will,
Germany being a good example.
They've taken a significant drop in their
exports to China
and that's having a, a significant impact
on the German economy.
That's not from the trade war.
Germany does not export a lot of products
to China that go through China,
get processed, and end up in the United States.
Germany is exporting a lot of high quality
chemicals,
precision machinery, luxury automobiles, things
like that.
I love German chemicals, myself.
German chemicals are some of the best.
Very different from Burmese chemicals, but-
Low quality Burmese chemicals.
And so, we see this spillover that this
is impacting a lot of countries from all over
Asia
and all over Europe.
So, if the Chinese economy continues to slow
down,
what will that mean for the global economy?
I think it's going to mean that
there's going to be a sustained global slowdown
as well.
I'm not necessarily of the opinion
that you're looking at a global recession
in the classical sense.
Typically speaking, global growth recession
is considered if growth drops beneath, say,
two to 3%.
I think it is possible that you
will see global growth drop beneath two to
3%,
which some might consider a global recession,
but we can expect that to, I think,
continue for the next couple of years, for
sure.
There's been a lot of talk about
decoupling the U S economy from China.
Would that protect the US economy
if there is a Chinese economic crash?
Well, one of the things that you've seen
go on throughout this trade war
is that actually US trade numbers, in aggregate,
have continued to grow at a relatively steady
pace.
There really hasn't been much of a change.
And so, everybody is saying,
"Well, wait a minute.
Why are we seeing trade numbers into the United
States grow,
essentially, on trend?"
Well, the reason is very simple.
Basically, the increase in exports from countries
like Mexico,
Vietnam, Thailand, places like that,
is being offset by the decline in exports
from China.
So, basically all we're seeing is,
these Chinese exports move to other countries,
and so, basically, we can expect this process
to continue for the next few years.
Just this week it was announced that, actually,
Samsung has moved all of its production out
of China.
And so, it's very big in Vietnam.
They've been moving into India.
Apple has supposedly set up manufacturing
in India.
And so, basically, we can expect this decoupling
to continue for the next few years, for sure.
So, over the years, many companies
have really tried to get access to the China
market,
but it seems like these risks have been known
for a long time.
Why did they make such a push to get into
the China market?
There was always this mythical,
if we can just sell one t-shirt to each person
in China,
that's a billion t-shirts in sales.
So, whether it was t-shirts,
or financial services or automobiles,
that was the focus.
And, for a long time I think people,
companies, were willing to make those trade
offs
because they were making a lot of money.
They were entering a semi-protected market.
They were working with SOEs most of the time,
investments of any significant size.
SOEs being State-Owned Enterprises.
State-Owned Enterprises.
And so, these companies were making a lot
of money.
As things have changed for multiple reasons,
the growth isn't what it is,
there's surplus capacity under the Xi administration.
The state has taken a much more central role
in everything.
I think companies have really begun to question
the trade-offs
that they have to make to be in the Chinese
market.
And so, is that a result of them changing
or the changing situation in China
with the economic downturn?
I think it's a function of both.
You know, if you had confidence in the economy,
you could say, "Okay, well there's a downturn
right now.
If you start layering on the factors of,
"Oh, well, you know now I have to hire
some communist party bureaucrat
just to hang out in my company all day.
Now if I know that they're going to be stealing
from me,
and now I know that I'm still going to be
asked for bribes,
and all of these other things.",
tariffs, concern about Chinese politics,
it definitely, in aggregate, pushes companies
to leave.
We don't see, historically, in any country,
we don't see companies choose to locate in
a country,
or move to another country, for any one reason,
whether it's a tax break or politics, whatever
it is.
It doesn't happen for one reason.
And so, companies moving is likely a reflection
on their overall confidence in China.
So, the Chinese communist party
has a lot of control over the economy.
That's the whole point of a state-led economy.
What do you think the next thing they're going
to do
to tackle this falling economy?
So, the most recent rumors or news reports,
take them for what they are, involve, essentially,
more of the same.
They're going to increase local government
bond quotas,
that they're going to push investment.
It will be interesting to see,
they've made some concessions about opening
up markets
to foreign financial service providers.
It will be very interesting to see because,
as in China,
they can change the rules,
and nothing changes at the end of the day.
So, it will be very interesting to see how
that plays out.
I think what it, what is notable is, to me,
as I look at these changes, and what I see
are,
first of all, more of the same,
like increasing the local government bond
issuance quota.
That's basically just allowing local governments
to issue more debt this year.
We're in October and they've already exceeded
the quota for the year,
and so, they're going to allow them to issue
more.
So, it seems like part of it is more of the
same,
which is not a good recipe.
And, I think what is concerning is,
is that they're still trying
to fiddle around the edges as Rome burns,
for lack of a better term.
What do you mean by that?
There are very large, systemic,
fundamental problems with the Chinese economy
and they're just not dealing with them.
And so, increasing the local government bond
quota for the year
is going to put a bandaid over a gunshot wound.
It's not going to fundamentally address the
problem.
And, I think that is the problem
they just still don't want to face up to.
Well, you said they're doing more of the same.
They've been doing this for years,
and people have been saying the Chinese economy
is going to collapse for more than a decade
now,
but more of the same has kept the economy
working.
So, will this work?
Well, it depends on what you mean by work.
I think one of the things is in...
I have a good friend that gave me this theory,
which I've been increasingly leaning in this
direction,
is that as long as they continue increasing
the money supply,
debt, continue building things,
even if nobody necessarily lives in those
buildings, e
ven if those office spaces aren't occupied,
things like that.
What their goal is they need to keep growth
going.
Well, to prevent any real risk to their goal
of build,
build, build, even if nobody's going to live
there,
they have to, basically, essentially,
begin closing themselves off more and more,
because that is going to lower the risk of
debt problems,
that's going to lower the risk of currency
problems. Okay?
And, I think that's what we're seeing
within the Chinese economy right now.
That is their growth model.
They have to continue doing that.
And, I think we're going to continue to see
a further closed-off China from the rest of
the world.
And so, if the Chinese economy does collapse,
what does that mean for the Chinese communist
party?
Well, I've always been of the opinion
that I don't like to talk about a Chinese
collapse
or financial crisis, for multiple reasons,
but I think one of the most fundamentalist
as to why I don't like that type of terminology
is that the Chinese communist party,
and to answer your question, the Chinese communist
party
has a very fundamental interest in making
sure that
there is never a financial crisis
or significant economic problem.
Their entire governance campaign slogan is
on economic management.
"We will give you a better standard of living,
and you have to accept these trade-offs."
And so, if there ever is a serious economic
problem,
it's probably not going to end well for the
CCP.
And so, this tells us,
and I think this fits pretty closely with
what we see empirically,
is that there is no bailout too big. Okay?
There is no check that they will not write
to say,
"We'll just sweep this under the rug some
way,
well we're merge it into another company.
We will set up a bad bank to buy out these
assets.",
something like that,
"So that we can keep the plate spinning.
So that we can keep it going."
And so, that tells us, the analogy that I've
heard
is that they will be very happy to be, essentially,
the way I would describe it is,
North Korea with a higher level of income.
And, I think that seems to be more
and more the way that the world is moving.
What happens to the rest of the world
if China can't make a bigger bailout.
Well, it depends on which it is.
If it's within China, the world will probably
say,
"That's your problem."
Okay? If it's a steel company in a Heilongjiang,
the rest of the world's probably going to
say,
"Okay. Hey, have fun with that." Okay?
The real risk, and I think you are seeing
real pressure in this now,
is if there is some type of US dollar-denominated
bond issuance
that they cannot repay for some reason,
and especially if it's some type of local
government,
because what that would do is that would cause
a lot of investors,
especially those that don't pay a lot of attention
to China,
they think of local government as almost sovereign-level
debt.
And so, if some of these companies started
being unable to replay their US dollar liabilities,
all of a sudden you have bankers that would
say,
"Well, wait a minute,
we're not going to buy those US dollar-denominated
Chinese bonds."
All of a sudden, there's a lot of US dollar
tightness.
All of a sudden, they're going to have trouble
buying imports.
All of a sudden, it becomes a much bigger
problem very quickly.
And, at that point, the world would take notice
very rapidly,
and it would put a lot of risk on the CCP.
Well, so what would that mean for your average
American?
It depends. So, with the flows that we've
seen
into a firm like US pension funds into bond
indexes,
that's specifically by Chinese debt, and in
US dollars,
it could mean that they would see
some type of drop to their pension or 401k.
That's a distinct possibility.
Generally speaking,
because it would probably be chaos in the
markets,
for lack of a better term.
In reality, the amount of exports to China
as a part of total GDP
are not large for the United States.
So, it probably would, would not have as significant
an impact
as other potential major financial and economic
events.
Well, thanks for joining me.
That was absolutely fascinating.
Thank you very much for having me, Chris.
Appreciate it.