On this episode of China Uncensored,
Chinese rockets are being launched in America!
A disease is affecting the Chinese military.
And finally, let the trade wars begin!
This is China Uncensored
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
I hope all the viewers in the US had a happy
Fourth of July
celebrating our Independence Day.
Of course, for viewers outside of America,
I hope you also had a...happy...Wednesday?
This year, Americans spent almost a billion
dollars
on Fourth of July fireworks.
Nothing like celebrating your nation’s freedom
by blowing things up.
And China helps us do it.
“About 70 percent of the professional display
fireworks
are manufactured in China."
And "Ninety-nine percent of the backyard consumer
fireworks
come directly from China.”
But while Chinese fireworks may be
launching in some parts of America,
there won’t be much of that from the Chinese
Communist Party’s
People’s Liberation Army.
At least according to the PLA Daily,
the official paper of the People’s Liberation
Army.
“China’s People’s Liberation Army
is ridden with ‘peace disease.’”
The problem is China hasn’t had had a war
since that one
with Vietnam in the 1970s.
And honestly,
it wasn’t even a very good one.
I know, you’re worried about the combat
readiness
of the Communist Party’s military.
Well don’t be.
Chinese leader Xi Jinping decided the PLA
will be a world class military...
by 2050.
Yes, by the time I’m a grandpa, and Xi Jinping
is...
still President of China.
But it turns out, Xi Jinping’s military
reforms
are less about creating a modern fighting
army,
and more about his own personal war
against his political opponents.
And that’s a war that’s very active right
now.
According to the PLA Daily,
over the past five years,
“At least 13,000 military officers involved
in corruption
have been punished.”
The anti-corruption campaign has been Xi’s
way
of purging powerful figures in the military
and making the PLA more loyal to Xi.
Many high ranking officers purged,
like Guo Boxiong and Xu Caihou,
were tied to Xi’s main nemesis,
the Guiana Shield Leaf Toad.
I’m sorry, I mean Jiang Zemin.
The resemblance is uncanny.
These purged officers were what Xi called
“the big tigers.”
But now Xi’s focus has shifted from purging
to what he calls “prohibiting omissions.”
According to retired PLA colonel Yue Gang,
“Apart from corruption,
job omission is the next key symptom of ‘peace
disease’
in the Chinese military that should be cured.”
Job omission is when Xi Jinping’s political
enemies
try to subvert him by...literally doing nothing.
That means instead of conducting normal training
drills,
they...don’t.
And instead, they just fake the training data.
In other words, the troops aren’t actually
training.
Hence, they have peace disease.
But you know, I think it’s going to be okay.
At least for anyone who goes to war with China.
Speaking of war...trade war!
Today the US and China tariffs go into effect.
Too bad the PLA can’t fight the trade war.
Then we’d definitely win.
We’ll have more on this story as it develops.
Three more American have been evacuated from
China
following mysterious health problems.
Several US employees tied to the embassy or
consulates in China
have been sickened after hearing a mysterious
sound.
There are fears it may be a sonic weapon.
Or as we mentioned before, really inept spying.
But a sonic weapon might not be the only new
experimental weapon in the hands of the PLA.
No, this isn’t the world’s most terrifying
flashlight.
It’s an experimental machine gun laser.
This image was released last month by the
Chengdu Hengan Police Equipment Manufacturing
Company.
It emits rapid pulses.
But its makers claim it doesn’t do
anything more than disorient people.
So basically it’s a giant strobelight.
I hear it also plays EDM.
China is actually developing
a wide range of experimental laser weapons.
Here’s another one: the ZKZM-500.
Official documents say it’s “non-lethal.”
But they also say it can produce
pain beyond endurance,
and “cause the ‘instant carbonization’
of human skin and tissues.”
So...not actually non-lethal.
Also, it’s also only 7 pounds,
has a range of half a mile,
makes no sound,
and its beam is invisible.
One researcher on the project said,
“Nobody will know where the attack came
from.
It will look like an
accident.”
Wow, this dissident spontaneously carbonized!
Must've been an accident!
Glad that’s in the hands of the world’s
most trustworthy police.
The good news is,
since this weapon is so far beyond
anything remotely out there,
some experts think the researchers
may have just been telling a tall tale.
So what do you think of the People’s Liberation
Army’s
peaceful disease and laser weapons?
Leave your comments below.
And before we wrap up,
it’s that time when I answer questions
from fans who support China Uncensored
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
Dafydd Nicholas asks
“Why does the Chinese population have less
criticism
of central government control than westerners
do?”
Well you see Dafydd,
Chinese people simply aren’t ready for democracy.
I mean, yes Chinese people in Hong Kong and
Taiwan
have been successfully electing their leaders
for decades,
but Mainland Chinese people
simply need the Chinese Communist Party.
The Communist Party assures us of this.
That’s why even though there are some
village-level elections in Mainland China,
the candidates have to be handpicked by the
Party.
Otherwise people would get confused.
That’s why you don’t hear much criticism
from the Chinese population
about the control the Communist Party has.
The kind of control that lets the Party dictate
what you watch on tv,
if you reincarnate...
Even when you die!
“Furthermore, there's a must follow order.
No one can die inside of Beijing.
Local officials would be held accountable
if anyone did.”
The people clearly love the Communist Party,
which must be why you don’t hear them
publicly complaining.
Also in the event that someone does complain,
the Party has these guys.
Thanks for you question Dafydd.
And remember,
if you want a shot at having your question
answered
on the next episode,
consider supporting China Uncensored on Patreon.
China Uncensored is only possible
thanks to viewers like you.
Thanks for watching.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Hey, want the latest China news?
Subscribe to China Uncensored!
And turn that notification bell on to make
sure
you find out when new episodes are out.
We publish a brand new episode
every Monday, Wednesday, and Friday—
and sometimes Saturday.
So check back frequently
but I’ve heard from many fans
that YouTube won’t notify you,
even if you have notifications on.
I guess they don’t like China Uncensored
too much.