On this episode of China Uncensored,
it’s the 100-year anniversary
of the Bolshevik Revolution!
Let’s have a Party!
A Communist Party.
Leave your money at home, though.
Also your means of production.
Really, anything you want to keep.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
The relentless March of History carries on.
Until it reaches its inevitable end with Communism.
Or Democracy.
I’m pretty sure it’s one of those.
Or robot domination.
OK, it's definitely one of those three.
So...communism, as we all know,
has been a smashing success.
Well, maybe not in any of these places.
But at least in these places.
Yes, visit beautiful North Korea!
You’ll never leave.
Seriously, you might not be allowed to leave.
So communism:
a smashing success.
At least if you’re talking about smashing
stuff.
Anyway, 2017 marks the 100-year anniversary
of the Bolshevik Revolution,
the first Communist uprising
that didn’t immediately fail.
In fact, it led to the creation
of the Soviet Union,
which took a full 70 years to fail.
Nonetheless, there are still some
who wonder whether communism can
“rise like a phoenix from the ash heap of
history.”
In looking back at communist history,
this opinion article conveniently omits
the death and destruction that
happened under communism,
while wondering whether it can have a rebirth.
You know, not like the old gulag kind of communism.
But a new, cool communism.
I think that article came out the same week
the New York Times Style section featured
the “Return of the Mullet.”
So in honor of the momentous 100-year anniversary
of Russia’s Bolshevik Revolution,
let’s take a look back at some of the things
that the New York Times Opinion Section
so quickly glossed over—
with a brief history of the Communist Party.
Marx and the Origins of Communism
The ideas of communism
can be traced back a long time.
But communism as we know it today
began in 1848 with the Communist Manifesto,
written by Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels.
The original hipsters.
Just look at those beards.
Karl Marx saw history from the perspective
of a 19th century European man.
Namely, he didn’t like Mexicans.
Or Black people.
Or Jews.
Least woke hipster ever.
Anyway, in the Communist Manifesto,
Marx and Engels—
Um, this Marx and Engels—
laid out their ideas for a heaven on earth
where,
“Communism abolishes eternal truths,
it abolishes all religion,
and all morality.”
Abolishing morality!
Great!
Now we can all club baby seals again!
I mean, for the first time!
I mean, nooo…
The Paris Commune
Karl Marx thought it was only a matter of
time
before the workers of the world would unite,
tear down society,
and establish communism the world over.
And obviously hoist him and his ideas up
on a pedestal.
Uhh, an equal pedestal!
But nothing happened.
For 23 years.
The first uprising that even remotely resembled
what Marx and Engels were talking about
was the Paris Commune of 1871.
Marxists.org describes it as
“the first successful workers revolution.”
It lasted all of 10 weeks.
Even Firefly lasted longer than that!
But in those 10 weeks,
the communist insurrection was very productive.
They killed tons of people,
burned down a quarter of Paris,
and destroyed countless artistic treasures.
Though at least the smoke covered up
Paris's urine smell.
And like Firefly,
this brief season of communism
gained a small cult following.
The Soviet Union
One of communism's early fanboys
was the guy who started Communist Russia.
Lennon.
Um, this Lenin.
Although Back in the U.S.S.R. was a great
song.
In 1917,
the Russian Czar was overthrown
in the February Revolution.
Then eight months later,
that government was overthrown
by the Bolshevik Revolution,
led by Lenin.
This Lenin.
Lenin also began the Red Terror,
a campaign of mass murder and torture
that killed up to 1.5 million people.
What's that, Shelley?
What do you mean, I have to hurry it up?
Yes, I know this is a brief history.
Ok so Lenin killed a bunch of people and stole
their stuff.
Then he died.
Then Stalin took over.
He invented the gulag system of forced labor
camps,
killed like 20 million people,
and stole way more stuff.
Then he died.
Then these guys ran the country for a while.
Meanwhile, there was an arms race,
a space race,
and the golden age of James Bond movies.
After World War II,
the Soviets set up communist governments
in satellite states like Poland and East Germany.
I see, no time for Poland.
What about East Germany?
Too bad, the Stasi did some really weird stuff.
Ok, then the Soviets also helped start
a bunch of Marxist-Leninist revolutions
in Eastern Europe, Africa, and the Borat parts
of Asia.
Anyway, eventually the guy with the thing
on his face
came to power,
David Hasselhoff sang a song on the Berlin
Wall,
and the Soviet Union collapsed.
And when the Soviet Union fell,
so did the rest of the Soviet bloc.
Like Nirvana, after Kurt Cobain.
Moving on to Asia.
The People’s Republic of China
After sitting out most of World War II,
the Chinese Communist Party under Mao Zedong
was in a prime position to “liberate”
the war-ravaged country
from the ruling Nationalist Party.
Mao set out to prove how good of a communist
he was
by killing way more people than anyone, ever.
And taking their stuff.
And then he died.
After that,
the Chinese Communist Party realized
it should also fix China’s economy,
or what was left of it.
So it gradually added some capitalist things
back in.
And then the Communist Party reformed.
See?
According to state-run media,
the soldiers were just getting
moo shu pork delivery.
So the Communist Party ditched communism.
Well, just the economic parts.
They kept the heart of communism:
mass surveillance, labor camps, brainwashing,
corruption, and of course—
lots and lots of killing.
Even today in China,
you can be tortured to death for doing this.
Or this.
But hey,
why worry about that when your business
can make money there?!
Just don’t pray for profits.
Speaking of no profits…
The Democratic People’s Republic of Korea
Following World War II,
the Americans and the Soviets split Korea
along an arbitrary straight line.
But the North and South had some... disagreements.
They eventually resolved them by
turning the straight border into a squiggly
border.
5 million deaths later.
North Korea is officially run by the Workers'
Party,
but it's actually run by a bizarre cult
that surrounds the Kim family.
Like Kim Jong-Il.
According to his official biography,
he wrote six full operas that
“are better than any in the history of music.”
Unfortunately not available on iTunes.
North Korea is also the second happiest
country on Earth,
right behind China.
That’s according to North Korea,
which calls itself the
Democratic People’s Republic of Korea—
a country where men can choose between
10 officially approved hairstyles.
Ah, the world of choice.
Khmer Rouge
Next in our brief history: The Khmer Rouge.
Not a film by Baz Luhrmann.
The Khmer Rouge was the communist regime
that carried out the Cambodian Genocide
in the 1970s.
It did not have any good songs.
Pole pot—um, this Pol Pot —
is the guy who ran the Khmer Rouge.
And he was a huge fanboy of Mao Zedong.
“Oh my gosh, I just want to say,
I loved your Great Leap Forward.
It was killer.”
And Pol Pot followed Mao’s example.
In just four years,
his regime killed 2 million people.
That’s a quarter of Cambodia’s population.
He especially targeted people who wore glasses,
or spoke a foreign language,
or smiled too much.
Wow, he sounds like a psychopathic
high school bully.
Did steal their lunch money too?
Yeah, probably.
Luckily for the remaining three-quarters of
Cambodia,
the Khmer Rouge government was toppled
after just four years,
when Cambodia was invaded by
the next country on our list.
Communist Vietnam:
Optimistically called the Democratic Republic
of Vietnam.
It was formed by the communist revolutionary
Ho Chi Minh in 1945.
After nearly a decade of war,
he and his army finally defeated the French,
stole their baguettes,
and made some amazing sandwiches.
Ho Chi Minh doesn’t get nearly enough credit
for his accomplishments.
In particular, he’s responsible for the
deaths
of about 2 million Vietnamese.
Meanwhile, the US decided that it had so much fun
in the Korean War,
it wanted to do a spin-off in Vietnam.
But in a surprise twist,
this Communist north eventually conquered
the south.
It was a horrible tragedy,
but it did provide an iconic scene for Miss
Saigon.
Next up, Laos.
Never mind, we don't have time for Laos.
Moving along.
Cuba
Cuba, you’ve got some ’splaining to do.
In 1959,
the US government initially supported the
coup
by Fidel Castro and the guy from the T-shirt.
But like a bad date,
the US soon realized it should not have swiped
right
on Castro.
So the US tried to overthrow him.
And failed.
Eventually the CIA gave up.
Just kidding.
They tried to assassinate Castro like 600
times.
At different times, they attempted to poison
Castro's milkshakes,
his face cream,
and his handkerchief.
They even hatched a plan to make his beard
fall out
so people wouldn't take him seriously."
Really?
The beard?
That’s low, even for the CIA.
Oh, and there was that time when the Soviets
tried to install nuclear missiles in Cuba,
and the world almost ended.
It didn’t, but the premise made an iconic
scene
for Planet of the Apes.
Over the last 60-plus years,
Cuba has not been particularly kind to its
own citizens.
But somehow, this T-shirt of a mass-murdering
communist
is still super popular.
Buy it now on Amazon.com!
Ironically, it’s not free.
And speaking of Che Guevara,
in Latin America…ah forget it.
And now, today…
At this point,
communist governments have mostly gone
the way of the dinosaurs.
But like dinosaurs,
there are people today who find them
immensely fascinating.
All over the world,
there are registered Communist parties.
You’ll meet people who say things like,
“Well Communism is great, man,
it’s just never been done right before.
If we could just do it without killing 100
million people,
it’d be totally awesome!”
Which is why,
to celebrate the aforementioned 100th anniversary
of the Bolshevik Revolution,
China Uncensored will be making a special
series of videos taking a look back at all
the
“awesome” memories we have of Communism.
So will communism “rise like a phoenix
from the ash heap of history”?
And if it does, how will the world respond?
I have one idea.
Thanks for watching this, um,
brief history of the Communist Party.
I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
See you next time.