On this episode of China Uncensored,
North Korea is threatening nuclear war,
and Chinese hackers want to make sure
we’re not prepared to deal with it.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Things on the Korean peninsula are heating
up.
The US is sending in warships,
China is urging restraint,
and North Korea promises destruction.
Now that we possess mighty nuclear power
to protect ourselves from U.S. nuclear threat,
we will respond without the slightest hesitation
to full-out war with full-out war and to nuclear war
with our style of nuclear strike,
and we will emerge victor
in the final battle with the United States."
Well, to ensure North Korea does not
emerge as the victor,
the US installed THAAD in South Korea.
It stands for Terminal High Altitude Area
Defense.
It’s kind of important,
in the event North Korea ever tries
to make good on its promise
to turn South Korea’s capital into
“a sea of flames.”
But now THAAD is under threat.
Not from North Korean missiles,
or shifting political winds,
or even public protests.
But from Chinese hackers.
According to cybersecurity firm FireEye,
“Chinese state-backed hackers
have recently targeted South Korean entities
involved in deploying a U.S.
missile-defense system.”
Remember: it's not just North Korea that doesn't like THAAD.
The Chinese regime doesn’t like it either.
Even though THAAD is designed to stop
North Korean missiles,
it could in theory allow South Korea
and the US to track Chinese missiles.
So there are two main hacker groups
from China involved here.
One FireEye is calling the Tonto Group—
there must be some Lone Ranger fans over there.
The other is nicknamed APT10.
It's also sometimes called Stone Panda.
That one has also been accused of hacking
a US trade lobbying group,
and also of rolling down hills
and gathering no moss.
There are some independent Chinese hackers
targeting South Korea, too.
But both Tonto and Stone Panda
have been linked to Chinese military intelligence
units.
This is not to say that the Chinese Communist
Party
is behind the hacks in any way.
I mean, sure the Chinese military
belongs to the Party.
But China never messes with other countries!
“China always sticks to the principle of
not interfering
in the internal affairs of other countries.”
It’s just a coincidence
that since the South Korean government announced
the deployment of THAAD earlier this year,
hacking attacks from China have been on the
rise...
and that some of these hacks
have been targeting entities related directly
and indirectly to THAAD.
Last month,
South Korea’s Ministry of Foreign Affairs
website
was crippled.
This Korean news agency
said Chinese hackers have targeted,
“the homepages of 10 South Korean firms
and some South Korean embassies
in other countries”.
The Ministry of Science, ICT and Future Planning
raised the country’s cyberattack alert level
to the second highest rating.
I guess the Future Planning division
didn’t see it coming.
And what has North Korea been doing
while the Chinese Communist Party has totally
not been
interfering in the internal affairs of South
Korea?
Well, they just held a massive rally
marking the 85th anniversary
of the North Korean army.
Even though Kim Jong-un wasn’t there,
don’t they still sound excited?
How do they all know when to say that?
I wonder what it would feel like to have
hundreds of people cheering your every word?
Pretty good, actually.
I may keep that around.
Anyway, where was the dear leader?
Why he was inspecting a pig farm.
They have lots of food in North Korea,
did you know?
Except I can’t seem to find Kim in this
picture.
Just a bunch of giant hams.
That is never going to get old.
But not to worry.
Chinese hackers may be trying
to mess with THAAD,
but THAAD is merely a precautionary measure.
I mean, it's not like North Korea
is holding any live-fire artillery drills
while US warships gather, right?
I'm sure everything will be fine.
So what do you think
of the Chinese regime’s cyber attacks
in retaliation for South Korea’s
missile defense program?
Was it a...THAAD idea?
Yep, definitely keeping that.
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China Uncensored,
once again I’m your host, Chris Chappell,
see you next time.