On this episode of China Uncensored,
a missile defense system can’t protect you
against your own hypocrisy!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
The Chinese Communist Party is furious!
Again…
To be more specific,
the Chinese regime is furious about THAAD,
or Terminal High Altitude Area Defense.
That’s the system the US is installing in
South Korea
that will protect them from
a North Korean missile strike.
The only thing I want to emphasize
is that we resolutely oppose the deployment
of THAAD
in South Korea.
How dare the United States
try to help protect its ally
from a rogue regime’s nuclear weapons...
...that it was able to develop because of
support
from the Chinese regime.
I mean, it’s not like China is going around
building
missile defense systems for other countries.
Oh.
So apparently, China is helping Pakistan
build something similar to THAAD,
called LOMADS.
LOMADS stands for
Low-to-Medium Altitude Air Defense System.
LOMADS also describes how the Chinese regime
feels about THAAD,
a low level of constant mad.
LOMADS is capable of tracking
and destroying targets that—
you guessed it—
fly at low to medium altitudes.
Let’s just hope those made-in-China rockets
don’t explode prematurely,
like those Chinese watermelons.
So why is China helping Pakistan
build a missile defense system?
Because India.
Well, not only India.
But according to this Congressional report,
Beijing has long exploited the longstanding
rivalry
between India and Pakistan,
aiming to keep India so preoccupied
with its western neighbor
that it will not have the ability to mount
a serious challenge to China’s power and
influence
in Asia.
That’s also one of the reasons why China
helped Pakistan build its first nuclear bomb,
as well as Pakistan’s indigenous
ballistic missile capability.
You see, China and India don't really get
along.
It's kind of like when you have that one
next-door neighbor that you dislike
because he's harboring a certain spiritual
leader
in his house,
after that leader fled your house
that was really kind of his house
that you liberated from him.
Also, you and this neighbor
briefly went to war over who owns the big
oak tree
that grows in the middle of your shared property line.
But more importantly,
India has the potential to be
a major economic rival to China.
India’s GDP is growing rapidly.
It recently even surpassed Great Britain.
Which is a delicious irony—
if you’re not from Great Britain.
India, like China,
has a huge population,
around 1.2 billion people.
But India has a distinct advantage:
India’s population is mostly young,
while China’s is aging rapidly.
And that’s why, boys and girls,
brutal population control is not the best
long-term policy.
Anyway, China has been undermining India
in a variety of ways.
They’ve sent nuclear submarines
into the Indian Ocean.
And more recently,
China blocked a motion
to add a Pakistani terrorist leader
to a UN Security Council Blacklist.
India, for its part,
hasn’t let China’s actions go unnoticed.
They’re seeking a 2.5 billion dollar deal
with Israel
for their own missile defense system.
The Indian one will be called LRSAM,
which is based on the Israeli one called SPYDER.
C’mon Israel!
That is really stretching the acronym thing.
Although I guess it is the only one
that's an actual word.
At the end of last year,
India also purchased a Russian-made missile
defense system
that will be delivered by 2020.
It’s called the S-400 Triumf.
Which is not an acronym at all.
It’s just what you get when you ask a first-grader
to spell a word they've never heard before.
But it’s still pretty impressive.
Look at the long list of missiles and aircraft
this Russian-made missile system can shoot
down…
Wait a minute,
those are all American planes!
Ohhhh, Russia!
Anyway, India is building up its missile defenses.
For many observers, this is understandable,
because India has had several wars with Pakistan.
Just like it’s understandable that South
Korea and the US
are building THAAD
because North Korea has threatened to turn
Seoul and Washington
into a heap of ashes.
Which is a totally stupid threat.
It should be “heaps of ashes,” plural.
Obviously Seoul and Washington would be
two separate heaps.
Anyway, while China is helping Pakistan
build a missile defense against India,
China is hypocritically complaining about
the US
helping South Korea build a missile defense
against North Korea.
But it’s not just some crybaby complaint.
It’s a strategic crybaby complaint.
As this report says,
China hopes to create the impression that
American defensive missiles,
not China's new offensive missiles,
threaten peace in Asia.
Sound like a report on the current situation
with THAAD and South Korea?
Well, it’s actually a report from 1999.
This has been the Chinese regime’s strategy
for a long time,
since even before I came on the scene.
The Chinese Communist Party has two goals
in complaining about America’s
missile defense in South Korea:
One, to ensure these missile defense systems
can never be used against China.
And two,
to undermine American influence in Asia.
So you can see why the Chinese regime
might criticize THAAD,
even as it helps Pakistan build LOMADS,
while also keeping an eye on India's LRSAM,
based on SPYDER,
not to mention the S-400
Triumf, the Insult Comic Missile Defense System.
So what do you think of China’s concerns
over THAAD
and support of Pakistan’s LOMADS?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China Uncensored.
Remember, China Uncensored is made possible
by viewers like you.
Consider supporting the show on Patreon.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.