New Zealand—the destination of choice
for fabulously wealthy Chinese.
After the United States, Australia, Thailand,
Canada, and the UK.
That’s why I came to New Zealand.
To see all it has to offer!
My first stop was in Karaka.
I came to see this stunning, brand-new,
ultra-modern 4,000 square foot, luxury lifestyle
home,
sitting on 10 acres of lush countryside.
With four sun-drenched bedrooms,
an expansive high-end kitchen,
and floor-to-ceiling windows.
Plus a heated saltwater pool complete with
gas fireplace.
I couldn’t wait to get the tour.
So what does a home like this go for?
Well this property is going to auction
and we would expect interest
at upwards of three million.
It is a brand new home,
it's only one and a half years old.
Everything's brand new here.
Wow.
Similar properties have sold in the
four to five million dollars around the area.
Four to five million dollars in the area?
Yes.
So it is a premium area in Karaka.
Is New Zealand still a hot property market
for Chinese buyers?
I think New Zealand will always be
a hot property market for Chinese buyers
because of what it offers.
Why are they attracted to this area?
I think it's due to, well,
it's the beautiful environment that Karaka
offers,
the lovely openness,
green pastures, fresh air.
There's a very good private school close by,
we do have quite a lot of Chinese people
looking in the area.
How many homes in the area
are going to Chinese buyers?
Well, the Chinese buyers,
they've been in the market quite some time
now.
I haven't got a percentage
but the last two properties that I've sold
in Karaka
have been to Chinese buyers.
How have Chinese buyer affected the property
market?
They've offered...
yeah, certainly they've offered competition
for local buyers.
Has that affected the prices of the houses
at all?
A little bit, yes, yes.
Yes, it has.
Turns out, more than a bit.
According to this report from the Economist,
New Zealand has the most unaffordable houses
in the world.
Prices have jumped 75 percent in four years,
largely because of foreign buyers.
And the majority of those are Chinese.
Karaka was so nice that I was thinking of
becoming a foreign buyer myself.
But I couldn’t spend all day lounging by
the heated saltwater pool.
I had more luxury homes to visit.
So I was off to Auckland, New Zealand’s
biggest city,
to check out one of its most sought-after
neighborhoods.
I spoke with real estate agent Diana West.
She offered to show me a 3 million dollar
suburban home.
It was...a different kind of luxury.
So this house will most likely go
for over 3 million dollars?
Absolutely
And so what is the draw to a location like
this?
Is it the stunning luxury lifestyle?
Well when you get rid of this
and build your luxury home it will be.
But it’s the location for the school zones,
you’ve got Auckland Grammar,
Ipsen Girls Grammar,
so it’s actually the land value here.
Because it’s such, once you get rid of this
house,
and build two luxury homes here,
they will be worth easily $3.5 million dollars
each.
In this property market,
how many homes are going to Chinese buyers?
I’d say 80-90%.
80-90$?!
How has that affected the property prices?
Well it’s driven them up hugely
because we’ve got an influx of population
and seemingly with a lot of funds available
and that has actually driven out a lot of
the local buyers.
Has that caused resentment?
Yeah it does.
For a number of years in fact,
the local Kiwi people wouldn’t come to auctions
because they said what’s the point?
We’re going to get beaten so yeah,
there has been resentment.
Okay, so 10 years ago
how much would a house like this have gone
for?
Probably a million.
A million.
So prices have basically doubled.
Or tripled in this case.
Because what’s happened in the meantime
was the council has changed all the zoning
rules,
so you’ve got properties like this
that would have just been one house,
and now have the ability for multiple dwellings.
Are Chinese buyers still as interested in
this property market?
There has been a little cooling.
We find in general the Chinese
are the first to get on the bandwagon
when they perceive there’s a lot of growth
in the market,
then, in general,
they are the first to recede and start to
become cautious
when they see the market plateauing
and that’s what we believe we’re doing
at the moment.
The market is cooling a bit.
Yes \hit is, a little bit.
Do you think it will ever go back to the pricing
of 10 years ago,
before the influx of Chinese buyers.
No, no there’s just too much population
pressure in Auckland.
Okay.
Particularly in these well sought after suburbs.
Trying to tackle this problem,
the government proposed new laws
regulating foreign buyers.
But Diana thinks its too little too late.
There are proposed laws
that would restrict foreign buyers.
Do you see that affecting the market?
No I don’t,
I think it’s a bit like shutting the gate
after the horse has bolted.
The real change we saw here
was when they brought in
the Bright-lLine Tax rules several years ago,
and that requirement was for people
to have a New Zealand bank account
and a New Zealand IRD number,
and that stopped a lot of the foreign speculation
happening from people who did not live here
because they couldn’t comply with those
rules.
And so that’s when we stopped seeing all
that happening.
So really, the people who have been buying
for the last couple of years
are generally resident or applying for residency.
So I don’t see this ban on foreign ownership
having any difference at all.
I realized that to be able to afford property
in New Zealand,
I would need to be fabulously wealthy
to be just moderately well off.
Which gives me an idea....
Welcome to Lifestyles of the Moderately Well
Off!
Life is slightly better
for the fabulously wealthy in New Zealand.
Luxury pools
Luxurious lounges
Exotic animals
All on the doorstep of your 3 million dollar
dream home.
Behold what the world has to offer
on Lifestyles of the Moderately Well Off!
So I might never be able to own
a luxury property in New Zealand.
But you know what?
Even without a house,
I can still enjoy the moderately well off
lifestyle.