On this episode of China Uncensored,
remembering 2016
because we have to.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Well, we all made it through 2016,
and we deserve a round of applause.
You know, there’s an old Chinese curse:
“May you live in interesting times.”
What's that, Shelley?
It's not actually a Chinese curse at all,
and was most likely made up by some British
guy?
Of course it was.
Anyway, boy, do we ever live in interesting
times.
So let’s take a look back at 10 of the biggest
stories
from China in 2016.
Number 10
Beijing, we have a problem.
China has ambitious space plans.
This is the Tiangong-1 space station.
China launched it in 2011.
Then in March 2016,
state-run Xinhua News announced that Tiangong-1
had completed its missions,
and would “descend gradually in the coming
months”
back down to earth.
But what they actually meant
is that China has lost control of the Tiangong-1.
And by “descend gradually” they meant
crash.
Yes, it will crash back down to Earth—
breaking apart into chunks as big as 200 pounds,
cannonballing down at terminal velocity,
landing somewhere that’s impossible to predict,
on an unknown date in 2017.
Just one way 2017 can have 2016 beat!
Number 9
China’s First Female President
By China, I mean the other China.
In January, the Republic of China elected
its first female President,
Tsai Ing-wen.
And Tsai has never officially acknowledged
the One China policy.
Which made the other other China really mad.
State-run Xinhua News published a commentary
that accused Tsai of being emotional, extremist,
and erratic.
Not because of specific policies, mind you.
But because she’s a single woman.
You see, as a single female politician,
she does not have the emotional burden of
love,
family, or children—
so her political style and strategies are
displayed to be
more emotional, personal and extreme.
Because as elections in several other countries
this year
have conclusively proven,
male political leaders are never emotional,
personal, or extreme.
Number 8
China’s Plan for Internet Domination
On October 1,
the US let its contract with ICANN expire.
Very simply,
very simply put,
there’s a department of ICANN that’s in
charge of
the Internet’s address book.
It makes sure users get to the websites they
intend to visit.
That address book is like the One Ring of
the Internet.
Whoever controls it controls them all.
An American organization had overseen ICANN
since time immemorial,
i.e. since Al Gore invented the Internet.
But as of October 2016,
ICANN is controlled by a “multi-stakeholder
model.”
It doesn’t belong to China, either...
but the Chinese regime has gotten pretty good
at manipulating the international stakeholders
that are now overseeing it.
Ultimately,
the Chinese regime’s goal is to control
the world’s internet,
and make it look more like the harmonious
internet
protected by China’s Great Firewall.
Without that pesky freedom of speech.
Number 7
The Panama Papers
April saw the biggest data leak in history:
the Panama Papers.
2.6 terabytes of documents were leaked
from a Panama-based company called Mossack
Fonseca.
And it was a huge scandal for the Chinese
regime.
Because fully one third of Mossack Fonseca’s
business
came from China.
Those leaked documents revealed a lot of information
about China’s elite,
including at least eight family members
of current and former members of China’s
Politburo Standing Committee.
The Panama Papers also revealed
how wealthy Chinese are increasingly moving
their money
out of China.
Number 6
China Steals a US Drone
Yes, the Chinese navy took a US research drone
in December.
It was measuring oceanic temperature and stuff
about 50 miles off the coast of the Philippines,
or 500 miles off the coast of China.
This caused an international incident, of
course.
Fortunately,
China gave the drone back once they found
out
it was totally boring research drone.
They gave it back
even though president-elect Trump told China
via Twitter
they could keep it.
I guess they didn’t get the message,
since Twitter is banned in China.
Number 5
China loses the South China Sea
China is embroiled in territorial disputes
with pretty much every one one of its neighbors
over the South China Sea.
That’s what happens when you claim pretty
much the whole thing.
But China’s plans for domination hit a little
snafu in July
when the Philippines successfully got the
UN
to hold an arbitration case in the Hague.
And the Hague ruled in a unanimous decision
that all of China’s claims are illegitimate.
It was a big win for the Philippines—
at least on paper.
But then this guy got elected—
the new president of the Philippines,
Rodrigo Duterte.
And that brings us to...
Number 4
China wins the South China Sea
President Rodrigo Duterte has been pushing
for closer ties with China,
and turning away from the US.
During his October trip to China,
he didn’t even bring up the territorial
dispute.
And it paid off for him.
Kind of.
The Chinese coast guard stopped blocking Filipino
fishermen
from fishing in the Scarborough Shoal.
Which gave me the perfect opportunity
to plant my flag there.
But by making this concession,
Duterte also weakened the Philippines’ future
claim
to the region.
In other words,
in the long term, China wins.
Number 3
Hong Kong Oath Taking Scandal
The Chinese regime has been aggressively encroaching
on freedoms in Hong Kong.
But pro-democracy lawmakers in Hong Kong
won a big victory in the September elections.
They won 30 seats in the Legislative Council,
giving them veto power over the pro-Beijing
side.
It was a great win.
Until these two took their oaths of office.
They held up flags that said Hong Kong is
not China.
And in their off-script oath,
they referred to China using a slur the Japanese
had used
during World War II.
That gave Beijing the excuse to make an “interpretation”
of Hong Kong Basic Law—
the interpretation being they disqualified
those two officials.
That opened the floodgates.
Chief Executive CY Leung
is now seeking to disqualify four others.
If they’re successful,
then the pro-democracy side loses its veto
power
in the Legislative Council.
In other words,
the Pro-Beijing side could do whatever it
wants.
And the Chinese Communist Party would win
Hong Kong.
Number 2
People finally start talking about Organ Harvesting
Ten years ago,
former Canadian Member of Parliament David
Kilgour
and human rights lawyer David Matas
began telling the world that the Chinese regime
was killing Falun Gong practitioners for their
organs.
And the world media was like,
“yeah, whatever, where's the smoking gun?”
But this year,
a lot of media started taking their claims
more seriously.
Because in June,
they released a new report that showed that
yes,
the Communist Party is killing Falun Gong
practitioners,
House Christians, and Uighur Muslims—
and selling their organs for profit.
And it’s on a scale of 60 to 100,000 organ
transplants per year.
Will 2017 shed more light on this terrible
practice?
Let's hope so.
And Finally, Number 1
Xi Jinping Goes Super Saiyan
Xi Jinping is the strongest leader China has
seen in a generation.
And this year, he powered up.
In April,
he assumed the title of Commander in Chief
of the new Joint Operations Command
of the People’s Liberation Army.
No one saw it coming.
And not just because he was wearing camouflage.
This was a major step forward in his purging
of rivals,
like people tied to former Chinese leader
Jiang Zemin,
who was seen as previously holding an iron
grip
on the armed forces.
Then at the end of October,
Xi Jinping became China’s core leader,
bringing Xi one step closer to becoming
what I like to call a “presitator”—
somewhere between a president and a dictator.
The internal power struggle within the Communist
Party
has raged on since 2012.
And 2017 will bring even more changes,
as many of the top leaders of the Party
are supposed to step down.
I bet those will be some fun retirement parties.
So what was your favorite China story of 2016?
Leave your comments below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next year.