On this episode of China Uncensored,
is there anyone who still believes in journalism?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
You know, it's hard out here for newspapers.
According to the Pew Research Center,
newspaper subscriptions are declining fast.
And ad revenues are falling, too,
so it's tough to make ends meet.
Fortunately, there’s at least one group
that hasn’t given up on Western journalism—
the Chinese Communist Party.
Yes, the Chinese state-run media
is paying to place its propaganda
in mainstream Western newspapers—
like the Daily Telegraph,
the New York Times,
and the Wall Street Journal.
Well, it’s not exactly propaganda.
Propaganda would be if a Chinese newspaper
ran a story called something like,
I don't know,
“Wherever you look, Red Reigns Supreme.”
But if you get a respected American newspaper
to run the same thing,
people think it’s credible.
So it becomes something that’s more accurately
called
disinformation.
That's when intentionally false or misleading
information
is planted in a way that would
make people believe it.
It was a technique masterminded by the Soviets,
and it's been fine-tuned
by the Chinese Communist Party.
This is the latest piece of disinformation:
A 5-page full color spread
published in the January 17th edition
of the Wall Street Journal.
Sure, it looks exactly like a bunch of news
articles.
But it’s an advertisement.
You can tell by the small text at the bottom
that says
“Paid by the Xinhua News Agency”.
And because it’s selling us Xi Jinping’s
vision
for a better world for all.
Yes, China has a plan for you, too.
That article also criticizes the US for it’s
“sense of superiority and impatience.”
Another article on that page accuses Europe
of being fueled by “rightist ideas.”
But if you’re concerned about the Communist
Party’s
anti-Western messages
being printed in the Wall Street Journal,
well, sure they’re in inside the Wall Street
Journal,
but according to the Wall Street Journal,
they’re not in the Wall Street Journal.
I emailed their spokesperson,
who responded:
“The Journal has run special advertising
sections
and other traditional advertising from China
Watch,
which are clearly labeled as such.
The Journal’s news organization is not involved.”
Basically,
if someone pays them to run an ad,
they’re not responsible for what it says.
As long as it's clearly labeled.
FYI, I also asked the Wall Street Journal
if they’d be willing to run a full-page
ad
that praises Stalin.
Strangely, they did not respond.
And here’s one of the most interesting things
this 5-page Chinese “ad” is selling:
Blasphemy That Masquerades as Art.
Yes, the Chinese Communist Party is a great
art critic.
After all,
they spent decades eradicating traditional
Chinese culture,
and twisting theater to its own political
ends.
So they know a thing or two.
So what is this so-called
“Blasphemy That Masquerades as Art”
that Chinese state-run media is criticizing?
Why, it’s Shen Yun!
A dance company that state-run media
accuses of being linked to Falun Gong,
a.k.a. Falun Dafa.Well, I am shocked,
shocked to hear this terrible secret
that no one knows.
Except for the fact that Shen Yun
explicitly says this on its own website.
Yes, Shen Yun is:
"reviving 5,000 years of civilization"
"features the world's foremost classically
trained dancers"
And look, it was
"established by Falun Dafa practitioners in
2006."
Whistle.
Blown.
What amazing investigative reporting
from Chinese state-run media.
If you’ve been watching China Uncensored
for a while,
you’ve heard me talk about the Chinese regime’s
weird obsession with slandering Shen Yun.
And if this is new to you,
let me tell you why the Communist Party
sees this Chinese-American dance show
as such an enormous threat.
Falun Gong practitioners are the
people getting their organs harvested in China,
as punishment for doing this.
And this.
Such a threat to social harmony.
Like yoga.
And yet—and this is true—
the Chinese regime has spent billions of dollars
since the late ’90s
creating a global propaganda campaign
to slander Falun Gong.
Including by planting disinformation
in foreign newswire services like the Associated
Press.
Anyway,
you can imagine that this latest
Chinese state-run media-slash-totally-not-Wall
Street Journal article
does not speak highly of Shen Yun,
calling it full of “far-fetched theme[s],”
that spare little effort in
“demonizing the Chinese government.”
Hey,
demonizing the Chinese government is hard
work.
Unfortunately for the Chinese Communist Party,
Shen Yun is actually really popular.
It plays to packed theaters every year
in hundreds of cities around the world.
I just saw their performance at New York’s
Lincoln Center
last week.
It sold out four shows in a row.
What’s so “blasphemous” about it?
Well, the show had about twenty dance and
music numbers.
Most depicted cultural and historic things
from China,
like a scene from Journey to the West.
But some of them also show an awareness of
modern China.
One had a monk with awesome fighting skills
defending a Buddhist temple from being demolished
by Communist officials during the Cultural
Revolution.
Another one showed Falun Gong practitioners
standing up to the Chinese regime’s persecution.
Imagine!
Using the arts to tell important stories.
What blasphemy.
Yes, according the article,
audiences get
“assaulted with everything the Falun Gong
propaganda arsenal
has to fire at them.”
Wow.
Let’s see what people assaulted with the
Falun Gong propaganda arsenal
have to say.
I laughed, I cried…
Colorful and vibrant and joyous.
The dancers - you guys are amazing!
Great experience.
Well worth it.
Why even a Wall Street Journal anchor
said she and her son enjoyed the show.
"…So I have him to thank
for introducing me to this beautiful culture."…
"Another good part
was when the monk's were fighting the Red
Guards."
But for the Chinese regime,
Falun Gong is a third rail issue.
They hate it when people talk about it positively—
because it rips apart their propaganda.
Like back in 2001 when the Wall Street Journal
won a Pulitzer Prize for reporting on the
regime's persecution
of Falun Gong.
That was before the Communist Party
started paying the Wall Street Journal, though.
For years,
the Chinese Communist Party has gone to great
lengths
to stop people from seeing Shen Yun.
Chinese embassies around the world
have written to theaters that hosting Shen
Yun
"may compromise relations"
between China and their country.
And pressuring them to cancel it.
Like in Spain.
Germany.
And even Florida.
That's pretty low.
Florida needs all the culture it can get.
Anyway, it's a tactic that generally backfires,
since when the news comes out,
it kind of makes people want to see the show
more...
But if an article inside a well-respected
paper like the Wall Street Journal
trashes Shen Yun as Falun Gong propaganda,
that could actually affect sales—
especially for readers who don’t realize
it’s an ad from Chinese state-run media.
But, come on, Wall Street Journal.
Are you really willing to print the Chinese
Communist Party's disinformation
for a few thousand bucks?
Wait, what’s that, Shelley?
Oh.
The retail price for a full-page color ad
in the Wall Street Journal
is 354 thousand dollars.
The Xinhua News ad was five pages,
so about 1.8 million dollars.
I mean, I’m sure the Journal gave them a
discount.
After all, they probably want repeat business.
But you know what?
If they’ll run a full-page Chinese propaganda
ad,
we should run a China Uncensored ad.
Except I don’t have 354 thousand dollars.
And that’s maybe too ambitious of a Kickstarter
campaign.
Hey, who needs a newspaper ad anyway?
Traditional media is dying!
I have my fifty-cent army!
Yes, China Uncensored fans,
I want you to spread the word about the show.
Remember that wanted poster of me that,
uh, someone, created?
Download it on this website.
The link is in the Description box below.
Print out 10 copies,
20 copies,
or as many as you can—
and put them up in a populated area near you.
Take a wide photo of one of the posters
and send it to me in an email at chinauncensored@gmail.com.
Don't forget to tell me where you put it up.
And we'll post those pictures on our Facebook
page.
This is going to be awesome.
So what do you think of the Wall Street Journal
allowing Chinese disinformation to be printed
in an ad in their paper?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
And put up those posters!
Click the link below.