Can China Outlast Trump?
Amnesty International gets Chinese pushback...
in New York!
And the worst boy band ever.
That and more on this week’s China news
headlines.
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Months of trade negotiations with China have
failed.
And are you really surprised?
Now the Trump administration is preparing
25% tariffs
on an additional 300 billion dollars worth
of Chinese goods.
Obviously the Chinese Communist Party is not
happy about the tariffs.
Chinese leader Xi Jinping called them foolish.
No, “foolish” is the Chinese Communist
Party censoring the letter N,
believing that will somehow stop people from
criticizing Xi Jinping.
Side note, it didn’t work.
Anyway, with respect to the tariffs,
state-run People’s Daily released this snappy
graphic
on its official WeChat account.
It says “Negotiate, sure!”
“Fight, anytime!”
“Bully us, wishful thinking!”
So the Chinese Communist Party is obviously
upset.
But I doubt surprised.
The Trump administration was demanding reforms
that the authoritarian regime is simply unwilling
to make.
That could be why the Chinese regime blew
up the trade deal.
According to Reuters,
“In each of the seven chapters of the draft
trade deal,
China had deleted its commitments to change
laws
to resolve core complaints
that caused the United States to launch a
trade war:
Theft of U.S. intellectual property and trade
secrets;
forced technology transfers;
competition policy;
access to financial services;
and currency manipulation.”
Maybe they expected the US government
to back down and sign the deal anyway.
But that’s not what happened.
So what impact will this have on China?
Well, the Chinese regime has kept their economy
afloat
no matter what disasters they’ve faced so
far—
bad debt, corruption,
a housing bubble, you name it.
They’re really good at finding short term
solutions.
In this case,
there’s the “hundreds of billions of dollars
that Beijing has pumped into the country’s
economy in recent months,
as well as the loans that officials have pressed
state-run banks to make to businesses.”
My guess is that the Chinese regime
is trying to hang on till the 2020 elections,
in the hopes that Trump will be replaced with
someone a lot softer on China.
And when it comes to election interference,
they’ve already been racking up experience
points.
But if the Chinese regime thinks it’ll get
easier for them
as long as a Democrat wins in 2020,
they should think again.
Democratic Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer
tweeted that Trump should “hang tough on
China.”
And most of the current Democrats running
for president
are now also hangin’ tough on China.
And while former Vice President Joe Biden
recently said
he didn’t see China as a competitor,
he was criticized by Bernie Sanders—
yes, Bernie Sanders.
I can’t wait for those two to debate.
Two Canadian citizens in China
have been charged with spying:
Michael Kovrig and Michael Spavor.
Chinese authorities arrested them both in
December.
That was after Canada arrested
Huawei executive Meng Wanzhou
for extradition to the US—
and the Canadian government refused
to simply let her go arbitrarily.
But don’t worry,
the Chinese charges against the two Canadians
are not arbitrary.
They’re definitely guilty...
of being Canadians in the wrong place at the
wrong time.
Amnesty International has spent years
criticizing the Chinese Communist Party.
But Chinese backed companies have spent years
buying up real estate in New York.
So guess who’s winning?
Amnesty International just had their lease
denied by China.
They were trying to move their New York Headquarters
to a building in lower Manhattan called Wall
Street Plaza.
“But just as the organization was about
to sign a lease last week,
the building’s owner said that its new parent
company,
a giant shipping conglomerate owned by the
Chinese government,
decided to veto the offer.”
Such a troll move.
Which is why I’m giving this a rating of
four Pepe the Poohs.
Huawei.
The Chinese telecom company
the US says is a national security threat,
and probably receives funding from the Chinese
military.
A lot of countries have banned Huawei
from building sensitive tech infrastructure.
But not the UK.
Why not?
Aren’t they concerned?
Of course not!
Because Huawei has told them they’re ready
to sign
a “no spy, no back door” contract.
I mean when was the last time
you heard Verizon give that guarantee?
The Huawei chief said,
“We are willing to sign ‘no-spy’ agreements
with governments,
including the UK government, to commit ourselves,
to commit our equipment to meeting the no-spy,
no back-door standards.”
Now believe it or not, there are still some
people
who are not satisfied with a “no spy agreement”
and still consider Huawei a threat.
I mean, there’s just no pleasing some people.
Speaking of not pleasing people —
Google.
Last year, The Intercept revealed
a secret project Google was working on
to create a censored search app for China.
Google spent a long time denying its existence.
Well, in an interview with the BBC,
former Google CEO Eric Schmidt,
defended the censored app that Google
had to eventually admit really existed.
It would have “many benefits”
and would “help change China to be more
open.”
Which is obviously why Google
spent so much time lying about its existence
and not even telling most of their employees
what they were actually working on.
Sounds like something to be proud of.
Unlike Google,
Wikipedia was unwilling to censor their website
in China.
Which is why the Chinese language Wikipedia
has been blocked in China since 2015.
Well, Now it’s been totally banned in all
languages.
Oh no.
Now Chinese trolls will have to use a VPN
to alter Wikipedia’s controversial China
content
for the rest of the world.
Now sure, Chinese internet censorship
and surveillance seem bad.
But on the plus side,
they’re giving us the latest greatest boy
band experience!
China Youth Credit Management is a group
working with the Communist Youth League.
They’ve recently designed an app
to incentivize “positive action”
by putting its users under constant surveillance.
But just in case this amazing-sounding app
doesn’t sell itself,
China Youth Credit Management
has created a music video to promote it.
It features China’s popular boy band TFBoys
and some other celebrities.
I love how clean cut and obedient they all
look!
I bet they all get good grades,
return library books on time,
and stay away from subversive content on the
Internet.
But this is great news for TFBoys.
Everyone knows you’re not a real boy band
until you make a propaganda music video.
Just like NSYNC’s famous Bye Bye Bye music
video
extolling the virtues of being puppets of
American imperialism.
And finally, a man in China has been arrested
for giving dogs illegal names.
Apparently he named his dogs after two common
job titles:
Chengguan and Xieguan.
“‘Chengguan’ are officials employed
in urban areas
to tackle low-level crime,
while ‘Xieguan’ are informal community
workers
such as traffic assistants.”
Local law enforcement,
and I use that term loosely in regards to
China,
said the man “caused great harm to the nation
and the city’s urban management,
in terms of their feelings.”
And hurting the feelings of law enforcement
is not very nice.
So they threw the guy in jail for 10 days.
That’ll teach him to respect the rule of
law!
And now it’s time for me to answer
a question from one of you—
a fan who support China Uncensored
with a dollar or more per episode,
by contributing through Patreon.
Today’s question comes from:
Uhhhhh, David Schwimmerer’s Russian twin:
“Chris, what is your favorite type of computer
password,
is it like a phrase about something absurd
and funny relating to the CCP,
making it hilarious for everyone as they watch
you?”
Great question!
My password is
“Winnie the Pooh Free Tibet Pro Taiwan Tiananmen
1989”.
Not only is it basically uncrackable,
it makes me laugh everytime I type it haha.
Cyber security is important.
Thanks for your question.
And thanks to everyone watching!
We could not make this show without your support.
Whether it’s supporting us through patreon
or just watching and sharing the show
with your friends and family.
So thank you from me
and everyone on the China Uncensored team.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.