On this episode of China Uncensored,
a polarizing issue.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
Now you just know a giant shopping mall in
a communist-ish country
has got to be something special.
And the Grandview Mall in Guangzhou is no
exception.
It has everything!
A movie theater,
indoor ice skating,
and as the Guangzhou travel guide puts it,
“all these lovely background music.”
But that’s not all.
There’s also the Grandview Mall Ocean World,
an aquatic wonderland!
Or as one person on Trip Advisor calls it,
“a mall with the most disgusting zoo in
the world.”
And the star attraction is...
the saddest polar bear in all of China.
Now you might be thinking,
what in the name of all that is holy is wrong
with that bear?
Well, it’s because he lives in a shopping
mall.
There’s not even any snow in his cage.
And he has to deal with people banging on
the glass to take photos of him.
Someone should give him a Coca Cola.
That footage comes from Animals Asia,
a Hong Kong based animal rights charity.
They’re trying to get the exhibition shut
down.
And so far,
they’ve gotten around 300,000 people to
sign a petition for just that.
Because it’s not just a sad polar bear.
There’s also six young beluga whales,
five walrus calves,
a wolf,
and arctic foxes.
And all of them are equally sad,
living in equally terrible conditions.
I’m mean seriously,
this little guy otter be kept in cleaner conditions.
Of course my favorite state run Party mouthpiece,
the Global Times,
wrote an article specifically to counter all
these accusations of cruelty.
As you might guess,
they interviewed the aquarium manager,
who also denies all the claims.
Local media, however,
reported that the Guangzhou Ocean and Fishery
Bureau
investigated and discovered that some animals
died while being moved into the aquarium.
This is by no means an isolated incident.
Quote unquote “Zoos” in China don’t
always put animal welfare as a top priority.
Monkeys and a bear racing on bicycles?!
What could go wrong?!
Wait for it…
I mean who could have seen that coming?
And besides general animal cruelty,
there’s specific animal cruelty you can
get in on!
Like feeding a live sheep to a tiger.
So is this a systemic thing?
Well, probably not.
According to Peter Li, Humane Society International’s
China expert,
“There’s nothing cultural or traditional
about animal abuse in China.”
The problem is that animal welfare laws in
China
are few and far between.
And where they do exist,
enforcement is pretty lax.
So this kind of stuff that PETA shows here
can happen.
Fortunately, as Animals Asia puts it,
“what is clear is that a significant section
of Chinese society
will not accept this.”
So what do you think about the saddest polar
bear in China?
Leave your comments below.
And if you’d like to actually do something
about it,
I’ve put a link to Animal Asia’s petition
in the description below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell, see you next
time.