Massive Protests in Hong Kong
Are making Carrie Lam Cry
Time to pack it in
Welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Okay, I have a message to the tens of thousands
of protesters in Hong Kong
who are upset about Beijing destroying their
freedoms.
You’ve gone too far!
You made poor Hong Kong Chief Executive Carrie
Lam cry.
“Some people say I'm betraying Hong Kong.
How can I betray Hong Kong?
I was born and raised here.
I was growing up here with all the Hong Kong
people.”
That poor woman is just trying her hardest
to make Beijing happy,
and you keep asking her to step down.
Have you ever tried walking a mile in her
shoes, huh?
Well, so you know how it feels to cry,
she allowed Hong Kong police to shoot tear
gas at protestors.
And if that doesn’t make you cry,
the pepper spray and rubber bullets will do
the job.
Hong Kong police have been kicking around
some other great ideas, too.
Wow, that’s some good leadership, Carrie
Lam!
Don’t feel too bad though,
because the Chinese Communist Party’s got
your back.
“China's central government will continue
its firm support
for the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region
government
to push forward with its amendments of the
two extradition bills.”
Those extradition bills are the reason
a million people protested over the weekend.
If they get passed,
Chinese authorities could, in some cases,
order Hong Kong authorities to arrest
and deport suspected criminals to mainland
China.
The Hong Kong Legislature was supposed to
debate the bill on Wednesday.
But these pesky protesters got in the way.
Look, those barricades are there for a reason!
To block off the protest area right outside
the legislature.
Well that plan clearly didn’t work.
At least 20 people were injured
and the extradition bill debate has been delayed.
Carrie Lam is calling the protests organized
riots.
And July 1 will be the anniversary of the
British handover of Hong Kong to the Chinese
Communist Party.
That’s just a couple weeks away,
so it’s possible these protests won’t
be ending anytime soon.
Now, in 2014, police also used tear gas on
protesters,
as well as some hefty violence.
That resulted in a months long occupation
of downtown Hong Kong
and international condemnation.
So you’d think Hong Kong authorities would
have learned their lesson,
that maybe police brutality is not the way
to deal with these kinds of issues.
Protesters on the other hand have learned
from the 2014 Umbrella Movement.
Back then, they used umbrellas to block police
pepper spray.
They’re doing that again this time too.
Just with better branding:
There’s a promo for the new Spider Man:
Far From Home movie!
And for some reason,
I have a sudden urge to go to the 7-11 in
Hong Kong.
In fact, that’s just what I’ll do.
By the time this video comes out,
Matt and Shelley and I will have landed in
Hong Kong to do interviews,
live streaming, and umbrella shopping.
Assuming we aren’t illegally stopped at
the border.
But as for Carrie Lam and her crocodile tears,
all I can say is,
see you later alligator,
in a while crocodile.
So what do you think of the growing protest
movement in Hong Kong?
Leave your comments below.
And before I go...to Hong Kong,
it's time for me to answer a question
from a member of the China Uncensored 50 Cent
Army—
the fans who support the show
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
Christopher Vaiuso asks,
“Why can't the US and other countries
just kick China out of the WTO?”
Now that’s a good question.
China has broken so many of its
World Trade Organization promises over the
years.
So why not kick China out?
Certainly, some in the Trump Administration
have suggested it.
The problem is,
the WTO doesn’t actually have a way to force
a member out.
In fact, no country has ever left the WTO,
let alone gotten expelled.
But according to the Wall Street Journal,
there is an article that can achieve the same
thing.
Using Article 23 might allow for amendments
to the WTO charter
that outright prohibits all the things China
is doing,
which would then force China out of the WTO.
The problem with that is the WTO usually requires
unanimous votes for doing something.
So China could just veto the whole thing.
But if that happens,
it is still possible if there’s a vote by
a supermajority of members.
So kicking China out of the WTO would be new
territory.
Possibly China’s sacred territory.
Thanks for your question, Christopher.
And thank you for watching.
If you’d like to support China Uncensored,
visit Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored,
and pledge a dollar or more per episode.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.