The Chinese Communist Party has been exposed
The tactics the Party uses to undermine democracy
have been laid bare
And countries around the world react
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
For years, the Chinese Communist Party
has been extending its tentacles into every
level of society
in democracies around the world.
But before the CCP’s plans for world domination
can succeed,
some people are beginning to take notice.
In 2018, Clive Hamilton,
a professor of public ethics
at Charles Sturt University in Australia,
released Silent Invasion:
China’s Influence in Australia.
It’s an indepth look at the tactics the
Chinese Communist Party
has been using to undermine democracy and
push its own agenda.
Ironically, his initial publisher dropped
the book
because of fear of a backlash.
But after a new publishing company put out
the book,
it became a canary in the coal mine.
Australian society began fighting back.
And today, Clive Hamilton joins me in the
studio
to discuss the progress that’s been made
over the past year
since the book was published,
and what more needs to be done.
Clive, it's great to speak with you again.
Are you still facing as much harassment from
your work
that's as when I first met you a year ago?
It's a bit hard to tell.
Obviously, I and others who do the kind of
work I do
need to think a lot and take measures about
security,
both cyber and otherwise.
So yep, it's a different world I move in now.
I bet!
Since your book Silent Invasion painted such
a bleak image
of how the Chinese commies party was influencing
all levels of Australian society,
has there been a change since it was released?
Well, it's certainly been a big shift in Canberra
in attitudes towards Chinese Communist Party
influence operations.
It's now widely understood that it's a big
issue,
a big problem for Australia.
The major news organizations
are onto it and they're looking for good CCP
influence stories,
and coming up with some terrific ones.
And the federal government has introduced
a number of measures,
including legislation which has been passed
by parliament
on a bipartisan basis.
Introducing a new criminal offense known as
foreign interference.
And there are a number of other legislative
and administrative measures
that the Australian government has taken.
So there's certainly a desire to push back
and there's a kind of structure in place now
which has attracted a lot of attention around
the world
from other countries including the United
States and Canada
to see what's happened in Australia
and whether our pushback strategy is being
effective.
It's a bit soon to say.
We've yet to see whether the new laws will
bite
or whether that means there will be prosecutions
or whether it means that Beijing
and its agents of influence in Australia
will change their strategies to stay on
the right side of the new laws.
So we won't know for a couple of years,
but certainly the atmospherics have changed
a great deal.
So people are talking about the issue a lot.
Specifically these foreign interference laws.
What do they do?
Well, the foreign ...
Well, let me get to the foreign interference
lawyer of several others.
There's a foreign interference ...
Sorry, foreign influence transparencies game,
which is modeled on the US FARA law,
which means that people who are trying
to influence political processes on behalf
of a foreign government
have to put their names on a register
and that's just come into operation.
The laws governing foreign,
particularly Chinese investment in Australia's
critical infrastructure,
electricity supply, gas supply-
Is 5G included in that?
Telecommunications.
The Australian government has announced that
Huawei and ZTE
are simply banned from putting their equipment
into Australia's 5G network.
And so the Australian government really led
the world on that
and it's a big question of whether the rest
of the Five Eyes nations
will follow suit.
And the various other measures,
but I think the central measure is the foreign
interference law.
And what that does is it defines
a new offense called foreign interference,
which ...
And foreign interference generally described
is foreign influence,
which is a covert coercive or corrupt.
And what it means is that any act
which is undertaken in a secretive way on
behalf of a foreign principle,
which can mean a foreign power or big corporation,
which is close to a foreign power-
Or a host of a show in a foreign country?
Certainly.
And if that host in the media
is trying to influence a government process,
or interfere in the democratic right of someone
in Australia,
then they are committing a criminal offense
and there are large penalties for them.
So this is really radical because it's a new
world
that governments are trying to come to grips
with.
It's not espionage.
Yes, espionage laws cover certain things,
but then there's this huge gap,
this gray area which the Chinese Communist
Party has been exploiting
in all kinds of countries.
And so the foreign interference law is a way
of trying to turn
some of that gray area black,
so that if you do that kind of stuff,
you could end up in jail.
So these foreign interference laws don't mention
China specifically?
No.
However, when the law, the bill,
was introduced to parliament by Prime Minister
Malcolm Turnbull,
former Prime Minister Malcolm Turnbull,
in his speech he specifically mentioned China.
And that caused a great deal of angst and
irritation in Beijing.
But it was a very bold move by Prime Minister
Turnbull
to finger China and the Chinese Communist
Party specifically.
So there's no doubt in anyone's mind that
this law is directed at China.
We don't have Russian interference in Australia,
not to speak of.
That you know of.
Well, maybe they are particularly clever and
they've gone under the radar.
But yeah, this law is about China.
Now, I know you talked about the risk of 5G
from Chinese telecommunications companies
like Huawei or ZTE.
What is the risk these companies and their
5G pose?
Well 5G, the fifth generation of mobile telecommunications
will completely transform the way our lives
operate
in the sense that they won't just govern our
cell phones,
but they'll also be crucial for all kinds
of communications
and industrial management processes.
Driverless cars, for example, will be operated
through the 5G-
Smart cities.
Smart cities, the whole box and dice.
CCTV, factual recognition, everything will
be a operated through 5G.
So if you have the potential for a foreign
adversary
who could at some point become an enemy with
essentially controlling
or having access to the equipment that organizers
transmits, 5G,
then you've got a major national security
issue on your hands.
And that's why Australia banned Huawei and
ZTE,
and why the US government hasn't formally
banned them,
but I believe is on the verge of doing so.
And similarly, New Zealand has banned those
companies.
Canada and the UK are the other two of the
Five Eyes nations,
are agonizing, coming under a huge amount
of pressure from Beijing
to allow Huawei into their networks.
But also their security services are saying,
"This would be crazy to do it."
So the governments are trying to make up their
minds still.
Well, speaking of the Five Eyes nations,
how do you think they are doing at handling
Chinese Communist Party's influence?
Well, Beijing would like nothing more than
to divide the Five Eyes nations.
To have the United States, for example,
unwilling to communicate or discuss it's secrets
with Canada or the United Kingdom.
This will be a major victory for Beijing-
Because for instance, they've used Huawei
Telecom infrastructure.
Exactly.
If Britain in particular had Huawei equipment
in it's 5G network,
and the United States and Australia and New
Zealand said,
"We're not going to have them."
We'll now have their, I'm guessing,
their international hookups to discuss the
deepest secrets
that they have about CCP interference for
example,
or activities in the South China Sea.
You name it.
The United States has flagged that it will
be reluctant
to communicate its secrets through a 5G network
because you won't be certain that it is secure.
That would be a big victory for Beijing
and so it's very worrying that the UK can't
make up its mind.
Germany is not in the Five Eyes,
but kind of close to it,
is also in the throes of trying to make up
its mind on this question.
So that's why Huawei's so important to Beijing
for its global program of influence and espionage.
So even if one of the Five Eyes nations used
Huawei infrastructure,
that would be a big victory for China
because then essentially that one country
would be excluded
and then you only have Four Eyes,
which doesn't really sound very-
It doesn't sound very good.
It sounds more like an insult then then a
secrecy pact.
Yeah, I think to a degree ...
It's a bit hard to say, but put it this way.
The the fifth I would would have to put
a very persuasive case to the other four,
not to quarantine them from the secret network.
And so Huawei is crucial for that reason,
but also it's the biggest telecommunications
equipment supplier in the world.
Kelley communications is growing in importance.
The only major competitors are from Europe.
There are no major US suppliers
of this kind of telecommunications equipment.
And so Beijing believes it can dominate
the global telecommunications market
and all of the implications of that through
through Huawei,
which is why when Canada, at the request of
the United States,
arrested they chief financial officer of Huawei
Meng Wanzhou in Canada,
Beijing has been desperate to get her back.
This is a really big deal for Beijing,
and indeed it is for Canada and the United
States as well.
So with all this, do you think the Australian
government has done enough,
or what would you like to see done?
I think we're seeing the start of the pushback
even in Australia.
We need to say the laws enforced.
We need to see people prosecuted under them.
There are a whole lot of other administrative
measures.
For example, the Australian government has
slowed down,
and in some cases stop the visas of Chinese
scientists
coming to Australian universities to work
with Australian scientists,
particularly on high tech research.
Some of which has military applications.
And when it was discovered that some of the
Chinese scientists
coming to Australia to work on cutting edge
technologies,
some of them are actually officers of the
People's Liberation Army.
This sent a chill through the intelligence
and defense networks of Australia.
They didn't know that until it was revealed,
particularly through the research of Alex
Joski.
And the same thing is happening in the United
States,
in Canada and elsewhere.
So we're just waking up to this level of penetration,
and I think we've got a long way to go before
we understand
the full nature of influence and interference
and develop
the tools to protect national sovereignty
and democratic institutions from CCP interference.
Now I know in Silent Invasion you make it
very clear
that you are talking about Chinese Communist
Party,
not the Chinese people or Chinese Australians.
And yet you still get accused of racism.
Not just by Chinese officials but by other
Australian politicians.
Yes.
How do you deal with that?
Well, fortunately I'm quite confident in the
fact that
I'm not an anti-Chinese racist.
I've got a pretty good history going back
some decades of calling out,
arguing against, writing about, researching
racism in Australia.
But what of course the Communist Party propaganda
department does
is attempts to ... When people like me make
claims
about Chinese Communist Party influence,
they try to throw sand in our eyes
with this accusation that it is anti-Chinese
and that any criticism of the Chinese Communist
Party is a defamation.
A libel against the Chinese people.
But the truth is that quite a lot of the work
that went into my book came from Chinese sources,
Chinese Australian academics, Chinese Australian
journalists.
The book itself was launched in Sydney
by a large group of Chinese Australians.
And a few weeks ago, a Chinese language edition
of the book
was published in Taiwan and is already selling
well I'm told in Hong Kong, in Taiwan.
So it's a very intense interest.
Because the point is in all of this, Chris,
that the greatest victims in Australia
of Chinese Communist Party influence activities,
are Chinese Australians.
And so it's regrettable, let's say, to use
a mild word,
that some Australian politicians
and also some academics and Sinologists,
not to mention a CCP activists on social media,
constantly make this accusation.
What we've seen though is that people from
both the left
and the right of politics in Australia,
and the left of the right,
are public debate in Australia,
have woken up to the threat of CCP interference
in Australia.
So it's as in the United States.
I've just been in Washington DC, and resisting,
pushing back against CCP influence in the
United is,
I think it's true to say,
the only major issue where there is a bipartisan
position.
It's really amazing how the communist party
can bring us all together.
Yes indeed.
And there's no accident.
I mean, I mean people on both the left and
the right
value and love the democratic institutions.
The freedom of speech, the national sovereignty,
the projection of parliament or government
from foreign interference.
That cuts across the ideological spectrum,
or at least it should.
Ideally.
Are you aware that often Chinese media,
will use the words of,
the criticisms of Australian politicians against
you in their reports?
Yeah, I've noticed that.
There was a particularly rabid article in
the global times,
the Communist parties kind of nationalist
tabloid.
And in it's English language version it launched
an attack on my book.
And the way it did it was it quoted prominent
Australian politicians
who like Bob Carr, who's sometimes known as
Beijing Bob.
Not by me, but others, Paul Keating and a
number of others,
who vigorously attack me and my book for its
alleged racism.
And of course the Global Times were very happy
to quite them.
And it accompanied this story with a mock
up photograph of my book,
Silent Invasion, being flushed down a toilet.
Sometimes CCP propaganda can be quite scatological.
But my question,
was it a regular toilet or a squat toilet?
It was a western style toilet.
Hey, that's not so bad.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, Clive, thank you very much for joining
us today.
It's a pleasure catching up with you and hearing
good news.
Would you say?
I think there are grounds for optimism,
where we were all pretty pessimistic two years
ago.
So the Western world, the democratic nations
are starting to push back.
It's only the beginning.
We won't know whether it succeeds for another
10 years,
but at least things have turned in Washington
and in Canberra,
and even in Canada.
And so I think there are grounds
for believing that we can protect our democratic
institutions
from the influence of this authoritarian power.
So yeah, I'm moderately optimistic.
Moderately optimistic.
I'll take that.
Thanks, Chris.
Thanks for joining us today.
Cheers.
Thanks for watching the interview with Clive.
He actually has much more to reveal to us.
Do you want to give us a sample?
Well, I've been in Canada and in Washington,
and there's been some pretty extraordinary
revelations
about the extent of CCP influence.
Canada and the United States are really
just starting to come to terms with it.
So it's big stuff.
So if you want to hear some of those extraordinary
revelations,
listen to the China unscripted podcast
where I sit down with Clive,
with Matt and Shelly.
It's a blast.