On this episode of China Uncensored,
a beautiful woman wants to go to China,
and the Chinese regime is freaking out.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I'm your host Chris Chappell.
There is a terrifying force sweeping the world,
and we are helpless against it.
I'm not talking about ISIS.
I'm talking about beautiful women.
Oh, beauty queens!
It's so unfair!
You look so beautiful,
and I look like the bad guy from The Matrix.
Now sure, when some people think of beauty
queens, they think of this:
"I believe that our education,
like such, as
in South Africa and the Iraq,
everywhere like such as, and."
But that isn't always the case.
That was Miss Teen USA.
But Miss World is different.
Their motto is "Beauty With a Purpose."
That that's why they were so thrilled to have
Chinese-born Canadian Anastasia Lin win Miss
World Canada this year.
"Anastasia Lin was crowned Miss World Canada
in May.
She has spoken out about religious persecution
in China,
and acted in films that highlight human rights
issues."
"The 25-year-old actress testified at a U.S.
Congressional hearing on religious persecution
in China in July."
Wow. That's actually pretty awesome.
That is "beauty with a purpose."
One reason she was inspired to speak out about
freedom of belief in China is the Chinese
regime's persecution of Falun Gong
a meditation practice.
She practices Falun Gong herself.
And if you've watched China Uncensored before,
you know that Chinese authorities throw a
fit at the mere mention of Falun Gong.
That's why
even though initially Chinese state-media
were proud to report that a Chinese-born contestant
had won Miss World Canada
they used a fake name for her.
And obviously didn't tell her whole story.
Later, when Anastasia's win and activism gained
more international media attention,
Chinese security officials threatened her
father,
who's still living in China.
So he called her and asked her to stop talking
about human rights.
"My initial reaction was of course I'm not
going to speak about this anymore.
My family's in danger.
But, after about a few days of thinking,
I realized, if they're able to silence me
now,
I won't ever get a chance to speak again.
Cause they know that [if] this tactic will
work on me,
I will submit to their manipulation this way."
Not only did Anastasia refuse to submit to
China's manipulation,
so did Miss World Canada's national organizers.
During the run-up to this year's pageant,
they received a mysterious threat:
"Don't be surprised if your sponsors start
pulling out due to an insulted Chinese government."
Not only did Miss World Canada ignore the
threat,
they forwarded the email to Anastasia.
And when the two Chinese judges intentionally
gave her a score of zero out of ten,
organizers ignored them, too.
Score one for Anastasia and for the folks
who run Miss World Canada.
And this courage in the face of threats is
why so many fans have been hoping she'll win
the international Miss World finals next month.
It'll make both Chinese people and Canadians
look good.
There's just one problem. Next month's finals
will be held in China.
"Anastasia Lin, the reigning Miss World Canada,
needs an invitation from the Chinese host
venue to apply for a visa that she says other
contestants have already received."
And she never got that invitation letter.
"So without the invitation letter from China
I cannot apply for the visa."
And rehearsals started on Monday.
It's just like that episode of Gossip Girl."So...
When's the party?"
"Saturday. And you're kinda not invited."
Wait, does that mean the CCP is Blair?
Anyway, not to worry.
Because this is the perfect opportunity for
Miss World to show that the "Beauty With a
Purpose" pageant won't let China get away
with using scare tactics to intimidate…
Wait. What's that Shelley?
They are letting them get away with it?!
According to the Daily Beast,
Miss World pageant organizers basically told
Anastasia, sorry,
there's nothing we can do.
You need China's invitation letter to get
the visa.
And since you didn't get the letter by last
Friday,
I guess you can't participate.
Now this may seem like a weird change of heart
for the Miss World organization, but it's
really not.
The folks who were so supportive of Anastasia's
activism before represented Miss World Canada.
But the finals in China are run by the larger
organization,
Miss World Limited.
It's a British company headquartered in London.
So naturally, Anastasia flew to London to
talk to them.
They told her they were too busy to meet with
her.
Then, as a media firestorm began to descend
on Miss World for,
you know, helping the Chinese regime intimidate
a Canadian citizen,
they told reporters,
"We do not know what is in a contestant's
background that would cause their visa applications
to be rejected."
Um... Falun Gong is what's in the contestant's
background, ok?
Did you even read about your own contest winner?
It's really not that big a mystery.
Or maybe Miss World Limited just doesn't have
time to deal with this.
But you know what they do have time for?
Millions of dollars.
You see, this year's Miss World will be held
in Sanya city on China's Hainan Island.
Since 2003, the Miss World Competition has
been held there seven times.
Six of those times were in a theater they
built specifically for the pageant.
This is great publicity for Sanya, and great
for China's overall soft-power propaganda.
That's why, instead of charging Miss World
to use facilities,
the Chinese city paid Miss World 4.8 million
dollars to be allowed to host them.
Not only that,
but Miss World was also allowed to keep all
the broadcasting fees paid by TV networks
outside of China.
So rather than demanding Anastasia's entry
into China,
or changing venues as a matter of principle,
the pageant will be held in the nice custom-built
Chinese theater, as the British organization
pockets loads of money.
See? "Beauty With a Purpose."
Money. Money's the purpose.
But perhaps there is something you can do.
Because if we allow China to stop Canada's
most beautiful woman from participating in
Miss World,
what will happen when China holds the winter
Olympics in 2022?
Should we also let them block any athlete
who says something critical about the Chinese
regime?
That's why one Canadian, presumably this guy...
“After you, ma’am”
...has started an online petition
where you can ask Chinese leader Xi Jinping
to let Anastasia into China for the Miss World
pageant.
"Because it's the right thing to do."
The link is in description below if you want
to join.
Show the Chinese Communist Party that they
can't bully the world into submission.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell.
See you next time.