On this episode of China Uncensored,
China's economy is seriously slowing down.
And that is not good for America.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I'm your host, Chris Chappell.
China's economy is slowing down
more than ever before.
Last year, China missed its official GDP growth
target.
And many experts say China's economic growth
was probably even slower than that.
This month, at the National People's Congress,
the government announced it's replacing its
GDP growth target with a target range:
which I guess is easier to hit-slash-fake.
But most importantly,
it's even lower than last year
meaning Chinese leaders are acknowledging
that things are getting worse.
But don't worry. They have a plan.
For more, I'm joined by China Uncensored producer
Matt Gnaizda.
Thanks Chris.
So first, how is the Chinese economy doing
right now?
Well, Chris, it's definitely slowing down.
But even the Central Government doesn't know
exactly by how much,
because city and provincial officials have
been making up local GDP growth figures for years.
That seems like a problem.
Yeah. Plus, China is struggling with growing
debt,
lower commodities prices, real estate bubbles,
a shaky stock market,
and, you know, some other things.
But at the National People's Congress this
month,
a big focus was on manufacturing.
What did they say?
The Finance Minister said Chinese wages are
too high,
and workers have too many rights.
Wow, spoken like a true communist.
Well, the Chinese government has a valid argument
to keep wages low.
What's that?
The cost of labor in China has been rising
so much that a lot of companies are looking
to get their stuff made elsewhere.
"Long-term, I'm looking at possibly thinking
of production in another third world country."
So now Chinese leaders want to boost the economy
in the short-term
by keeping wages down so China's manufacturing
can stay competitive.
It's like, there's all that talk in the US
about China taking American jobs
and now even poorer countries are taking Chinese
jobs.
That's the gist of it.
So is China's plan going to work?
It might. But it's like a game of Jenga.
Every move you make now could lead to a more
serious problem down the line.
Like for one, Chinese leaders already recognize
that in the long-term,
they really need to shift away from low-wage
manufacturing
and develop service and technology industries.
And for two?
For long-term growth,
China needs to increase domestic consumption.
And that can only happen if Chinese citizens
have more money to spend.
Hence the need for higher wages.
And frankly, Chinese domestic consumption
is what America has been hoping for
ever since President Clinton helped China
get into the World Trade Organization.
"This agreement is a good deal for America.
Our products will gain better access to China's
market and every sector from agriculture to
telecommunications to automobiles."
Well, American companies are selling products
in China now.
True, but not nearly as much as they'd hoped.
Instead of America dominating the Chinese
market,
China has been dominating the US market
which CNN explains here.
"We were about equal in 1985,
and we have not risen nearly as much in terms
of the products we send to China."
Ok, so the plan hasn't worked so far
but eventually Chinese people will have the
spending money to buy US products, right?
Well, not if Chinese leaders keep workers'
wages low.
And by the time wages really do go up enough,
it may be too late for American companies.
Because China has spent the last couple decades
creating its own versions of US products
so it doesn't have to buy so much from America.
Like how the Chinese government banned Microsoft
Windows 8,
and replaced it with a homegrown knockoff,
NeoKylin.
Or how the Chinese government banned its agencies
from buying iPhones
and instead encouraged them to buy homegrown
phones like obvious knockoff Xiaomi.
Or how the Chinese military copied the design
of the Hummer,
and created their own Eastern Wind vehicle.
Hmm... it's like there's a pattern here.
There might be.
And the key is that with China's economic
slowdown,
the market for US products there may not get
as big as US companies hope.
So the promise of the US economy benefiting
from helping China grow is looking more and more
like this.
I just don't understand why we're not getting
any closer!
Thanks Matt.
And for an in-depth look at how China's manufacturing
slowdown has affected Chinese workers,
watch this video from our friends at the Financial
Times:
"Some Chinese firms are resorting to the unthinkable.
Importing workers."
So what do you think about China's economic
slowdown? Leave your comments below.
Once again, I'm Chris Chappell. See you next
time.