Bitcoin crashes
After yet another Chinese crackdown
How much power does China have over crypto?
Welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
This episode is sponsored by PC-Doctor Toolbox.
Protect your PC from software crashes, hardware
failures, and the kind of glitches that make
your life miserable.
Speaking of crashes, Bitcoin!
After hitting a mid-April high of 65,000 dollars,
the price of bitcoin tumbled below 30,000
dollars.
And China is to blame.
You see, the Chinese Communist Party doesn’t
like Bitcoin.
For one, the Party can’t control it.
And for two, the Chinese regime is spending
big to create its own digital currency.
Which it would control.
Ironically though, China is where most of
the bitcoin mining happens, particularly here
in Sichuan Province.
Basically, enormous computer banks are used
to verify bitcoin transactions, and you get
rewarded with bitcoin.
It’s an energy intensive process.
And thanks to China’s massive reliance on
coal, China has the energy to fuel it.
Until this week, when Chinese authorities
ordered 90% of China’s Bitcoin mining operations
to shut down.
Local electric companies in Sichuan were ordered
“to immediately stop supplying power to
crypto mining projects.”
And “local authorities [were banned] from
approving new mining projects.”
But that’s not all.
The Chinese regime isn’t just going after
Bitcoin miners.
They’re also going after people who use
it.
And they’re getting major Chinese banks
to help.
I’ll explain more after the break.
Welcome back.
And just a reminder, if you like China Uncensored,
we do accept Bitcoin.
Visit chinauncensored.tv/support to find out
how you can help us fight YouTube demonetization
with Bitcoin.
So 90% of China’s Bitcoin mining has been
shut down.
There’s actually a big silver lining to
that, which I’ll get to in a moment.
But the Chinese Communist Party is also getting
major Chinese state-run banks and so-called
private Chinese companies involved in the
latest crackdown.
The People’s Bank of China summoned these
groups “and told them to ‘strictly implement’
recent notices and guidelines from authorities
on curbing risks tied to bitcoin and cryptocurrency.”
And in China, the main risk tied to Bitcoin
is using it.
Financial firms were told to identify customers
using or trading crypto.
And cut off their ability to send or receive
money.
Five major Chinese banks wanted to show how
much they agree with the Party’s new crypto
directives.
So they took the initiative.
They said they’re going to “Prohibit the
use of their accounts for virtual currency
transactions.
They pledged to promptly put a stop to such
transactions, close bank accounts and report
signs of such activities to the authorities.”
“They also called on members of the public
to report virtual currency-related transactions
to the banks.”
Yes, your neighbors can turn you in for using
bitcoin.
Modern problems require modern cultural revolutions.
And recently, Chinese police arrested over
a thousand people for alleged money laundering
with crypto.
Obviously if the Chinese Communist Party says
these people were committing crimes, it must
be true.
And as I mentioned, so-called private Chinese
companies are joining the crackdown too.
Like China’s version of PayPal, AliPay . That
is of course owned by Jack Ma, one of China’s
richest men.
Who disappeared for three months after criticizing
Chinese regulators.
Don’t worry, he wasn’t dead.
He reappeared.
After a major crackdown on his tech empire.
And now he’s just lying low, focusing on
hobbies.
His hobbies include reading, painting, and
staying out of prison by doing whatever the
Communist Party wants.
Like cracking down on crypto.
Alipay said it will monitor and investigate
accounts for using crypto, and block or remove
those users.
That’s huge, since Alipay is used by more
than one billion people, and 80 million merchants.
Alipay also plans to use algorithms to detect
so-called abnormal transactions, flag them,
and restrict certain accounts from receiving
money.
I see no potential for abuse there.
Alipay also said merchants using cryptocurrencies
will be blacklisted and banished from the
platform.
Now this is hardly the Chinese Communist Party’s
first crackdown on crypto.
“Several years ago [China] imposed bans
on domestic cryptocurrency exchanges and digital-currency
fundraisings known as initial coin offerings.”
And according to Forbes, “The cryptocurrency
market has still not recovered from when China
announced its intensifying regulatory crackdown
on cryptocurrencies in mid-May.”
“The market’s total value, now around
$1.4 trillion, is around 56% of what it was
just over a month ago.”
In other words, it’s dropped by nearly half.
But as I said, there’s a silver lining to
all this.
As the Global Times says, as a result of this
ban, “Chinese miners must form alliances
to migrate overseas, to places such as North
America and Russia.”
In the long run, getting the majority of Bitcoin
mining out of China and out from under the
thumb of the Chinese Communist Party is good.
It means that the Party won’t ever be able
to manipulate Bitcoin transactions by controlling
more than half of the mining power.
And that protects everyone who invests in
Bitcoin.
And this episode is sponsored by PC-Doctor
Toolbox.
Computer and software crashes, hardware failures,
and general computer slowdowns are way too
common.
And they can come up during the worst times—like
during a business meeting, or when you're
traveling away from home, and your trusted
IT person isn’t around.
If you're concerned about the health of your
computer and want tools to prevent untimely
system issues, you should be using PC-Doctor
Toolbox.
Stop crashes before they happen.
And we have a special 50% off discount just
for China Uncensored viewers: Use the link
and coupon code below to take advantage of
this limited time offer.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.