On this episode of China Uncensored,
China uncensors America.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored. I’m your
host, Chris Chappell.
You know, a lot of you have said things like,
“Hey Chris, stop criticizing China!
You should do America Uncensored.”
Well, guess what?
China Central Television has already done
it for me!
Last month, state-run CCTV broadcast
this documentary to millions of households across China.
As they pursue human rights,
does the US judge other countries,
or are they equal with them?
This is the human rights record of the human
rights defender.
So, I decided to watch this 45-minute, awkwardly
titled documentary.
Fortunately, they added English subtitles
to the version on their US website.
It begins...here.
Now don’t worry, not everything they point
out happened five decades ago.
But it’s true, the US army did some pretty
terrible things in Vietnam.
CCTV then goes on to describe
a dozen other more recent human rights problems America has.
For example, police violence.
And privacy violations.
And of course, racism.
After watching all this,
I was absolutely outraged, because...
I actually agree with CCTV.
America does have problems.
And CCTV is absolutely right to point them
out.
I was even going to say so in the comments
below
but CCTV’s comments section seems to be
disabled.
But my point is, exposing America’s problems
is healthy.
It helps us improve.
That’s why America’s founding fathers
wanted a free press.
Americans are pointing out America’s problems,
too.
For every single problem CCTV talks about,
there have already been public protests
that the police permitted, and the American
media covered.
In fact, CCTV used American media coverage
of those protests in their documentary.
Americans have protested everything.
The Vietnam War.
Police brutality.
Mass surveillance.
Racism.
Because in America,
the government and media don’t pretend that
America doesn’t have its own problems.
Even elected officials here are free to speak
their minds:
"I'm Matt Rosendale and this is how I look from a government drone.
Spying on our citizens
that’s just wrong.
I'm Matt Rosendale and I approve this message."
And so while I agree with CCTV that there
really are human rights problems in the US,
it’s their conclusion that has a major flaw.
Dialogue and not criticism,
cooperation and not antagonism
are the correct path for
promoting the human rights
of every country.
What they’re really saying is: Don’t criticize
China until you fix your own problems first.
By that logic, during World War II,
America should never have helped liberate
Nazi concentration camps
because America had its own internment camps
for the Japanese.
Look, if everyone had to be perfect before
they could point out other people's issues,
what kind of world would we live in?
America isn’t great because it doesn’t
have problems.
America has lots of problems.
America is great because it gives Americans
the ability to publicly address those problems.
We even have an entire genre of comedy shows
that are all doing some version of America Uncensored.
So when CCTV asks,
"As they pursue human rights,
does the US judge other countries,
or are they equal with them?"
I say, no, the US is not equal with China.
Not until I can go to China,
interview experts there who can speak freely,
use footage of Chinese protests broadcast
by local Chinese media,
criticize Chinese policy however I want,
and upload my videos to a China-based website...
without being “harmonized.”
But until then,
I’ll just have to keep uncensoring China
from the good ol’ U.S. of A.
And look, if CCTV wants to upload their propaganda
documentary to a US-based website,
I say go for it.
Just don't disable the comments.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
Don't forget to comment below however you
want.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell. See you
next time.