Hong Kong needs to be more “patriotic”
According to China’s Communist officials
Welcome to
China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.\h
The Chinese Communist Party is ordering Hong
Kong to be more patriotic.
But before we begin, YouTube is demonetizing
a lot of our videos, and they’re secretly
unsubscribing people.
You can help us stand up to censorship and
ensure you get notified of new episodes by
supporting us on Patreon.com/China Uncensored,
for as little as a dollar an episode.
Hong Kong has been embroiled in a pesky pro-democracy
movement the Chinese Communist Party just
can’t seem to crush.
Which is why the Communist Party is now saying
Hong Kong must be ruled by patriots.
Yes, beatings will continue until patriotism
is achieved.
The call for patriotism comes from Xia Baolong,
director of the Hong Kong and Macau Affairs
Office.
Nice guy.
Earlier this week he delivered a speech where
he said “Hong Kong should be governed by
‘patriots.’”
Now that might sound vague and...unnerving.
After all, how can you tell who is a Patriot?
Well, it’s really simple.
According to Erick Tsang, Secretary for Constitutional
and Mainland Affairs, “You cannot say that
you are patriotic but you do not love the
leadership of the Chinese Communist Party
or you do not respect it—this does not make
sense.
Patriotism is holistic love.”
Holistic love.
You love all of the Party.
From the honeyed face of Winnie the Pooh to
the ethnic cleansing in Xinjiang.
Makes sense.
After all, the Communist Party believes love
is never having to say you’re sorry.
For killing people and taking their stuff.\h
This call for patriotism in Hong Kong actually
goes back to a speech made by former Chinese
leader Deng Xiaoping in 1984.
This is when he was trying to lay out the
One Country, Two Systems model the Chinese
Communist Party would eventually use...and
then when it was no longer convenient, totally
discard.
Hey, broken promises are just a part of being
in love.
Deng Xiaoping said, “What is a patriot?
A patriot is one who respects the Chinese
nation, sincerely supports the motherland’s
resumption of sovereignty over Hong Kong and
wishes not to impair Hong Kong's prosperity
and stability.
Those who meet these requirements are patriots,
whether they believe in capitalism or feudalism
or even slavery.”\h
Makes sense.
To love Chinese communism, you do have to
be okay with their weird combination of capitalism...feudalism...and
slavery.
That speech was in 1984.
Fast forward to today, and Hong Kong officials
may soon be forced to take a patriotic oath.
“Anyone who fails to take the oath—or
is deemed to have done so in an insincere
fashion—would be immediately disqualified
from office and banned from running in elections
for the next five years.”
All this talk of patriotism ties into major
changes coming to local elections in Hong
Kong, which I’ll get to in a bit.
But since we now know who is a patriot, how
do we know who is not a patriot?
More after the break.
Welcome back.
So we know according to the Chinese Communist
Party, a patriot is someone who’s okay with
slavery and genocide.
So what are the characteristics of someone
who is not a patriot?
Well, lucky for us, Hong Kong and Macau Affairs
Office director Xia Baolong spelled it out
for us in his recent speech on patriotism.
So who is not a patriot?
Well, he says those are people who: “hysterically
attack the central government by various means;
publicly promote Hong Kong independence; beg
foreign countries to pressure and sanction
China and Hong Kong; violate Hong Kong’s
national security law; challenge the fundamental
system of the country; and refuse to accept
or deliberately distort Hong Kong’s constitutional
order.”
So...these 2 million people, not patriots.
Keep in mind, Hong Kong only has a population
of 7 million, so...the Communist Party might
have to look hard to find patriots.
Which is why the oath of office for district
council members is so important.
You see, the Chinese Communist Party never
let Hong Kongers directly vote for their chief
executive.
They don’t even let them vote for half of
the city’s Legislative Council.
And when Hong Kongers elect the wrong candidates
for the half they can vote for, the candidates
now get disqualified.
But there are still elections for district
councillors.
District councils are the equivalent of local
town councils, and they usually deal with
issues like “littering, rat problems, traffic
flow issues or minibus routes.”
Yes, it’s a glamorous job.
But district councils are the only completely
directly elected positions in Hong Kong.
Which is why they became hugely symbolic during
the protests in 2019.
In a November 2019 district council election,
pro-democracy candidates won 90% of the district
council seats.
The pro-democracy candidates gained control
of 17 out of the 18 district councils.
Previously, all 18 had been controlled by
pro-Beijing officials.
It showed that the people of Hong Kong supported
the pro-democracy protesters.
And it was a huge embarrassment for Beijing.\h
And it was also significant because District
Councilors get to choose 117 members of the
1200 seat committee that elects Hong Kong’s
Chief Executive.
Now almost all those other seats are controlled
by Beijing allies, so there’s no way those
District Councilors could have a decisive
impact.\h
But the District Council gets a few seats
in Hong Kong’s legislature, too.
And that meant that for the first time ever
the pro-democracy camp had a chance to actually
win a majority in the legislature.
That would give them actual power to stop,
or at least slow down, the Chinese Communist
Party’s encroachment over Hong Kong.
Which is why last year’s Legislative Council
elections were postponed.
It was not because of the coronavirus.
After those legislative elections were postponed,
the Chinese Communist Party forced out all
of the pro-democracy legislators.
That’ll stop them from trying to win elections.\h
And now that Beijing has taken care of Hong
Kong’s legislature, it’s time for Beijing
to disqualify district councillors, too.
And stop them from running in elections.
But maybe I’m being cynical.
Because Hong Kong Chief Executive Carrie Lam
says that the patriots-only rule is not meant
to exclude democrats from politics.\h
It’s only meant to exclude the unpatriotic
ones that do things like...believe in democracy.\h
So here’s what Xia Baolong’s speech suggests
to me: At the beginning of March, the Communist
Party will hold what it calls the Two Sessions.
That's an annual gathering of the Party’s
political elite.
China’s rubber stamp Congress will then...rubber
stamp any policy action the Party wants.\h
And I wouldn’t be surprised if there’s
some kind of further reform to make Hong Kong
even more “patriotic.”
It’s all part of the Party’s holistic
love.\h
And now it’s time for me to answer questions
from a member of the China Uncensored 50 Cent
Army, fans who support China Uncensored on
the crowd funding website Patreon.
Samy Fay asks, “Last weekend.
I went thru a lot of the Unscripted episodes.
I'm loving these and among my favorites where
the ones in which you invited Joshua Philipp.
His historical background is fabulous.
I think another invite should be considered.
No?”
Samy, I’m glad you like the China Unscripted
podcast!
For those of you who aren’t familiar with
it, we’ve had loads of guests on.
But one of the stand outs was Joshua Philipp,
host of the show Crossroads.
He gave us a lot of really mind blowing information
about the history of Communism.
I’ll put a link to those two episodes below.
We had briefly talked to him about doing another
episode and rounding out the trilogy, but
we never moved forward with it.
So to all of you watching, would you like
to see that?\h
Thanks for that Samy!
And thank you for watching.
Support China Uncensored.
Join the 50 cent army and get access to lots
of cool perks, like asking me question on
the show, by signing up at Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.\h
See you next time.