On this episode of China Uncensored,
the solution to being criticized
is to hang out with people worse than you!
That’s why I hang out with my producer Matt.
(Matt, off screen): Hey!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
Sorry, I’m just going through some old photos.
I mean you probably saw their Facebook status.
Malaysia just changed its relationship status
with America to
“it’s complicated.”
Never saw it coming.
I mean,
look at at how great these two looked together!
In 2014, Obama became the first president
in nearly half a century
to visit Malaysia.
That’s him and Malaysia’s Prime Minister,
Najib Razak.
Najib let the US make surveillance flights
over the South China Sea
from Malaysian territory.
Then the two of them spent Christmas Eve together
playing golf in Hawaii.
I mean, the countries have basically the same flag!
But then this guy came along and ruined everything.
Now Najib is calling China “a true friend,”
and wants to take their relationship to “new heights.”
Najib is in China this week.
He’s already signed an agreement to buy
four Chinese naval vessels
for about 34 billion dollars.
It’s Malaysia's first big defense deal with
China.
And frankly, a lot to spend on a first date.
More shocking,
Malaysia has “pledged with Beijing to
handle South China Sea disputes bilaterally.”
It wasn’t supposed to be like this.
The Philippines, Malaysia, Vietnam, and Brunei
have all been in long-standing territorial
disputes with China
over the South China Sea.
And Obama was the knight in shining armor,
with his mighty Pivot to Asia,
the hero who pledged to protect the little
guy
from the big red dragon.
But now,
says Prime Minister Najib,
one should not let “former colonial powers”
“lecture countries they once exploited
on how to conduct their own internal affairs.”
Wow.
He sounds like...
"I will break up with America.
I would rather go to Russia and to China.
First the Philippines,
now Malaysia.
It’s looking more like dominos.
No, the other Dominos.
Yeah, it looks good now,
but you’re gonna regret it later.
Because if the Philippines and now Malaysia
have decided to negotiate their disputes with
China bilaterally,
that weakens everyone’s ability to negotiate
as a bloc
with US muscle behind them.
So the real winner here is China.
Divide and conquer.
It’s the same strategy kids with divorced
parents use
to get more Christmas gifts.
Now I can’t say for sure why Malaysia or
the Philippines
have decided to go this route.
But...China is Malaysia’s biggest trading
partner.
The second biggest for the Philippines.
And, let’s be honest,
even in his awesome knight costume,
Obama hasn’t been able to accomplish much
when it comes to resolving the South China
Sea dispute.
But within just four months of taking office,
Philippines president Duterte seems to have
solved the problem...
at least for for Filipino fishermen.
Maybe Najib sees that and thinks,
if you give a little,
you’ll get a little.
All you have to do is give up your territorial
claims.
Now you might think,
this route the Philippines and now Malaysia
are taking
seems a bit like giving up ownership of your
house
in exchange for the privilege of renting it.
It sounds like a lousy deal.
But there could also be another reason for
their
cozying up with China.
Remember how the US criticized Duterte’s
extra-judicial killings
in his war on drugs?
And then reneged on selling assault rifles
to The Philippines?
And then Dutere was all like...
"Mister Obama, you can go to hell."
Well, a similar thing back in July—
when the US sort of accused Malaysia’s prime
minister
of stealing money from his own country.
Long story short,
three-and-a-half billion dollars went missing
from a Malaysian sovereign wealth fund.
The US filed lawsuits to seize some of the
assets
the money bought.
The investigation is still ongoing
and Prime Minister Najib has not been formally
charged with anything.
But it did kind of put a strain US-Malaysia
relations.
So...China!
The Chinese regime won’t criticize you
for extrajudicial killings or corruption.
Obviously.
So if that’s your thing,
well,
I can see why you’d want to ditch the red-white-and-blue
knight
for the red dragon.
So what do you think about Malaysia's new
ties with China?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.