well as you say it is very striking that just as\h
we talked earlier about the fact that uh in the us\h\h
the uk even some european countries uh australia\h
uh and others um there is this rethinking\h\h
going on and to varying degrees uh um at the same\h
time the vatican seems to have gone in precisely\h\h
the opposite direction at a time when we're\h
seeing the worst what many would say is the is\h\h
the most severe crackdown on human rights uh in in\h
general in china um since the tiananmen massacre\h\h
and probably the most severe crackdown on religion\h
uh since the cultural revolution i mean when the\h\h
vatican china agreement was was first\h
reached two years ago and it was\h\h
made as a provisional agreement for two years i\h
was critical of it at the time but i i at least\h\h
was willing to give uh the pope and the vatican\h
the benefit of the doubt i i didn't doubt that\h\h
that their motives were uh to um better protect\h
uh the freedoms of at least catholics and ideally\h\h
religious freedom more broadly and so i thought\h
although i was skeptical that this agreement would\h\h
in any way achieve that i i thought well let's see\h
what happens in the two years that it's in place\h\h
um my concern now with the renewal or at least the\h
likely renewal i think it technically it's it will\h\h
be renewed um uh shortly i know the vatican\h
has told beijing they want to renew it and\h\h
um strangely given that beijing's got everything\h
they want out of it um uh they my understanding\h\h
is beijing hasn't yet responded but let's assume\h
it is renewed which i think is a fair assumption\h\h
um firstly the text of the agreement is still two\h
years on a secret text we we know that it relates\h\h
to the appointment of bishops but the actual\h
detail of the agreement remains a confidential\h\h
text even cardinal zen who is basically the only\h
chinese cardinal um who's free to speak his mind\h\h
uh just about um uh he has has not seen the uh\h
text um so if it's such a good deal why can't\h\h
we all know about it why is it secret yeah the\h
vatican would keep secrets i mean unheard of\h\h
well well that's true that's true but but\h
generally these kind of agreements don't\h\h
shouldn't be secret unless there's really\h
something to hide so um but but also it has\h\h
clearly not achieved assuming the goal behind it\h
was to better protect uh catholics the situation\h\h
for catholics has worsened uh no catholic priest\h
that was in jail before the agreement was reached\h\h
has been released to my knowledge and quite a few\h
have been arrested or disappeared since then so\h\h
it hasn't led to any improvement we've seen um\h
not only what's happened in hong kong but also\h\h
what many would say uh may well be a genocide\h
uh facing the weakers um and this agreement\h\h
seems to have brought the pope silence we haven't\h
heard him say anything not even a prayer for hong\h\h
kong for christians in china uh for the uyghurs\h
uh for for any of these issues so it's uh\h\h
i mean i've written quite a lot about it\h
and um i'm probably not the vatican's i've\h\h
never been the ccp's favorite person but\h
i'm probably not the vatican's either now\h\h
um but it's it makes no sense to me uh the ccp\h
gets everything they want out of it in terms of\h\h
uh control and dominance and i don't see what\h
the vatican or the catholic church gains at all
you