On this episode of China Uncensored,
is it war on the open sea?
Lies!
Betrayal!
Backstabbing!
Things are heating up in the South China Sea
as the Chinese regime has a massive confrontation
with Australian warships!
Australia is sending warships through the
South China Sea.
The story was first reported by Australia’s
national broadcaster, ABC.
An official described the confrontation between
Chinese
and Australian warships as “polite, but
‘robust.’”
Yeah, well you know what else is robust?
Australia’s international engagement!
Clearly we’re on the brink of World War
III.
And what does Christopher Pyne,
Australia’s defence minister
and most annoying man in Australia have to
say about
the most dangerous confrontation of the 21st
century?
He said, “I think ‘confrontation’ is
somewhat of a
tabloid-style description of what goes on
in the South China Sea very regularly.”
Did he say, tabloid?
Uhhh, right, how dare all the media talk about
it
like it was some big confrontation!
Oh...they’re all calling it a challenge
now.
Okay.
Uhh, well...you know,
the fine journalists over at the Express in
the UK
called it a confrontation that might bring
World War III—
and they’re not a tabloid.
I mean, look at what other fine reporting
they do.
NASA SHOCK: Huge ‘alien herd of animals
found
in space probe images of Mars’
Or “Monstrous 7ft creature pictured
after ‘MURDEROUS RAMPAGE’”
Oh!
And “End of the world 2018:
Will the Rapture occur on April 23?
SHOCK prediction says YES.”
That’s today!
Very important news!
I’m glad I have been so well informed...
Look, it’s hard to make money with news
these days.
Is it so wrong jazz things up a little bit?
What’s that Shelley?
Oh, yes it is.
For everyone else.
Not for me, obviously.
This is a comedy show.
Okay, so details of the “confrontation”
are actually bit sparse.
But what we do know is that three Australian
warships
sailed through the South China Sea
on their way to Vietnam.
The problem is, there’s a wee bit of disagreement
about what’s international waters,
and what’s part of China.
See, the Chinese Communist Party says that
everything within this 9 dash line
is China’s territorial waters...
...and that it has been since ancient times.
But if that isn’t convincing enough for
you,
the Chinese regime went ahead
and built artificial islands in the South
China Sea.
And put missiles on them.
China’s Defense Ministry confirmed
that last week’s confrontation,
I mean, challenge, did happen.
Typically when this happens with American
warships,
the Chinese navy says,
“You’re in Chinese territorial waters,
get out.”
And the American ships respond,
“Uh, no, this is international waters.
Deal with it.”
In fact, the US regularly engages in these
“freedom of navigation operations”
every couple of months.
That really doesn’t float the Chinese regime’s
boat.
It’s hard to militarize a region and seize
control
from six other competing claims...
...when the US constantly reminds everyone
that your navy isn’t all that.
However, it’s unusual for Australia to do
this.
Especially since China is Australia’s biggest
trading partner.
In the past Australian officials have been
hesitant
to confront the Chinese regime.
I just hope the Chinese navy made sure to
translate
their message into Australian English.
“Listen up, ya bloody drongos.
This here’s fair dinkum Chinese waters.
No bogans allowed.”
But the relationship between China and Australia
is not doing so well lately.
Just look at the tension between this kangaroo
and panda
in my favorite Chinese state-run media the
Global Times.
Earlier this month, everyone in Australia
freaked out over news the Chinese Communist
Party
is considering setting up a military base
on the island nation of Vanuatu,
1,200 miles off Australia’s coast.
The Chinese regime denies it, of course.
But several years ago,
they also said they weren’t militarizing
the South China Sea,
and look where we are now.
It’s hard to deny the Chinese regime
has been expanding its military reach.
Not just in the South China Sea,
but also all along the Indian ocean.
That’s the String of Pearls theory—
the Chinese regime is making deals with countries
that could eventually mean port access
for the Chinese navy.
But Australia’s recent freedom of navigation
operation
seems to a way of pushing back.
Now sure, Chinese state media may have
some harsh words for them.
Like saying that “Australia has a twisted
attitude toward China”
and that Australia really ought to
“work with China and other regional countries
to maintain peace and stability” in the
South China Sea.
But ultimately,
when Australia pushes back on the South China
Sea,
there’s not much the Chinese Communist Party
is going to do.
Yes, they’ve been able to throw their weight
around
with smaller countries in the past.
But times are changing.
Now there’s the threat of a trade war with
the US—
a trade war that Chinese authorities had better
resolve
because China has the most to lose.
So in this political climate,
the Chinese regime can’t afford
to play hardball with Australia.
The Chinese economy is already under serious
threat.
And that’s not tabloidy.
Even top Communist officials are talking about
it.
So if ever there were a time for Australia
to challenge the Chinese Communist Party,
this is it.
And Australia knows it.
So what do you think about the “confrontation”
between Australia and China?
Leave your comments belows!
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Hey, if you like China Uncensored’s approach
to China news,
versus say...the tabloids,
consider supporting us on the website Patreon!
It allows fans of the show to contribute
for each episode we publish.
Viewer support is what saved the show
after YouTube took away most of our ad revenue.
So visit pateron.com/chinauncensored
to find out how you can support the show
and get some cool stuff in exchange.