On this episode of China Uncensored,
Trade War, huh!
Good God.
What is it good for?
Well it’s actually complicated…
Welcome back to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
My favorite topic—
War!
It makes great headlines and is good for views.
Except when it’s a trade war.
Then, eyes kind of start to gloss over.
Even mine.
But—what’s happening right now
between the United States and China
is actually super interesting.
Because President Donald Trump has done something
truly unusual for a US president—
at least when it comes to China.
He’s kept a campaign promise.
Here he is two years ago
at the 2016 Republican National Convention.
Our horrible trade agreements with China and
many others,
will be totally renegotiated…
We are going to enforce all trade violations,
against any country that cheats.
And here he is last week.
"China has been taking advantage of the United
States
for many years.
Really, if you look at it since the start
of the World Trade Organization
and they have really done a number in this
country.”
Weird.
It’s the same message.
And over the past year,
it seems Trump has actually been taking the
Chinese government to task.
On trade issues, at least.
In August 2017, he launched two probes
into unfair trade practices
by China and other countries
in the steel and aluminum industries.
Then in January this year,
he imposed tariffs on solar panels and washing
machines.
Which is basically a tariff on China,
since China makes so many of them.
And then in March, President Trump followed
through
with tariffs on steel and aluminum.
And some began to worry about a trade war.
The Chinese Communist Party certainly wasn’t
happy.
“...we will not hesitate to immediately
make
a fierce counter strike.
We are not ruling out any options for retaliation.”
Are...hugs an option?
Because I’m ready to export!
Wait...What’s that Shelley?
China has a 25% tariff on hug imports!
Forget that.
So the question is, as in any war…
are we all going to die?!
Doesn’t China own tons of US debt?!
There’s almost a 400 billion dollar trade
deficit,
stocks have been up and down,
and China makes most of the world’s umbrellas.
If it rains in New York,
am I going to get wet?!
Yes.
We will all get a little wet.
Here’s what happened next.
The Chinese government put their own tariffs
on $3 billion dollars worth of US imports.
Trump responded by threatening more tariffs
on another $50 billion in Chinese goods.
Then China did the same.
And now Trump has called for the biggest tariffs
yet—
on $100 billion dollars worth of Chinese imports.
And then Xi Jinping said that when Trump’s
momma
sits around the house,
she sits around the house.
And then Trump released a diss track called
“No More Chocolate Cake for You.”
The point is,
a lot of what’s going on right now is trash
talk.
Both sides are trying to raise the stakes
to see who backs down first.
But should the US put tariffs on Chinese goods?
Well, that’s something the US Commerce Department
had actually recommended back in February.
So Trump imposed those tariffs.
And then a miracle happened:
Democrats agreed with Trump.
Like Democratic Senate Minority Leader Chuck
Schumer.
“I don’t agree with President Trump on
a whole lot,
but today, I want to give him a big pat on
the back.
He is doing the right thing when it comes
to China.”
Even Senator Elizabeth Warren supports the
tariffs.
“And, I have to say, when President Trump
says he’s putting tariffs on the table,
I think tariffs are one part
of reworking our trade policy overall.”
And perhaps most surprising of all,
“fake news” CNN is willing to give tariffs
a shot.
“Let’s be honest,
on one big fundamental point,
Donald Trump is right.
China is a trade cheat.”
How heartwarming.
No matter how deep our political divisions,
we can still be united by the fact that
the Chinese Communist Party is a dirty cheater.
That doesn’t mean the tariffs are perfect
or have everyone’s support.
The Chinese Communist Party may be cheating,
but imposing tariffs is only a partial solution
to some of the bigger trade problems.
And in the short term,
tariffs make things more expensive,
so that could also hurt US consumers.
That being said, the Chinese Communist Party
has refused to play by the rules
of the World Trade Organization—
so tariffs may be the best available option.
Tariffs are like ordering a salad at McDonald’s.
It’s not what you really want,
but it’s a less unhealthy option than everything
else.
China joined the World Trade Organization
in 2001,
thanks partly to lobbying by former presidents
Bill Clinton and George W. Bush.
They wanted to give US businesses
access to the China market.
And in particular,
President Clinton pitched the idea that
if China’s economy opens up,
it would force the government to make political
reforms.
Well, that definitely worked.
Or not.
And while US businesses have gotten access
to the Chinese market,
many of them are getting their intellectual
property
stolen by their Chinese joint venture partners.
And according to this report
from the United States Trade Representative…
when it comes to exports,
the Chinese government has been subsidizing
local manufacturers,
like steel and aluminum factories—
and that’s allowed it to dump goods on the
US market
at unfairly low prices.
Chinese leaders have repeatedly failed to
follow through
with commitments to facilitate free trade...
...and the Chinese Communist Party has been
increasingly creating an unfair environment
for foreign companies.
The problem is, when China entered the WTO,
the Chinese Communist Party knew that Western
companies
were desperate to access over a billion potential
customers in China.
So desperate, that the Party could cheat and
get away with it.
It’s like when you’re the only kid your
neighborhood with a Nintendo Switch.
They’re coming over to play no matter how
much of a jerk you are.
If a trade war does start,
it might hurt the US in the short term.
For example, US consumers would face rising
prices.
But in a trade war, the country that’s a
net exporter
has the most to lose.
And that’s China.
As the New York Times says,
“Exports account for a big share of Chinese
economic growth.
Because the United States buys so much from
China,
Washington has many more ways to hit Chinese
manufacturers.”
The Chinese Communist Party depends on a stable
economy
to justify its rule,
and the economy is already struggling with
bad debt,
capital flight, and corruption,
just to name a few of the problems.
So if there was a trade war,
China would be hurt more than the US.
But will there be a trade war?
That’s not clear yet.
Like I said earlier,
right now it’s still mostly trash talk.
And trash talk is, of course,
Trump’s original superpower.
Which has confused the heck out of Chinese
leaders.
According to this article,top-level Chinese
officials
are desperately asking American experts
whether Trump is serious or just bluffing.
Well, maybe those Chinese officials
need to watch China Uncensored.
Because we predicted this last year,
right after Trump took office.
Click the link below to check out our episode
“Who would win a US-China Trade War?”
But it’s not just Trump’s trash talk
that’s throwing Chinese officials for a
loop.
Last week Trump suggested that maybe
America should consider rejoining the TPP
trade deal—
which he had rejected last year as a bad deal.
But it is good as a way to put pressure on
China.
And there are signs that the Chinese Communist
Party
could be caving to the pressure.
Chinese leader Xi Jinping recently made a
speech
pledging to open up the Chinese economy and
cut tariffs.
Although Xi’s speech was also pretty similar
to one he made last year, so it’s unclear
whether it means the Chinese Communist Party
will actually make any changes.
It could just be more talk.
Of course China’s foreign ministry wants
you to know
that if there are changes,
pressure has nothing to do with it.
"I can definitely tell you that China’s
announcement
of the significant initiatives on further
opening up
is not related to the current economic and
trade conflicts
between China and the United States.”
Absolutely not.
It’s probably because Donald Trump and Xi
Jinping
are such great friends.
Like Pooh Bear and Tigger.
I know they said Obama was Tigger.
But really, Trump is the right color.
So what do you think of Trump’s tariffs
on China
and the possibility of a trade war?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
For years,
Western business have put up with
a lot of sketchy things
in order to gain access to the China market.
That includes never advertising with, say,
YouTubers critical of the Chinese Communist
Party.
That’s why China Uncensored relies on financial
support
from viewers like you.
Click the orange button to visit Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored,
and find out how you can support our show.