It has recently come to the attention of the relevant departments that
the foreigner Chris Chappell
creator of the so-called "China Uncensored" program
has plans to spread his anti-China rhetoric around the world.
It seems this person has plans to cause chaos in
Hong Kong, Taiwan, and other places
all of which have undeniably been Chinese territory since ancient times.
The aims of this so-called TV host are unclear,
but YouTube viewers have asked him to stop spreading anti-China propaganda,
and many netizens have questioned whether he is funded by the CIA.
Western media reporting on him should be clear-minded.
and not ignorantly follow the declining influence of the United States,
such as by falsely referring to the so-called "China Uncensored"
as a "hilarious YouTube channel" or "informative."
Earlier this week,
the People's Liberation Army General Political Department
issued a notice and called on all friends of China
to put up this wanted poster
so that the world can see the true face of this so-called host.
The relevant departments have provided a link
to download this Wanted poster.
Friends of China should print out this Wanted poster,
and post it on walls and other locations in their country.
All people should make great strides in spreading this message
and stopping the frenzied attacks by anti-China forces.
Additionally, take a photograph of yourself with these posters and
email it to ChinaUncensored@gmail.com
to remind Chris Chappell that he is being watched,
and that he cannot fool the great people of China.
He has made serious mistakes,
and should make a self-examination and correction.