NBA star Lebron James blunders on Hong Kong
While US Lawmakers pass landmark legislation
And a breakthrough in the US-China Trade War?
That and more on this week’s China Uncensored.
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
This week’s China news headlines!
Hong Kong.
The city version of the “this is fine”
dog.
Protests have continued there for 131 days.
Hongkongers are upset about the Chinese Communist
Party
trying to annihilate their freedoms.
And how the Hong Kong government and police
force
are being pawns of the Communist Party.
And definitely the police brutality.
And pro-democracy legislators made very clear
what they think
about Hong Kong Chief Executive Carrie Lam
at her annual policy address this week.
Hong Kong's protests moved inside
the city's legislature on Wednesday.
The city's least popular post-colonial leader
had her annual policy address adjourned
after some lawmakers stood on desks,
chanted protest slogans and held up banners
of Carrie Lam
with blood on her hands.
Hey, that’s Tanya Chan.
I just interviewed her!
I’m glad to see she’s doing well.
The lawmakers were also chanting the popular
slogan
“5 demands, not one less.”
The protesters have 5 demands of the Hong
Kong government,
including an investigation into police brutality.
Carrie Lam had to cancel her speech and do
a pre recorded broadcast later in the day.
But don’t feel too bad for her.
Feel bad for Jimmy Sham.
He’s the head of the Civil Human Rights
Front.
They’re an umbrella group that’s organized
some of the biggest rallies over the past
few months,
including this one from June 16,
with 2 million people,
in a city of only 7 million.
The Civil Human Rights Front has always made
a point of keeping their rallies and marches
peaceful and non violent.
Something the four men who attacked Jimmy
Sham with hammers,
clearly do not value.
That was the second attack on him in less
than two months.
And do you know what Jimmy Sham said
as they put him in the ambulance?
Five demands, not one less.
Sham had head wounds and is still in the hospital,
but he’s going to be ok.
Meanwhile the Civil Human Rights Front
is planning another march on Sunday,
for which they posted this upbeat slogan:
You can’t kill us all.
Historically speaking, that hasn’t stopped
the Communist Party from trying.
Of course, the protests in Hong Kong
have caught the attention of the American
public as well.
Especially thanks to the NBA.
Houston Rockets general manager Daryl Morey
tweeted this image supporting the Hong Kong
protests.
And then the entire NBA attacked him,
because the NBA has 4 billion dollars on the
line in China.
And the Lakers and Brooklyn Nets were also
about to play
an exhibition game there.
Just as the controversy was dying down,
LeBron James also criticized the original
tweet.
We all do have freedom of speech,
but at times there are ramifications
for the negative that can happen
when you’re not thinking of others.
When you’re only thinking of yourself.
I believe he wasn’t educated on the situation
at hand and he spoke.”
Then there was a huge public backlash.
Protesters in Hong Kong burned and trampled
his jersey,
while here at home, critics piled on,
and LeBron James memes are trending on twitter.
Then LeBron said that it was very hard
for the Lakers in China that week,
so Morey should have waited a week to send
the tweet.
Yes, *he’s* had a difficult week.
Meanwhile, the people of Hong Kong
enjoyed sunshine and rainbows
and the police handed bought everyone ice
cream.
But I personally think we’re being too hard
on LeBron James.
After all, he’s single-handedly kept this
story in the news,
giving more people the chance to learn about
what’s happening in Hong Kong
and how repressive the Chinese regime is.
Plus, Lebron has overcome a lot of challenges
in his life
to get where he is.
He is truly an inspiration.
I mean, can you imagine how hard it must be
to play professional basketball without a
spine?
Meanwhile, and I can’t believe I’m saying
this,
American politicians have shown that they
do have a spine.
The US House of Representatives has passed
the Hong Kong Human Rights and Democracy Act.
Hong Kong has special trading status with
the US.
It’s not treated like the rest of Mainland
China,
because it supposedly has rule of law.
But this bill would allow for an annual review
to see if Hong Kong’s legal system
is really autonomous from the rest of China.
And if not,
the US will take Hong Kong’s special trade
status away.
It would also lay out a process for the President
to impose sanctions and travel restrictions
on Hong Kong authorities
who are responsible for arbitrary detention
and torture.
And it makes sure that Hongkongers
who have been arrested for protesting
would still be able to get visas to the US.
The House also passed the PROTECT Hong Kong
Act,
which would ban the export of things like
tear gas to Hong Kong police.
Both bills still have to pass the Senate.
Carrie Lam was not too excited.
“I would like to express extreme regret
that
the U.S. House of Representatives approved
legislation
of the Hong Kong Human Rights and Democracy
Act this morning.
A foreign government or a foreign parliament
is meddling in Hong Kong's internal affair.”
Aww, that’s so cute.
She’s learned to speak exactly like her
masters in Beijing.
But there is some good news for Carrie Lam
in all this.
The Hong Kong people have been nominated for
a Nobel peace prize!
And technically, she’s a Hong Kong people.
Of course the Chinese Communist Party is none
too pleased
by all the attention it’s getting over Hong
Kong.
“Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs spokesman
Geng Shuang
warned American lawmakers to stop meddling
in China’s internal affairs
‘before falling off the edge of the cliff.’”
To be fair he’s been watching a lot of Looney
Toons lately.
While Chinese leader Xi Jinping has been reading
a lot of fairy tales lately.
On a recent trip to Nepal, he warned,
“Anyone who attempts to split any region
from China will perish,
with their bodies smashed and bones ground
to powder.”
Fee-fi-fo-fum, I smell the blood of rebellion.
So the question on everyone’s mind
is whether the new Hong Kong legislation
will affect the US-China Trade War.
There does seem to be some movement on that.
A preliminary deal has been agreed on that
includes
“a commitment by China to buy $40 billion
to $50 billion
of American agricultural products per year.”
That would be much more than before the trade
war.
And President Trump was modest about his success
as usual.
“The deal I just made with China is, by
far,
the greatest and biggest deal
ever made for our Great Patriot Farmers
in the history of our Country.”
Now there’s the question that Trump
even acknowledges about whether US farmers
can even produce that much.
Though I’m sure that problem can be solved
with a little science,
and a little moral flexibility.
Genetically engineered spider corn anyone?
However, the preliminary deal hasn’t been
signed...
and there’s a whole bunch of other things
it doesn’t address.
So the trade war is still not over.
But it could be the start of the human-spider
corn wars.
But it’s not just Hong Kong the US is worried
about.
The White House is also warning about
untrackable Chinese ships carrying Iranian
oil.
The US has imposed oil sanctions on Iran
to tackle the country’s nuclear program.
And any country that buys Iranian oil faces
sanctions too.
But China was the largest importer of Iranian
oil.
Now there’s concerns China will continue
to buy Iranian oil,
but smuggled on untrackable ships.
Of course, when has the Communist Party
ever done anything deceitful?
Accusations have emerged that Apple’s Safari
browser
is sending some user data to the Chinese company
Tencent.
Apparently, Safari has privacy feature
called Fraudulent Website Warning.
And Safari would send information
to Google Safe Browsing and Tencent Safe Browsing.
Oh.
Good.
But Apple responded saying
they don’t share the website of the URL,
and plus it only applies to Mainland China.
So don’t worry.
Apple would never lie to you.
DreamWorks’ latest film Abominable
is being kicked out of theaters in Vietnam.
That’s because of this.
A map used in the movie showing China’s
9-dash line,
China’s territorial claim to the entire
South China Sea.
Apparently even including Taiwan.
Now a Filipino official is calling for that
scene
to be cut in their country.
Which really isn’t fair.
After all, Hollywood has been a part of China
since ancient times.
But don’t worry, it’s not just Hollywood.
Why, ESPN, reporting on the NBA China controversy,
used this graphic.
“Now let’s switch to the NBA,
Lebron and the Lakers arrived in Shanghai
China...”
Yeah, let’s take a look at this.
Not only does this have the 9 dash line,
it also has Taiwan,
and disputed territory with India
called Arunachal Pradesh as part of China.
Now, it’s possible someone might have corrected
this obvious blunder
before it ever aired,
but then again ESPN did tell employees not
to discuss China,
Hong Kong politics in an internal memo.
And now you know why I’ve spent seven years
of my life
making a show warning Americans
about the Chinese Communist Party.
And that’s it for this week’s China news
headlines!
And now it’s time for me to answer a question
from one of you—
a fan who support China Uncensored
with a dollar or more per episode,
by contributing through the crowdfunding website
Patreon.
Logan asks,
Do you feel the South Park Episode “band
in China”
did a good job highlighting a lot of these
issues?
Logan is talking about a recent episode of
South Park
about US companies and Hollywood self censoring
and generally selling out to appease Chinese
censors.
I think they did a great job with that episode.
There’s a reason why people in Hong Kong
are playing it on the streets.
It felt like the episode touched on
the personal experiences of the writers
having to deal with all the Hollywood censorship
to appease the Chinese Communist Party.
And they didn’t pull their punches.
I mean, they even brought up organ harvesting.
That’s about as third rail an issue as you
can get with China.
Really, I think South Park,
combined with the NBA scandal,
did a great job of helping more Americans
than ever
realize that the Chinese Communist Party
is a horrible authoritarian regime,
and just how much control they have in the
United States,
all because of money.
The episode even showed the NBA and Lebron
James—
and this was before the NBA scandal happened
later that week.
Thanks for your question, Logan.
And if you have a question for me
you want to hear answered on the show,
sign up to join the China Uncensored 50 cent
army,
by supporting the show with a dollar or more
per episode.
Again, YouTube is demonetizing us so much
we would have to shut down the show
if it weren’t for your support.
And to everyone, thanks for watching!
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.