On this episode of China Uncensored,
I’ve got SARs!
You know, Special Administrative Regions.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
I’m here in Macau as part of our Pivot to
Asia Tour.
Macau is the often overlooked
Special Administrative Region, or S.A.R.,
of China.
Like Hong Kong, it’s officially under the
One Country, Two Systems policy.
That’s where Hong Kong and Macau are officially
part of China’s territory,
but have their own separate governments,
and currencies, and border control.
It was the agreement the Chinese Communist
Party made
with the former colonial powers in charge—
because, let’s face it, everyone knew
the system in mainland China left something
to be desired.
But that’s about where the similarities
between Hong Kong and Macau end.
And here are 5 major differences.
Number 5: Colonial History
Hong Kong became a British colony in 1842
after the first Opium War.
The British seriously built up the place
and made it into an important, and prosperous,
gateway to mainland China.
But in 1997, the British Empire
reluctantly gave Hong Kong back to China—
under the condition that the Communist Party
allow Hong Kong
to have a high degree of autonomy.
Unsurprisingly, since 1997,
the Communist Party has been working hard
to renege on that promise.
Photos from the handover show that
then-leader Jiang Zemin
had his fingers crossed behind his back the
whole time.
Macau, on the other hand,
was under Portuguese influence for more than
400 years.
Portuguese first settled there in the mid-16th
century,
and it officially became a Portuguese colony
in the 19th century.
It used to be a big trading hub,
but as the Portuguese empire declined,
Macau stopped being as prosperous.
Macau’s handover to China
happened in 1999 with way less of a fuss than
Hong Kong.
Number 4: Languages
The two official languages of Macau are Cantonese
and Portuguese,
even though few people in Macau speak Portuguese
anymore.
Many signs around the city will have Chinese
characters and Portuguese.
But because of the influence of mainland China
and the influx of mainland tourists,
more and more people in Macau are speaking
Mandarin.
Hong Kong, being a former British colony,
has long been dominated by Cantonese and English.
However, in 2012, Mandarin narrowly overtook
English
as the second most commonly spoken language
in Hong Kong,
thanks to efforts by the Chinese Communist
Party to spread Mandarin,
especially in the education system.
Number 3: The Economy
The British turned Hong Kong into a world
city.
Today it’s one of the biggest financial
centers in the world,
called one of the Four Tigers of Asia,
along with Taiwan, Singapore, and South Korea.
Macau’s economy is much smaller than Hong
Kong’s.
It’s also rich, but for
different reasons.
It’s basically Las Vegas on steroids.
In 2013, Macau’s gambling industry
was seven times bigger than Las Vegas’s,
with a whopping $45 billion in gambling revenue.
Macau is the only place in China where casino
gambling is legal.
So it’s no surprise
that Macau is the 6th biggest tourist destination
in Asia.
But it’s also taken a hit recently.
Because you know how gambling is a great way
to launder money?
I mean, um, I don’t know that.
But corrupt Chinese officials sure do!
But now Xi Jinping’s anti-corruption campaign
has officials running scared.
Just 12 months after Xi’s visit to Macau
in 2014,
shares of Macau’s six casino operators plunged
by more than half.
Number 2: Macau is the model S.A.R.
Between Macau and Hong Kong, Macau is clearly
the filial child.
Not like that Hong Kong—
always getting involved in democracy protests,
demanding freedom,
and generally causing trouble for those
hardworking communist officials in
Beijing.
Fortunately, in Macau, there is almost no
democratic movement,
let alone an independence movement.
That’s why Chinese state-run media have
praised Macau.
After Hong Kong’s 2014 pro-democracy Umbrella
Movement,
the People’s Daily published an editorial
saying,
“Macau people are content and grateful.
Hong Kong people are a bit rebellious and
resistant.”
Global Times wrote,
“Political stability is the key to Macao’s
economic development
which ensures social stability.
The One Country Two Systems have maximized
Macao’s development potential.
And Number 1: Anti-Subversion Law
Imagine police being allowed to burst into
your home,
search your stuff, and arrest you without
a warrant,
just because you’re suspected of “subversion”
of the Chinese Communist Party.
Well, Article 23 is a draconian anti-subversion
law that could do just that.
In 2003, when Beijing pushed the Hong Kong
government to pass it,
half a million Hong Kong citizens took to
the streets in protest,
and stopped it.
Macau, on the other hand,
passed Article 23 seven years ago—
with almost no resistance.
Uhh, wait a minute.
Shelley, am I safe here in Macau?
Ok.
So I’m going to wrap this up.
What do you think are the biggest differences
between Hong Kong and Macau?
Leave your comments below.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
and I’ve gotta go back to Hong Kong now.