On this episode of China Uncensored,
Beef!
It’s what’s for dinner.
If you’re the US president visiting Asia.
China builds a magical island maker.
No, seriously that’s what they’re calling
it.
And finally,
you might want to stand for the Chinese national
anthem.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
In our top story,
Japan and China go to war...
over who can serve the better meal
to visiting US President Donald Trump!
Japanese Prime Minister Shinzo Abe
will be tough to be beat.
While the two played golf,
he served the president a $10,
100% American Angus beef patty hamburger
from a local Tokyo burger joint.
Afterwards, the burger joint
that made the President’s Colby Jack Cheeseburger
sold out
as the people of Japan
flocked to try the presidential meal.
But Trump is now in China,
and Xi Jinping knows just what President Trump
hungers for above all else:
one-upping Obama.
Donald Trump has become the first US president
ever,
since the founding of the People’s Republic
of China,
to dine in the Forbidden City.
Actually, the first foreign official ever.
For 500 years,
the Forbidden City was the palace of China’s
emperors.
Hmm, actually,
I wonder if this decision has more to do with
Xi Jinping comparing himself to China’s
emperors
than anything else.
President Trump has congratulated Xi Jinping
on become the most powerful Chinese leader
since Mao Zedong.
Which is a weird compliment if you think about
it.
I don’t think Angela Merkel would like it
if you congratulated her on being
the most powerful German leader
since Hitler.
But there was one important question on everyone’s
mind
when Trump landed in China.
With the world’s most sophisticated and
oppressive censorship
over the Internet and social media,
how was Trump gonna Tweet?!
Well, we didn’t need to worry.
Even though Twitter is banned in China,
a White House official told reporters,
“The president will tweet whatever he wants.
That’s his way of communicating
directly with the American people.”
I have never been more proud of Trump’s
tweets.
We’ll have a more in-depth look at
President Trump’s visit
in next week’s full episode.
In other news,
outspoken social commentator Katy Perry,
who apparently also sings or something,
has made no secret of her angry feelings
about President Trump.
But when it comes to China,
a country where leaders
routinely kill their own citizens,
she might not be so outspoken.
China Digital Times uncovered this letter
floating around on Weibo,
allegedly from Katy Perry.
It says she promises to
"observe the laws and regulations in China,
comply with the management of the regulators,"
and not to "add or change any content without
authorization,"
"do or say anything religious or political,"
or "participate in any activities that jeopardize
China’s unity and integrity."
So I don’t think she’ll pull a Bjork
and start shouting “Tibet” during a concert.
Also, Bjork was talented.
Ok Katy Perry jokes aside,
this is an eye-opening look
at how the Communist Party extends its censorship
across the entertainment world.
After all,
Katy Perry is definitely not the only artist
who’s been asked to sign a letter like this.
Unless the CCP was especially disturbed
by the subversiveness of Left Shark.
Meanwhile, three US college basketball players
from UCLA
were detained by police in Shanghai,
for allegedly stealing from a Louis Vuitton
store.
Unfortunately for them
the store was a knockoff.
What is not a knockoff, however,
is China’s new magical island maker.
That’s what they’re calling
the latest Chinese dredging vessel…
...that can dig up 6,000 cubic meters an hour
of the ocean floor
and churn out brand new islands for the Chinese
regime.
Just like the brand new islands the Chinese
regime
already built in the South China Sea.
And they’re probably never going to stop,
even though they maybe ought to.
The way Steven Tyler is probably never going
to stop
coming out with new albums,
even though maybe he ought to.
And while the CCP is building artificial islands
in the middle of the ocean,
they’re also building artificial support
for themselves
in Hong Kong.
Just a bit of background,
in Mainland China,
a new law has now upped the jail time
for disrespecting the national anthem—
from 15 days, to 3 years.
It’s those kinds of laws
that Hong Kong was supposed to be exempt from
under the One Country, Two Systems policy.
Which is why Hong Kongers
have been very disrespectful of the anthem.
Well, “the People’s Congress passed a
decision
demanding Hong Kong adopt the National Anthem
Law.”
That is being met with intense protest.
Except for in the totally still independent
Hong Kong government.
According to one Hong Kong official,
“Hong Kong will try to enact a law
penalizing people who boo the Chinese national
anthem
‘as soon as possible.’”
No decision has been made about jail time
yet.
Speaking of jail time—
and Hong Kong’s eroding freedoms—
Umbrella Movement leaders Joshua Wong and
Nathan Law
have been given a chance to appeal their prison
terms.
You know,
the ones the courts re-sentenced
after judges decided their original sentences
of community service that they’d already
served
weren’t harsh enough.
And also after Nathan Law had become an elected
official,
but then was kicked out,
for reasons totally unrelated to the fact
that he’s critical of the Chinese Communist
Party.
What do you think? Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China Uncensored.
Once again I'm your host, Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
You may need to travel to Japan
to get a great all-American hamburger,
but you only need to go to ChinaUncensored.tv
to get great episodes of China Uncensored.
Every Friday we upload a half hour episode
for free,
that you can’t see anywhere else.
So visit ChinaUncensored.tv.
Preferably with a hamburger in hand.