What did Pewdiepie do to get banned in China?
A stabbing in Hong Kong
And China sets its sights on Taiwan
That and more on this week’s China Uncensored.
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
This week’s China news headlines!
In Hong Kong, protesters once again
took to the streets last weekend.
Organizers say 350,000 marched,
but because police did not give permission,
it was technically an illegal rally.
“...That means anyone who comes out
will inherently be breaking the law.
So that's the tactic the Hong Kong government
is using.
So don't think that the movement is slowing
down.
In fact, it is growing stronger and stronger.
And if you pan your camera around,
every single one of the protesters today
standing around here today,
are literally breaking the law.”
The march happened just days after
a brutal attack on Jimmy Sham,
head of the Civil Human Rights Front.
They’re an umbrella group that’s organized
some of the biggest rallies over the past
few months.
They also originally organized this Sunday’s
march,
but backed out after police said no.
But that didn’t stop protesters from marching
anyway.
And that didn’t stop police from responding
with tear gas
And water cannons shooting blue dye laced
with pepper spray.
However, protesters did light a fire.
And some did throw petrol bombs.
But as for the barricades protesters erected,
police now just drive through them.
And they also decided to spray this mosque
with water cannons,
even though there weren’t any protesters
there.
Creating a mess that protesters then helped
clean up.
Hong Kong police later said that spraying
the mosque
with a water cannon was an accident.
The kind of accident where they stopped the
water cannon.
Carefully took aim.
And then sprayed it several times.
Hong Kong police:
successfully alienating every part of Hong
Kong society.
But it’s not just police Hong Kong protesters
need to worry about.
On Saturday, a man stabbed a teenage protester
in the neck and stomach.
The protester had been handing out flyers.
Ok, no one likes flyers, but that’s taking
it too far.
It was so bad that the protester’s intestines
were exposed.
He was taken to a hospital,
where he is in serious condition.
So who was this guy?
Apparently a cook from mainland China.
After stabbing the protester,
he threatened others,
yelling that Hong Kong was part of China.
That’s really not how a chef
should be putting his knife skills to use.
Speaking of someone who’s job performance
hasn’t been great,
the Financial Times is reporting that Beijing
might replace Carrie Lam as Hong Kong’s
Chief Executive.
That might have been enough to stop the protests...
four months ago.
At this point, it’s kind of like when a
teacher you hate
is replaced by a substitute teacher who’s
even worse.
What I’m saying is, Carrie Lam’s replacement
is going to be Miss Viola Swamp.
But one thing that the Hong Kong government
did finally do this week:
the Legislative Council formally withdrew
the extradition bill
that sparked the protests.
Which might have been enough to stop the protests...
four months ago.
I’m seeing a theme here.
But for Hong Kong protesters,
the NBA is a gift that keeps on giving.
At a Nets vs Raptors preseason game over the
weekend,
hundreds showed up wearing Stand with Hong
Kong t-shirts.
A group of Tibetan activists also showed up.
As did a group of pro-honey protesters
dressed as Chinese leader Xi Jinping.
And during the season opener between the Lakers
and the Clippers,
protesters passed out thousands of Stand With
Hong Kong t-shirts.
Which led to this magical moment.
It
brought a tear to my eye.
The NBA of course has been criticized for
selling out to China
after controversy over a pro-Hong Kong tweet
sent out by Daryl Morey,
the general manager of the Houston Rockets.
According to NBA commissioner Adam Silver,
the Chinese Communist Party asked him to fire
Morey,
but he refused.
Of course, Chinese state-run television says
that’s a dirty lie,
the Party would never do that
and he should really watch his back
because retribution is coming!
Not only is the Chinese Communist Party
spreading censorship in America,
it’s also threatening Americans who don’t
bow before it.
And that’s why I’ve spent the past 7 years
of my life
making a show warning people
about the Chinese Communist Party.
On Monday, China’s defense minister said
conquering Taiwan is a national priority.
Of course he didn’t say conquer.
That sounds bad.
The Chinese Communist party calls it reunification.
You know, when the Communist Party
seizes control with military force,
kills a bunch of people,
and replaces the rule of law with authoritarianism.
Re-unification.
With an island that was never part of
the People’s Republic of China to begin
with.
Of course, taking over Taiwan will be expensive.
Fortunately, the Chinese regime
has a brilliant money making scheme.
Sue the US!
China is seeking billions in penalties against
the US
at the World Trade Organization.
Ironically, the suit relates to
“a case dating to before the Trump administration,
and unrelated to the tariffs it has slapped
on Chinese goods.”
“China is seeking US$2.4 billion
in retaliatory sanctions against the United
States
after it failed to comply with a WTO ruling
in a tariffs case dating to Barack Obama’s
presidency.”
There’s a problem with this money making
scheme though.
If the WTO could actually enforce its rules,
and stop countries from cheating,
China would have a lot more to answer for
than the US.
The Yang gang is in trouble!
No, not Andrew Yang.
Navy Lt. Fan Yang
and his wife, Yang Yang.
“Yang had top secret clearance with the
P8 squadron,
an anti-submarine unit.
The Federal Government accuses him
of working with two Chinese nationals
to get them military equipment
which would ultimately be funneled
to the Communist government.”
Great.
So if China ever invades Taiwan,
the US will have had a helping hand in it.
Now while selling weapons to a Communist regime
at odds with the United States
may sound distinctly unAmerican,
Yang makes up for it
by doing the most American thing possible.
Spreading America’s love of guns.
“He's also accused of taking a Chinese national
to a local gun range
and selling at least one gun illegally.”
Guns are banned in China for civilians,
so many Chinese nationals come to the US
to experience guns for the first time.
That probably still doesn’t make up for
selling US weapons
to the Communist government of China.
But he isn’t the only one!
According to this press release from the Department
of Justice,
“Li Tao, 39, sought to export “highly
sensitive” military
and space technology from the United States
to China.”
I believe we have footage of that interrogation.
Have you ever stolen from an employer?
Yes.
And where were you employed?
NASA.
What’d you steal, a rocket ship?
No, just some pens.
And some plans.
Plans?
Space plans.
And that, kids, is Mr. Show.
I’ve now educated you on the truly important
things in life.
Some good news for once.
Uighur activist Ilham Tohti
has been awarded the Sakharov Prize for Human
Rights.
In not as good news,
Tohti was imprisoned for life back in 2014
for doing radical things like encouraging
dialogue
and reconciliation between Uighurs and Han
Chinese.
The European Union gave the prestigious award
to Tohti.
In response, the Chinese regime
announced that Europe was cancelled.
And finally, YouTube star Pewdiepie has been
banned in China!
Now at first you might think,
oh that’s because YouTube is banned in China,
so even the world’s biggest YouTuber would
be banned.
But that’s not the reason.
Apparently the Hong Kong protests
have even entered the world of YouTube let’s
plays.
Behold, analysis of the Hong Kong situation
from Pewdiepie.
The next meme needs a little bit of context.
It involves Hong Kong and China.
For those of you who don't know,
Hong Kong is a semi autonomous state,
it has its own laws,
or law system or jurisdiction, I don't know.
Then outta nowhere, someone from NBA tweets
I support Hong Kong,
and then NBA is like,
"Oh God, we need Chinese money."
“China is like that one person on Twitter
that can’t take any criticism and just blocks
everyone”
Deep.
What’s that Shelley?
With 100 million subscribers,
Pewdiepie managed to let more people
know about China and Hong Kong
than I have in 7 years on this show?!
I knew I should have started a let’s play
channel instead!
Now I’m questioning all my life choices.
But before I go down that rabbit hole,
it’s time for me to answer a question from
one of you—
a fan who support China Uncensored
with a dollar or more per episode,
by contributing through the crowdfunding website
Patreon.
Michael Sun asks,
“Are there those in mainland China
who are sympathetic to the protestors' cause?”
That’s a really interesting question.
Unfortunately it’s very difficult to know
what people inside Mainland China
think about the Hong Kong protests.
Since everything is so censored inside China,
it’s difficult to tell how much people actually
know.
Plus, the Chinese state-run media
have been pushing constant propaganda
accusing Hong Kong protesters
of being violent rioting separatists
bent on splitting apart the motherland.
When we were in Hong Kong in June,
we did interview some Mainland tourists.
Check it out, it’s called
What Chinese People Really Think about Hong
Kong Protests.
Most were pretty reluctant to say anything.
If someone in Mainland China has managed to
hear about the protests and develop some sympathy,
it would be very dangerous for them to express
it.
Often, we hear stories like this,
where Mainland Chinese viciously defend the
Party line even abroad.
That said, I wouldn’t be surprised if China
had plenty of people
who hold cynical views of the Communist Party,
even if they keep those views to themselves.
Thanks for your question, Michael.
And if you have a question for me
you want to hear answered on the show,
sign up to join the China Uncensored 50 cent
army,
by supporting the show with a dollar or more
per episode.
Again, YouTube is demonetizing us so much
we would have to shut down the show
if it weren’t for your support.
And to everyone, thanks for watching!
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.