On this episode of China Uncensored,
a detained Taiwanese activist
gives a “confession”
at an “open” trial in Mainland China.
Welcome back to China Uncensored,
I’m Chris Chappell.
Love means never having to say you’re sorry.
Unless you’re a Taiwanese citizen
who betrayed the love of the Chinese Motherland
by criticizing the Communist Party.
Then you need to apologize.
On television.
With two policemen behind you.
This is Lee Ming-che.
He’s a Taiwanese democracy activist.
He went missing back in March
when he visited mainland China.
People were worried about him at the time,
but then he reappeared,
only six months later,
safely in a courtroom in China,
being charged with subversion of state power.
It’s what authorities called
an “open trial.”
Open in that it would be
an open and shut case.
His wife was allowed to fly in
from Taiwan to attend.
She had this to say before leaving Taiwan.
“I want to plead to the Taiwanese people,
that if they see Lee Ming-che
making unpleasant actions or statements
during the trial that are
not in accordance with his free will,
please forgive him.
This is just the forced guilty plea
that China is so good at.”
And to show her support,
she even got these arm tattoos.
They say, “Lee Ming-che, I’m proud of
you.”
Yeah, Chinese prison is so hard-core,
people on the outside get the tattoos.
Well, anyway, with three very serious-looking
judges,
and policemen seated nearby,
Lee Ming-che made his confession—
totally of his own free will.
“I spread malicious attacks
that defamed the Chinese Communist Party
and China’s government
and China’s current political system,
and I incited subversion of state power.”
Subversion of state power
is a really broad charge
that can pretty much mean
anything the Communist Party wants it to.
Lee also confessed he committed
these acts of subversion because
he had been misled by media
in the West and Taiwan
about the reality of mainland China.
Hmmm...
That sounds suspiciously similar to the confession
by Chinese human rights lawyer
Jiang Tianyong last month.
Jiang also said that
he had been misled by Western ideas.
So what kind of misleading ideas
did Lee Ming-che have?
Well, Lee is a community college professor
in Taiwan.
More importantly,
he also volunteers with an NGO
that monitors Taiwan’s adherence
to international human rights standards.
And he had frequently made trips to China
to discuss Taiwan’s transition
from martial law to democracy.
But when Lee traveled to mainland China
this past March,
he disappeared.
Eventually the Communist Party announced that
yes, they had abducted Lee,
a citizen of Taiwan,
and held him for over 170 days,
under investigation for
“harming national security.”
So, apparently, the Chinese regime
has decided to make it crystal clear
to the entire world
that they will never adhere
to those evil Western ideas
like international human rights standards
or transitioning to democracy.
This is especially a big deal in Taiwan.
Lee Ming-che is the first Taiwanese citizen
to be charged in mainland China
with “subversion of state power.”
And his case has created a big strain
on China-Taiwan relations.
Relations have already not been
particularly good since the new Taiwan president
Tsai Ing-wen was elected in 2016.
She belongs to the Democratic Progressive
Party,
which believes that Taiwan is independent
from mainland China.
After Tsai took office,
China suspended direct diplomatic contact
with Taiwan.
But not only does Lee’s case
further strain relations,
it also raises the much bigger question
of what will happen if mainland China
and Taiwan are ever unified—
the way the CCP insists they must be
in the future.
Even people in Hong Kong are concerned.
They held a protest on Monday.
I’ll let former Hong Kong legislator
and democracy activist Lee Cheuk-yan explain.
“It’s a warning from the Chinese Communist
Party,
anyone outside China including Taiwan
or even Hong Kong or elsewhere.
If you want to,
what their words are, interfere,
in Chinese internal affairs,
supporting human rights,
then you will be arrested.”
So essentially, Lee Ming-che’s case
represents the larger issue of how the CCP
treats people who’ve committed
so-called crimes that,
in democratic countries,
would be considered free speech.
As for Lee Ming-che,
he’s still awaiting the sentence in his
case.
The Taiwanese government has pledged
to do whatever they can
to ensure his safe return.
The Communist Party still has a chance
to soften the impact—
for example, by deporting Lee back to Taiwan
instead of throwing him in prison.
But no matter what they do now,
they’re not going to convince
the people of Taiwan
that reuniting with the mainland
is going to be all sunshine and rainbows.
And coming up after the break,
the Chinese Communist Party
is losing my religion.
Where did they put it?!
You know, you could have
seen this segment a week earlier
if you had gone to ChinaUncensored.tv.
We upload a full half hour episode
every Friday for free.
So if you haven’t already,
be sure to check out ChinaUncensored.tv.