On this episode of China Uncensored,
China doesn’t care about your views on race.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Boy, the whole world is envious
of China and Africa’s good relationship.
At least that’s what my favorite state-run
media
the Global Times says.
I wonder if they know Africa
is a continent and not a country?
You see,
China was a victim of European colonialism
too.
They get it.
That’s why any relationship with China
will be one of win-win cooperation.
China has been building roads,
railroads, and ports in Africa.
Why they even built
the new African Union Building.
Now some obviously jealous Western powers
are trying to say,
“Oh, those infrastructure projects
are creating huge debt.
Oh, you’re giving the construction jobs
mostly to Chinese workers
and not to locals.
Oh, you bugged the African Union building
and inserted a backdoor into its computer
network.”
Some have even dared to suggest
that China might be a type of colonial power.
Look, sure the Chinese regime is stripping
African countries of natural resources.
Sure, these countries are getting
an unfair deal on those construction projects.
Sure, the occasional Chinese company
has been accused of stealing water from locals.
But China will never repeat the kinds of mistakes
made in the past by people from the West.
Anyway, here’s some blackface
from the annual CCTV Spring Festival Gala.
"Why did you cheat your mother?
Mum, I don't want to get married so early.
I want to go to China to study (abroad).
I want to be like Chinese people,
roll up your sleeves and get to work
and gain a thumbs up from the world’s people."
Ha HA!
Yes, thumbs up from the world’s people.
Now this may be shocking to you,
but the mother in that skit
was actually not African.
She was a Chinese woman in blackface.
Oh and she was followed around
by an African man dressed as a giant monkey.
Which is totally normal in Africa.
All this hasn’t been received very well.
That skit was set in Kenya,
and has the actress in blackface
saying things like, “China has done
so much for Africa.”
And, “I love Chinese people.
I love China.”
Strange that they have to
pay someone to say that.
Now to be fair,
China has a very different history of race
relations
than say, the United States.
But this is not the first time
China has been nailed for being a tad
racially insensitive towards Africans.
This ad for a Chinese laundry detergent
shows a black guy taking the tide pod challenge,
then being shoved into a washing machine,
and emerging as a nice Chinese man.
And one museum featured photos of black people
alongside the animals they supposedly look
like.
What makes the CCTV Gala different, though,
is the amount of thought that went into it.
This is the biggest propaganda showcase
of the year.
800 million people watch it.
It’s quite literally the government of China
putting on a show.
And it goes through countless rounds of vetting
by Chinese censors.
This didn’t just accidentally happen.
A lot of people had to look at this and say,
“Yup!
This is a good idea.
This will really get a thumbs up
from the world’s people.”
Meanwhile, yet another person
has fallen victim to the crime
of hurting the feelings of the Chinese people.
This time Chinese model Liu Wen.
Was her sin worse than blackface?
Oh, way worse.
On Instagram,
she wished her fans a
“Happy Lunar New Year.”
She was supposed to say,
“Happy Chinese New Year!”
Even though it’s celebrated throughout Asia
as the Lunar New Year,
you should only refer to it
as the Chinese New Year!
Some more patriotic Chinese netizens
freaked out.
One Chinese user wrote on Instagram,
“If you want to become Vietnamese so badly,
get out and don’t come back to China.”
Does that make sense?
Obviously not.
Instagram is banned in China.
How did that person get access?
Anyway, model Liu Wen has now
corrected her grave mistake
of thinking that not all Asians are Chinese.
So what do you think of the blackface
on the Lunar New Year Gala?
I mean Chinese New Year Gala?
I mean Spring Festival Gala?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Well the Chinese Communist Party
is certainly rotten.
But you know what never goes bad?
Food from Thrive Life.
Thrive Life sells freeze dried meals
that stay fresh.
And if you order through the link
in the description below,
China Uncensored gets a cut.
I wouldn’t ask you to eat their food
if I didn’t also personally love it.
So support your belly and China Uncensored
by buying some delicious food from Thrive
Life.
The link is below.