The Chinese Communist Party is great...
At spying on people.
And not just inside China...
but also in America.
Welcome back to China Uncensored. I’m Chris
Chappell.
The Chinese Communist Party has an extensive
network of spies.
And over the last two decades,
the Party has rapidly developed its espionage
tools.
Shelley Zhang sat down with intelligence researcher
Matt Brazil,
co-author of Chinese Communist Espionage:
An Intelligence Primer, to learn more.
Thank you for joining us, Dr. Brazil.
Happy to.
So, in your book, you say that Chinese espionage
has now become like a global superpower.
So, how scared should we be?
They're world-class.
And the reason we like to call them world-class
is that they have recently become equal in
ability
and reach to any other world-class power like
the United States,
Russia, France, and Britain.
Looking at the history of Chinese intelligence,
it seems like it wasn't really ...
Especially in terms of foreign intelligence,
it wasn't really that way until the early
2000s, is that right?
They began to really get serious in the 1990s.
And as we talk about in the book,
it was in 1989 that state security decided
that they wanted to revamp education
not only for their own officers but for the
general population.
And so right after Tiananmen Square, they
commissioned a book on Li Kenong,
one of their early heroes and who was also
the head of their intelligence service in
the '50s.
So, they paid for it, they found the researchers.
They wrote the introduction to the book on
Li Kenong.
And they emphasize that this is for younger
generations to learn
about the heroes of the past so that they
can sharpen their own skills
and realize that they too can make a contribution
to the revolution.
So, why is it important to look back at the
history
of the communist party's espionage activities?
Chiefly because it tells us the facts about
how the Chinese communists
have run intelligence operations like everybody
else.
The reality of “everybody spies” applies
to the Chinese
as well as to everybody else.
It also underlines the fact that their operations
have always been professional, secret, compartmented,
limited to only a few people.
And it runs against the old American idea
that there is
a grains of sand approach by the Chinese,
which means basically that China likes to
use thousands of ordinary
Chinese people overseas to do their spying
for them.
Nothing could be further from the truth,
and that unfortunate characterization leads
to the idea that
every Chinese person is a potential spy, which
is silly,
but it's gained a lot of traction in the US
and some other countries.
And so, we were very concerned about that
idea
because it leads to false assumptions.
It leads to bad policy.
And so we tried our best to make clear that,
that's not the case using this book.
What would you say is the biggest misconception
about Chinese communist espionage?
One of the biggest misconceptions is that
it's mysterious.
And indeed, in the modern day, Kang Sheng,
the black sheep of the communist party
who was actually expelled after he died,
he's criticized for his mysticism because
he used to insist
that he could smell a spy, that he could tell
a spy by looking at them.
And indeed, he persecuted innumerable people
with that kind of assumption,
and it was accepted, and he was backed up
by Mao.
He was one of Mao's most loyal adherence and
Mao was loyal to him as well.
It doesn't seem like a great way to run a
spy organization though.
Shoot first and ask questions later.
Not a good thing. I agree.
So, one of the things that you brought up
in your book
that I thought was particularly interesting
was the idea
that in the Chinese Communist Party,
the intelligence information would kind of
get filtered through
this Marxist Leninist lens.
Can you give us an example of what that means?
One of the most difficult problems they face
internally,
which they may or may not acknowledge internally
is they use this Marxist Leninist lens to
analyze practically everything.
So, they have a historical sense that ...
They've got it all figured out as Marxist
Leninist.
They have a theory. They have science.
They have a way of looking at history that
enables them to predict the future.
And when things go wrong,
then they typically ascribe that to being
somebody's mistake
or a leftist deviation or something of that
sort.
And that makes it hard for them to explain
things
when they can't find that deviation or that
villain to blame things on.
And so that means that when they try to explain
a problem
to their higher ups who also go for this view,
that if they can't find somebody to blame
it on,
then it becomes difficult to make a proper
explanation.
So, this is why they've actually gone after
foreigners like Nate Thayer, for example,
the man who reported on the death of Pol Pot.
He was approached by the Shanghai State Security
Bureau
and asked to write some briefs on different
problems,
and they can take something like that, something
written by a foreigner
and show it to somebody who wants to know
about a particular problem.
And if there's some piece of information in
that analysis that's a little bit heretical,
they don't get blamed for it.
So, it's like, "Well, that was what this foreigner
said, so that's okay."
But if it's from an internal source,
then it has to kind of be politically correct.
Yes. You may be familiar with Cankao Xiaoxi,
which until the mid '90s was a classified
publication.
So, for the audience, Cankao Xiaoxi or Reference
News
is a collection of foreign news reports
that would not ordinarily make it into the
Chinese press.
And same thing there.
We can put information out about something
going on outside of China
or maybe even inside of China through a foreign
news report
and not get blamed for it, and not get persecuted.
Interesting. In the book, you talk a little
bit about the difference
between the Ministry of State Security and
the People's Liberation Army,
how they're both responsible for intelligence.
But in terms of Western analysis of that,
we seem to focus more on the PLA than the
MSS.
Is it important to have that distinction?
It is, because until the reorganization that
happened three years ago,
the PLA was perhaps the leader in foreign
intelligence,
or at least they were the more visible part
of PRC foreign intelligence,
because they were getting caught.
You may be aware of how a US cybersecurity
organization,
a private company managed to actually turn
the cameras
back on the PLA's laptops and view the pictures
of the analysts at work
and that's how the FBI got their pictures
for those wanted posters.
Right. When the justice department indicted
some PLA soldiers. Right?
Yes, exactly.
Now, MSS apparently has been just as successful,
maybe even more successful in cyber operations,
but the point is they have maintained a much
lower profile.
And so my coauthor, Peter Mattis,
likes to call this realization that has occurred
in the last 10, 15 years
that there's so much more stuff to be gained
through cyber espionage.
He likes to call it a dreadnought moment,
as in the change in navy ships at the turn
of the last century
where ships suddenly had more armament
and bigger guns and longer range.
That whole idea of having bigger guns and
longer range
can be applied here, because now instead of
having to recruit spies,
get them in, or run a very expensive
and very elaborate signal intelligence operation
to get your information that requires satellites
and outstations
and thousands of analysts and intercept operators.
A lot of technology, a lot of money.
Now, the ability to get these things done
can be seen in the software code
that's used to infiltrate foreign systems.
And, of course,
once you get into the Office of Personnel
Management computers
or United Airlines computers,
because a lot of U S government people fly
on
United or Anthem Insurance computers,
a lot of US government people took insurance
through Anthem.
There's an unbelievable wealth treasure trove
of information in these places.
As they've done throughout their history
and as all intelligence agencies do,
the Chinese services are going where the secrets
are.
You say in the book that they could have been
targeting the OPM hack
to get the information of government officials.
What would they do with that information?
Well, every government official who gets a
security clearance
has to fill out a form.
If it's the case of most of the agencies,
it's called the SF-50, the Standard Form 50.
So, you're putting down in that form not only
your name,
social security number and date of birth,
you're putting down all your friends,
all the addresses you've lived in the past
X number of years.
Whether or not you've had exposure to foreign
nationals.
And so all this information together provides
a marvelous profile
for someone who is thinking about testing
out,
possibly recruiting an American.
So, they could actually be targeting officials
to spy for the MSS or something?
Yes. And, of course, not only the OPM information,
but also the stuff we use every day now,
because we need to get our names out there
to further our careers.
LinkedIn has, as you may have read,
become a big resource for not only the Chinese
services,
but also ... If you look at the Open Source
Center
that's run by our intelligence community,
they have advertisements out there for people
to work for them and do precisely the same
thing.
I want to ask about corporate espionage now.
Can you name a company that's gone into China
that hasn't been spied on?
That would be hard to do in the affirmative
or the negative,
but there's a baseline of surveillance on
all foreigners
and all Chinese people in China.
And that baseline of surveillance,
if you're Chinese, it includes your urban
personnel file.
It includes all the information that goes
into your national ID card,
including your race and so on. It includes
where you work.
If you're a foreigner, when you travel to
China, just like ...
This happens in Thailand to where I recently
visited.
You check into a hotel, they copy your passport
and they immediately give it to the police.
Now, the reason they do this ...
And if you put yourself in the shoes of the
local public security bureau,
if something goes wrong with a foreigner,
then they're responsible, because you're on
their turf.
They're going to have to answer for whatever
it is you did or didn't do,
the movements you made or didn't make.
So, that's why they have a strong incentive
to know all about you at that basic level.
But they don't really look at you unless they
have reason to.
They have interest in you if you are working
for some sort of sensitive company with high
technology
or if you've come to China and you start to
do religious proselytizing.
Or on the Chinese side, if you're a Chinese
citizen,
they're interested in you if you're a Tibetan,
or if you're a Uyghur, or if you're a dissident,
or if you're a lawyer for dissidents.
Then, of course, they intensify the surveillance.
If you're a foreigner who goes to China and
you misbehave,
even if it looks to you like certain things
are legal.
If you misbehave, you don't cross all your
T's and dot all your I's,
then you might be subject to a more intense
examination as well.
So, does that include people who go to China
for business reasons?
Yes.
As a former corporate security advisor,
do you think that companies in the US are
cognizant
of the risks of going into China now?
Is that pretty well known?
They are, but whether or not they do proper
training is another question.
And whether or not their employees accept
these realities
is another question.
Because when you go to China,
the first thing you notice if you're from
a Western country
that has a Western level of street crime
is there tends to be less street crime.
And you also run into people who are very
polite to you,
who treat you with deference.
And it's easy to fall into the impression
that everything is a lot better here.
But the reality is that if there's any interest
in you as a foreigner,
then you're going to be subject to very intense
surveillance.
And you won't see it because it's done very
well.
So, it won't be in kind of like guys in sunglasses
following you
that you could necessarily spot.
A lot of it might be technology related.
Yes. With all the cameras in China now,
it's amazing how many cameras there are and
what they can do.
Of course, we've read about how artificial
intelligence,
AI, is being employed to be able to identify
people.
Police are now experimenting with glasses
that they can use to identify people
that are linked through WiFi to mainframe
servers with all that information.
So, it's difficult to evade surveillance in
China if you're a subject of interest.
Of course, if you're not, if you're considered
to be an ordinary person
going about their business and you're no threat
to the state,
then you're virtually ignored.
How do you think you and I would do?
I think they'd go after you.
That makes me feel better.
Because of your exposure in public.
I know that when I used to do my work there
that I was watched.
And I used to do stuff that was only recently
legal.
For example, it used to be totally illegal
to do TSCM work,
which stands for technical surveillance counter
measures.
That's finding bugs in tables and walls and
stuff like that.
That used to be totally illegal.
However, the company in the United States,
which I won't name, that sells this stuff,
that has world-class equipment.
I've been trained at their Tennessee facility
and they have lots of customers in China.
And why is that?
That's because surveillance,
electronic surveillance in China has become
so ubiquitous.
It's not only the government anymore,
it's also private individuals.
It used to be, for example, up until about
that if you wanted to buy electronic eavesdropping
equipment,
you had to go to Hong Kong.
You'd go to Nathan Road in Kowloon where all
the camera shopsare
and you'd be able to find bugs that would
work with an FM radio
and more sophisticated ones that had their
own receivers and so on.
But starting about then, this stuff was sold
on the mainland by mail.
And so now, companies are spying on each other.
There are plenty of private investigations
companies
that are using this stuff like mad.
And so the Chinese side decided to make legal
the acquisition
and use of anti-bug detection equipment at
that level,
at that sort of semi-professional level,
but they don't allow you to search for stuff
that is at the professional level,
the police level listening devices.
So, if it's corporations,
like Chinese corporations spying on each other,
that's something that you could try to protect
against?
Yes, and that's something that is consistent
with the Chinese approach
using law to rule China.
So, as you probably heard many people say,
China is not a country that is governed by
law.
It's a country that they use law to govern.
And so what they've wanted to do over the
past 10 years is institute laws
that are relevant to many areas,
but also relevant to espionage so that
they can have codified approaches to catching
spies
that don't allow for any deviation from Party
policy.
So in other words, they've got it all down
on law,
what you can do and what you can't do.
And that eliminates some measure of corruption,
because local officials don't have latitude
to do whatever they want.
They have to follow the law if they're trying
to catch spies.
Obviously Taiwan is a huge interest to the
Chinese Communist Party.
Has there been a lot of espionage related
to things like the Taiwan elections
that are coming up?
Espionage between those two sides, Taiwan
and the Mainland,
indeed is a long running activity on both
sides.
There are a lot of cases that we have in the
book.
We scratched the surface only in the book
of course.
And indeed when we did our research,
we had a chance to go through some archives
at the Interior Ministry in Taiwan to get
some of the historical stuff.
And the number of cases there is in the thousands.
So there's a long practice of the two sides
spying on each other
because each considers the other to be its
major threat
because each offers a Chinese alternative
to the other.
And the elections of course are a very strong
interest to Beijing,
Taiwan elections,
because they are concerned about the incumbent
government
eventually moving toward advocating independence
of Taiwan
from the Mainland.
Do you have an example of the type of espionage
that they would use related to Taiwan?
Yes. There are numerous examples.
One of them, for example, involved a Colonel
in the Taiwan Army
who went to China after he retired and was
recruited there,
probably not intending to be recruited,
but he was spotted, assessed, cultivated and
recruited,
and then he went back to Taiwan and started
to try to recruit others.
And he was found out by a junior officer that
he had known in service
whom he approached and thought he could recruit
to be part of aspiring,
but that junior officer reported him.
The Taiwanese military has been a special
target
of the PRC services for obvious reasons.
In terms of the US, what do you think the
US government
has to watch out for from these Chinese security
agencies?
The problem that US officials tend to complain
about
is that they're overwhelmed and under resourced.
That's the biggest problem.
It's important to remember that the Chinese
agencies
are using professionals to do their work.
And there's another aspect to this too,
on the industrial espionage side of relatively
amateurish operations
done by state-owned enterprises themselves.
They've been given letters of marque from
the King, if you will,
to go out and get technology secrets by themselves.
And this is illustrated quite well
in these two FBI videos that you may be aware
of.
They're kind of cheesy, but they're factual.
One is called Game of Pawns.
I did watch that one.
Yes.
Game of Pawns about the Glen Duffie Shriver
case.
When this young man who was studying in China
in a very controlled,
where there's a baseline of surveillance and
then you can drill down
if you're really interested in somebody.
Well, the Shanghai State Security Bureau
became very interested in him and they recruited
him
to try to pass the foreign service exam,
and then to try to join CIA and paid him a
lot of money to do that.
So, that's Game of Pawns.
The other video is called Company Man.
And Company Man is about a state-owned enterprise,
trying to get industrial secrets regarding
industrial glass
from a company in New York.
And you can see in this particular video that
they went about it
in a very slapdash and reckless way
and they got caught because of that.
There seems to be a certain level of entrepreneurial
espionage
when it comes to the corporate espionage things.
Thanks to Deng Xiaoping.
Was there anything that surprised you as you
were researching this book?
I was surprised by the number of cases that
we were able to uncover and talk about.
And one of the things I was very surprised
about
was the level of sophistication that has been
pursued successfully
over the past 20 years.
But I think it's important to remember that,
that the whole Marxist Leninist thing with
them being
super committed to Marxism and communism as
a vision,
the part of the Chinese government where the
truest believers reside.
There's no moral equivalence in my mind,
but you might say the same thing about our
own security services
and we like to make fun of it.
The television series on Adult Swim called
American Dad for example,
features a dad who works for the CIA.
He has this misshapen square jaw.
It's ridiculously huge.
He wears an American flag on his lapel.
He's totally macho and full of testosterone,
and he doesn't tell his family anything about
his work.
Because everybody spies,
every society that has a sophisticated and
large bureaucratic intelligence service,
their citizens are human beings.
They react to that stimuli in kind of a human
way.
Thank you so much for joining us, Dr Brazil.
Happy to.