On this episode of China Uncensored,
can you trust vaccines?
Well, if you’re in China, maybe not.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I'm your
host Chris Chappell.
Vaccines: a life saving technological breakthrough?
Or poison injected into your children?
If you'd like save time,
you can go ahead and begin
the anti-vaxxer flame war in the comment section
below.
Still here? Good.
Let's talk about a vaccine scandal!
Chinese pharmacist Pang Hongwei had been illegally
trading in vaccines.
But authorities were quick to act and she
was sentenced to three years in prison,
later reduced to five years probation.
That was in 2009.
But then in 2011,
instead of stopping her illegal vaccine trade,
she somehow began working with local officials
in 24 provinces,
for five years, creating one of the biggest
health scandals in Chinese history.
I wonder if that violates the terms of her
probation.
As of now, this $90 million dollar scandal
has exposed
29 pharmaceutical firms, 16 health departments
and 357 officials.
Here's how it worked:
According to China's FDA,
Pang was buying cheap vaccines
from drug companies that were either expired
or close to their expiration date.
Then she sold them across China.
And local officials cooperated—for a profit.
See, local governments don’t get money from
the central government,
so they're often forced to come up with some…creative
ways
to make money, like:
land seizures, fines for violations of the
one (and now two) child policy, and selling vaccines.
Provincial disease control centers mark up
the vaccines
and then force hospitals to buy them.
And while some vaccines for diseases like
polio and tuberculosis
are considered mandatory for everyone and
are free
others, like for chickenpox or meningitis,
Chinese citizens have to buy themselves.
Now if you think this whole local government-backed
monopoly
on expired or nearly expired vaccines could
go on forever,
well, it didn't.
It only went on for five years.
That’s when police stumbled upon Pang's
stash of vaccines
in an unrefrigerated storeroom in an abandoned
factory.
Apparently vaccines are supposed to be refrigerated.
So for five years, people across China were
paying for vaccines
that were expired and weren't stored properly.
Now while that may sound bad,
what’s even worse is that officials covered
up the scandal for an entire year.
In fact, the only reason it came to light
is that authorities asked suppliers in March
to step forward
so they could trace potential victims.
In other words, they were afraid the problem
might become too big to cover up,
so they decided to 'fess up.
Just like they did with SARS.
So you might be asking yourself…
"Won't someone please think of the children."
Well…
"I felt very scared and worried about my child
after I heard this news."
So is there a risk of getting poisoned from
expired vaccines?
According to the World Health Organization…
"This is not the case.
Vaccines that are improperly handled can lose
their potency
and they may not protect the child against
the disease the vaccine was intended to prevent."
So you can see why authorities covered it
up for a year.
There was nothing to worry about!
Expired vaccines just lose their potency.
They don’t kill you.
Unless you die from the disease they’re
supposed to protect you against
because you never got a real vaccination.
As for Pang, she’s been detained,
but police haven't announced any specific
charges,
because, you know, not telling people things
has worked out so great in the past.
But some say that if courts feel they've endangered
lives,
they could face the death sentence.
The Chinese people already don’t have much
faith in Chinese goods,
from all the fake medicine, fake food, toxic
milk, or that time in 2013
when a couple of infants died following a
Hepatitis B vaccination
but the Chinese FDA said it was unrelated
but who really believes what the Chinese government
says anyway?
And this five-year-long-scandal-plus-one-year-cover-up
has not helped.
Doctors in China are already reporting a big
drop-off in vaccinations across the country.
So what do you think about vaccines?
What’s that, Shelley?
You’re saying it’s a bad idea to ask viewers
to comment on that?
Well, in that case, what do you... love most
about puppy dogs?
Leave your comments below. Once again, I'm
Chris Chappell. See you next time.