A WHO expert warns that the Coronavirus Outbreak
Is just beginning
As an authoritarian crackdown in China
Only gets worse.
This is China Uncensored,
I’m Chris Chappell.
It’s time for an update on the deadly coronavirus.
First some good news.
This coronavirus now officially has a name:
COVID-19.
And naming something gives you power over
it.
At least according to Rumpelstiltskin.
I mean, COVID-19 sounds much better than
“that mysterious deadly disease we can’t
stop”!
Now we can say with confidence that COVID-19
is that deadly disease we can’t stop!!!
Yeah, doesn’t that sound much nicer?
And don’t worry, they put a lot of thought
into that name
to make sure it was totally woke and non-offensive.
“We had to find a name that did not refer
to a geographical location,
an animal, an individual or group of people
and which is also pronounceable
and related to the disease.
Having a name matters to prevent the use of
other names
that can be inaccurate or stigmatising.”
I’m still offended.
They should have called it the Kung Flu.
Still, you should be terrified.
A WHO expert said the outbreak is just beginning!
He means the outbreak outside China.
And if the coronavirus is left unchecked,
60% of the world could be infected.
“With 99 percent of cases in China,
this remains very much an emergency for that
country
but one that holds a very grave threat to
the rest of the world,
unless we use the window of opportunity that
we have now.”
Which is why COVID-19 should be treated as
public enemy number 1.
“A virus can have more powerful consequences
than any terrorist action,
and that's true.
And if the world doesn't want to wake up
and consider this enemy virus as public enemy
number one,
I don't think we will learn from our lessons."
Man, and China claims it’s the US that’s
spreading fear.
As of recording, there have been more than
1,300 deaths
and almost 60,000 cases of infection in China.
There was a huge jump in the number of cases
this week.
That’s because Hubei Province,
which is the hardest hit by the virus,
has changed how they count cases.
They’re now counting patients who have symptoms
and CT scans that look like COVID-19,
but haven’t tested positive for it.
One reason for that is a shortage of test
kits.
Of course those are only the official statistics.
Even with the jump in cases,
most experts think the numbers are actually
much higher.
Which is why it’s a little funny that the
Chinese regime
keeps refusing international help.
Chinese doctors really want the help.
But the Chinese Communist Party seems resistant
for some reason.
I guess the Party probably feels they’ve
got the situation covered.
I mean, authorities have started seizing,
“private hospitals, hotels, apartments,
cars and even face masks”.
You know, I wouldn’t want to seize the face
mask
of someone who could have the coronavirus.
But I’m sure seizing someone's car is definitely
a quarantine protocol,
but I’m not sure why all of the seized cars
are Ferraris.
Weird.
By the way,
the doctor who uncovered the SARS coverup
in 2003—
he’s under house arrest.
Don’t worry, he’s in good hands.
Last year, they put him in a military hospital
for a month.
According to friends and family,
“The doctor...was given medication,
which led to severe memory loss.”
Well, that’s one way to cover up a coverup.
I told you last week about Wuhan citizen journalist
Fang Bin.
Police in hazmat suits came to his house,
confiscated his electronics,
and forcibly detained him.
He was released after being told to report
more “positive” news about the coronavirus
outbreak.
But this week, he wasn’t so lucky.
Fang Bin has gone missing again.
According to Quartz,
he was arrested the same day he posted this
video to YouTube.
“Resist, all citizens!
Hand the power of the government back to the
people!”
I wonder if that’s connected.
Fang’s disappearance comes less than a week
after
another citizen journalist, Chen Qiushi,
who traveled to Wuhan to cover the outbreak,
disappeared.
According to his family,
he may have been forcibly quarantined by local
authorities,
even though he wasn’t sick.
Here’s part of a video Chen posted shortly
before he disappeared.
I’m afraid.
In front of me is the virus,
and behind me is the legal and administrative
power of China.
As long as I live in this city,
I will continue to report.
I only report what I see and what I hear.
I really want to be blunt, right?
Today, I’m going to say something blunt.
Mfer,
I’m not even afraid of death.
You think I’m afraid of the Communist Party?
I can see why the Communist Party
felt that Chen needed to be quarantined.
They don’t want him to spread his dangerous...ideas.
But I wouldn’t want you to think the Chinese
Communist Party
is only dealing with the coronavirus through
cover ups,
property theft, and detaining journalists.
They’re also firing people.
In a classic move,
the Communist Party secretaries of Hubei province
and Wuhan are being purged.
Everyone saw that one coming.
But Chinese officials who aren’t yet purged
are still fighting the coronavirus!
The state-run China News Service released
this footage.
It shows a sterilizing wheel in the city of
Qongqing
that can disinfect a person in 20 seconds.
Wow, the Party is great!
They built two of these, which, combined,
they say,
can meet the needs of a thousand people!
That sounds great, unless you can do math.
Then you realize that in a city of 30 million
people,
this meets the needs of just 0.003% of the
population.
Taiwan has crashed a WHO meeting.
Who needs permission when you’re a BALLER!
Actually, it was way less cool than that.
It was just an online technical conference.
Also, Taiwan worked it out ahead of time with
the WHO.
But Taiwan crashing the world’s lamest party
was still a big deal for the world’s most
authoritarian Party.
The Chinese Communist Party gets angry when
any organization—
including the WHO—
treats Taiwan in any way
that implies Taiwan is an independent country.
Even if that means risking the lives of 23
million Taiwanese people.
But there is one party that I’m sure is
worth everyone’s time.
In the Chinese city of Chongqing,
a man wrapped himself with firecrackers,
doused himself in gasoline
and threatened to set himself alight
unless village officials approved his birthday
party amid the outbreak.
That’s a man who takes his birthday a little
too seriously.
And that’s it for this update on the coronavirus.
And as you may have heard me mention YouTube
is targeting coronavirus coverage
as “too controversial for advertisers.”
All our episodes about the coronavirus have
been demonetized—
either temporarily or permanently.
If a news show can’t generate income while
reporting the news,
it can’t survive.
YouTube would have shut down China Uncensored
years ago like this.
But fortunately,
we have the support of viewers like you,
who I call the China Uncensored 50 cent army.
Through your contributions on the crowd funding
website Patreon,
China Uncensored has survived to today,
so we can let you know about important China
issues that affect you,
like a deadly global pandemic.
So as a thank you to supporters,
I answer a question from them at the end of
some of my episodes.
Today’s question comes from Jump Dawg:
“Chris, is there any information on Coronavirus
infection
in China's rural areas?”
Now that’s a good question,
but answering it is going to be difficult.
If the Chinese regime can successfully cover
up the statistics of Wuhan,
a city of 11 million people,
it’s going to be even easier to cover it
up in more rural areas of China.
But I think we can guess that the coronavirus,
sorry COVID-19,
is hitting the poorest people in China the
hardest.
Those insanely rich Politburo members are
probably doing just fine.
The rural poor, however,
don’t have access to good hospitals,
or in some cases even mediocre hospitals.
Things may not end well for them.
But don’t worry,
top officials will be fine.
Thanks for your question, Jump Dawg.
And if you’d like to join the China Uncensored
50-cent army,
head over to patreon.com/chinauncensored to
learn more.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.