On this episode of China Uncensored,
sure, the Chinese Communist Party is trying
to steal
American innovation at every turn.
But that doesn’t mean we can’t take their
money, right?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Made in China.
A symbol of quality workmanship and cutting-edge
technology.
At least, that’s what Chinese leader Xi
Jinping
wants you to think.
In 2015, Xi Jinping announced a new economic
model
called Made in China, 2025.
It’s focused on “The task of upgrading
and accelerating technological development.”
On this show, we’ve talked about several
ways the Communist Party has,
uh, “accelerated technological development”
in the past.
Like by hacking and stealing US intellectual
property,
then reverse engineering it at Chinese Technology
Transfer Centers.
So much faster and easier than starting from
scratch.
China has also weaponized trade,
according to Republican Senate Majority Whip
John Cornyn.
“In many instances China has simply used
trade as a weapon,
coercing US companies into entering joint
ventures
and other business agreements that require
the company
to hand over key technology and know how,
the so-called secret sauce.”
And I always thought secret sauce was mayonnaise
plus high fructose corn syrup,
left out in the sun for three days.
Today, we’ll be talking about a third way
the Chinese Communist Party
acquires American tech.
They simply buy the American tech companies!
Part of Xi Jinping’s Made in China 2025
plan
is encouraging Chinese companies
to invest in foreign tech companies.
In particular—high tech industries like
artificial intelligence,
robotics and space travel.
You know, your basic Isaac Asimov novel.
I guess Xi must be a fan.
The amount of money China has pumped into
US tech
skyrocketed after Made in China 2025 was announced.
Deals with Chinese investors jumped from 66
in 2013 to 165 in 2017.
Chinese companies have invested in everything
from Uber, to Airbnb,
to even Grindr!
I think the Chinese government might be getting
a little more data than they bargained for
with Grindr.
Ok, Grindr jokes aside, in some cases,
Chinese companies are investing in tech companies
that are developing technology critical to
national defense or infrastructure,
or that possess a lot of data on Americans.
The Pentagon considers all this investment—not
just Grindr—
a serious risk for the United States.
This report from last year warns that the
Chinese Communist Party
is stealing the Crown Jewels of U.S. Innovation.
Yes, those are the jewels everyone on Grindr
is suddenly worried about.
China’s venture capital investment is at
an all time high.
And, according to the Pentagon’s report,
the US government isn’t doing enough to
address the risk.
The threat is so serious that both President
Obama
and President Trump agree on it.
And I thought they didn’t agree on anything.
In December 2016,
Obama stopped a Chinese takeover of the US
subsidiary
of a German semiconductor manufacturer.
The semiconductors industry makes the microchips
that are the core of any advanced technology
the Chinese Communist Party would like to
get their hands on.
Obama blocking that takeover helped curb
the amount of Chinese money going to into
US tech.
But Chinese companies potentially buying sensitive
US technology
was still a problem.
In September 2017,
Trump blocked a Chinese purchase of Lattice,
another US semiconductor maker.
And earlier this year,
Trump blocked the sale of yet another US chipmaker
because of Chinese security issues.
Obama and Trump weren’t doing this on their
own, though.
Although they blocked these deals using executive
orders,
they did it on the recommendation of
the Committee on Foreign Investment in the
United States,
or CFIUS.
CFIUS is a committee that involves several
top-level US government agencies,
and it’s chaired by the Treasury Secretary.
It was founded in 1975 to oversee purchases
of critical US industries by foreign countries.
But the CFIUS committee hardly ever met.
Until after 9/11.
Then Congress passed new legislation
that increased the role of CFIUS.
And according to Politico,
CFIUS did not have the resources to keep pace.
One official described 80-hour work weeks
with no time off.
CFIUS carries so much weight that just their
recommendation
against a deal is often enough to make it
fall apart,
without even getting the president involved.
At the beginning of this year,
CFIUS rejected a planned Chinese takeover
of Moneygram
because of national security concerns.
A month later, CFIUS rejected a state-backed
Chinese company’s
acquisition of another US chip maker.
But, an overworked CFIUS can’t catch everything.
Here’s an example.
Last year, a semiconductor maker, ATop Tech,
filed for bankruptcy.
But, it had a market share of 1 billion dollars,
because of a ground-breaking product:
“an automated designer capable of making
microchips
that could power anything from smartphones
to high-tech weapons systems.”
So a company called Avatar Integrated Systems
swooped in and bought it.
Now no one in the semiconductor industry had
ever heard of them.
Turns out,
it belonged to a big shot in China’s steel
industry,
and it looked like he set up Avatar
for the sole purpose of buying ATop Tech.
At the time,
others in the semiconductor industry
and even a Pentagon official had warned the
bankruptcy court
that letting Avatar buy ATop Tech was a bad
idea.
But the deal went through anyway,
because the whole thing flew under the radar
of CFIUS.
Last year,
Defense Secretary Jim Mattis warned that
“CFIUS is both outdated and overburdened”
...and needed to be updated.
The Trump Administration said,
“modernizing CFIUS would strengthen our
ability
to protect national security and enhance confidence
in our longstanding open investment policy.”
There are two bipartisan bills going through
Congress
that aim to strengthen CFIUS.
They want to do things like expand the types
of transactions
CFIUS would look at,
including bankruptcy cases like ATop Tech.
But there are some serious challenges to CFIUS
even if one of the bills passes.
See, it’s not as simple as just blocking
a Chinese state-owned enterprise
from purchasing, say, American Secret Sauce
Inc.
What about a Chinese national,
who becomes a New Zealand citizen,
but gets his money from the Communist Party,
and wants to buy an American business?
What about a Mexican company whose stock
is partly owned by a Chinese conglomerate,
and that Mexican company wants to buy an American
business?
What about a local Chinese businessman in
the United States,
who’s a US citizen,
but the Communist Party is funneling money
to him through a relative?
Things start to get very murky,
and you have deal with some unpleasant things
that the Chinese Communist Party would love
to exploit.
Like, the idea that stopping Chinese investment
is motivated by racism.
Then there’s the counter argument by those
who want to
see more Chinese investment.
An IBM policy executive said in a January
Congressional hearing
that the new bill “could constitute the
most economically harmful imposition
of unilateral trade restrictions by the United
States in many decades.”
I mean sure, China is run by an authoritarian
regime
with a national plan to systematically steal
Western technology.
But they’ve got a lot of money,
and we want it!
Why be a negative nancy?!
And it’s that kind of broad-minded policy
vision
that led IBM to sell punch-card technology
to the Nazis,
enabling them to “calculate exactly how
many Jews
should be emptied out of the ghettos each
day”
and onto trains to you-know-where.
A similar argument is made overall in Silicon
Valley—
that Chinese investment money is a good thing
and fuels innovation.
I get it.
It seems like,
it’s a free country,
why not take the money!
It doesn’t matter who it comes from.
And that fits in just fine with the Chinese
Communist Party’s
plan for Made in China 2025.
So what do you think about Chinese investment
in US tech?
Leave your comments below.
And before you go,
it’s that time when we answer a question
from a supporter of the show,
a member of our China Uncensored 50-Cent Army.
This question comes from...
Jonathan Swanberg
“Hi Chris,”
Hi Jonathan.
“What is the real cost of stolen Intellectual
Property (IP)
from the US to China?”
Great question.
The answer depends on who you ask.
The Intellectual Property Commission says
IP
theft costs the US economy $600 billion dollars
a year,
largely from China.
But it might be much bigger than that.
Casey Fleming—
whose company BLACKOPS Partners Corporation
consults for Fortune 500 companies—
he says the actual cost is closer to $5 trillion
dollars a year.
And that’s because
(a) You have to factor in the total future
value.
Not just products sold,
but also the loss of future innovation and
American jobs.
And (b)
A lot of big companies that get hacked, haha,
don’t report it publicly because it’s
too embarrassing
and could make stock prices drop.
It’s quite likely that the Chinese military
has hacked
just about every big American corporation.
It just doesn’t get publicized.
And that’s all for this episode of China
Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
On the one hand,
I’d love to take millions of dollars from
some mysterious company in China.
On the other hand,
that might sliiiightly affect the integrity
of China Uncensored.
That’s why we’re funded by direct support
from viewers like you,
members of our 50-Cent Army who contributed
a dollar or more per episode.
Click this orange button to visit our Patreon
page and become a supporter.