On this episode of China Uncensored
I'm rubber and you are...
one of the most powerful politicians in the
world!
Hello and welcome to China Uncensored, I'm
your host, Chris Chappell.
Did everyone have a good Labor Day?
I spent mine at the half-off Ray Ban sale.
But while the rest of America was taking one
last trip to the beach,
President Obama was hard at work
at the G20 summit in scenic Hangzhou, China.
What makes it scenic is that you can actually
see it.
Unlike in other Chinese cities,
where you can measure smog by the pound.
In fact, the Hangzhou government recently
issued a reminder
to visitors from other parts of China:
no need to worry,
that big ball of fire in the sky is just the
sun.
So President Obama was in Hangzhou for the
G20 summit,
which is the annual meeting of leaders of
the world's 20 biggest economies.
China's state-run media declared the summit
a huge success,
and proved it with a slideshow of Xi Jinping
shaking hands with other world leaders.
I know they're trying to make Xi Jinping look
powerful,
but I gotta say, with every photo,
he looks more and more like he has to pee.
It's because it's Japan.
And it was also a success according to this
Reuters article,
because "open confrontation [was] largely
avoided."
Setting the bar pretty low there.
That's like saying Thanksgiving was a success
this year
because Aunt Marge didn't get drunk
and accuse Uncle Al of making her give up
her dreams of being an artist...again.
The success of the G20 is good news for the
Chinese authorities,
who congratulated themselves on their speed
gentrification of Hangzhou.
They made the city appear clean, upwardly
mobile, and harmonious.
Clean, by shutting down factories to reduce
pollution;
Upwardly mobile, by forcing millions of poor
migrant workers to leave the city;
and harmonious by arresting human rights activists.
Thereby solving all of China’s fundamental
problems.
After all, if you can’t see it, it doesn’t
exist.
Which is the way I approach my student loan
debt.
We got a lot of people who can relate to that.
Why was the Chinese regime so hung up on having
the summit be perfect?
Hosting prestigious international events
is part of their decades-long push for increasing
their "soft power."
No, that's not the last man standing in a
pillow fight.
“Soft power” is projecting a positive
image of China
that will get them increasing influence and
respect on the global stage.
Like when Kanye West says he’ll stop being
a douchebag.
Hey, that’s a hygienic product and a compliment.
But it didn’t go totally smoothly for China.
When President Obama landed in Hangzhou for
the G20,
he couldn’t get off the plane,
because someone forgot to bring—the stairs.
That made it look like China was snubbing
the US,
which Chinese officials deny.
And I actually believe them,
because forgetting to take passengers off
the plane happens all the time.
Anybody here ever fly into Newark?
But hey, Obama was cool with that,
he just went out the cargo bay door.
"I'm out of here in ahhh 6 months.
I could give ahhh diddly, ahhh squat."
And that would have been fine...
except that US reporters went to go watch
Obama getting off the plane.
And they were stopped by Chinese authorities.
And when the reporters protested,
one Chinese official shouted,
"This is our country, this is our airport."
And then US Secret Service was like,
well, your airport sucks.
And then the Chinese Ministry of State Security
was like, your face sucks.
And then the US State Department was all like
“Fine, China, we won't sit with you at the
G20 lunch table.
And neither will Germany or France.”
Obviously that last part was a joke.
It would never get that ridiculous.
And we wouldn't have actual government agencies
getting involved.
Actually, Chris--
What’s that Shelley?
Well, the US Defense Intelligence Agency actually did respond
They Tweeted: "Classy as always China."
Haha, that's a pretty good one.
That's not a joke, Chris.
I've got the tweet right here.
Wow.
I guess global politics really is like middle
school.
How did Chinese officials respond?
Luckily, Twitter is banned in China.
Right, if you can't see it, it doesn't exist.
The point is:
there was some controversy at the G20.
In fact, the diplomatic fight inspired the
Globe and Mail
to publish this article
about how the cracks are showing behind China's
soft power push.
China spends an estimated 10 billion dollars
a year on external propaganda.
But the Globe and Mail says the rest of the
world isn't so impressed anymore.
They quote China experts comparing China today
to South Africa during apartheid.
The say China's government is much
worse now than it was five years ago.
According to the article,
2016 China is so different from the China
of 2008,
which\h"held the world spellbound with the
sweep of its modernization,
the skill of its planners
and the competitiveness of its athletes.
Yes, 2008 China was so dreamy.
But then it put on some weight,
grew a beard and kept hanging out with supermodels
nearly half its age.
But here's the truth about 2008 China.
The one that supposedly held the world spellbound.
Here's how the Chinese government
prepared for the 2008 Summer Olympics in Beijing.
They guaranteed that the city would be clean,
modern, and harmonious.
Clean by shutting down factories to reduce
pollution;
modern, by demolishing half a million homes
and displacing more than a million people;
and harmonious, by arresting human rights
activists.
Sound familiar?
Look, it's not that the Chinese regime
has suddenly and unexpectedly gotten worse.
It's been bad for a long time.
But they were just better at hiding it,
and most of us honestly weren't paying that
much attention.
I mean, we didn’t even have China Uncensored
back then,
so how could you have known about it?
So it may seem like if you can't see it, it
doesn't exist.
But the good news is that now,
more and more, we can see it.
Just like the air in Beijing.
So what do you think of the G20 and China's
soft power push?
Leave your comments below.
Once again, I'm Chris Chappell. See you
next time.