China wants to replace the United States
as the regional power in the Middle East.
And big deals with Saudi Arabia are the key.
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Saudi Arabia has been a long-time US ally.
Sometimes even a close friend.
All the way through President Trump, too—
though he seems slightly less comfortable
with the hand-holding.
Now the story of why the US and Saudi Arabia
have been friends is a whole other topic.
Maybe someday on America Uncovered.
But the big news is that the Chinese Communist
Party
is looking to step in.
Chinese leader Xi Jinping wants to tie Saudi
Arabia
to his Belt and Road Initiative—
the trillion dollar global infrastructure
plan
supported by a seriously terrible propaganda
song.
The future's coming now!
The Belt and Road is how!
That song is also a virulent strain of earworn.
Anyway, the Chinese Communist Party’s ultimate
goal
in improving ties with Saudi Arabia is to
become
a dominant foreign power in the Middle East.
Of course, history has not always been kind
to
foreign powers in the Middle East.
But the Chinese Communist Party probably doesn’t
know this,
since it rewrote all the Chinese language
history books.
I guess nothing happened between 1966 and
1976.
Ok, back to Saudi Arabia.
That country invests heavily in the United
States.
And it’s mainly through the state-owned
Saudi Public Investment Fund.
It’s one of the largest sovereign wealth
funds in the Middle East,
with about 300 billion dollars in assets.
That’s a lot of money.
Like, investing three-and-a-half billion dollars
into Uber
was chump change.
By 2030, the Saudi Public Investment Fund
plans to invest more than 2 trillion dollars
worldwide.
And a big chunk of that could end up in China.
The head of the Saudi Fund was in Beijing
last month
for a forum on Xi Jinping’s Belt and Road
Initiative.
He told CNBC,
“This is the first time for me to go out
and meet asset managers,
companies, Chinese entrepreneurs,
and they are really very impressive.”
And now, a spokesman for the fund said they
were
“planning to open a new office in Asia ‘to
focus on China.’”
Now wait just a minute.
Questionable dealings with Saudi Arabia
are supposed to be a US thing!
This is just another case of the Chinese Communist
Party
stealing our intellectual property.
And they’ve been working on this for a while.
In February, the Saudi Crown Prince
met Xi Jinping in China.
They had great things to say about each other.
Xi Jinping said,
“The two countries should speed up
the signing of an implementation plan
on connecting the Belt and Road Initiative
with the Saudi Vision 2030.”
That’s Saudi Arabia’s own massive economic
plan.
And the Crown Prince said,
“Saudi Arabia is full of confidence in the
bright future
of China's development under the leadership
of President Xi.”
That was obviously the right thing to say,
because the two countries then signed
28 billion dollars in deals.
Wait, that gives me an idea!
You know, I, too am full of confidence in
the bright future
of China’s development under the leadership
of Presitator Xi.
Can I have 28 billion dollars now?
No?
How about just enough to pay off my student
loans?
OK, how about a tunafish sandwich?
Anyway, that 28 billion was just a continuation
of a 65 billion dollar investment and trade
deal
signed by the Saudi King and Xi Jinping in
2017.
It’s good to be king.
You can hold hands with every world leader.
Many of the Belt and Road projects
will include energy grids and ports.
There are reasons behind these agreements.
China is hungry for oil.
Especially to fuel the Belt and Road.
China gets oil from all over the Middle East,
and has invested heavily in the region.
And that’s made China a powerful force,
as different countries, including Saudi Arabia,
compete for Chinese investment.
Now, China has historically had trouble in
the Middle East
because they’ve supported Iran for years.
And a lot of other Middle Eastern countries...
don’t like Iran.
But the Chinese Communist Party has solved
that problem...
with billions of dollars.
Yes, through the Belt and Road,
China has become the largest trading partner
of the Arab League, including Saudi Arabia,
as well as Iran.
And the Chinese Communist Party could even
eventually replace the US as a power in the
Middle East.
I mean it’s been so fun and easy for the
US;
I can see why China would want a piece of
the action.
So Saudi Arabia is boosting oil exports to
China.
And it’s helping China build several of
its own oil refineries,
through joint ventures with the Saudi
State-run oil company Aramco.
Saudi Arabia is also helping build
a 10-billion-dollar oil refinery
in a Chinese-controlled port in Pakistan.
That’s key Belt and Road real estate right
there.
These oil deals are important,
because the latest US sanctions on Iranian
oil
also apply to China.
Meaning, the Chinese regime either has to
defy US sanctions, and face the penalty,
or it has to find other sources of oil.
Though so far,
China hasn’t reached out to Saudi Arabia
for more oil.
As far as we know.
But to say the China-Saudi relationship is
just about oil would be crude.
Saudi Arabia also is a strategic location
for China’s Belt and Road Initiative.
It would give China access to the Red Sea
through Saudi ports,
which means easier access to the Suez Canal
and the Mediterranean Sea,
where China controls a major port to Europe
through Greece.
And is also investing in a key port in Italy.
And Saudi Arabia gets more out of this
than just a market for oil.
It gets an alternative to the United States.
Global oil prices are being kept down
by increased US shale oil production.
And inside the US,
there’s less support for Saudi Arabia,
especially over the war in Yemen.
However, President Trump vetoed that resolution.
Still, Saudi Arabia is looking for new allies.
To that end,
Saudi schools will now be teaching Mandarin.
That decision happened after that 28 billion
dollar deal
Saudi Arabia and China signed in February.
Because when you’re an absolute monarch,
you can just decide those things on the spot.
And you can also totally sell out the Muslims
inside China
without public oversight.
The Chinese regime has been putting the Uighurs,
a mostly Muslim ethnic minority,
into concentration camps
and trying to wipe out their language and
culture.
They call it fighting terrorism and extremism.
Well, after that 28 billion dollar deal,
the Saudi Crown Prince said
“China has the right to carry out anti-terrorism
and de-extremisation work for its national
security.”
And if that involves putting a million Uighur
Muslims
into Chinese concentration camps,
so be it.
At least they’ll be learning Mandarin.
So what do you think of Saudi Arabia’s
growing ties with China?
Leave your comments below.
And now, I’m going to answer a question
from one of you—
who supports China Uncensored
through the crowdfunding website Patreon.
Today’s question comes from...
Charlie Matsubara.
“What are the best and worst things about
living and working in NYC?”
What’s the best thing?
Living in a city that has pancakes this fluffy.
I’m kind of obsessed.
What’s the worst thing?
Living in a city that has pancakes this fluffy.
I’m pretty sure I’ve discovered a new
type of diabetes.
Thanks for you question.
And if you’d like me to answer your question
on the show,
sign up to support China Uncensored
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
We rely on your support to keep the show going
since YouTube likes demonetizing videos
that are too controversial.
Which happens to include a lot of videos
that criticize the Chinese Communist Party.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.