On this episode of China Uncensored,
this advanced technology could secretly make
you sick,
and the whole time you’d have no idea what’s
going on.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your...
wait do you hear that?!
It’s like some kind of subtle and vague,
but abnormal sensations of sound and pressure.
“...we got a health alert saying,
I can read you part of it,
a US government employee in China recently
reported
subtle and vague, but abnormal sensations
of sound and pressure.”
Wow!
Are they sure it wasn’t just from watching
CNN?
On Wednesday, an embassy spokesperson reported
that an employee in the US consulate in Guangzhou
...experienced a “variety of physical symptoms”
between late 2017 and April 2018.
The employee was sent back to the United States,
and diagnosed with a “mild traumatic brain
injury.”
This statement from the embassy warns,
“While in China,
if you experience any unusual acute auditory
or sensory phenomena
accompanied by unusual sounds or piercing
noises,
do not attempt to locate their source.
Instead, move to a location where the sounds
are not present.”
Which sounds really creepy.
Especially since it’s consistent with what’s
called a sonic attack.
And no, that’s not the newest burger from
Sonic.
A sonic attack uses weaponized frequencies
that can’t be heard clearly by the human
ear,
but can trigger very real physical responses.
The BBC says some of the symptoms include,
“vertigo, vomiting or uncontrollable defecation.”
Which is also a symptom of your late night
Sonic Attack.
According to the US Secretary of State,
what happened to the US diplomat in China
is medically similar
to what happened US diplomats in Cuba back
in 2016.
“We had an incident in Guangzhou that was,
that the medical indications are very similar
and entirely consistent with the medical indications
that have taken place to Americans working
in Cuba.”
If you’re curious, Gizmodo has uploaded
that sound,
which seems like an incredibly bad idea, but
hey, it’s the internet.
Let’s take a listen.
Yeah, it’s definitely Yanny.
What’s that, Shelley?
What do you mean, it’s Laurel?
Ugh, well you’re obviously wrong.
Anyway, enough of that!
It’s time for another fan question.
Brett, Uhh, Brett asks,
Has China Uncensored gotten any offers from
Superfunds,
SuperPACs or other geopolitcal groups to push
a specific political agenda?
Good question.
Let me put it this way.
The other day we reached out to Audible for
sponsorship.
You know, Audible, that advertises on everything.
Well, apparently they felt China Uncensored
was too “political.”
If you’re political agenda is criticizing
Communism and the Chinese communist Party,
it's pretty hard to find support.
Superfunds?
Geopolitical groups?
Not likely.
That’s why we rely on you, my 50 cent army!
Fans of the show who contribute a dollar or
more per episode
on the China Uncensored page on the website
Patreon.
And as a way of saying thanks,
you get to submit questions we answer an air.
So if you’re already a Patreon supporter,
don’t forget to leave your questions for
me over on Patreon.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Thanks for watching.
Click this orange button to support
China Uncensored on Patreon.
Join thousands of other fans to make China
Uncensored even better.
Click here now.