China, Russia, and Iran
Are teaming up for Naval Drills
In the Indian Ocean
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
This episode is sponsored by Surfshark.
You should be using a VPN like Surfshark to
protect yourself whenever you go online.\h
So, President Biden is facing a lot of challenges
in just the first few weeks of his presidency.
The latest—a meeting of the Legion of Doom.
That’s right, Russia, China, and Iran are
holding joint naval drills in the Indian Ocean.
I’m sure India is thrilled.
The naval drills will begin mid-February.
Wait a minute.
Mid-February?
I know what this is.
It’s a new holiday.\h
Look at the success of Valentines spin-off
holiday Galentine’s Day.\h
So obviously the next step is Villain-tine’s
Day.
When you celebrate with all of your favorite
villains.\h\h
And their navies.\h
According to Moscow’s ambassador to Tehran,
“The drills would rehearse search and rescue
operations and ensuring the safety of shipping.”
Similar drills were held back in 2019.
Now get this—these new drills were announced
shortly after the only US aircraft carrier
in the Middle East—the USS Nimitz was ordered
back to the US.
Last year, the Trump Administration had ordered
the Nimitz remain in the area because of heightened
tensions with Iran.
But according to the New York Times, since
President Biden is looking to renew the Iran
Nuclear Deal that Trump withdrew from, he
ordered the ship back to its home port in
Washington.
But the alliance between Russia, Iran, and
China is making the US military pretty nervous.
This week, US Central Command chief Gen. Kenneth
McKenzie gave a keynote speech about the threats
posed by these powers.
He said, “The United States faces increasing
competition in the [Middle East] from Russia
and China both vying for power and influence
through a combination of diplomatic, military
and economic means.”
And China has a particular interest in the
region.
“China is dependent on the region for half
of its crude oil.
China continues to cultivate trade relationships,
economic investment and comprehensive partnerships
among regional states.
China uses its ‘Belt and Road’ initiative
and the China-Pakistan economic corridor to
expand Chinese influence and presence within
the [region].”
However, the US is doing its own joint naval
drills, with Australia and Japan, clearly
aimed at sending a message to China.
According to a Chinese military analyst, “The
exercise is to ensure the connection between
the Guam base and other bases, if it comes
under attack from Beijing.”
That was backed up by a US General, who said,
“China and Russia can increasingly hold
overseas US bases at risk.
To adapt, the air force must evolve from its
dependence on well-established airfields or
risk building an operational edge.”
But in addition to those drills, it seems
the USS Nimitz (Corner Box) made a little
detour, and is now joining another US aircraft
carrier for training drills in the South China
Sea.
It’s “the first large-scale "freedom of
navigation" operation aimed at Beijing since
the start of the Biden presidency.”
And that “comes just days after the destroyer
USS John S. McCain conducted operations in
the vicinity of the Paracel Islands, a disputed
archipelago in the region claimed by China,
Vietnam and Taiwan.”
So things are really heating up in the South
China Sea.
This is going to turn out well.
And this episode is sponsored by Surfshark.
When you go online, you should be using a
VPN like Surfshark to protect your identity.
Everything you do online is being tracked
and logged—by the websites you visit and
your internet service provider.
And in many cases, by the government.
And if you’re in an authoritarian country
like China, Russia, or Iran—this kind of
tracking can put you at risk of surveillance
and even arrest.
So I recommend you use Surfshark to protect
yourself online.
When you use Surfshark’s CleanWeb mode,
you’ll be protected from trackers, plus
a lot of ads and malware.
With one account, you can connect as many
devices as you want.
Try it out with a 30-day money back guarantee.
And Surfshark has a special discount for China
Uncensored fans.
Go to surfshark.com/uncensored and use the
code UNCENSORED to get our special deal that
includes 3 extra months for FREE.
Click the link below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.