On this episode of China Uncensored,
Get LinkedIn... to a Chinese spy network!
We’re really running with the Cold War 2
theme
And finally, here’s one fight the Shaolin
Temple doesn’t want.
This is China Uncensored
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
The Chinese Communist Party wants to target
America’s best and brightest.
But there’s more than 300 million people
in the US.
If only there was some way to narrow down
and search for the ones with the right kind
of credentials.
Oh right!
LinkedIn.
See?
I’m even on there.
That’s why, according to the US counter
intelligence chief,
China is waging a super aggressive spy campaign
on LinkedIn.
Yes, LinkedIn.
The Chinese Communist Party
has even infiltrated the most boring social
media network.
And their spy campaign isn’t just super
aggressive,
it’s super effective, too.
Chinese agents have set up
an as of yet undisclosed number of fake accounts,
“contacting thousands of LinkedIn members
at a time.”
The Chinese agents look for foreigners
with access to government and commercial secrets.
Then they offer them jobs, for example,
at a so-called think tank in Shanghai.
And once the foreigner takes the job,
they’ll be expected to give up the secrets.
Sounds sketchy and super illegal, sure.
But you got to admit,
it’s a pretty clever way to
trick people into betraying their country:
“Hey, it’s my job!
I have to do it for money!”
So far, we don’t know how many people
this aggressive campaign has successfully
recruited.
But this is something both British
and German authorities have warned of previously.
Which is why I’ve added to my LinkedIn profile
that I’m not a good candidate for a spy.
The US has asked LinkedIn to take action
to shut down these Chinese agents’ accounts.
Could you imagine being the Chinese spy
whose job is to recruit people through LinkedIn?
You thought you were going to be James Bond,
but instead you’re writing the worst recruiting
emails ever.
And incidentally, this is not the first time
LinkedIn
has been at the center of some China controversy.
When they went into the China market back
in 2014,
they started censoring users’ profiles on
the Chinese site
if those profiles had content relating to
the Tiananmen Square Massacre or Falun Gong.
Even if those users were in America.
The modern world depends on technology in
space.
For example,
if it weren’t the GPS satellites
put up by the US government,
I wouldn’t be able to use Google Maps
to find the nearest Medieval Times theme restaurant,
and enjoy an evening of good old-fashioned
jousting.
So, since we rely so much on GPS satellites...
this might be a problem.
For years, China has been building up
its anti-satellite capabilities.
In 2007, China shot down
one of its own weather satellites with a missile.
Its most recent anti-satellite test was last
year.
Chinese authorities claimed it was just
a totally normal missile defense system.
The US, for its part,
has been falling behind China and Russia
for the future of space warfare
But really, these are exciting times.
As a top official said, we’re in Cold War
With an Arms Race 2
With a Space Race 2
Now some might tell you this could all lead
to World War 3.
But, really, that’s ridiculous.
It will be Space Wars 1.
I said “space wars”, Disney.
You can’t sue me!
But I wouldn’t want you to worry that
we won’t still have warfare right here on
Earth, too.
Because China may be also helping with that.
China is helping to set up
a mountain brigade in Afghanistan to fight
terrorism.
And China has a long history of mountain brigades.
What?
It’s clearly an Outlaws of the Marsh reference.
Come on, people!
It’s a classic.
It’s literally one of the four Chinese classics.
Ok, back to Afghanistan...sadly.
Now, supposedly,
Chinese troops won’t actually be on Afghan
soil,
according to the Afghan embassy in Beijing.
But despite that very believable denial,
China has already paid for and started building
a training base
for Afghan troops inside Afghanistan—
in the the Wakhan Corridor,
which is next to China’s Xinjiang Autonomous
Region.
Xinjiang is where the Communist Party
has detained up to a million Muslims.
Is this mountain brigade really about fighting
terrorism?
Or is it more about cutting off any hope of
escape?
Speaking of no escape,
China’s State council has made it easy
for the happy people of Macau, Hong Kong,
and Taiwan to get Chinese residence cards—
so they can live and/or work in mainland China.
Surely there’s no sinister catch to this!
Here’s the sinister catch.
Misbehave, lose the card.
That could spell trouble for say, Hong Kongers,
who hold the incorrect view of democracy in
Hong Kong.
Or Taiwanese who hold the incorrect view of
what a country is.
Speaking of gradually eroding freedoms,
a new high speed rail linking Hong Kong and
Mainland China
is opening soon.
Part of the train station inside Hong Kong
has been ceded to Mainland Chinese control.
Meaning, for example,
mainland anti-subversion laws can be enforced
in Hong Kong—
if you’re, say, a dissident
and accidentally step over the line.
Now I know that sounds controversial, but
don’t worry.
The handover was done in a secret ceremony.
“The event was closed to press and neither
news media
nor local lawmakers were given advance notice.”
Probably because if they announced it,
too many overjoyed people would have come
to the train station
to celebrate this historic event,
creating a public safety issue.
That must be the reason.
Hong Kong’s chief executive Carrie Lam,
who was appointed by pro-Beijing interest
groups,
tried to ease Hong Kongers’ worries.
She said “It was not a ceremony per se,”
and also that, “There was nothing sneaky.”
Which is about as reassuring as when your
friend says,
don’t worry, your car is fine.
You have collision insurance, right?
The Chinese Communist Party is not spiteful.
I would never accuse it of that.
But, remember how Australia barred Chinese
telecom companies
from building their 5G network,
because of national security concerns?
Well, it turns out, that same day, in a total
coincidence,
the biggest Australian broadcaster, ABC,
was blocked on the Chinese internet.
Or the ban could be because I was once interviewed
on ABC.
Six months ago.
Ok, it was probably because of Huawei.
The Chinese Communist Party is trying to “sinicize”
religions.
In other words, make religions
more loyal to the Chinese Communist Party.
Maybe this is some sort of
alternative to persecuting Christians.
And Muslims.
And Tibetans.
And Falun Gong.
I mean, wouldn’t it be easier of those religions
could just be morally flexible,
and change their core beliefs to worship
the atheist Communist Partyinstead of their
god or whatever?
Of course it would!
And you know who “gets it”?
The Shaolin Temple.
They just hoisted the Chinese flag.
A first in its 1,500 year history.
State-run media said it was because
they were leading the way in sinicization.
Although, according to one Shaolin monk
who spoke to Radio Free Asia,
it was because authorities forced them to
do it.
I mean...couldn’t they have fought back?
Isn’t fighting back what Shaolin monks are
supposed to do?!
It’s the kung fu movie we’re all waiting
to see!
A small group of rebel monks take on
and defeat the entire Chinese paramilitary!
While playing soccer!
But sadly, the only kung fu move they did
was “docile tiger, obedient dragon”.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And now the moment you’ve been waiting for,
I answer questions from fans who are
a part of the China Uncensored 50 Cent Army,
a group of rebel viewers who support this
show
on the crowd funding website Patreon.
David Michael White asks,
“Chris, will you participate in No Shave
November?”
Oh David.
You don’t remember the last time I did that?
Never again.
I can’t do that to all of you.
Unless, you think it looks good...
I could be talked into it...
what’s that Shelley?
Okay, I will not be growing a mustache again.
Thanks for your question, David.
And for all of you, if you want to send me
your questions,
become a member of the China Uncensored 50
cent army
by supporting the show on Patreon with a dollar
or more per episode.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
Thanks for watching.
Did you know we also make a half-hour version
of this show every week?
It’s broadcast on the NTD network in New
York, LA, and San Francisco.
Plus you can it on our free app for Amazon
FireTV, Apple TV, and Roku.
Or visit ChinaUncensored.tv.