On this episode of China Uncensored,
China has agreed to stop selling oil to North
Korea.
So why does it seem like China
is still selling oil to North Korea?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Matt Gnaizda.
Chris is still on vacation
somewhere much warmer than New York.
But unfortunately, I’m not.
On today’s episode,
is the Chinese Communist Party violating UN
sanctions
by sending oil to North Korea?
This story was sparked by—yes,
another 140-character announcement
from the Leader of the Free World.
President Trump wrote:
“Caught RED HANDED—
very disappointed that China
is allowing oil to go into North Korea.”
And the thing about Trump Tweets is that,
after he types just a few sentence fragments
with his thumbs,
the entire world feels compelled to respond.
Including us at China Uncensored, apparently.
So first, Trump uses Twitter
to accuse the Chinese regime
of allowing oil transfers to North Korea
despite UN sanctions that they agreed to.
Then, the Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesperson
admitted everything.
Just kidding.
She denied it.
I assume she was just taking advice from Shaggy.
It wasn’t me!
Specifically, the spokesperson said China
never allows Chinese citizens and companies
to engage in activities that violate
UN Security Council resolutions.
Except, for, um,
how South Korea seized that ship,
with a Chinese crew,
on its way to deliver oil to North Korea.
And then seized a second ship
suspected of providing oil to North Korea.
So yeah, except for those two times—
plus maybe a few other times authorities
hopefully don’t ever find out about—
Chinese citizens and companies
would never engage in activities
that violate UN Security Council resolutions.
By the way,
the first ship was actually caught in late
November.
South Korea said it had seized
the Lighthouse Winmore,
which had a Hong Kong flag.
It was suspected of transferring 4,000 barrels
of oil
to a North Korean ship.
The second oil ship, the KOTI,
was seized on December 19
at a South Korean port about 50 miles
south of the North Korean border.
It had a Panamanian flag,
but the crew was mostly from China...
and also Myanmar, weirdly.
South Korean media says
intelligence and customs agents are still
investigating.
But, c’mon, what difference
does a few thousand barrels of oil make?
Apparently, a lot.
Over the past year,
the US has been pressuring China hard,
to get them to stop all trade with North Korea.
It’s a different tactic than the Obama administration
used.
The had tried to convince North Korea
to give up its nuclear weapons program
through Six-Party Talks,
and by issuing stern warnings.
“I’m uhhh very disappointed in uhhh your
behavior.
I want you to stop, or I’m uhhh
going to ask you again.
Nicely.”
But for some reason that didn’t work.
So the new administration is trying out a
tactic
from the guy who comes to the presidency
with a different kind of life experience:
“I’m rich.”
“I’m really rich.”
“The beauty of me is that I’m really rich.”
So the rich man’s solution
is to go after their money.
Squeeze the money until North Korea is in
so much pain
it cries uncle.
Oh wait, Kim Jong-un already killed his uncle.
Anyway, North Korean leader
and extreme hair clipper enthusiast, Kim Jong-un,
has been threatening the US with his nukes.
Kind of.
By saying “the entire United States
is within range of our nuclear weapons.”
Which is such a thinly veiled threat
that it’s pretty much see-through.
It’s like saying,
“You know, I’m standing close enough to
your face
that it’s within throwing distance of my
fist.
I’m not threatening you.
I’m just stating the fact
that you are within range.”
So at the US’s urging,
China has, in theory,
stopped oil exports to North Korea.
This is something that is
“painful and potentially destabilizing
to the regime of Kim Jong-un.”
Well, apparently, it’s working.
Despite the occasional accidental shipment
of 4,000 barrels of oil.
Because, again, according to prolific Tweeter
and also president Donald Trump,
“Sanctions and ‘other’ pressures
are beginning to have a big impact on North
Korea...
Rocket man now wants to talk to South Korea
for first time.
Perhaps that is good news,
perhaps not—
we will see,
exclamation point.”
We will see, actually—
maybe even this coming Tuesday.
Because South Korea has proposed
high-level talks with North Korea.
Technically, the talks are supposed to be
mostly about North Korea’s participation
in the upcoming Pyeongchang Winter Olympics.
But also, they might maybe hopefully talk
about
that other little thing.
Well, yeah, but specifically, that little
thing.
Fortunately, we know that talks with North
Korea
always work.
At least they might work now,
as long as Chinese authorities
actually cut off North Korea’s oil supply,
instead of just saying they’re definitely
not not doing it.
Wait, what’s that, Shelley?
What?
Russia is supplying North Korea with oil?!
What do you think?
Will this new US strategy be at least
marginally more effective than the old one?
Leave your comments below.
Once again, I’m Matt Gnaizda.
Time for a loud beep.
Now I know why Chris needs a vacation.
Unfortunately for him,
he’ll be back at the end of next week.
In the meantime,
check out our website,
ChinaUncensored.tv,
for all the half-hour episodes with Chris
you may have missed in 2017.
Click here.