On this episode of China Uncensored,
what to do with too many college graduates.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Being young in China isn't all sunshine and
bubble tea.
For example,
this year almost 8 million young people will
graduate university
and enter the job market.
And there’s not enough jobs for them.
If you thought the US job market was tough,
China is a place where 10,000 people applied
to be a receptionist.
Economic opportunities?
Hold please!
The housing situation is not a rosy picture
either.
In fact, a lot of them live together in crowded underground compounds
called ant colonies.
A large number of restless,
unemployed young people can be a recipe for
disaster.
Especially when they’re mostly men—
because of that whole sex-selective abortion
thing
that resulted from decades of the Communist
Party's One-Child policy.
Fortunately, the Party has a solution.
They've just issued guidelines calling for
more college graduates
to work in poor rural communities.
That actually sounds like a good idea:
Programs that would employ young people
while also using their skills to help the
country.
Let's see what the guidelines say.
Ok...here we go.
General requirements.
Guiding ideology?
“Fully implement the spirit of the 18th
National Congress of the CPC
and the Third Plenary Session of the 18th
CPC Central Committee,
the Fourth Plenary Session,
the Fifth Session of the CPC Central Committee,
the Sixth Plenary Session of the 18th CPC
Central Committee
and the Sixth Plenary Session of the 18th
CPC Central Committee,
thoroughly implement the new series of important speeches
of Xi Jinping...
something something...
four comprehensives...
core socialist values…”
Is this how they write everything?
Let's just skip ahead.
Ok, here's something.
Encouraging college students to join the PLA.
They’re calling on “excellent college
graduates
to make contributions from the army barracks.”
Hopefully more excellent than 3,500 students
in Peking University's 2011 class,
who made 6,000 trips to the doctor during
their mandatory
two-week military training.
Guess they just weren't ready for those long
marches.
But you see, there’s been a rise in military
dropouts.
According to China’s Military Service Law,
anyone between the ages of 18 and 22
must serve two years in the People’s Liberation
Army.
They won’t take just anyone though.
You have to be healthy,
and you have to hold the right political views.
For example,
for an officer,
30 to 40% of his career is spent not on training,
but on political work.
That is, “studying CCP propaganda,
singing patriotic songs,
and conducting small group discussions
on Marxist-Leninist theory.”
You can see why the Party
would want to encourage young people to volunteer.
What many young Chinese are doing
is opting to postpone the draft
until after they graduate from college.
By which point they’re past the age requirement
and can just skip it entirely.
Don’t worry,
even if they do,
they still won’t have missed out on that
patriotic education.
Across China,
first year high school students and college
freshman
are required to go through military training.
Mostly it involves marching drills and singing
patriotic songs -
something every teenager loves.
Military training for students began in 1955.
But then in 1989, this happened.
Waves of restless,
educated young people thought the Communist Party
wanted to hear what they had to say.
That didn’t go so well.
Universities were now seen as a problem for
the Party—
hotbeds of counter-revolutionary protest.
That’s when a comprehensive patriotic education
campaign
was started.
By 2001,
military training had become mandatory for
all high school
and college freshmen.
And it seems to have worked.
I mean, democracy was, like, so 80s.
But that doesn't necessarily translate
into people wanting to join the military.
For years,
the Chinese military was a career option for
people
who couldn't afford or get into college.
But Chinese leader Xi Jinping
is actually trying to make the military leaner—
by laying off hundreds of thousands of soldiers
and putting an emphasis on technology.
So why is the PLA
trying to recruit more excellent students?
Well, having more educated officers for one.
And as a bonus,
it’s a way to keep potentially restless
young people occupied
instead of festering as marginalized out of
work layabouts
in ant colonies.
Yeah, those Chinese youth are too entitled
and individualistic.
I mean, they may be hardworking,
but they're getting too selfish.
Do they even think about core socialist values
anymore?
Wait a minute...
that sounds familiar!
Chinese millennials sound just like us American
millennials.
Well, not the core socialist values part.
But we have more in common than you might think.
Maybe this is good.
Maybe we can all put a little less emphasis
on preparing to fight each other,
and go get some bubble tea instead.
So what do you think about China’s excellent
students?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.