On this episode of China Uncensored,
how not to make your village look good.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Chinese officials love promoting their local
jurisdictions.
It reflects well on them
and helps them not get purged.
It’s a proud tradition,
dating back to the days of the Great Leap
Forward,
when local officials would report huge crop yields,
even as crops lay rotting in the field
because the farmers were being forced to produce steel.
People literally moved their crops next to
the train tracks,
so that when Chairman Mao passed by,
things looked great!
Look at these kids,
jumping on a huge crop yield!
Too bad it's a fake photo—
one of the most famous ones used during the
Great Leap Forward.
Anyway, it led to famine.
It was a Great Famine though!
Of course, those were the old days.
Times have changed.
Now there’s Photoshop!
So local officials show their commitment to
their constituents
by visiting the elderly,
inspecting the ecological development,
and of course,
overseeing the destruction of bootlegged alcohol.
It kind of looks like they were way better
at faking photos
before Photoshop.
But the relentless drive to improve spurns
them forward.
Because officials in China’s Anhui province
have taken the time to brush up their photo
skills.
This lovely slide show is from a publicity
shoot
that’s totally meant to attract visitors
and investors
to the sleepy village of Jiulonggang—
and absolutely not a vanity project by the
deputy village chief,
Wang Xue,
who just happens to be the woman in the photos.
Wow, she's got some great...
Instagram filters.
After the photos went viral,
state-run media emphasized that this was a
personal album
that she spent her own cold hard yuan on.
And that she was doing it just to make sure
that people saw the beauty of...
her hometown.
But Chinese netizens missed the point,
because they seemed more focused on Ms. Wang
than the rural beauty of the village.
One wrote,
“Before I come, I need to know,
do you have a boyfriend?”
He should be executed…
Except, they may have a point.
Because, let’s take her out of the photographs
for a moment...
and now the romantic,
rustic charm,
just seems a bit more run down than anything
else.
I mean,
is this a stairwell you want to be in?
Yeah,
looks more like Silent Hill now.
By the way, Chinese netizens,
Ms. Wang is single,
and “jokes she would be
surprised and happy to get a boyfriend through
this photoshoot.”
I would say she has a higher chance of getting
a boyfriend
than the village has of getting tourists.
Of course,
this is just one of many attempts at good
publicity
happening in any number of villages in China.
It's all part of a tourism push being promoted
by Chinese authorities,
who are trying to encourage people to spend
money to help the economy.
Different villages are trying to play to their
strengths.
Like this tea village that's trying to encourage
tea tourism,
by "repainting houses and building roads."
Or this village,
which is encouraging street art to attract
tourists.
What the heck is that?!
It's like a set for American Horror Story:
Menagerie.
These Chinese villages have got to stop getting
their inspiration
from horror movies.
It's getting unbearable!
But that's not the best idea a village has
had.
No, that prize goes to the village leader
in Xianfeng, Sichuan,
who thought that if he filled the village
with monkeys,
it would surely draw tourists!
He organized villagers
to lure 73 monkeys down from nearby mountains.
And it worked!
But then tourism started to dwindle,
and villagers couldn’t afford to feed the
monkeys,
of which there were now more than 600,
and so the monkeys took to eating their crops instead.
Who was that village leader, anyway?
Well, I was wrong.
The lizards are a godsend!
But isn't that a bit shortsighted?
What happens when we're overrun by lizards?
No problem.
We simply unleash wave after wave
of Chinese needle snakes.
They'll wipe out the lizards.
But aren't the snakes even worse?
Yes, but we're prepared for that.
We've lined up a fabulous type of gorilla
that thrives on snake meat.
Then we're stuck with gorillas!
No, that's the beautiful part.
When wintertime rolls around,
the gorillas simply freeze to death.
So what do you think?
If you were a village chief,
how would you promote your locale?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.