Where did the coronavirus begin?
Was it of natural origin?
Or was the scientist who said that\h
just covering for his colleagues?
Welcome to China Uncensored. I’m Chris Chappell.
Before I start, did you know YouTube\h
demonetizes a lot of our videos?\h\h
Especially when they’re about\h
the coronavirus. That’s why\h\h
we rely on direct viewers support. Go to\h
Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored to learn more.
An update on the coronavirus situation. First,\h
you may remember that early on last year,\h\h
scientists condemned the idea that the\h
coronavirus could have come from a Chinese lab.
Back in February 2020, U.S. scientist Dr.\h
Peter Daszak, president of the New York-based\h\h
EcoHealth Alliance, pushed back against that idea\h
in this article in the medical journal the Lancet.
“We stand together to strongly condemn conspiracy\h\h
theories suggesting that COVID-19\h
does not have a natural origin.”
He also wrote in a February 2020 email that\h
“Scientific evidence overwhelmingly suggests\h\h
that this virus originated in wildlife,\h
as have so many other emerging diseases.”
Well it turns out the scientific evidence\h
wasn’t actually scientific evidence at all.\h\h
Last week, Dr. Daszak’s spokesperson told\h
the Wall Street Journal that actually,\h\h
“The Lancet letter was written during a time\h
in which Chinese scientists were receiving\h\h
death threats and the letter was intended as\h
a showing of support for them as they were\h\h
caught between important work trying to stop an\h
outbreak and the crush of online harassment.”
Ok, that’s understandable that he\h
didn’t want Chinese scientists to get\h\h
death threats in the early days of the pandemic.\h
But then he wrote another article in June about\h\h
why the idea of the coronavirus coming\h
from a lab was a conspiracy theory.
Dr. Dazak’s statements are under scrutiny\h
because he’s one of the World Health Organization\h\h
investigators who are traveling to China to\h
investigate the origins of the coronavirus.
But other scientists have brought up some pretty\h
big conflict of interest problems. That’s because\h\h
“Dr. Daszak has been a longtime\h
collaborator of Dr. Shi [Zhengli]\h\h
since they worked together to trace SARS\h
viruses to bats after the 2003 epidemic.”
Dr. Shi’s work studying bat coronavirus at the\h
Wuhan Institute of Virology has been theorized as\h\h
one of the possible origins\h
of the current pandemic.\h
Over the past year, more and more\h
people have been questioning—could\h\h
the coronavirus have begun in a Chinese lab?
Once upon a time, you could get deplatformed\h
from social media for even suggesting that.
But the State Department recently suggested\h
that researchers at the Wuhan Institute of\h\h
Virology had a coronavirus-like\h
illness in the Autumn of 2019.
“The U.S. government has reason to believe\h
that several researchers inside the Wuhan\h\h
Institute of Virology became sick in autumn 2019,\h
before the first identified case of the outbreak,\h\h
with symptoms consistent with both COVID-19\h
and common seasonal illnesses. This raises\h\h
questions about the credibility of senior\h
researcher Shi Zhengli’s public claim\h\h
that there was ‘zero infection’ among the Wuhan\h
Institute of Virology’s staff and students.”
It also says, “The CCP has prevented\h
independent journalists, investigators,\h\h
and global health authorities from interviewing\h
researchers at the [Wuhan Institute of Virology],\h\h
including those who were ill in the fall of 2019.\h\h
Any credible inquiry into the origin of\h
the virus must include interviews with\h\h
these researchers and a full accounting\h
of their previously unreported illness.”
So it really is possible that the coronavirus\h
leaked from a Chinese lab. Of course we don’t\h\h
know yet, as the investigation is still ongoing.\h
But this whole incident with Dr. Daszak just\h\h
goes to show: Sometimes conspiracy theories\h
just turn out to be investigative journalism.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.\h
I’m Chris Chappell. See you next time.