On this episode of China Uncensored,
"Potato, potato, tomato, tomato.
Oh let's call the whole thing off."
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
You know some people say neither, I say neither.
Some say Diaoyu, others Senkaku.
Let’s call the whole thing off.
Please?
Before we all get dragged into World War III?
Last Thursday, the Chinese regime decided
it just didn’t have enough on its hands
with territorial disputes in the South China
Sea.
Why limit it to conflicts with Malaysia, Indonesia,
Brunei, Vietnam, and the Philippines
when you can anger Japan, too,
by sending your navy ships to the East China
Sea?
This lovely archipelago is at the center of
a rocky territorial dispute
between China and Japan.
China calls them the Diaoyu Islands.
Japan—the Senkaku Islands.
Tomato, tomato?
Not when exclusive oil, mineral and fishing
rights
in the surrounding waters are on the line.
And China just sent a military frigate through
what’s called Japan’s contiguous zone
that’s the area of sea between 12 and 24
nautical miles from the coast.
Now China has been sending lots of ships
into the waters around the Diaoyu, Senkaku
Islands,
since Japan nationalized them in 2012.
But this is the first time an actual military
vessel was sent in.
And boy, Japan was fuming!
"We're deeply concerned that Chinese naval
ships entered the waters
contiguous to our Senkaku islands for the
first time,
and this behavior unilaterally escalates tensions."
Oh, ok. They’re deeply concerned.
That doesn’t sound too bad, right?
“The consequences are impossible to underestimate.
I think tensions between the two countries
are greater now
than they’ve probably been in half a century.”
In half a century?
You mean like, since the countries were at
war with each other?
That’s probably not a good thing.
For, like, anyone.
Especially the Chinese ambassador to Japan.
Japan’s vice foreign minister reportedly
called him at 2 in the morning
to register an official complaint.
And you know, this might not have been the
smartest move for the Chinese regime.
China’s whole attitude in the past has been
“It’s our islands, we’ll sail where
we want!”
But that’s not what they did.
According to the United Nations Convention
on the Law of the Sea,
a military vessel sailing through a contiguous
zone is perfectly legal.
Japan really didn’t have grounds to issue
a formal complaint.
In fact that same night,
three Russian military ships did the exact
same thing.
And while the Japanese government is investigating
whether there’s a connection,
they didn’t protest the Russian ships.
Sure, it sounds impressive that China
sent a military frigate to the Senkaku Islands.
Wavin’ their flag in the air like they just
don’t care.
But it’s all bluster.
Because if they really didn’t care,
they would have sailed through territorial
waters.
That is, less than 12 nautical miles from
shore.
But that could result in an actual armed conflict
with Japan,
and by extension, the United States.
And if that happened,
it'd be hard to call the whole thing off.
Besides, at the end of the day...
“Both countries have much bigger stakes
than struggling over an uninhabited island in
the middle of nowhere.”
So let’s call the whole thing off, ok?
So what do you think is behind China
escalating tensions now in both the South
and East China Seas?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next
time.