In this episode of China Uncensored,
behind the scenes of Looper.
Hi, I'm Chris Chappell.
Welcome to China Uncensored.
Now you've probably heard of this movie
that came out last weekend: Looper.
But here's something from behind the scenes that
you might not have heard.
And it has to do with China
Don't worry, no spoilers.
First of all let me tell you a bit about China's
movie industry.
It's crazy.
They have all these bizarre rules like
you can't make a movie or TV show that has
time travel.
There goes my dream of "Bill and Ted 3: Adventures in China"!
But they also make it incredibly difficult
for foreign films.
Only 34 are allowed a year inside China.
So how does a foreign film about time travel
end up not only getting into China,
but making more money on its opening weekend
there than the US?
Easy!
Just get co-produced by a Chinese company,
like Beijing-based DMG Entertainment.
You see, originally director Ryan Johnson
wanted the dystopian sci-fi tale to be held
in Paris
until he found out that China would give him
a lot more money
if he set it in Shanghai.
And so naturally,
according to the dialogue in the final version
of the film,
China is the place to be in the year 2074.
Which is funny because I thought China was
so polluted that the rivers are turning red.
But, hey, it's the future.
So, anyways, you wanna know how the movie ends?
Bruce Willis is his own father!