bjbj,(,( On this episode of China Uncensored,
China doesn t have a military? Hi, welcome
to China Uncensored, I am Chris Chappell.
So China doesn t have a military. And I know
what you re thinking, now hold on there Chris,
it seems almost every day we hear about China
developing a new fighter jet, or aircraft
carrier, or threatening military action against
Japan. Okay, sure there was the time that
China s state run CCTV used footage from Top
gun and passed it off as a military drill.
And then there was a the time they also used
a map to describe troop movements between
Turkey, Iraq and Iran that looked an awful
lot like a map in the popular online video
game World of Warcraft. So perhaps China s
army is an army of dreamers, but China still
an army, right? Well, not really. China the
country doesn t have a military, the Chinese
Communist Party does. Same thing, right? Actually,
no, they are two very different things, and
this is almost never explained in the Western
media. For most of the beginning of the 20th
century, the Communist Party was trying to
takeover China from the Kuomintang Nationalist
Party. They weren t really making any pr ogress
until World War 2 when Japan invaded China.
Eventually the Japanese were expelled but
Kuomintang armies were ravaged. That s when
the Communist Party seized the country and
expelled the Kuomintang. It s actually a little
funny that the Chinese regime always stirs
up anti-Japanese sentiment because really,
they played a big part the Partys takeover.
Actually I think a party official did say
that once, what was his name again, snap snap
snap. Oh right. Chairman Mao. Japanese capitalist
and warlords have done a good deed for the
Communists, if ever we need to say thank you,
I would like to say Thank you to Japanese
war lords. So needless to say, not everyone
in China was very happy that this guerilla
army of Communists just seized control of
the government. So as Mao Zedong consolidated
his power, he famously said, All political
power comes from the barrel of a gun. The
communist party must command all the guns,
that way, no guns can ever be used to command
the party. In China, you can t own a gun.
The only one s with guns are the People s
Liberation Army and they are controlled directly
by the Chinese Communist Party, not the state
or government of China. That s three million
soldiers, the world s largest active military,
that pays allegiance directly to the Communist
Party, not to the Chinese government, and
they re certainly not there to defend the
Chinese people. There is no state military.
Only the hired guns of the Party. To put it
in a way that s easy to understand, imagine
that in the US, the Republican Party, or the
Democratic Party, choose your poison, seized
control of the government, dissolved the US
military and established their own personal
army and forced everyone to do what they say.
That s been China for the past 60 years. And
here s where it gets weird. China still has
a government. It s just that the Communist
Party has latched onto every level of it,
kind of like a parasite. So in China, you
have your government officials at the provincial
level, down to the city, county, township,
and village level. But then at each of those
levels, you also have what s called a Party
secretary. They re appointed by the Communist
Party and have absolute power, so even if
a village actually elects a leader, that leader
just has to follow along with whatever the
Party Secretary says and he gets his orders
from the top of the Party. China s National
People s Congress? The BBC calls it a rubber
stamp congress. Even though there are different
political parties involved, those parties
are just controlled by the Communist Party,
and everything they put forward is approved.
It s a sham. President Hu Jintao? President
Xi Jinping? China doesn t have a president.
They just made that up to trick people into
thinking that their brutal oppressive communist
regime is a democracy. The president of China
is really the head of the Communist Party.
There is no Presidential election. In reality,
China is in the grip of the Communist Party,
and they control all the guns. Thanks for
watching this episode of China Uncensored,
once again I m Chris Chappell, see you next
time. [Content_Types].xml #!MB ;c=1 _rels/.rels
theme/theme/themeManager.xml sQ\}# theme/theme/theme1.xml
G$$DA : BR \{i5@R V*[_X ,l\Y Ssd+r] 5\|E Vky-
V4Ej 6NGU s?^V * 7;wP EBU` 5<V8
LStf+] C9P^ wB>VD GGHPXNT, /M,W m2iU [[v _Xtl
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.rels 6?$Q
K(M&$R(.1 [Content_Types].xmlPK _rels/.relsPK
theme/theme/themeManager.xmlPK theme/theme/theme1.xmlPK
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.relsPK
<a:clrMap xmlns:a="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/main"
bg1="lt1" tx1="dk1" bg2="lt2" tx2="dk2" accent1="accent1"
accent2="accent2" accent3="accent3" accent4="accent4"
accent5="accent5" accent6="accent6" hlink="hlink"
folHlink="folHlink"/> Chris Normal.dotm Chris
Microsoft Macintosh Word PICT* g9kZc g9g9kZg9^
g9kZ^ g9kZkZ^ kZo\{ o\{kZo\{ ?g9Ns\{ g9g9Z .kZc
g9g9kZw g9g9^ g9g9^ kZg9g9kZZ kZo\{^ o\{kZkZo\{o\{kZkZo\{s
o\{kZ\{ kZo\{g9o\{c kZkZo\{w g9o\{c o\{kZg9o\{ kZkZo\{g9g9^
g9kZo\{kZc o\{o\{s kZkZo\{o\{Z o\{o\{ kZo\{c kZo\{s
g9kZkZs g9kZkZg9s kZo\{kZc o\{kZs kZo\{kZ^ g9o\{s
g9g9o\{s g9o\{w kZkZo\{o\{g9kZw kZg9s kZo\{w kZo\{w
o\{g9s g9kZc o\{kZZ o\{g9^ g9o\{g9 kZo\{o\{w kZg9V
Nsg9V NskZc g9g9R g9g9kZZ g9g9o\{g9o\{g9w g9kZg9c
g9g9kZZ g9kZkZc o\{kZs g9kZkZZ o\{g9g9s o\{o\{s
o\{o\{s kZo\{s o\{kZc o\{o\
o\{o\{s o\{g9o\{s g9kZo\{s kZo\{ g9g9c g9o\{c g9o\{o\{kZ^
=g9Z o\{o\{R g9V g9g9\{ o\{g9kZo\{s o\{kZo\{s o\{kZo\{s
g9kZo\{ o\{o\{kZo\{o\{kZs o\{o\{g9g9s g9kZs kZg9c
g9g9s kZg9s g9g9kZw g9o\{kZg9g9c g9g9s kZg9kZg9kZg9s
g9kZs kZkZo\{ AkZc g9kZV kZg9R kZg9V kZkZZ
kZNsV g9kZo\{s kZo\{s o\{o\{kZZ o\{o\{g9 g9kZc o\{kZg9s
kZkZo\{o\{g9s o\{o\{g9w o\{o\{g9o\{s o\{kZs g9g9kZs
g9g9w g9kZV kZg9s o\{kZg9kZg9g9s g9kZs kZkZ
g9kZc g9g9Z o\{g9s o\{o\{s kZkZ g9o\{g9^ o\{o\{Z
o\{o\{ kZJR^ Nsg9V g9o\{R g9o\{g9^ g9kZkZg9c kZg9s
g9g9kZg9w o\{o\{kZg9kZkZ\{ kZo\{ kZ)c g9kZg9g9kZc
o\{o\{kZkZg9g9o\{kZkZ o\{g9s kZg9o\{kZkZo\{o\{^ o\{o\{kZ
o\{=g9kZg9w o\{g9w o\{kZg9kZs kZg9s g9o\{kZkZo\{o\{kZs
o\{kZg9kZkZg9kZg9kZZ g9kZo\{g9kZ^ o\{kZo\{kZo\{s
g9kZg9kZs g9g9s %g9R o\{g9R *o\{Z Bo\{g9kZg9
g9g9o\{^ g9kZc kZg9kZg9o\{g9kZg9s kZkZg9s kZo\{g9g9c
kZkZc kZg9g9c kZo\{w o\{*\{ kZo\{w o\{o\{kZg9s o\{kZc
o\{kZc o\{o\{kZs o\{o\{kZw o\{o\{s o\{o\{c o\{g9s 2o\{g9w
kZo\{o\{g9w o\{g9s g9kZs g9o\{w o\{o\{s ,o\{c g9g9s
kZg9g9c g9o\{c g9g9o\{c g9o\{g9s g9g9c kZg9kZw
g9g9s g9kZs )kZZ kZkZ^ g9kZkZc o\{kZkZg9w kZg9c
o\{g9Z g9g9s g9g9kZZ o\{o\{ o\{o\{w g9o\{w o\{o\{s
o\{o\{w o\{o\{kZo\{o\{kZs kZo\{o\{s kZg9o\{s o\{o\{kZs
o\{kZ g9g9s kZo\{o\{kZo\{o\{w o\{o\{s g9o\{g9kZo\{g9
g9kZg9s o\{kZ g9)kZo\{g9g9kZo\{kZo\{g9s kZkZo\{R
g9o\{kZo\{g9g9c o\{g9\{ g9o\{g9kZw kZo\{g9kZg9kZR
kZkZg9kZ o\{o\
kZkZs :g9g9o\{o\{g9kZo\{o\{s o\{o\{kZo\{o\{kZs kZo\{kZo\{s
o\{o\{kZc o\{o\{w kZo\{w o\{o\{kZo\{o\{Z o\{g9g9o\{g9o\{kZg9o\{o\{kZg9kZo\{kZo\{
o\{kZ^ g9o\{kZs kZg9kZkZg9kZkZg9s g9kZg9kZkZs
kZg9kZo\{kZg9kZg9s o\{kZkZc kZkZ kZo\{w kZg9^
g9o\{g9^ o\{g9c kZg9Z g9kZc kZg9^ o\{g9kZ o\{NsR
kZkZ^ kZkZV g9g9^ g9g9^ g9kZc g9kZ g9#^ g9g9kZc
g9o\
kZkZo\{o\{kZg9^ kZg9^ kZg9c o\{g9o\{^ g9g9kZc
g9g9c g9o\{Z g9o\{w kZo\{w o\{g9\{ kZo\{kZs o\{kZo\{kZw
o\{o\
g9g9w kZkZg9c g9g9o\{g9c kZkZg9s g9g9kZ g9g9^
g9NsZ kZo\{c o\{o\{V g9g9c Title Microsoft Word
97-2004 Document NB6W Word.Document.8