On this episode of China Uncensored,
China’s People’s War on Terrorism
expands to Afghanistan!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Okay, okay, okay,
let me just clear something up.
Just because you see military vehicles,
doesn’t mean you’re looking at the military.
You see in November,
an Indian publication released these photos
from the Little Pamir region, along the border
between China and Afghanistan.
Okay, okay, okay,
let me just clear something up.
Just because you see something that looks
like a Hummer,
that doesn’t mean it’s a hummer.
That’s actually a Chinese made Dongfeng,
eastern wind,
a knockoff of the American Hummer.
So is the Chinese military patrolling in Afghanistan?
No, don’t be silly.
According to that spokesman,
they were Chinese police.
Military vehicles.
Not military.
Of course as the Financial Times points out,
the spokesman also denied there were ongoing
“non-military patrols on the Afghan side
of the border”
The Afghan side also denied it so...
I’m not sure what to say about those...
Chinese military knockoffs patrolling along
the border.
Though the think tank Central Asia-Caucasus
Analyst
say the statements of eyewitness,
diplomats, and an unnamed Chinese official,
made for “overwhelming evidence”
that they were Chinese troops.
But we could argue back and forth all day
over whether Chinese military vehicles patrolling
Afghanistan
constitutes some form of military or non military
patrol,
which it isn’t.
Uhh, anyway.
The Wakhan Pass is a narrow strip of territory
that borders Pakistan, Tajikistan, and connects
to China’s western Xinjiang region.
You might be wondering,
why the weird shape?
Well, in the 19th century,
the British and Russian Empires
were fighting over Afghanistan,
a tradition that countries still carry on
to this day.
The Wakhan corridor was a territorial agreement
between the two to separate what was then
British India and Russia—
a sort of, “okay you two,
go to opposite sides of the room”.
Just one of the many fun decisions
foreign countries have made about Afghanistan.
And now—China.
China-Afghan ties have been...
warming for a while now.
And I’m not just talking Afghan girls
learning Chinese kung fu.
For example, in 2015,
the Afghan government arrested Chinese Uyghur
Muslims
and sent them back to China,
in exchange for China’s help talking with
the Taliban.
Proving China’s commitment to fighting terrorism.
But China may have legitimate concerns
about Islamic extremists entering China.
According to the Chinese regime,
the Turkistan Islamic Party,
headquartered in Afghanistan,
has conducted terror attacks inside China.
But they probably aren’t getting through
here.
Crossing from Afghanistan to China at this
border point
is almost impossible.
According to the Central Asia-Caucasus Analyst,
“the high plateau of the Little Pamir can
only be reached
by vehicle from Tajikistan,
as mountains without roads block the access
for vehicles f
rom the Afghan and Chinese sides.”
So that means even these Chinese military
vehicles
which are absolutely not part of the military,
must have gone through Tajikistan to get there.
Which makes sense,
because China and Tajikistan also have
a military relationship.
There are also no footpaths
and those border mountains reach as high as
16,500 feet.
So probably, terrorists are not streaming
through there
on their way to China.
China is also pursuing big economic deals
in Afghanistan.
According to China's state-run Global Times,
"The Corridor has huge importance geopolitically
and geo-economically,
as it allows China to access a treasure trove
of mineral deposits."
Ah, the promise of Afghan mineral deposits!
Like this copper mining operation,
that unfortunately has all these pesky ancient
Buddha statues
that simply must go.
So it’s weird both sides are being so cagey
about whatever kind of patrol this was.
In July, China gave military aid to Afghanistan—
a first.
A month later, China joined Afghanistan, Tajikistan,
and Pakistan
in the Quadrilateral Cooperation and Coordination
Mechanism.
It was a military cooperation agreement
dressed up like an anti-terrorism agreement.
And the source that spoke to Central Asia-Caucasus
Analyst
said the countries conducted patrols
on almost a weekly basis.
And then suspended them.
I mean, these patrols were definitely happening.
I mean, we have the pictures.
So why the denial these drills ever happened?
Does this mean the Afghan government is lying?
Or worse, did the Afghan central government
simply
not know what is happening in its own borders?
That’s not too far fetched.
In theory, local officials could have authorized
it
on their own.
This is a pretty remote region.
This all comes at a time when
US presence in Afghanistan is waning.
President Obama withdrew nearly all US troops
by the time he left office.
So is China trying to fill a power vacuum
left by the US?
Is the Chinese regime simply seeking to protect
its growing business interests in the country?
Or are they concerned about
terrorists entering China?
If that’s the case,
why the patrols in the middle of harsh terrain
where it's virtually impossible to cross into
China?
But just a word of warning to China:
Don’t start leaving your troops in Afghanistan.
It’s probably not going to end well.
What's that Shelley?
Or I guess you could just leave troops in
Afghanistan forever.
So what do you think about the mysterious
appearance
of Chinese military, or police, or...whatever,
in Afghanistan?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.