On this episode of China Uncensored, to arms,
my 50-cent army! To arms!
Hi welcome to China Uncensored, I'm your host
Chris Chappell.
Mothers in law.
Often a punch line in and of themselves.
Except when they get kidnapped.
Some of you may know my friend and fellow
YouTube celebrity Ben Hedges.
He's the host of Laowai Kan Zhongguo.
And this is Ben's mother in law, Sheng Xiaoyun.
And this is Ben's mother in law's house—after
it was ransacked by Chinese police.
...which looks roughly like my old house in
the Bronx after it was ransacked by a drug-crazed
lunatic.
And before ransacking her home, police went
to the elementary school where she works,
and kidnapped her.
That must have been fun for the kids.
So it turns out, Xiaoyun committed what the
Chinese regime considers the one of the most
heinous crimes imaginable: Filing a legal
complaint.
And while you may think that being a former
elementary school teacher already makes Xiaoyun
a scourge on society, there's one other thing
you should know.
She practices meditation—Falun Gong, which
is based on the principles of truth, compassion,
and tolerance.
And in China, believing in those principles
is dangerous.
Because in 1999, Chinese leader Jiang Zemin
decided to eradicate anyone who practiced
Falun Gong.
So he created the world's biggest internal
security force, and used it to kill them.
But since current Chinese leader Xi Jinping
came to power in 2012, he's been waging war
on the Jiang Zemin political faction that
used its genocide of Falun Gong to grab power.
In the past few years, Xi has arrested and
purged hundreds of Jiang's men under a so
called "anti-corruption campaign." That includes
some of the highest ranking members of the
Communist Party.
I guess many Falun Gong practitioners in China
felt then that this might be a good time to
file complaints against Jiang Zemin.
You know, for all the torture and genocide.
And technically in China, there's a mechanism
for doing that.
You file a complaint with the Supreme People's
Court and the Procuratorate.
So Xiaoyun, having been harassed multiple
times by China's internal security police,
including being tortured in a labor camp for
a year, decided it was within her legal right
to file a complaint of her own.
In fact, since June this year, Chinese people
have filed well over a hundred and fifty thousand
complaints against Jiang Zemin.
And some of them have then been abducted or
harassed by police.
Now before you say, "Well, what did you expect?"
First of all, blaming the victim allows this
type of genocide to happen.
But more important, the legal complaints against
Jiang are both legitimate and have legal standing.
And how the China government handles them
deals with the fundamental issue of whether
or not China can have rule of law.
If Chinese people are arrested for exercising
the rights supposedly guaranteed by the Chinese
constitution—such as filing a legal complaint—how
can you expect the Chinese regime to follow
laws about intellectual property theft?
International trade?
Cyber espionage?
The South China Sea?
But even more important, this is a chance
for you to do something, while at the same
time, getting to harass one of the jerks who
makes life miserable for ordinary Chinese
citizens.
Xiaoyun was detained by police from this Chinese
police station.
And this is the actual name and phone number
for the police chief responsible for her arrest.
So get your phones out, my precious 50-cent
army, and give Police Chief Yu Changjun a
call...
...and tell him to release Sheng Xiaoyun.
This number is also in the description below.
Obviously, you'll have better luck communicating
with him if you speak Mandarin.
You know, before he hangs up on you.
I'm not kidding, by the way.
Actually call this number.
And then send me an email with the subject
line "I Called the Police" and tell me what
happened on the call.
My goal is to have 500 viewers call this number.
I think that'll be enough to give him the
message that it's not ok to arrest your citizens
for filing a complaint.
Let's help rescue my friend Ben's mother in
law.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell, see you next
time.