Hello,
and welcome to China Uncensored.
This is the third fan meet-up we have ever had,
and we're doing it now at YouTube Space New York.
This is a little more professional than that
hole-in-the-wall dumpling place we did in Hong Kong,
Mama Deng's Dumplings,
which was fantastic,
but things are coming along.
Matt has gone mad with power.
he's printed everyone name tags.
Muahahahahaha!!!
I'll try to fire him...
He even printed me out a custom name tag.
Thank you, Matt.
Thank you, we're very professional here.
So, with this level of professionalism and respect being given to me,
I'm sure this fan meet-up will go swimmingly.
What's it like to be a undercover CIA operative
trying to undermine China?
I'm very happy to answer that,
but I will have to kill all of you here if I answer that.
So is that okay?
Bloopers? I've never made a mistake...
I mean, people shouldn't say, you know,
"Free Tibet, or free Taiwan, Hong Kong..."
It's all of China that needs to be freed from the Communist Party.
The U.S. lifted a 50-year arms embargo
on which of China's neighbors?
Vietnam.
Great. Which would you like?
Poster.
Poster!
Whoever gets this will have a real collector's item.
It's even autographed by me.
You can use that to forge my signature,
steal my identity if you'd like...
Seamus Light!
Since these are never gonna see the light of day,
I might as well just read a few...
"Horror at China's Human Meat Market!"
This is one I personally find the most terrifying...
"Inside Jiang Zemin's Mouth."
Just so you know, the prompter is not up yet.
So if we could just keep the applause going until...
On this episode of China Uncensored,
I am rubber and you are...
one of the most powerful politicians in the world...
Uh, actually Chris...
What's that, Shelley?