On this episode of China Uncensored,
A bakery hurts the feelings of the Chinese
people.
I blame gluten.
A buddhist temple did what?
And finally, you say potato, I say re-education
camp.
This is China Uncensored.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
In our top story, check out these guns!
Wait, zoom out.
THESE guns!
That was on board the USS Iowa, back in 2015.
And now, the Trump administration has
the Chinese Communist Party in its sights.
The CIA has said the US and China are in a
cold war.
And so it’s apparently time to bring back
some Cold War missiles.
This week Trump signed into law the 716 billion
dollar defense budget
we first told you about when Congress passed
it two weeks ago.
There’s a lot in there that seems to be
directly targeting China.
Perhaps literally.
One of the things the defense bill
focuses on is cruise missile defense,
and it names the threat from China as a reason.
You see, after the Cold War ended,
the US stopped making long-range ship sinking
missiles.
I mean, the Soviet Union fell.
Why would you ever need them?
Well, today, China has several supersonic
missiles
that have a range of 240 miles.
The US Navy's Harpoon missile has a range
of only about 80 miles.
But now the US Navy has gotten the green light
to
“stick it to China with game-changing new
missiles”.
The US Tomahawk missile has a range of 1,000
miles,
but in its current state,
it’s only designed for land targets.
But now, the Navy wants to repurpose it
into an anti-ship cruise missile.
And with a range of 1,000 miles—compared
to China’s 240—
the Tomahawk missile would be a game changer.
The new US defense budget also focuses on
strengthening military cooperation with India,
China’s largest rival in the region.
And it calls for a public report on the Chinese
regime’s
aggressive actions in the South China Sea
and Indian Ocean.
But that wasn’t the only bombshell...or...missile
shell?...
that the new defense budget dropped.
It also called for strengthening
the military and defense relationship with
Taiwan—
the country that everyone has to pretend is
not a country.
Needless to say, the Chinese Communist Party
isn’t happy.
Strongly dissatisfied, in fact.
You know, with all the times the Chinese regime
has said it has hurt feelings…
...I’m really beginning to wonder
if it’s really just a self-esteem issue.
Speaking of Taiwan, Taiwan’s president Tsai
Ing-wen
visited the United States this week,
on her way to Latin America.
She had a short stopover in Los Angeles,
where she gave a speech and met with US officials.
And stopped to drink a boba tea at a local
Taiwanese owned bakery,
as you do when you’re president.
The visit is a sign of warming ties between
the US and Taiwan...
if you ask American state-run media.
But if you ask Chinese state-run media,
well they don’t have much to say.
I guess they don’t want to give much attention
to her visit.
But a Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesperson
had earlier expressed concern,
urging the US, quote
“not to allow the transit by the so-called
Taiwan leader.”
But in a move that’s not petty at all,
you know that Taiwanese bakery President Tsai
stopped at?
Well, it has stores in mainland China, too.
And now Chinese state-run media are sort of
suggesting
people boycott all 538 of them.
As you do when you’re Chinese state-run
media.
So faced with a possibly boycott, the bakery
released a statement
saying that they of course support the 1992
consensus
that lays out the One China policy.
You know, where both China and Taiwan
both agree there’s only one China,
but just don’t talk about which China that
is.
And of course then everyone stopped being
angry.
Just kidding.
Previously the 85-degrees bakery
was famous for its sea salt flavored coffee.
Now they’re just famous for hurting
the feelings of the Chinese people.
I just want to stop and say that we live in
a world where a bakery
has to declare that there’s only one China.
What is the point of satire anymore?
Speaking of Chinese propaganda, the Confucius
Institute.
The Confucius Institute is a world-wide education
program
that teaches the Mandarin language,
with a dash of communist propaganda.
That’s because it’s run by the Communist
Party’s United Front.
And it’s paid for mostly by the Chinese
government.
Well, guess who won’t be adding funding
from now on?
The Pentagon.
This new ban on funding Confucius Institutes
on US college campuses is, weirdly,
under the same defense bill as those new missiles.
Now to be clear,
the Pentagon never actually funded Confucius
Institutes.
The Pentagon funds its own language programs
at US universities.
But then Arizona State University,
which has both a Confucius Institute
and a Pentagon-funded language program,
had a great idea.
Officials at the university “bragged about
mixing
the school’s Pentagon-funded Chinese language
programs
and its Chinese Communist Party-funded Confucius
Institute.”
One Arizona State University official also
said that
since the Pentagon was funding its Confucius
Institute,
that proved that the US government didn’t
see
the Confucius Institutes as a national security
threat.
Which was not true.
Oops.
That claim got picked up by Chinese state-run
media and...
I think you can see what happened from there.
So now US universities have to choose between
a Pentagon-funded program and a Confucius
Institute.
If they want to have both, they have to apply
for a waiver.
And they can’t mix the funds.
One issue is that there are more than
100 Confucius Institutes in the US.
But only 12 universities have Pentagon-funded
programs in Chinese.
So if the US government wants to counter
Chinese Communist Party-sponsored language
programs,
it’s got a long way to go.
Speaking of propaganda, the Communist Party
has been rebuilding a lot of the old Buddhist
temples across China—
including some of the ones it destroyed in
the 1960s.
It doesn’t mean the Communist Party is ok
with religion now.
It’s not.
It never was.
But, boy do tourist attractions sure make
money!
So why not invest in rebuilding some temples!
Of course, all the old monks with their “traditional”
ways of thinking
have been kicked out, or they died, or were
killed.
And now they’ve been replaced by younger
monks
who really understand how integrate modern
communist thought
into those stuffy old Buddhist teachings.
Like the monks at a Yuantong temple in southern
China.
They totally get it.
That’s why, “For an additional 73 dollars,
monks at the temple [would] perform rituals
to guarantee
that the deceased will be reincarnated in
the United States.”
Now you might be wondering, why charge so
little money?
Millions of people want to leave China.
They could have charged thousands of dollars!
I guess the catch with reincarnation is,
you have to die first.
Of course, the Yuantong temple totally denies
that it ever offered this service.
And I believe them,
because I read it in The Global Times.
Speaking of religion,
there’s about 10 million people
in the Autonomous Region of Xinjiang
who belong to the Uighur ethnic group,
and they’re largely Muslim.
Well, at least they have a generations-old
culture
of Muslim customs and traditions and holidays.
But believing in Allah, that’s very dangerous,
according to the Communist Party.
And that’s why over the last year or so,
Chinese authorities have rounded up as many
as 10% of all Uighurs—
I’m talking about potentially a million
people here—
and put them into re-education centers.
And according to one former inmate,
they were forced to drink alcohol and eat
pork.
That’s because pork and alcohol are forbidden
for Muslims.
But really, bacon and whisky in prison doesn’t
sound that bad—
compared to the ideological re-education,
physical torture,
and mysterious deaths in custody.
But don’t worry!
According to a Chinese delegation to Geneva,
there are “no such things as re-education
centers.”
No, no!
These places are actually
“vocational education and employment training
centers.”
But somehow, I feel like maybe they’re spinning
that story.
Because there’s another description
of these totally-not-reeducation camps—
this time, from the Communist Party Youth
League.
They claimed that they’re actually hospitals...
treating people infected with religious extremism.
Which is very thoughtful,
since almost no one else in China gets free
healthcare.
And before we go, normally this is the time
I answer a question
from a fan who supports China Uncensored through
Patreon.
But there are other ways to support China
Uncensored, too.
So this time, I want to tell you a story about
something amazing
that a fan in Indonesia did.
His name is J.
Ok, it’s not really J,
but he didn’t want me to use his real name
because Indonesia is not exactly a free country.
So last week, J messaged us on Facebook
about why the China Uncensored YouTube channel
was no longer available in Indonesia.
And I was like, “Wait... what?”
It turned out that Indonesia’s biggest mobile
phone telecom company
Telkomsel was blocking China Uncensored.
Here’s what our channel looks like normally,
and here’s what it looked like for users
on Telkomsel.
And this isn’t a small issue.
Telkomsel serves half of Indonesia,
which is the fourth largest country in the
world.
So more than 100 million people were being
blocked
from watching China Uncensored on their phones.
And that’s a big deal,
because Indonesia doesn’t have a good
wired internet access in most places,
so most people watch YouTube on their mobile
phones.
So I told J, “I want to do an episode about
how Indonesia
is blocking China Uncensored.”
And then he told me that this has recently
been an issue
affecting lots of YouTube channels there.
There’s apparently been a big effort
by the Indonesian government
to block online content related to violence,
pornography,
and “negative content”—whatever that
is.
So I asked J to contact Telkomsel
and ask them which of their terms of use
China Uncensored might be violating.
And it turned out—surprise!—
it was none of them.
But here’s the bigger surprise: Literally
the next day,
Telkomsel had unblocked the China Uncensored
YouTube channel.
In other words,
it seems that one phone call from a viewer
accomplished something
that helped more than 100 million people
get access to China Uncensored again.
So J: My sincerest thank you.
You are truly a member of the China Uncensored
50-Cent Army.
And that’s it for this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.
The Chinese Communist Party is buying up influence
around the world!
That’s why this is an urgent call to our
fans.
If you like how we uncensor China,
consider joining our 50-cent army.
Go to the crowd funding website Patreon.
If you can,
contribute a dollar or more to help keep the
lights on here.
We’ll give you some cool perks,
and you’ll have a chance to ask me questions
I’ll answer on air!
The revolution is now!