On this episode of China Uncensored,
China just stole a US Navy drone, and the
Navy watched it happen.
Which, was better than starting a war.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
On Thursday, China stole an underwater US
research drone
in the South China Sea.
The USNS Bowditch, an unarmed military research
ship,
was sailing about 50 miles off the coast of
the Philippines.
They were conducting research with two underwater
drones called ocean gliders.
And the Chinese Navy...simply grabbed one
out of the water.
“The Defense department says
the Bowditch immediately made contact to ask
for it back,
but the Chinese ship simply sailed away.
Friday, Pentagon officials asked again.
Spokesman Captain Jeff Davis told reporters:
“it is ours and we would like it back.
And we would like this to not happen again.”
“Hey, you took my drone!”
“Yeah? What are you going to do about it?!”
“Give it back! Give it back!”
According to US officials,
the Chinese probably thought they were stealing
a spy vehicle.
It was not.
U.S. officials say it was a research drone
that was
“simply measuring ocean conditions.”
But you know, “steal” is such a strong
word.
"First, I want to say that we really don't
like this word ‘stolen’
and this word is completely incorrect.
As state-run media explained,
they were just trying to find out who the
drone belonged to.
“In order to prevent the object from endangering
the safety of the ship or people,
the Chinese rescue vessel took a professional
and responsible approach
and carried out identification checks on the
object.”
That’s right, they merely discovered it,
after stalking that US Naval ship,
and wanted to identify whose it was,
right as the drone was about to dock with
the ship.
I mean, China “highly values peace and stability
in South China Sea.”
Like when they put weapons on artificial islands
they built in disputed waters.
But China has now agreed to return America’s
drone—
presumably after they discovered it wasn’t
that cool after all.
And that’s the end of the story.
Except it isn’t.
Because Donald Trump.
Many experts believe this drone-seizure was retaliation for that time two weeks ago,
when Trump took a phone call from the president of Taiwan.
Or that time one week ago when Trump questioned
the entire One China policy.
But in fact, this is something the Chinese regime has done before:
test out America’s new president.
In 2001, just after George W. Bush assumed
office,
two Chinese warplanes made threatening maneuvers
near a US spy plane
flying near China’s Hainan island.
And then one crashed into it—
killing the Chinese pilot and forcing the
US plane to land in China.
And then in 2009, shortly after Obama took
office,
a group of Chinese navy vessels harassed a
US naval research ship.
But if China was trying to send a message
to Trump, well,
Honey Badger don’t care.
Trump tweeted,
“We should tell China that we don’t want
the drone they stole back.
Let them keep it!”
Which turns that earlier fight into:
“We stole your drone.
What are you going to do about it?”
“Nothing. Fine. Keep it.”
“Fine then.”
Of course, the US probably will still get
the drone back
since it’s not a top secret spy plane.
And also—as most of us have forgotten already—
Barack Obama is still president.
Anyway, what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell, see you
next time.