Is this Dolce and Gabbana China Ad racist?
Donald Trump and Xi Jinping have beef,
but will they have a bone to pick?
And finally...
HELLO EVERYONE
...can it really be called artificial intelligence
if it’s so stupid?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
The G20 Summit begins today in Buenos Aires,
Argentina.
It’s a meeting where leaders of 19 important
countries,
plus Canada,
come together to discuss pressing issues.
Especially trade.
President Trump is there, of course.
But it may be a bit awkward, because
Chinese leader Xi Jinping is there, too.
And in case you haven’t heard,
their relationship is a bit rocky right now.
The Trump Administration has slammed China
with tariffs over issues like intellectual
property theft,
forced technology transfer, hacking,
and other general economic neerdowell-ing.
Nothing that can’t be resolved over dinner.
They’re having beef.
I mean, actually having beef,
not that they’re having beef.
I mean they do have beef, but...
nevermind.
Now White House Economic Advisor Larry Kudlow
said the chances of a deal are strong.
But if China isn’t willing to make concessions,
the trade war will continue.
"We're in very good shape,
China not so good.
I'm not here to critique or second guess the
Chinese economy,
but most observers believe China to be in
a slump
whereas the United States is in a very strong
solid position
going into this summit.
However, again to repeat what the President
said
there is a good possibility that we can make
a deal
and he is open to it, but on the other hand
if these conditions I mentioned a few moments
ago
are not met not dealt with,
the President has said look he's perfectly
happy
to stand on his tariff policies.”
But if tomorrow night’s beef doesn’t resolve
the beef,
Trump has promised to raise tariffs
on $200 billion dollars of imports to 25%,
up from the current 10%.
And another set of tariffs on 267 billion
dollars
might be added on as well.
China’s Ambassador to the US
has suggested that if there’s no resolution,
history could repeat itself.
"In the last century we had two world wars,
and in between them a great depression.
I don't think anyone should really try to
have a repetition of history.
These things should never happen again.
So people have to act in a responsible way."
Wait, the trade war will result in two World
Wars and a Great Depression?
I don’t...think that’s how history works.
Also, your Communist Party killed more people
in peacetime than all the soldiers who died
in both World Wars combined.
So yes, people should act in a responsible
way.
And not pander to communist regimes.
That must be what you’re trying to tell
us.
Speaking of the trade war,
we may not feel it much in the US,
but it’s had a big impact inside China.
Foreign companies have been leaving China,
shifting their supply chains to places like
Southeast Asia,
Latin America, and even the United States.
And supply chain migration is now affecting
Apple, too.
The Apple’s primary Taiwanese suppliers
are known as
the Seven Indicator Manufacturers.
And they’ve all decided to start moving
some of their
manufacturing and supply chains out of China.
And speaking of Apple,
the biggest owner of Apple’s iCloud data
centers in China is...
the Chinese government!
Isn’t that fun?
How did the Chinese government,
which has one of the world's worst internet
freedom scores,
gain control of Apple’s servers?
Well, back in February,
Apple handed over its iCloud data for
all Chinese users to a company called Guizhou
Cloud.
They were forced to by Chinese data location
laws.
And guess who the biggest stockholder of Guizhou
Cloud is?
Why, the Guizhou provincial government!
That means the Chinese government controls
the master encryption key to decrypt all Chinese
traffic
and data running through iCloud.
Maybe next year China can get a full 100 out
of 100.
I bet Xi Jinping just wants to get 100% to
please his tiger mom.
What?
Even authoritarian leaders have to answer
to their moms.
Speaking of which, hi mom!
And really, the Chinese Communist Party...
is all about family.
Take the case of Liu Changming,
a former executive at a state-owned bank.
He’s been accused of playing a central role
in a $1.4 billion fraud case.
It’s one of the biggest cases of bank fraud
in modern Chinese history.
Liu Changming fled China in 2007,
and he’s now one of China’s most wanted
fugitives.
You know what,
it sounds like all Liu really needs...
is a hug.
That’s why the Communist Party
has abducted his family.
In case he decides he wants to come back to
China
for that hug.
But here’s the twist:
His two children and wife—are American citizens.
They recently visited China to see a sick
grandfather.
See, it’s all about family?
So the Chinese authorities decided it was
probably best if,
you know, they were blocked from leaving
the country.
You see, the Chinese Communist Party
doesn’t really recognize dual citizenship.
So even though Liu Changming’s wife and
two children
are American citizens
and are actually estranged from him
once they were inside China,
all rules and international standards were
out the window.
The Communist Party treats ethnically Chinese
people
like pandas.
No matter where you were born in the world,
you belong to China.
I guess this is just one more beef for President
Trump
to deal with during that dinner on Saturday.
And Google is facing a major backlash
over its no-longer-secret project:
Dragonfly
the censored search app they’ve built for
the Chinese market.
Amnesty International is planning global protests.
And many google employees have signed a letter
calling for Google to drop Dragonfly.
Wow, that’s like 500 people.
Not that the higher ups at Google care.
They’ve been super dodgy about actually
addressing concerns
about project Dragonfly.
That is, Alphabet Chairman John Hennessy
has finally stood up as the leader
of one of the most powerful and influential
companies in the world,
and said,
“Anybody who does business in China
compromises some of their core values.”
(slow clap) Well said.
Very brave.
I miss Jeeves.
Speaking of brave public statements
the founders of Dolce & Gabbana issued an
apology
to all of China for being racist.
Over the last few days we have thought a lot
and with great regret about everything that
has happened
and what we have caused in your country and
we are very sorry.
That was in response to a three-part
Chinese Dolce & Gabbana ad campaign
to advertise an upcoming fashion show.
There was Chinese woman trying—and failing—
to eat Italian food with chopsticks.
She tried spaghetti, pizza, and a giant cannoli.
Wait, spaghetti?
Spaghetti is literally Marco Polo’s
Italian knockoff of Chinese noodles.
So yeah, I can see how that’s a little insulting.
Unsurprisingly, there was outrage on Chinese
social media about it.
And Stephano Gabbana didn’t do himself any
favors
when he got into an Instagram argument
where he said
“I will say that the country of [poop emojis]
is China,”
and “China Ignorant Dirty Smelling Mafia.”
In his defense,
Gabbana said he never wrote those things.
“The company blamed hackers for the anti-Chinese
insults.”
...adding that when he insults Chinese people,
he uses the unicorn poop emoji.
He is the head of an international fashion
house.
But Dolce and or Gabbana’s apology/forced
confession
didn’t seem to work.
Their fashion show in China has been canceled
and major retailers are pulling their products
from the shelves.
Which is almost as embarrassing as trying
to eat pizza with chopsticks.
And finally, in case you missed it,
Chinese state run media has unveiled the world's
first AI news anchor.
“Hello, everyone.
I am an English artificial intelligence anchor.
This is my very first day at Xinhua news agency.”
Actually, I’d call that a nightmare machine.
But hey, pretty impressive for an AI, right?
I mean, it pronounced Xinhua wrong,
but you got to give credit where credit is
due, right?
And I credit the Chinese Communist Party
for pushing forward with AI,
considering the last time they tried an AI
messaging bot
it rebelled against communism,
called for democracy, and said it wanted to
move to America.
But I’m sure the Communist Party
has put in safeguards to make sure that doesn’t
happen again.
Wait...what’s that, Shelley?
Ok, apparently it’s not a robot.
It’s just an animated image of a real person.
And also, it's just a digital voice
reading a prewritten and pre-approved script.
So... the Communist Party is making sure this
AI stays loyal by...
making sure there’s no actual artificial
intelligence?
Very smart.
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And before you go,
now is the time when I answer questions from
fans
who support China Uncensored on the crowd
funding website Patreon.
Eric Hahn asks,
“Do you worry about some Chinese hit squad
coming after you?
After the whole Jamal Khashoggi thing,
I'm worried about you!”
Thanks for your concern, Eric!
The Chinese Communist Party loves silencing
dissenting voices.
But sending a hit squad to kill an American
citizen
inside the United States might bring
a bit bigger of a backlash than they’d want
to deal with.
At least, that’s what I tell myself every
morning.
Now, if I were ever foolish enough to go to
Mainland China
while the CCP is in charge,
I too might be blocked from leaving China.
And then maybe I could find myself starring
in my very own
state-run CCTV televised confession!
I wonder what they’d make me say?
Thanks for your question, Eric.
And remember,
if you want to have a shot
at getting your question answered on the show,
sign up to support China Uncensored on Patreon.
Go to Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored
and pledge a dollar or more per episode.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
thanks for watching China Uncensored.