On this episode of China Uncensored,
what’s happened to Chinese leader Xi Jinping??!!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Have you seen Xi Jinping?!
I’ve been looking everywhere for him.
In his favorite chair,
in the boardroom,
in staged propaganda footage,
and I can’t find him!
Wait a minute,
I think I see him...
here.
Oh-no-wait-here.
No, Xi isn’t tired,
he’s just wearing fatigues.
And he’s the first Chinese Communist Party
leader to do so.
Here is shaking hands with members of the
People’s Liberation Army
all of them, whether a green shirt, a blue
shirt,
or even one of the PLA’s new red shirt brigade.
For some reason, the numbers in that brigade
seem a little low.
So why the hot new style?
Well, Xi just gave himself a promotion.
According to state-run media,
he’s now the commander-in-chief
of the military's Joint Operations Command
Center.
Why?
According to Party Mouthpiece Xinhua, Xi said,
“The current situation requires battle command
to be highly strategic, coordinated, timely,
professional and accurate”
as well as suave, sophisticated, and exuding
the rich smell of mahogany.
So until Xi Jinping came to power,
the People’s Liberation Army never had a
joint command.
Joint command is where the different branches
of the military
--air force, army, and navy--
can work together and know what the others
are doing.
Kind of important, right?
That’s why pretty much every modern military
has one.
But in China,
the problem has been that that whoever’s
charge of the joint command
would also have tremendous political power.
And since your typical Party leader
is pretty much in a constant battle to get
some edge over all the other jerks,
that never happened.
Well, now Xi’s got an edge over the other
jerks.
Even though when Xi was elected
haha, sorry, that get’s me every time
even though after Xi won the presidential
power struggle,
he also became head of the Central Military
Commission,
this latest move suggests that Xi feels
he needs to solidify his control over the
military even further.
Xi has been in a constant battle with other
Party members
tied to former Chinese leader Jiang Zemin.
Xi’s anti-corruption campaign is really
just a way
to purge the most powerful members of Jiang’s
clique.
And the military has been no different.
China’s Central Military Commission was
once stacked with Jiang Zemin’s people.
Jiang had appointed a total of 79 generals
in his time.
That’s why, since 2012,
Xi Jinping has been purging and reforming
the military with one clear purpose
to give himself more direct control.
And to ensure that he’s the brains of the
operation,
top leaders now have to report directly to
him via video link,
and he’s increased military spending tremendously,
last year reaching 130 billion dollars.
Plus, Xi has reformed and reorganized the
military,
with new divisions like the PLA Rocket Force,
or PLARF.
PLARF controls China's missile arsenal,
and is at the same level as PLAGF, PLAAF,
and PLASSF,
which also controls CPLASF.
Maybe Xi should also reorganize the making-up
military acronyms force,
or MUMAF.
According to China Daily,
Xi’s new position as head of the Joint Operations
Command Center
will “hone their ability for "informationized
warfare."
“Informationized warfare”?
Xi may not be a professional soldier,
but he’s clearly a professional...
word creator guy.
But I think this is the real message he wants
to give.
Because clearly, not everyone is loyal enough.
So what will Xi do with his new power?
Leave your cynical comments below.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell, see you next
time.