China’s economy *was* slowing down.
But now it’s getting back on track.
How does it do that?
And what does it mean for the US trade war?
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Good news everyone:
China’s economy seems to be stabilizing.
That’s based on official economic data
from the first quarter of this year.
“More now on those growth numbers out of
China overnight,
which seem to signal stabilization
in the world’s second largest economy.”
But wait, you say,
good news about China’s economy
from China Uncensored?!
Aren’t you a CIA-backed anti-China propaganda
outfit
whose goal is to hurt the feelings of the
Chinese people?
Well, don’t worry!
Because none of those things are true.
Including China’s economic rebound.
“It comes after that country
flooded its economy with stimulus money.”
That is to say,
the reason China’s economy seems to have
stabilized
is that the central government has been
pumping billions of dollars into it.
“Beijing flooded the financial system with
money
in a whatever-it-takes approach to arrest
a slowdown.”
Because in China,
they don’t just deal with slowdowns.
They arrest slowdowns.
And throw them in labor camps.
Anyway, the Chinese Communist Party
is deeply concerned about economic slowdowns.
Its political model for the past 40 years
has been:
We’ll let people make money,
so they don’t complain about
our authoritarian system.
But as soon as people can no longer
make as much money,
they might start to question
the Communist Party’s rule.
I mean, who would go for a communist party
that doesn’t help you make money?
So what have Chinese central authorities
been doing to pump up the economy?
They’ve been pushing banks to make more
loans.
Last month,
Premier Li Keqiang called on China’s state-owned
commercial banks to ramp up their loans,
especially to MSEs—
that is, micro and small enterprises.
Chinese banks have already issued
a record number of loans this year.
New bank loans totalled 865 billion dollars
between January and March.
That’s 20 percent more than a year ago.
On top of that, the central government
has been encouraging local governments to
issue bonds,
which means they’re borrowing more money.
Local governments have raised $100 billion
dollars
in new bonds in the first quarter.
That’s *700 percent* more than a year ago.
Which is crazy,
because just last year,
“the same local governments were scolded
for borrowing too much and hiding their debts.”
But for now, all this economic stimulus is
working.
The Chinese economy appears to be stabilizing.
And this is important for Chinese leaders.
Because they don’t want to “appear weak
while the trade negotiations [with the US]
continue.”
Originally, Trump wanted to have
a new trade deal with China by March 1—
otherwise he promised to increase tariffs
on Chinese goods.
That would hurt China’s economy a lot.
But the whole trade deal thing is complicated.
The US has been pushing the Chinese Communist
Party
to make real structural reforms
in how the Chinese economy operates.
And those are no fun.
So China has been procrastinating.
It’s like when your mom
wants you to clean your room,
and not just shove everything into the closet
like you usually do.
The US wants China to declutter their economy,
Marie Kondo style.
Do those state-backed export subsidies really
spark joy?
Lucky for China,
Trump knows how hard it is to let go.
So he delayed the March 1 deadline for the
tariffs—
at least until he could meet with Chinese
leader Xi Jinping in April.
But then that April meeting never happened.
And now it looks like it could be pushed back
to June.
Like I said, procrastinating.
And by June,
it’ll be summer,
and do you really want to put spend your summer
doing trade negotiations?
Wouldn’t you rather be at the beach?
Never mind.
The beach is terrible.
Wait...that must be Trump’s strategy!
He wants to make sitting in an office
and doing paperwork all day seem appealing!
But in order to get there,
Chinese leaders have to offer
the kind of free market reforms the US wants.
So the US may not be happy about the fact
that
Chinese state-owned enterprises
are the ones picking up a lot of the slack
in this recent economic activity.
Plus there’s the whole issue of needing
an enforcement mechanism to stop anyone
from cheating on the trade deal.
Which won’t be easy.
And what if the Chinese Communist Party
decides that the trade deal doesn’t spark
joy?
So will US trade negotiators look at China’s
recent stimulus
as a sign that China’s economy is strong
again?
Or will the US see this stimulus as a weakness,
and use it as leverage to force the Chinese
regime
to make more concessions?
That’s unclear.
But regardless,
“the [Chinese] government simply cannot
afford
to think about the medium term
and must focus on short-term continuation
of the credit bubble.”
Yes, short-term thinking is the way to go.
So for now,
China’s economy is stabilizing.
But eventually,
the long term will come.
And in the meantime,
all the debt they’re creating is a ticking
debt bomb.
And time bombs tend to explode at some point.
Unless you’re MacGyver.
But hey, that’s a future problem, right?
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And now it’s time for me to answer
a question from one of you—
a viewer who supports China Uncensored
through the crowdfunding website Patreon.
Rodney Hall writes:
I appreciate that you guys would like to maintain
a semblance of privacy in your personal lives,
hence the fact that you don't talk over much
about yourselves
(except for Chris and his student debt).
But Matt is so low key that I've become curious
about him.
I think the most significant personal facts
he's revealed are that he is a blond and has
a living room.
Care to elaborate?
Nope, that’s pretty much all there is to
Matt.
He’s blond and has a living room.
Really Chris?
That’s it?
I’m a complex human being.
Ok, fine...tell me one interesting thing about
yourself.
I...I like alpacas.
Thanks for your question, Rodney.
And thank you to all of my amazing supporters—
my 50-Cent Army—
for contributing a dollar or more
through our Patreon website.
Your support is what keeps us going.
Even Matt.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.