China is known for all sorts of knockoffs.
But this one will blow your mind.
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
The Eiffel Tower.
The architectural marvel that made this city
famous.
I’m talking, of course, about the city of....
...Hangzhou, China!
Yes, Hangzhou, known in ancient times for
its divine pagodas,
grand canal,
and peerless beauty.
Now, it’s also known for its large-scale
knockoff of Paris.
Back in 2007,
ambitious developers began building
what they call the “Tianducheng Resort”,
on the outskirts of the city.
And for millions of Chinese citizens who may
never get
a chance to leave the country,
it gives them an opportunity to at least get
a glimpse of bon Paris...
even if it’s a knockoff.
And really, who can tell the difference?
Seriously, do you think you can?
I’m going to show you 20 side-by-side images
from French photographer François Prost.
In each slide,
one photo was taken in Paris and the other
in Tianducheng.
Which one is the real Paris?
Grab a pen and keep track of how many you
can guess correctly.
Ready...
Set...
Go!
How many did you get right?
And have you been to Tianducheng,
or its knockoff version in France?
Leave your comments below.
And I want to give a special thanks
to photographer François Prost
for sharing his great photos with us.
Follow him out on Instragram: @francoisprost.
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell...
Or are you a knockoff?