On this episode of China Uncensored,
To know the future, you must understand the
past.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I'm your host Chris Chappell.
If you've been to any Chinese restaurant in
the United States,
you've been served a fortune cookie.
A lovely little saying, some lucky numbers,
maybe it teaches you a word in Mandarin.
Yes, fortune cookies are a beloved Chinese
restaurant tradition all around the world.
But why can't you find fortune cookies in
China?
In fact, the ancient art of fortune cookies
was nearly lost forever.
It was a dark time in China's history.
One that few people even know about.
So today, we bring you a China Uncensored
exclusive investigation
into the secret history of the fortune cookie.
The origins of the fortune cookie stretch
back to the roots of recorded Chinese history--the
Shang Dynasty.
In a grand ceremony to determine the fortune
of the nation for the coming year,
the emperor would toss oracle bones into a
bronze "ding" vessel that would then be lit.
A mystic would interpret the cracks that formed
on the bones as predictions for the future.
Clearly, a feudalistic superstition.
That's why, during the Cultural Revolution,
when Mao Zedong began destroying the Four
Olds
--a systematic campaign to wipe out traditional
culture--
he targeted the fortune cookie.
"That was the official reason Mao gave for
the
'Smash Confucius, Smash the Cookie' campaign.
But there were actually much more sinister
reasons behind it."
Dr. Iris Wolsey is one of the world’s foremost
experts on fortune cookies.
"After the Shang emperors,
it became a folk tradition.
People started putting their own spirit tablets
with fortunes and charms written on them
in steamed rice cakes to celebrate the Lunar
New Year.
Whoever ended up with the cake with the tablet
would have good fortune for the coming year."
"Unless they broke their teeth."
"At a certain point, they switched to paper."
But for Mao Zedong,
fortune cookies were more than just feudal
superstition.
They were also political.
During the late Ming Dynasty,
the making of fortune cookies became part
of esoteric rituals,
dominated by secretive clans with occult practices
rooted in geomancy, fengshui, and fortune
telling based on the Bagua and I-ching.
One of these clans had a charismatic leader
who convinced his followers that he had the will of Heaven,
and the will of heaven
was for him to become
Emperor.
That led to the Le Zaohua, or Happy Good Luck,
Uprising of 1629,
and later the 1633 Chang Fu, or Everlasting
Fortune, Rebellion.
Which they most definitely were not.
Both rebellions failed,
but they greatly weakened the Ming Dynasty.
And they were partly responsible for the dynasty's
collapse and conquest by the Manchus in 1644.
So it's no wonder that,
in the 20th century,
Mao Zedong was afraid the fortune cookie could
threaten his rule.
At least that's the accepted scholarly interpretation.
But it turns out, there might be more to the
story...
"No, no that's totally wrong.
That's not why Mao turned against fortune
cookies at all."
I went to Manhattan's Chinatown to interview
Jing Fong.
He's a seventh generation fortune cookie master
from the southern Har Gow school.
His was one of only a handful of fortune cookie families
that left China before the Cultural Revolution,
and have carried on the tradition overseas.
"I've been making fortune cookies for nearly
40 years."
"You...don't look that old."
"My mother put a fortune cookie in my hand
before I learned to walk."
His fortune cookie factory now supplies nearly
one quarter of the Chinese restaurants in
the United States.
"Mao was a secret believer in the power of
Fortune Cookies.
That’s why during the Chinese Civil War,
when the Communists were fighting the Nationalists,
Mao had his troops use fortune cookies to
deliver secret messages between Revolutionary cells.
He believed it was the fortune cookies that
helped him win the war."
But according to these memoirs written by Mao’s doctor,
Mao later became obsessed with fortune cookies.
Especially after several predictions proved
eerily correct.
"You mean, the fortunes were accurate?"
"Yes.
One fortune Mao got read,
'When metal is depleted, the earth will become
weak.'
That's based on the Five Elements theory.
Earth generates Metal.
The five elements theory is a profound skill
that Chinese people use to predict the future.
From this perspective,
Mao was using a skill that he didn't completely
grasp."
According to Jing,
Mao thought this prediction meant that unless
he increased steel production,
the “earth,” or China, would be weak and
vulnerable to foreign invasion.
So during the Great Leap forward,
he drove the entire population into steel
production.
Even in rural areas, entire forests were leveled
just to fuel the furnaces.
But it was all a waste.
They couldn’t get the temperatures high
enough and so the metal was brittle and useless.
In fact, that was one of the contributing
factors to the Great Famine.
"'When metal is depleted,
the earth will become weak.'
30 million people starved to death.
The Earth element correlates to the stomach."
"Whooooaaaa."
"There were other fortunes, too.
The entire reason Mao blocked Zhou Enlai from
getting treatment for his cancer
is because of a fortune cookie predicting
that if Mao died first,
Zhou would take over his legacy."
"And it’d be Zhou’s face up in Tiananmen
today.
Wow, so, I’m really impressed by the history
of your art.
I was wondering,
can I have one of your fortune cookies?"
"Knowing the future can be a burden as much
as it is a gift."
"I’ll take my chances."
"'You will have the number one show on YouTube.'
Oh wow!!!
Oh. Wait there’s more...
'Visit Learn Chinese Now for the true meaning.'"
And thank you for watching.
What do you like most about fortune cookies?
And if you comment below—
no spoilers please.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell. See you next
time.
OK, so for the real story behind this episode,
here's my friend Ben Hedges from Learn Chinese
Now.
Yu ren jie.
That’s how you say April Fool's day in Chinese!
So when an elementary student
tells his teacher
that the principal wants to see him in his office,
and he actually goes there to find it was
fake...
Yu ren jie.
That was me who pulled that one.
When the BBC tells you spaghetti grows on
trees...
The last two weeks of March
are an anxious time for the spaghetti farmer.
After picking,
the spaghetti is laid out to dry in the warm Alpine sun.
Yep,
it's yu ren jie.
Or when you see a video that says "traditional"
Chinese Fortune Cookies
were suppressed by the Communists but preserved
in America.
It must be
yu ren jie.
Sorry to break the illusion.
You guys really believed that right?
But Chris, the Communists did suppress a lot
of stuff right?
I mean Chinese American food uses a lot of
broccoli.
That is surely one of the cuisines that were
suppressed in the cultural revolution right?
I wish the communists had suppressed broccoli.
It's the bane of a good General Tsao's Chicken.
Anyway, if you like humor and want to learn
some useful words in Mandarin,
click here to go to Ben's channel,
Learn Chinese Now
where you can, you know,
learn Chinese now.
He uploads new awesome videos every week.