On this episode of China Uncensored,
if the South China Sea is dominated by China,
then the Indian Ocean should be dominated
by...
China! Obviously.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Well folks, I have good news and bad news.
The good news is that India and China probably
aren’t
entering a Cold War era nuclear submarine
race.
The bad news is it could actually be worse.
And it turns out the US might be right in
the middle of it.
China and India are the two most populous
countries on earth.
They’re also economic rivals,
share the world’s longest contested land
border,
and are importing more weapons than any other
countries out there.
What could go wrong?
You see, just because the South China Sea
clearly belongs to China,
doesn’t mean the Indian Ocean belongs to
India.
A senior captain from China’s National Defense
University made that clear.
Now that wasn’t some kind of threat, obviously.
But just for the sake of argument,
if you were wondering how many submarines
China would need
to blockade India,
the answer is 10.
Not like they've thought about it before,
but it would be 10.
And the 18 naval bases the Chinese regime
is building
along key trade chokepoints surrounding the
Indian Ocean
would have no part in such a purely hypothetical
blockade.
Oh, and that nuclear submarine that was patrolling
around the Gulf of Aden last year? Don’t
worry.
That was just to hunt pirates.
Because submarines are the best choice for
that.
You also shouldn’t worry about the two Chinese
submarines
that docked in Pakistan last year.
You know, Pakistan: India’s nuclear-armed rival.
The Chinese were probably just showing off
the goods
to help secure that 8-sub construction deal
they
finalized toward the end of last year.
And yet for some reason,
India seems nervous about the frequent visits
Chinese submarines
are making to the Indian Ocean.
As if China’s rapid buildup of artificial
islands was just
"an effort to break out of the South China
Sea,
and then project into the Indian Ocean,"
you know, as "one of the opening moves in
China’s quest
for global military and economic dominance."
Ridiculous!
But just in case, India and the US
started off the month with talks about anti-submarine
warfare.
For decades, India has maintained its distance
from the US.
But China’s recent submarine activities
have changed that.
India and the US have conducted joint military
exercises before,
but now they’re stepping it up.
Last month, US Defense Secretary Ashton Carter
and his Indian counterpart
issued a joint statement saying they would
strengthen military ties.
Part of that meant India would finally allow
the US military
access to Indian military bases.
The US, for its part,
has agreed to give India access to weapons
technology,
like the P-8, its most advanced submarine
hunter.
Apparently it can track a sub from the sky.
This is all to help India narrow its military
gap with China.
And believe me, the gap is pretty darn big.
China has the biggest navy in Asia, with 300
vessels.
62 of them are submarines, 4 of which can
fire nuclear ballistic missiles,
according to a report by the Pentagon last
year.
India has less than half as many ships,
including only one nuclear sub,
which is on lease from Russia.
And both countries have a lot at stake.
China and India get more than 40 percent
of their GDP from international trade.
So it makes sense that they would both want
to secure
the tremendously profitable ocean trade routes.
But the US is the world leader in anti-submarine
warfare.
It got a lot of experience from going through
a very similar situation
with the Soviet Union during the Cold War.
Though with one very key difference.
According to this report by the Lowy Institute,
the threat of nuclear annihilation
kept tensions
between the US and the Soviets from escalating.
But as for India and China,
their submarines are both too few in number
and not technologically advanced enough
to be an effective nuclear deterrent.
In other words, back in the day,
both the US and the Soviets knew that if they
launched a nuclear attack first,
they wouldn’t be able to stop the other
side from launching one of theirs.
But with China and India,
each might feel that they could launch a nuke,
and still successfully stop the other side
from detonating one of their own.
This might then be a problem that both India
and China
want to pump up their sub presence.
Then when you add to that Pakistan and North
Korea
are both trying to get nuclear subs,
on top of US presence in the region,
well, it’s getting a little crowded over
there.
But not to be outdone with that whole
being-able-to-blockade-you thing,
later this year, India, the US, and Japan,
will be holding joint military drills near
the Philippines.
That’ll be sure to ease tensions.
But you know what kind of sub the Chinese
Communist Party fears the most?
Subs...to China Uncensored.
So subscribe today!
What do you think about the tensions in the
Indian Ocean?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell. See you
next time.