On this episode of China Uncensored,
can the Chinese Communist Party just buy South
Korea?
Morally, I mean.
Also with millions of dollars.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
I was in South Korea a couple months ago.
And one thing that struck me is how much influence
there is there from China.
Chinese tourists.
Chinese restaurants.
Even knock-off Chinese toys.
Now by and large,
South Koreans I spoke with were very welcoming
to Chinese people.
“We have a long history between the Chinese
and Koreans.”
But you know whose influence most South Koreans
don’t really like?
The Chinese Communist Party.
I mean, the only reason communist North Korea
is still around
to threaten the South is because they were
backed by the Chinese Communist Party.
But China likes to play both sides.
That’s why China is now South Korea’s
biggest trading partner.
But people there are still wary of the Communist
Party’s influence.
And they should be!
Because there’s new evidence that South
Korea’s national state-run TV broadcaster
has sold out to China.
I’m talking about KBS.
And the theater they own, KBS Hall.
Back in December,
KBS Hall signed a contract for this show,
Shen Yun, to perform there.
But then, in January,
KBS suddenly canceled the contract,
and fired the person who signed it.
But I told you in March,
“I don't want to make wild accusations about
what's behind KBS Hall's cancellation of Shen Yun."
Well now I do want to make wild accusations.
And by wild accusations,
I mean show you the hard evidence that the
Chinese Embassy was behind it,
and forced KBS to break their contract.
And it involves millions of dollars.
But first, some background.
Shen Yun Performing Arts is a Chinese-American nonprofit
that does an annual classical Chinese dance show.
It tours around the world.
And while you might think that spreading Chinese
music and dance
would be just want Chinese leaders would want
You’re right. They do.
But only if they can completely control the
message.
And with Shen Yun, well…
the Communist Party can’t control it because,
guess what?
It was founded by Falun Gong practitioners,
and a couple of its dance numbers depict contemporary
issues,
like Falun Gong meditators standing up to the
Communist Party’s suppression.
Let's just say the Communist Party is not
a fan.
So they try to kill it.
Like sending a Chinese agent to slash a Shen
Yun tour bus’s tire
so it would explode while driving down the
highway with 50 dancers inside.
Which fortunately didn’t happen, but still.
The Communist Party also tried to stop theaters
around the world from showing Shen Yun.
Because apparently the greatest threat to
China's stability
is freedom of expression in other countries.
Most theaters, of course, have stood up to
the Communist Party
which is why you can watch Shen Yun in more
than a hundred cities every year.
Which brings us back to South Korea.
So as I told you,
KBS Hall in Seoul cancelled Shen Yun in January.
That was a breach of contract.
So Shen Yun’s promotion company sued KBS.
After my episode in March, the South Korean
court ruled in favor of Shen Yun.
In this document,
the court wrote that KBS had no legitimate
reason to break the contract,
and that the show must go on!
So organizers got to work,
selling thousands of tickets for the shows,
scheduled for May 6 through 8.
But then, on May 4, the court suddenly reversed
its decision,
canceling Shen Yun once again.
And it came just ahead of a long national
holiday weekend,
so there was no way to appeal.
And the show did not go on.
You see, it turned out KBS Hall had lied in
court.
During the initial lawsuit, they told judges
a
“Shen Yun performance is unsuitable for
KBS Hall,”
but “denied China’s influence on its decision.”
instead, saying it would damage KBS’s public
image.
Well you know what really damages KBS’s
public image?
Perjury.
Because in order to get the court to rule
in its favor,
KBS eventually ’fessed up, and showed the
court not one
but two letters from the Chinese Embassy in
Seoul
directly proving “China’s influence on
its decision.”
This one dated January 22 contains some thinly
veiled threats, including:
“KBS is Korea’s largest television station
and its influence on Korea is significant;
it also has friendly ties with China Central
Television.”
And
“[China] hopes that KBS will consider China–Korea
relations when making decisions.
Do not provide a venue for Shen Yun to perform.”
It’s kind of like what the mafia does.
“I’m gonna make him an offer he can’t
refuse.”
But KBS covered it up at first.
It only revealed the Embassy’s threats when
it felt it had no choice.
Now you might think the South Korean court
would have said,
“A foreign government doesn’t get to threaten
our country.
And hey KBS, you just lied in court.”
But instead it said,
“Oh you’ve been bought out by China?
Well then yes, absolutely!
You can go ahead and break your contract.”
You see, in the final ruling,
the South Korean court judge wrote that if
KBS Hall were to allow Shen Yun to perform,
KBS, quote, “may face a huge loss which
can’t be compared
with the income from ticket selling.”
And here it says that,
as a major TV broadcaster,
KBS’s broadcasts to China are worth more
than the equivalent of 8 million US Dollars
per year.
Because while it may be illegal to break a
contract under normal circumstances,
it’s ok if you’ll make lots of money from
breaking it.
So after decades fighting against one brutal
communist regime,
the South Korean government simply sold out
to another for a few million bucks.
So what do you think? And what would you like
to say to KBS?
Leave your comments below.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell. See you next
time.