On this episode of China Uncensored,
making mischief in the South China Sea.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
A US Navy destroyer has just sailed through
sacred Chinese territory.
And by sacred Chinese territory,
I mean the artificial islands
China began building three years ago
in the middle of the ocean.
The destroyer USS Dewey
sailed 12 miles off the coast of this—
Mischief Reef.
Which is a fitting name.
It’s part of a chain of islands
called the Spratlys—
a chain claimed by China,
Taiwan, Vietnam, and the Philippines.
Except, this isn’t what the Mischief Reef
looks like today.
That photo is from 2014
when it was just a boring old
submerged reef—
underwater at high tide.
But while those other countries
have been trying to solve the dispute
with international arbitration,
the Chinese Communist Party took action.
First they dredged up a little sand.
And then some more sand.
And now, that little reef is a full-fledged
island.
Yes, a tropical island getaway,
full of white sand beaches,
palm trees,
a well stocked tiki bar--
And, of course, military installations.
China, in addition to building those islands,
is now militarizing them,
basing military aircraft,
military warships and missile systems
on these manufactured reefs.
The US is responding by sailing
its warplanes and warships
through these waters
to demonstrate its point
that they remain international.”
Now this isn’t new.
The US has been conducting what it calls
“Freedom of Navigation” Operations,
or FONOPs,
for years under former US President Barack
Obama.
Thanks, Obama!
That's when the US Navy
sails ships through international waters
to challenge excessive territorial claims
made by other countries.
And according to the US Navy,
they're pretty standard procedure,
and not just directed at China.
In fact,
last year the US Navy
challenged excessive claims from 22 countries.
But this is the first patrol
conducted in the South China Sea
since Donald Trump took office.
And just like FONOPs are standard procedure
for the US Navy,
reacting to them with anger is standard procedure
for the Chinese Communist Party.
The actions by the U.S. undermined
China's sovereignty and security interests,
and they are very likely to cause
unexpected sea and air accidents.
Yeah, if you’re not careful,
maybe one of your precious destroyers
might accidentally fall down the stairs.
In fact, according to China’s Defense Ministry,
two Chinese frigates had ‘warned and dispelled’
the USS Dewey after it had entered its waters
without permission.
That isn’t exactly how the US put it, though.
In fact, the US has said very little at all
about the incident.
CNN only got the story from an American official
whose name wasn’t cited.
It follows a May statement
from Pentagon Spokesperson, Captain Jeff Davis
that the Trump administration is going to
do things
a little differently.
Instead of announcing each of the FONOPs,
they would only be released publicly in an
annual report.
Despite his strong campaign rhetoric against
China,
President Trump has been trying to build
a positive relationship with Chinese leader
Xi Jinping
over the last few months.
Mostly because Trump wants China’s support
tackling the North Korea issue.
This whole incident comes as Xi Jinping
called for a strong, modern navy
at the 12th Party congress
of the People's Liberation Army.
It also follows Philippine President Duterte
alleging that Xi Jinping threatened him with
war
if the Philippines drills for oil
in disputed waters.
He said: 'Well if you force the issue,
we'll be forced to tell you the truth.
What is the truth?
We will go to war.
We will fight you.
And despite what Duterte said last October...
I will break up with America.
I would rather go to Russia and to China.
...now he seems to be asking for US help.
So we seek the help of America,
a concerted effort of all the member states
of the United Nations,
are they willing to fight?
Because if they're willing to fight
then we are,
but if it was only me,
why would I do that?
It will result in a massacre
and it will just destroy everything.
So maybe the Trump administration
wants to show it will make good on its promise
to defend the South China Sea.
Or maybe, it's the just the US's turn
to make a little bit of mischief
at Mischief Reef.
So what do you think about the US Navy's
Freedom of Navigation operations?
Leave your comments below.
And let me just take a moment again
to thank everyone who supports this show
by contributing via Patreon.
Patreon is a website where you can pledge,
for example, a dollar per episode.
And that allows the China Uncensored team
to keep making great content for you
every week.
So click the button at the end
to visit our page on Patreon.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I’m your host Chris Chappell.
See you next time.