On this episode of China Uncensored...
"We are never ever getting back together"
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I'm your host Chris Chappell.
Ah China, the world's growth engine.
At least according to top Chinese officials.
When western companies first went to China
it was like...
"Does this guy know how to throw a party or
what?"
But now...
"This Party's over."
Because a lot of US companies are planning
to leave China,
or have left already.
That's according to the 2016 business climate
survey by the American Chamber of Commerce
in China.
"Our survey reflects that one in four companies
are moving operations."
Wow. One in four.
They surveyed 500 members that make up a representative
chunk of US companies operating in China.
The survey also found that, increasingly,
businesses are flatlining, in yellow, or losing
money, in red.
77% said they feel "less welcome" in China
than before.
Nearly 80% say they've been negatively affected
by China's Internet censorship.
And perhaps one of the worst hit has been
the musical instrument insurance company,
Fallin' Gong.
Now for years, China's economy has experienced
a meteoric rise.
"...the meteoric rise, the rapid growth of
China."
Which is weird,
because I'm pretty sure meteors don't rise.
But anyway, now the...rising meteor
is falling back down.
"China's economy is slowing.
This is a known fact."
Many experts think China's GDP growth data
is inflated
even entirely man-made.
Oh, wait, sorry, it's not experts saying that
it's China's own Premier, Li Keqiang.
More than half of American companies surveyed
said they're struggling with labor costs.
There are other problems, too.
The biggest challenge companies say they face
is "inconsistent regulatory interpretation
and unclear laws."
Which I assume was a multiple-choice answer.
There are some other fun reasons to leave,
too.
52% of survey respondents say the risk of
getting intellectual property stolen
is greater in China compared to other places
they do business.
And 52% also say they've had trouble recruiting
senior executives
to work in China because of air quality issues.
So in summary, American companies are struggling
with paying people,
dealing with a legal system that has more
holes than Swiss cheese,
getting their stuff stolen,
and also they can't breathe.
So for the one in four companies that have
left or plan to leave China,
where are they headed?
What's that, Shelley?
Not back to America??
Mostly, to other countries in Asia, like Vietnam,
Thailand, and India
--you know, so they can...
continue to exploit the low wages of developing
nations for their own profit.
So there are lots of reasons, apparently
--even according to the bullish American Chamber
of Commerce--
not to do business in China.
And yet still, over half of the businesses
still consider China to be one of the top
three investment destinations.
They'll just do it with more "calculation
and caution."
Right. I think it's best put like this:
"Fool me once, shame on you.
Fool, can't get fooled again."
What do you think about US companies leaving
China,
and their reasons for doing so?
Leave your comments below and subscribe for
more episodes of China Uncensored.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell, see you next
time.