On this episode of China Uncensored,
a shining example how democracy works in China.
Welcome back to China Uncensored,
I’m Chris Chappell.
Who says China can’t have democracy?
Certainly not my favorite Chinese state-run
media,
the Global Times.
As they point out,
democracy is prospering under
the glorious one-party rule of the CCP.
I mean, Chinese Democracy is banned,
but I assume that was just a matter
of musical preference.
Other than that,
democracy is doing great in China.
And of course,
there’s no better example than Wukan,
located in Guangdong Province.
It’s sometimes referred to as China’s
democracy village.
Which is way better than being known
as China’s Underwear Town,
and yes that is actually a thing.
For decades in Wukan,
local officials had been getting rich off
stealing villagers’ land,
and selling it to developers.
But in 2011,
residents took to the streets,
protesting to get rid of the crooked village
leaders.
And in a surprise move,
then Party Secretary of Guangdong, Wang Yang,
resolved the protests not with tear gas and
tanks,
but by letting the villagers hold open elections.
And they ended up voting seven of the protest
leaders
into office.
Technically village elections have been allowed
in China
since the late 1980s,
but elections are often “managed”
by the local Party secretaries
so truly meaningful elections are rare.
Funny how that happens.
So actually in Wukan,
it seems the Communist Party did a great thing;
instead of turning to violence and repression,
they experimented with greater democratic
reforms.
Now you might be thinking:
“Chris, in five years of hosting China Uncensored,
this is the first positive thing you’ve
ever said
about about the Communist Party.”
Yes, I’ve certainly changed my tune.
Which is why the rest of this episode
is just pandas frolicking in the snow.
Ok, that’s enough.
Wukan was such a success story back in 2011.
Let’s see what’s happening in Wukan now,
in 2017.
Oh, this seems like a good sign!
A giant billboard!
With doves flying over Tiananmen Square
while armed soldiers look on.
It says, “Advance solidly to execute the
strategy
of loving the people and enforcing the border.
Police and citizens collectively build a harmonious
and civilized Wukan.”
Well that sounds lovey, and dovey.
But enforcing that border is important.
Otherwise, dangerous elements could sneak
in,
like reporters.
“Today Wukan is sealed off by checkpoints
and armed police.”
Well, one Reuters reporter did sneak in.
And this is what he observed.
“Every street corner from accounts that
I’ve heard
have video cameras,
high definition surveillance cameras.
There are plainclothes police everywhere,
and there’s still a massive battalion of
riot police.”
Now while that sounds bad,
there’s a very good reason
for the heavy police surveillance.
You see, there’ve been some problems in
Wukan.
Last year,
the leader that the villagers elected, Lin
Zuluan,
was frustrated.
Even though he got elected,
communist officials at every level
were blocking him from carrying out the changes
they had promised him five years earlier.
So he threatened to bring the villagers out
to protest again.
But instead of giving in to his threat,
authorities simply arrested him and forced
him
to confess to a bunch of corruption charges.
Then the villagers protested that.
And the CCP responded
in pretty much the way you’d expect.
And now, a year later,
all’s quiet on the Wukan front.
According to one of the former protest leaders,
“All of the other former Wukan protest leaders
have since quit their posts,
been jailed, or harassed.”
The only possible explanation is that...
they were all bad leaders.
See?
Chinese people just aren’t ready
to elect their own representatives,
and need the strong, benevolent hand of the
CCP
to pick their leaders for them.
Jackie Chan was right all along.
And really, how could the man who made
both Shanghai Noon and Shanghai Knights
ever be wrong?
But back to Wukan.
It’s not just the protest leaders
who have gotten in trouble.
Ordinary villagers were sentenced to prison
for illegal assembly,
disrupting traffic,
and spreading false information.
So it seems we’re back to the status quo.
It really was the perfect strategy from the
CCP.
Pretend to give in to people’s demands,
allow elections,
then undermine those elected leaders at every
opportunity,
then eventually arrest those leaders
and establish a police state.
And who’s making that police state possible?
Um...the West is, I guess?
Now it’s interesting to note that Wang Yang,
the Guangdong Party Secretary
that allowed for elections in the first place,
has recently been promoted
to the Politburo Standing Committee.
That makes him one of the seven
most powerful men in all of China.
Maybe that means he’ll push for democracy
in the rest of China.
After all,
I hear democracy is flourishing in Wukan.
What do you think?
Leave your comments below.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
So maybe you can’t vote in China.
Or protest.
Or watch this YouTube video.
But for the 99% of you not illegally watching
this
with a VPN in China:
Remember: you can and should go to ChinaUncensored.tv
to watch new full half-hour episodes every
Friday.
Check it out!
ChinaUncensored.tv.
Or just click the square button.