I’m here with Andrew Choi,
the executive producer of the movie, “Ten
Years,”
which won Best Film in the Hong Kong Film
Awards.
Andrew, thanks for joining us.
I’m a huge fan of this film,
I’ve seen it at least five times.
Tell me,
what’s it like working with Channing Tatum
and Chris Pratt?
What’s that, Shelley?
Oh, that’s a different movie also called
“Ten Years…”
Andrew, excuse me for just
a moment.
Okay, Andrew, thank you.
Pardon the interruption.
So I just watched “Ten Years,”
which is apparently a collection of five short
films
about the Chinese Communist Party’s erosion
of freedom
in Hong Kong.
So the film is set in 2025,
ten years in the future of Hong Kong.
Why are there no robots or sentient machines?
Well, because we have a very limited budget.
That’s the best answer!
Actually, we talked to the director and said,
we only have 100,000 dollars Hong Kong per
film.
So it’s very, very low budget.
Per each of the five films?
- Yeah
So total, 500,000 Hong Kong dollars budget.
So I don’t think you can have a robot with
this budget.
Always cardboard.
So why did you get involved with this film?
Well, I think we started out 3 years ago,
it was 2013,
me and my co-producer, Ng Ka-Leung,
who’s a wonderful director,
we just finished a documentary film in Hong
Kong
also talking about some of the changes in
Hong Kong.
And we had the idea that,
oh, after this documentary film want to do
a feature film
about the future of Hong Kong?
Because back then you could kind of sense
that
Hong Kong is changing.
Of course the influence of China is,
you can feel it’s getting
more and more involved in the Hong Kong issues.
So we were just asking the question,
what’s next for Hong Kong?
So “Ten Years” was very successful in
Hong Kong -
sold out theaters.
Were you expecting this kind of response?
Definitely no.
We never imagined we could have such a
huge response.
At the beginning we were imagining,
maybe one theater can show it for one week.
At the end, theaters showed it for eight weeks,
total of six cinemas show it.
But even after eight weeks,
our film was still doing quite well.
It was selling out in all cinemas.
But the cinema told us,
sorry Andrew, but we won’t have any screening
time for you next week.
And we were asking why.
“It was making money for you guys.”
He just says, “I’m sorry,”
I just don’t have any slot for you guys.
So that’s an interesting part,
since that normally won’t happen in Hong
Kong.
Why do you think there was that?
Well, of course they won’t tell us the reason.
But you can kind of know it’s self-censorship
from the cinemas.
But yeah, we don’t have the chance
to continue to show it in the cinema.
We show it in the community.
So we did 150 screenings since February this
year
in universities, community centers,
different high schools or even churches.
So yeah, people are eager to watch our film.
So we continued to screen it for 5 or 6 months
in the community.
And then it won Best Film at the Hong Kong
Film Awards.
How did you feel about that?
So we were very surprised,
and of course we were honored.
But I think this film,
not just because that we,
in terms of production quality, I don’t
think we are in that level.
In terms of the meaning,
in terms of response from the Hong Kong people…
But I think people appreciate it for the timing
of the film,
that it was released.
And people say, well, it seems like things
we’re talking about i the film
are actually happening in Hong Kong.
So people say you are prophesying the future,
and it’s really happening.
And so it generated more awareness to the
Hong Kong people.
And I know some people said the things that
happen in the movie
could never actually happen in Hong Kong.
But then as you say, shortly after it came
out there was the
five Hong Kong booksellers that were detained
in mainland China,
in the past few months there’s the interpretations
Beijing is making about Hong Kong legislators.
So do you feel that opinion has changed
that this could never happen?
Well, actually, people are saying that we
should
change the title of the film.
Instead of “Ten Years,” we should name
it “This Year.”
Because we are imagining the future ten years
from now, right?
2025.
But just a few months after we release the
film,
people are saying things are already happening
in Hong Kong.
You can really sense these things are going
to happen
in the near future.
Actually, when you do the film
all the directors have this in mind that,
we don’t want to see the story
that we talk about in the movie happen in
real life.
But unfortunately, things are already happening,
as you said.
Some of the conspiracy theories that we talk
about
in the first film,
people can associate…
Actually, the Mong Kok Incident in February
this year -
there’s a riot.
Fishball Revolution.
People kind associate,
“oh, this is what you’re talking about
in the film.”
And of course the bookstore,
in the film we talk about a secret bookstore.
So people associate those things we’re talking
about
with things that are already happening.
And when we do the local community screenings,
especially after the Q&A session,
we always say that, in real life,
things are more ridiculous than what we’re
talking in the film.
And because of the political nature of the
film,
have you face any censorship or pressure because
of it?
Not directly.
We are asked very often,
“are you guys being followed?”
“Are you guys afraid?”
No.
So far, no.
But I think - I think we can feel the pressure,
especially when we know,
when we were nominated in the Hong Kong Film
Award,,
The main news, Global Times, wrote an article
about us,
that we are spreading virus.
Spreading despair.
I believe the specific term they used for
the film was a
“Thought virus.”
- Yes, thought virus!
Congratulations!
Actually, yes!
After this news came out,
we were just saying we got free publicity.
In Hong Kong, when the government say something,
you’re no good,
it means that’s very good.
So it helped people to do more of our film.
We really believe that our film
is doing something right.
It’s definitely, actually, a good way to
understand
things that are happening in Hong Kong.
Any plans to take the film to the mainland?
Well, there’s a pirated version.
Yup, I heard it is quite popular among the
mainland people.
There’s a lot of download - a lot of BT,
I heard.
Of course it’s illegal.
But that’s probably the only way we can
go in.
I don’t think you’ll be making that box
office revenue.
No, there’s no box office there.
But we released in Taiwan, the film.
And we went to, I think,
over 30 international film festivals in the
past year.
I think we did arouse quite a few interests
in different areas in the world.
And we just released a DVD.
And we released it online.
So hopefully more people will see the film.
For the China Uncensored viewers in the US,
is there any way they can see the film?
I think we’re gonna release it in iTunes
and Google Play
in the US as well.
So you guys have a chance.
But I can share a little bit about our next
project
because it’s related with “Ten Years.”
Because we went to a lot of international
film festivals,
we got the idea of “Ten Years,”
it’s a very local topic about Hong Kong.
But when we show it in other countries,
people are very interested.
Not only to Hong Kong,
but they kind of reflect off of their own
country.
So we’re going to have a project called
“Ten Years: International.”
We’re going to go to different places to
do a local version of “Ten Years.”
For example, we’re going to Taiwan.
We’re gonna do a “Ten Years: Taiwan.”
We’re gonna have local Taiwan directors
to do a “Ten Years” about Taiwan.
We’re gonna do Thailand, Japan, and Korea…
We want to bring this to different places,
and continue this discussion about the futures
of different countries.
So that’s going to be interesting, yeah.
Well since you mentioned the next project,
you know,
I’ve been told I have a certain, um,
cinematic appeal.
I don’t know if you would consider maybe
casting
me in something, particularly if it involves
sentient machines in the future.
You look like a Matrix!
Something like that.
That’d be good.
Yeah.
If I make a “Ten Years in US,” I’ll
probably cast you.
Well ten years in the future of the US would
be pretty, uh…
I wanna talk about this, because I was in
New York…
Cut the cameras!
Yeah, cut the cameras.
One final question: at the end of the film,
it ends with the phrase, “it’s not too
late.”
I know people are saying that Hong Kongers
have become very
pessimistic and cynical.
Do you feel it’s not too late?
Do you feel there’s still hope?
Well, I think it’s gonna be difficult.
I think the control and censorship
is gonna be even more tightened in Hong Kong.
At the same time, with all the screenings,
we’ve talked to many people,
especially younger generation of Hong Kong.
And we feel they’re all concerned about
the future.
And they really want to fight for something
they used to enjoy in Hong Kong.
Freedom of speech,
freedom to do their own things,
to have a good jurisdiction system in Hong
Kong -
I think young people are, I think, stepping
up.
I can see the future in them.
It’s gonna be difficult, but I think
but more and more people are gonna fight for
what we used to have as an international city.
And that’s why we think it’s never too
late.
If we lose hope,
then we’re gonna be very pessimistic.
But if we keep the hope,
and keep the hope in people, especially…
That’s how we see it.
Well thank you for joining me, Andrew.
The film is called “Ten Years,”
be sure to check it out,
and keep your eye open for the US release.
I highly recommend the film.
Thank you.
- Thanks again.