Cars in China
are being swallowed by giant sinkholes.
They’re also exploding.
Welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
This episode is sponsored by Surfshark—because
you should be protecting your identity whenever
you go online by using a VPN like Surfshark.
China is opening up!
But not in the way we all hoped.
Watch closely.
In less than a second after a motorcyclist
crossed the road, a massive pit opened up.
And it swallowed up a car like it was a hot
dog eating competition.
Luckily, the driver was ok.
That was on June 5th in China’s Jiangxi
province.
A similar incident happened two days earlier
in another Chinese province, Guangdong.
On a calm evening, a massive sinkhole there
suddenly opened up and swallowed half a bus.
And over in Qinghai province, this bus fell
into a 30-foot deep sinkhole that again appeared
out of nowhere.
Then the bus exploded, killing 6 people.
In my previous episode about exploding manhole
covers , I talked about Tofu Dreg Construction.
Basically, a lot of infrastructure in China
is made on the cheap—with low quality materials,
and poor safety standards.
Mostly, this is due to corruption that happens
during various phases of construction.
Things end up getting built, but they’re
not built to last.
Take for example the Hang-Shao-Tai Expressway
It’s a massive 100-mile expressway that
cost about 6 billion dollars to build.
Last week, one of the bridges totally collapsed
before it was even completed.
The Expressway Bridge collapsed.
I was just cooking food, and I got f*cking
startled to death.
And the crazy part?
Other parts of that expressway have already
been opened for traffic!
Are those parts safe?
I guess we’ll find out eventually.
Chinese officials are in such a rush to develop,
and increase GDP—that the look of a city
becomes more important than the lives of the
people living there.
And sinkholes are part of that problem.
In December of 2019, a 120-foot deep sinkhole
suddenly appeared on a street in Guangzhou.
“2 cars and 3 people fell into the hole.
After arriving at the scene, the first action
was not to save people, but to fill it in...
The authorities did not rescue people at all.
One mother cried, ‘They just buried my husband
and son there alive!’”
And Chinese authorities don’t like taking
responsibility when things go wrong.
Because that would look bad.
Here’s another video that went viral last
week.
It shows a sudden explosion happening at the
gate of the Fuxin Government Office in Liaoning
Province.
“At around 2:20pm on May 24, near the east
side of People’s Square, a two-wheeled motor
vehicle was driving from east to west and
suddenly exploded...The cause of the explosion
is still under investigation.”
Yes, it’s still under investigation.
Meanwhile, officials have already decided
what happened.
It was a spontaneous explosion, with nothing
further to look into.
However, some Chinese netizens noticed a discrepancy
from the official report.
The clip obviously shows the explosion happening
in front of a government office, not the People’s
Square like the report said.
Plus, it was a sudden explosion.
Not a typical motorcycle explosion—because
when those batteries explode, they usually
start by emitting smoke.
A lot of smoke.
Whereas this explosion was sudden and clean,
with no smoke beforehand.
And that led to even more controversy over
whether this was actually someone setting
off a bomb to target government officials.
“Informed netizens disclosed that the biker
was strapped with explosives at the entrance
of the Fuxin City Government office, waiting
for the black car to go out.
When it arrived in front of the motorcycle,
it detonated homemade explosives and carried
out a suicide attack.
However, the officials did not announce the
results of the investigation.”
But Mao forbid the real story should come
out!
People might then start to question why anyone
would target the benevolent government!
—the government that’s always there to
make sure people are safe.
Except when they’re not.
The problem is, corruption is deeply rooted
in China.
It’s happening at all levels of government
and the Communist Party.
Perhaps some day, a gaping hole will reveal
itself, and officials won’t know how to
get out.
But until that day, maybe don’t drive in
China.
Or walk in China.
Or go to China.
And this episode is sponsored by Surfshark.
Because you definitely can’t access the
real internet in China.
But wherever you are in the world, when you
go online, you should be using a VPN like
Surfshark to protect your identity.
And if you’re doing, say, an investigation
into whether an official report is true, using
a VPN can help protect you from surveillance
and even arrest.
So I recommend you use Surfshark to protect
yourself online.
Plus, when you use Surfshark’s CleanWeb
mode, you’ll be protected from most trackers,
ads and malware.
With one account, you can connect as many
devices as you want.
Try it out with a 30-day money back guarantee.
And Surfshark has a special discount for China
Uncensored fans.
Go to surfshark.com/uncensored and use the
code UNCENSORED to get our special deal that
includes 3 extra months for FREE.
Click the link below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.