On this episode of China Uncensored,
Hong Kong gets ready for rule of law…
Nathan Law.
Hi, and welcome to China Uncensored.
I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
Elections were just held for the Hong Kong
legislature.
It was a record voter turnout.
Not since the British handover of Hong Kong
to China
have so many people showed up to vote.
It’s almost like they want a voice
in the future of their special administrative
region.
And it was a crucial election.
You could kind of look at it like a boxing
match.
In one corner,
weighing in at 43 of the 70 seat Legislative
Council,
you have the pro-Beijing politicians,
looking to defend their business interests
with the Mainland Communist regime.
In the other corner,
weighing in at just 27 seats,
the scrappy pan-democrats,
who favor self-determination and autonomy
for Hong Kong.
The pan-democrats needed to keep
a minimum of 24 seats in the Legislature
or they’d lose their veto power.
If that happened,
Beijing could do whatever it wanted with Hong
Kong.
And we know from watching history
how bad that could be
I have just received word
that the Emperor has dissolved the council
permanently.
The last remnants of the Old Republic
have been swept away.
And Vegas odds would back the pro-Beijingers.
Because this isn’t exactly a fair match.
The pro-Beijing side are coming in with boxing
gloves
filled with rocks,
wrapped in barbed wire,
and set on fire.
Because this election is to democracy
what SPAM is to meat.
It kind of looks like the same thing.
They try to sell it as the same thing.
But when you open it up
and take a whiff,
you know there's something deeply wrong.
When the British gave Hong Kong back to China
in 1997,
the Chinese regime agreed that Hong Kong
would get to keep the freedoms everyone else
in China
was denied.
Which is why in 2014,
Hong Kong’s massive student-led
pro-democracy protest called the Umbrella
Movement
didn’t end up like this.
But over the years,
the Chinese regime has been gradually eroding
Hong Kong’s freedoms,
in much the same way Chinese leader Xi Jinping
has eroded the Zhongnanhai pantry
I’ve never seen Xi Jinping so happy...
And as always,
the Party made sure this election came out
in Beijing’s favor.
First of all,
the election was only for 40 of the 70 seats
on the Legislative council.
The other 30?
Those are chosen by “functional constituencies”
— basically a group of business leaders,
special interest groups,
and hooded robed figures that appear
only under the light of a full moon.
And these 30 functional constituencies
pretty much always vote the way Beijing wants.
In other words,
officials with ties to the Chinese regime
automatically have veto power,
no matter how the election turns out.
Then,
the Hong Kong electoral commission
forced candidates to sign pledges of loyalty
Six refused to sign
or were considered insincere
and banned from running.
Did I mention the Communist Party was eroding
freedoms in Hong Kong?
Okay,
so far so good.
This is looking like a great election!
Doesn’t stop there, though.
During the campaign,
Nathan Law, one of the pro-democracy candidates,
was convicted of unlawful assembly
for his role as one of the key figures
in the 2014 Umbrella movement.
The good news is that
a sympathetic judge said he was showing concern
for society
and sentenced him to 120 hours of community
service
instead of jail time.
So that didn't work out.
But throw into the mix a little bit of vote
rigging
and general thuggery
and you've got this election in the bag!
Except for that whole “record voter turnout”
thing.
And Hong Kongers,
for some reason,
are getting a little afraid of mainland encroachment.
So instead of losing seats,
the pan-democrats ended up gaining:
Now they have 30 seats in the legislature.
30 out of 70 seats doesn’t sound like much.
But remember, only 40 seats were up for grabs,
so they’ve done pretty well.
And guess what?
Six of those are young protest leaders,
including Nathan Law.
And Beijing would have gotten away with it
too,
if it weren't for you meddling kids!
Chinese media, of course,
responded with their usual gloom and doom
State-run Xinhua,
citing the Chinese government organ
that oversees Hong Kong and Macau,
talked about "resolute opposition" to
any form of "Hong Kong independence."
But here’s the problem.
As Time Magazine put it,
after the Umbrella Movement didn’t result
in any meaningful reform,
“the protest leaders were dismissed by critics
as hapless,
unschooled fringe ideologues
who ultimately lacked real political power.”
Well, now they have real political power.
And it’s going to be a lot harder to dismiss
them.
So what do you think of the recent election?
And what do you think is in store for the
future of Hong Kong?
Leave your comments below.
And remember,
since YouTube is being all weird about ad
revenue,
consider supporting China Uncensored on Patreon.
The link is below.
And while you’re at it,
check out our Instagram, Facebook and Twitter
account.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
See you next time.