On this episode of China Uncensored,
if the Chinese regime thinks it can
take a bite out of Australia,
like it were some kind of Vegemite sandwich,
they...have never tasted Vegemite before.
Welcome back to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Something terrible has happened in Australia.
Something that will make your skin crawl.
“G’day, losers.”
Don’t worry, that’s not a real movie.
It’s just an extremely bizarre
Australia tourism ad.
What I’m actually talking about
is much worse than
a Crocodile Dundee reboot.
Ok, slightly worse.
It’s the Chinese Communist Party’s
ongoing campaign to subvert
Australian politics and society.
There’s been a recent revelation
that millions of dollars
worth of campaign contributions
came from donors with
links to the Chinese regime.
Yeah, China, you call that a knife?
Well, this is a knife:
Australia is fighting back,
by tightening rules on foreign investment.
You see, Chinese state-owned enterprises
having been investing in critical Australian
electrical and gas infrastructure.
And there’s been a recent surge of purchases
of Australian agricultural land.
This is a potential national security concern:
letting a foreign,
sometimes hostile authoritarian regime
control your energy and food supplies.
Imagine if you could do that in Settlers of
Catan.
Maybe it wouldn’t take so long to get through
a game.
But in real life, letting another country
control your resources is a bad idea.
So Australia is putting in place some new
rules.
One of them is that agricultural land must
be
widely marketed for at least 30 days to Australians
before it can be offered to foreigners.
Yes, foreigners in general.
No particular foreigner.
We’re not naming names here.
But it’s China.
See, Australia has received more
Chinese overseas investment
than any other country except the United States.
And if you adjust for GDP,
Australia has 14 times more Chinese investment
than the United States.
That’s a lot of cans of Fosters.
That’s Australian for beer.
Wait, what’s that Shelley?
Okay, I’m being told
real Australians drink VB.
Anyway, all this Chinese investment
has made Australia’s intelligence agency
ASIO nervous.
They have a security rating system,
from negligible to extreme.
And I’ll give you one guess
as to which country was just ranked extreme.
“In a couple of examples,
we have the threat level at extreme.”
“And government officials have told 9 News
that China
is listed by ASIO as an extreme threat.”
ASIO also warned that Chinese interference
isn’t limited to politics,
but across Australian society as a whole.
Other countries have made similar moves
restricting foreign investment
from Chinese companies—
also over security concerns.
Because as I’ve explained in previous episodes,
all large Chinese companies have significant
connections
to the Communist Party—
even privately owned ones.
For example, last month,
the US government blocked China’s
Ant Financial from acquiring
US company MoneyGram.
The UK has made similar moves.
Of course the Chinese regime
says all this is just silly.
The Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesperson
even took a page out of the
China Uncensored playbook
and went all sarcastic on us.
I assume she’s a big fan.
She said that if Australians regard
all the millions of Chinese visiting
or living in Australia as spies,
then no wonder Australians feel nervous.
Haha.
What a funnybone tickler.
Except, her sarcasm completely
mischaracterizes what’s happening.
In fact, Prime Minister Malcolm Turnbull
has made it pretty clear that Australia’s
security concerns are not about targeting
Chinese Australians,
or even visiting Chinese.
“I want to be very clear,
we have focused on the activities
of foreign states and their agents in Australia,
and not the loyalties of Australians
who happen to be from another country.”
And a mountain of evidence is piling up about
the danger Chinese-backed companies present.
“Australia has backed a new
United States defense strategy
naming Russia and China
a greater threat to national security
than Islamic terrorism.”
So, Chinese regime falls back on
accusations of racism—
saying Australians are just being prejudiced
against Chinese people.
“Such comments pander to certain
irresponsible reports in Australian media,
they are full of prejudice against China.”
Except that’s not going to work.
Because interference from the Chinese regime
has gotten so bad,
it’s got some Australians saying,
you know what,
our alliance with the US is actually
pretty good by comparison.
“About 8 months ago,
I couldn’t imagine me taking this position,
and defending the US alliance.”
This is pretty significant.
A huge part of Australia’s economy
relies on China.
According to Stratfor,
“China accounts for 30 percent
of Australia's trade.”
But the push for regulating Chinese investment
has been building since 2015.
That’s when a Chinese company
leased a major Australian port.
That caused waves of concern,
not just in Australia
but also in the US.
In 2016,
Australia blocked China’s attempts
to buy a controlling share of Ausgrid,
a major Australian electrical network company.
The shares were bought buy
two Australian pension funds instead.
So Australia’s new rules affect agriculture
and the energy grid.
But they don’t cover Australia’s
second-biggest industry:
Mining.
And right now, an Indian company is seeking
Chinese investment money to buy
a $13 billion dollar coal mine in Australia.
The Chinese money is sort of their last option.
The local Australian banks all turned it down
because they don’t want to be caught up
in a project that could have
huge environmental costs.
But China?
They’re fine with it.
After all,
those aren’t China’s resources at risk.
The Australian government’s
increased controls on foreign investments
are probably coming at a good time.
After all,
they wouldn’t want those 37,000 miles
of pristine beach and all those wineries
to belong to a foreign country.
Otherwise what would they put
in their tourism ads?
Actually, that beach does look pretty nice.
I think I’m due for another vacation...
Well played, Australia.
So what do you think of Australia
curbing investment from China?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.
Wait, before you go,
I have something important to tell you.
You know, not many companies are brave enough
to advertise on China Uncensored.
But there is one I want you to know about.
They sell amazing food:
Thrive Life.
And unlike a lot of other meal delivery food,
they’ve got GMO Free,
Gluten Free,
and organic options.
And unlike Blue Apron,
Thrive Life meal packs won’t go rotten
in you fridge after a couple days.
Thrive food is freeze dried,
so it lasts several months,
even years.
I know what you’re thinking.
Freeze dried food?
Are you sure about this?
I was skeptical too...
until they sent me a box of samples.
And I can honestly tell you,
it’s delicious.
They sent me this whole box.
There’s a ton of amazing food in here.
Everything from snacks to meals.
My personal favorite,
South Pacific-Style Stir Fry with Pulled Pork.
Now I know,
it comes in a box,
but this is what it looks like cooked
and it only took me a few minutes to make.
And they sell hundreds of other foods.
Uncensoring China takes a lot of energy.
And I don’t always have time to plan meals.
I can’t tell you how many times food in
my fridge
has gone bad because I couldn’t cook for
a few days.
Thrive Life basically solved this for me.
It’s super convenient,
tastes great,
and I don’t have to worry about it going
bad.
It’s also more affordable the Blue Apron.
I’ve provided a link below to order.
Just try one or two meals.
You’re gonna love it.
And China Uncensored gets a commission
on any purchase you make.
So this is a great way to help the show,
and get some tasty food out of it.
Plus, if Kim Jong-un ever does launch a nuke,
you’ll have all the food you need
in the post-apocalyptic future.
So help out the show,
and buy yourselves some treats from Thrive
Life.
Click the link below.