On this episode of China Uncensored:
China calls to reduce tensions on the Korean
Peninsula.
And to prepare for war just in case.
Hi welcome to China Uncensored, I'm your host,
Chris Chappell.
You know, when I heard that North Korea
conducted its
fourth nuclear test in January, I
thought,
now's the perfect time to come to South Korea!
That's why I'm here,
overlooking the border between North Korea
and South Korea.
With tensions rising,
this could become a flashpoint for war—
and not just between two countries, but four:
North Korea,
South Korea,
China,
and America.
The relationship between these countries is complicated,
to put it mildly.
Everyone knows North Korea is run by a cruel,
oppressive regime.
I mean, look at it!
Seriously, it's right over there.
Anyway, even though North Korea supposedly
has a scary military,
that doesn't mean it has a strong one.
But no one actually wants the North Korean
regime to collapse.
Imagine millions of refugees streaming across
the border
into South Korea or China.
Who would take in those
tired, poor, huddled masses yearning to breathe
free?
Probably not.
So the order of the day is just prevent North
Korea
from launching any nuclear weapons,
while at the same time,
hoping it magically transforms itself
into a democracy somehow.
They could call it the Democratic People's
Republic of Korea.
What's that, Shelley?
Oh.
Anyway, everyone is preparing for the worst.
Especially after North Korea followed up its
nuclear test
by launching that long-range rocket
on February 7th,
and celebrating it in the creepiest way possible.
In this editorial by my favorite Chinese state-run
media, the Global Times,
the author says that
"[China] should prepare for a war...
Even though there is a very low probably that
a war will occur,
[China] should be 100 percent prepared."
Meanwhile, South Korea and the US are talking
about setting up a
Terminal High Altitude Area Defense system
in South Korea.
It would launch missiles like this,
which could shoot a North Korean ballistic
missile out of the air—
including one carrying a nuclear warhead.
Previously, South Korea had rejected using
the US military’s THAAD.
What changed their minds?
Oh, right.
But China strongly opposes the use of THAAD.
They say it threatens China's national security.
Which would be true if China fought alongside
North Korea
in a war against South Korea and the United
States,
like they did in what they still call
"The War to Resist US Aggression and Aid Korea."
But no one wants Korean War II.
Or World War III.
Which is why the US wants to put THAAD in
place as quickly as possible.
Because the US and South Korean governments
see it as a deterrent,
as well as a useful but hopefully-never-used
defense.
China also hopes it never gets used,
because that could be the first step in destabilizing
North Korea.
Not that China actually likes North Korea,
It just enjoys the political power it gets
from a rogue state.
That's why the Chinese Communist Party is
propping up the North Korean regime
by giving it weapons and aid.
China is also North Korea's largest trading
partner by far,
on the order of more than $5 billion dollars
a year.
And China is also the main way North Korea
evades international sanctions.
So by putting itself in this position,
the CCP is forcing the rest of the world to
come to it for help.
But this strategy may come back to
bite them.
For one, North Korea is becoming harder for
China to control.
They couldn't stop them from launching the
long-range rocket,
even though they tried.
And now other countries are taking actions
that could hurt China.
For instance, the US just passed new sanctions
against North Korea,
including sanctions against Chinese companies
that do business with North Korea.
Plus the THAAD missile defense system does
shift
the balance of military power in the region,
and not in China’s favor.
But the whole whole missile testing, exploding
nukes
is really just a way for Kim Jong-Un to consolidate
his power.
Because his youthful good looks won't last
forever.
So will there be war on the Korean Peninsula?
I don't plan to stick around long enough to
find out.
What's that, Matt?
What do you mean, we're going to North Korea?!