On this episode of China Uncensored...
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I’m your
host Chris Chappell.
Well, it's that time of year again.
When June 3 transitions peacefully to June
with absolutely nothing happening in between.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you…
What’s that Shelley?
Oh my...no! No!
You’re joking right?!
I’m sorry ladies and gentlemen,
but it turns out there is a June 4,
and it marks the day the Chinese Communist
Party went too far!
They blocked Tumblr.
I know right?!
Somehow Tumblr managed to be one of the only
foreign social media platforms
not blocked in China—until now.
How will Chinese people know how high Xi Jinping's
pants are now?
The social media revolution now depends on
you, Friendster.
Shoot.
This was of course in the lead-up to the 27
year anniversary of the 1989 Tiananmen Square Massacre,
or as many young Mainland Chinese refer to
it,
“who cares?”
It’s a time when you can be arrested for
dangerous and subversive acts,
like remembering.
Of course, outside Mainland China,
there is no state-mandated amnesia.
From New York to Hong Kong,
tens of thousands of people marked the anniversary.
And in a move that will surely only improve
Cross-Straits Relations,
Taiwan’s new president had a message for
China’s leadership on Facebook.
“There’s nothing scary about democracy.
Democracy is a good and fine thing.”
And while you might expect that to result
in more accusations from Chinese officials
that Tsai is just a crazy unbalanced woman,
it probably won’t.
After all, she wrote this on Facebook,
so how will they ever read it in China?
Unless, Chinese state-run media with Facebook
accounts tell them.
But now that June 4 has passed,
we can all breathe a sigh of relief and get
on with our lives,
happily avoiding getting political.
At least, for 6 weeks
when the next sensitive anniversary comes
up.
July 20 1999, when the Chinese regime began
doing this to people
for doing this.
So what’s your favorite way to forget June
4?
Leave your comments below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell. See you next time.