Proof the Coronavirus is a Biological weapon
Small victories for Hong Kong
And outrage against the Chinese Communist
Party.
That and more on this week’s China News
Headlines
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
The coronavirus.
Is it a biological weapon?
For a long time, there have been conspiracy
theories
that the coronavirus that spread from Wuhan,
China was a biological weapon.
That’s even a conspiracy theory t
he Chinese Communist Party has pushed.
The Chinese foreign ministry spokesman tweeted
the US army brought the coronavirus to Wuhan.
Keep in mind, he’s not just any old crackpot
conspiracist.
He’s the Foreign Ministry Spokesman for
a country.
But we’ll never know for sure if the coronavirus
was a biological weapon, right?
Well, proof has just come out that it is a
biological weapon.
Just not the kind of bioweapon you were thinking
of.
See, most of the United States’ medical
supplies
and generic drugs are made in China.
Great choice, by the way.
And now, Communist Party mouthpiece Xinhua
is saying they can impose pharmaceutical export
controls to quote,
throw America into the Mighty sea of the coronavirus.
When the Communist Party threatens to attack
America
by withholding critical medical supplies
needed to stop a deadly virus outbreak—
that is a biological weapon.
If only America had been willing to do
the Chinese Communist Party’s bidding,
this would never have happened!
Speaking of not doing the Communist Party’s
bidding,
President Donald Trump.
He loves to call it the Chinese Virus.
And the Communist Party hates that.
“Recently some U.S. politicians have linked
the novel coronavirus to China.
This is a smear of China.
We are very angry and strongly oppose it.”
Yeah, “some U.S. politicians”—not gonna
name names here.
Now, I recommend you watch my recent episode
“Coronavirus: How China Spun Criticism Into
Racism”
for a better understanding of what the Communist
Party is trying to do here.
But in a way, I agree with the Chinese Foreign
Ministry Spokesman.
I think President Trump needs to stop calling
it the “Chinese virus.”
That’s because we’re just getting into
stupid fights about
whether saying Chinese virus or Wuhan virus
is racist.
Which turn into fights about whether Trump
Which turn into fights about whether *everyone*
is racist.
That is exactly what the Chinese Communist
Party wants!
Because it means we’re so busy fighting
each other
that we’re losing sight of the bigger picture
here.
I don’t advocate calling the coronavirus
the Wuhan virus or the Chinese virus.
It’s unfair to the Chinese people who are
victims
of their authoritarian regime—
the one that caused this problem in the first
place,
by covering up the spread of the virus and
silencing
people who tried to get the truth out.
Let’s not forget that it’s the Chinese
Communist Party—the CCP—
that’s ultimately responsible for this pandemic
and all the people
who will die from it.
So I say, from now on, we call it the CCP
Coronavirus.
All the cool kids are doing it!
Which is why I have to tip my hat to the law
firm in Florida
that is suing the Chinese regime for their
coronavirus coverup.
“[The Chinese Government] suppressed information
rom the global medical community that could
have averted
or minimized the damage that has been done.”
So props to that Florida law firm.
Because if there’s one foe the Chinese Communist
Party
should be afraid of, it’s Florida Man.
I assume that’s what the lawyers in Florida
look like.
Of course, the Chinese Communist Party completely
denies
the ridiculous accusations that they would
ever
want to suppress information.
On a totally unrelated note,
China just announced it will expel American
journalists.
That includes, “American journalists working
for The New York Times,
The Wall Street Journal and The Washington
Post”
That is a blow.
I wonder if those media companies will continue
taking money from China’s propaganda department
to publish the Communist Party propaganda
called China Watch in their newspapers.
Chinese authorities say their decision to
expel American journalists
is because the Trump Administration put restrictions
on Chinese state-run media operating in the
US—
because, you know, they’re Chinese state-run
media,
and therefore by definition agents of the
state.
But even those restrictions did not expel
all the journalists,
or force those Chinese media to shut down.
Still, China’s foreign Ministry Spokesman
said this is ultimately America’s fault.
“The steps China has taken are countermeasures
to the US’s unreasonable oppression of Chinese
media.
China is compelled to take them.
China shouldn't be responsible for the cause
and the result of the current situation.
If any American media has any issue,
please raise it to the US government.”
That’s a tall order.
I can’t remember a time when American media
have ever been willing to criticize the US
government.
But the Trump Administration is not taking
China’s actions lying down.
“U.S. Secretary of State Mike Pompeo on
Tuesday hit back at China
over its decision to kick out American journalists
from the New York Times,
Wall Street Journal and Washington Post.”
“The Chinese will tell you that they want
more people to know about their country,
yet they continue to take actions like the
one you've seen today,
where they deny the world the capacity to
know
what's really going on inside another country.”
I can’t imagine what the Chinese Communist
Party
would be trying to cover up.
The Chinese Communist Party has been trying
to spin
the coronavirus at home and abroad.
You know, focus less on the coverup and more
on how swift, decisive,
transparent, and cooperative China’s coronavirus
response has been.
In other words, they are lying through their
teeth.
State-media have also been praising...their
state-media reporters,
for their brave coverage of the epidemic.
Like Liao Jun.
Only problem is, Chinese people hate all of
it!
“Chinese social media has recoiled with
anger at the lionization of Ms. Liao,
saying she helped propagate fictions that
clouded
the severity of the outbreak in its early
days.”
And that anger is now flaring “into broader
attacks
on the Communist Party’s muzzling of the
news media.”
So now, the Party will do what it always does
when its propaganda backfires.
Attack the critics!
“Online enforcers are dragging in hundreds
for questioning as an assault on online speech
continues.”
That includes any pesky tycoons who criticize
Xi Jinping.
Wait, are we actually getting to the point
where Chinese citizens
are less likely than Americans to believe
Chinese Communist Party propaganda?
Speaking of the Party’s coronavirus coverup,
remember Dr. Li Wenliang?
He was detained by the police after warning
his colleagues
about the coronavirus on Chinese social media.
He later died of the coronavirus himself,
which sparked a huge backlash against the
government in China.
Well, Chinese authorities have investigated
Dr. Li’s case,
and guess who’s to blame?
The local police!
It was their fault.
And they will be dealt with accordingly.
The investigators also wanted to clear one
little thing up.
You see, it appears that some “hostile forces”
are attacking the Communist Party by calling
Dr. Li
a “hero” for standing up to the system.
Well, the joke’s on those hostile forces,
because Dr. Li was a member of the Chinese
Communist Party!
Is that really the message you want to go
with?
Dr. Li was a member of the Communist Party,
which was ultimately responsible
for the spread of the disease that killed
him.
So there!
We showed you!
In other news,
now might be a good time to quit the Chinese
Communist Party.
Speaking of getting rid of the Chinese Communist
Party,
here’s an update about Hong Kong.
You may remember how the city has been embroiled
in massive protests against the Chinese regime
for nine months.
Well, according to a Reuters Exclusive,
what we all thought was happening turns out
to have been true—
“Officers from China’s top internal security
force—
the People’s Armed Police—
joined Hong Kong police on the frontlines.”
Color me shocked.
But another blow might be coming to the forces
of evil in Hong Kong.
Remember back in August when Hong Kong police
attacked protesters on the Hong Kong subway?
Well, a court has ordered the subway operator
to release CCTV footage of it.
Authorities claimed there was no police brutality.
Really?
Well, now they might have a harder time denying
that.
Another small victory for the Hong Kong protest
movement: Chan Kin-man,
one of the leaders of the 2014 Umbrella Movement,
has been released from an 11-month prison
sentence
he got for peacefully protesting.
He said he had no regrets.
But Europe is about to have some major regrets.
France is going to allow Huawei gear in its
5G network.
The US has called Huawei a national security
threat,
since it’s closely tied to the Chinese Communist
Party.
You know, the one responsible for the CCP
Coronavirus
that’s spreading around the world.
I guess France surrendered to the pressure.
German Chancellor Angela Merkel is also a
fan of Huawei.
She’s trying to block other lawmakers from
blocking it.
It’s like there’s a split in Berlin,
where one side is in favor of the communists.
Speaking of which,
Merkel says there’s no reason to be suspicious
of gifts of medical supplies from China.
I believe this is how they’re shipping them.
Part of the problem with getting medical supplies
from China
is how the Chinese regime uses them as propaganda.
Chinese Foreign Ministry Spokeswoman Hua Chunying
shared this video of Italians singing thank
you China
as the Chinese national anthem plays.
The problem is, it’s fake.
Or as the Italians say, fake news.
With the CCP coronavirus happening,
many people have been forced to stay at home.
But even so, exercise is still important.
I would just think, military exercises might
not be the priority.
Despite the pandemic,
the Chinese regime is still finding time to
harass Taiwan.
Some things never change.
Next up, I’ll answer a question from a fan
who supports China Uncensored on Patreon.
But first, did you know YouTube has been secretly
unsubscribing people from the show?
Take a moment to make sure you’re still
subscribed.
And if you haven’t subscribed, what are
you waiting for?
This question comes from carbide149.
“Would you say that ordinary citizens are
falling for China's lies
as much as media outlets and politicians have?”
Ah, that’s actually a question with a very
encouraging answer.
Some Western media are unfortunately
eating up the propaganda about racism,
and the lies that China’s response to the
coronavirus
was so much better than the West’s.
But as I mentioned earlier in the episode,
many Chinese people are furious at the Chinese
regime.
China was the worst hit by the CCP Coronavirus
pandemic.
And the response by the regime has been more
brutal than helpful.
A lot of people in China also know the Party
tried to cover it up,
and persecuted doctors who tried to blow the
whistle.
And this reminds me of something Chinese lawyer
Chen Guangcheng
told Shelley in an interview a couple months
ago:
The people he’s in contact with in China
all understand
that the Chinese Communist Party
is the cause of the problems in Chinese society.
They just can’t say so online, because they
might be arrested.
But they know it, and they don’t like it.
So some day, I really think the Chinese Communist
Party
will be taken down by the Chinese people.
And many reporters in the West will be left
scratching their heads
wondering how it happened.
That’s how it went down with the Soviet
Union.
That’s how it will go down with the Chinese
Communist Party.
Thanks for your question Carbide149.
And thank you for watching.
Remember,
YouTube has been demonetizing almost all of
our videos.
They’d have run us out of business
if it weren’t for support from fans like
you
who contribute through the crowdfunding website
Patreon.
I call them the China Uncensored 50-cent army.
If you’d like to hear your question answered
on the show,
join the China Uncensored 50-cent army
by going to patreon.com/ChinaUncensored.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.