On this episode of China Uncensored,
chop up your enemies for Chinese New Year!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I'm your host Chris Chappell.
Wow, finally!
Chinese New Year is right around the corner,
February 8th.
Another year nearly over and all I can say
is I'm glad to have survived.
I have so many enemies.
Probably.
All of them out to get me.
But now that it's New Year,
I can get back at all those petty people for
every imagined slight.
You know, petty people!
Those people that love to pry into other's
affairs and stir up trouble.
But not to worry,
because according to a tradition in some regions
of China,
the Lunar New Year is apparently a time to
get back at all of them!
Now as you know,
Chinese New Year is also a time for homemade
dumplings, or jiaozi.
But you don't want petty people interfering.
So make sure you do what this guy does:
Mold your jiaozi filling into the shape of
some petty person you know, and then chop!
That's why on the fifth day of the Lunar New
Year
some people do a tradition called 剁小人
duò xiaorén,
or chopping petty people.
You see, China has a long tradition
--in stories, art, and music--
of ordinary people being wronged,
but not having the power to do anything about
it.
Especially when it comes to being wronged
by people in power.
And so they turn to the supernatural realm
for justice denied on Earth.
Hence, traditions like chopping up petty people.
Wow, this guy must know a lot of petty people!
And this guy, well...
he might actually have some anger issues.
Anyway, as you make your dumplings from the
symbolic minced flesh of your enemies,
you need to of course pinch those dumplings
closed.
As this man demonstrates, that's part of the
tradition, too.
It's called pinching petty people's mouths.
Another fun tradition is writing the names
of people you don't like on the bottom of
socks, and then stomping around in them.
It's called 踩小人 Cǎi xiǎorén
--stepping on petty people.
This is actually a thing...
to the extent that you can even buy socks
with the words "petty person" printed on the
bottom.
What's that Shelley?
You think that's petty?
All right...
Shelley.
Anyway, speaking of Chinese traditions,
2016 will be the Year of the Monkey.
That's according to the traditional Chinese
placemat zodiac.
And to celebrate,
it's time for the 3rd annual China Uncensored
Viewer Contest Gala Extravaganza Spectacular
Event Thing.
For the uninitiated, here's how it works:
Draw your best Year of the Monkey monkey
and send it to me on my Facebook page.
I'll pick the winner based on my completely
arbitrary standard of how much I like it.
The grand prize is...
a collectors' edition China Uncensored poster
personally signed by a poorly paid worker
in squalid factory conditions.
And I will send you the poster in the actual
mail.
So keep your eye out for a future episode
where I announce the winner.
Once again, I'm Chris Chappell.
Happy New Year!