America Has Taken a Stand
Against the Chinese Communist Party
The Senate passed two new bills
supporting Hong Kong protesters
But Hong Kong’s freedoms are still under
siege
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
Before we begin, remember,
YouTube is soft censoring China Uncensored.
All our Hong Kong episodes are instantly demonetized
and there’s really not a lot we can do about
it.
Which is why we rely on your support.
If you can,
contribute to the show on the crowdfunding
website Patreon.
We’ll give you some cool stuff depending
on your level of support.
It’s patreon.com/chinauncensored and the
link is below.
So with that out of the way, good news on
Hong Kong!
Finally!
Over the past few decades, US officials,
both Democrats and Republicans,
really dropped the ball on China.
But now, miraculously,
Democrats and Republicans are working together.
And in real life, not an episode of the West
Wing.
What inspired both sides to reach across the
aisle?
A scrappy little region halfway around the
world,
standing up for freedom and democracy,
looking to America to stand with them.
Wait, maybe this *is* an episode of the West
Wing.
No, the West Wing has better music.
This week, the US Senate unanimously passed
both the Hong Kong Human Rights and Democracy
Act
and the PROTECT Hong Kong Act.
And again, unanimously means that all the
Democrats
and all the Republicans agreed on something!
“The Senate has just sent a resounding message
to the Chinese Communist Party and President
Xi
that the United States stands with the democratic
protesters in Hong Kong.”
“The Hong Kong Human Rights and Democracy
Act is important legislation.
It is bipartisan legislation.
[...]
The people of Hong Kong are engaged in an
existential battle for liberty.”
Hey, that’s Democrat Chuck Schumer...
agreeing with Republican Ted Cruz!
In fact 13 US Senators,
both Democrats and Republicans,
used this opportunity to speak
in support of the Hong Kong protesters.
They also trashed the Chinese Communist Party
for its human rights abuses,
including putting the Uyghurs in concentration
camps,
crushing democracy activists,
and harvesting organs from Falun Gong practitioners.
That’s right, US Senators called out the
Chinese regime
for killing political prisoners for their
organs.
That is the number one thing that the Chinese
Communist Party
does not want people to talk about.
What is this strange thing I’m feeling?
Am I...proud...of the US Congress?
While I come to grips with this strange new
reality,
here’s Republican Senator Marco Rubio
on what the Hong Kong Human Rights and Democracy
Act does.
“Its most important element is it requires
the secretary of state to annually certify
whether Hong Kong warrants being treated differently
than China.
If Hong Kong is no longer autonomous—
and that's the rationale for different treatment—
then they should no longer receive that treatment.”
For instance, all the tariffs Trump has hit
China
with would also apply to Hong Kong.
This bill also gives the US government the
ability
to sanction individuals who violate human
rights in Hong Kong
and deny them entry to the US.
Meanwhile, the PROTECT Hong Kong Act bans
US companies
from selling crowd control tools to Hong Kong
police—
things like tear gas, rubber bullets,
pepper spray, and water cannons.
No more Remington shotguns for this guy.
But these bills aren’t a done deal yet.
Both bills have been approved by the US House
of Representatives.
But they still need to be signed into law
by President Trump.
Now, this may surprise you,
but the Chinese Communist Party is not happy
about this.
“The aim of this (act) is to support those
extreme forces
who are seeking to oppose China and cause
chaos,
damage Hong Kong's prosperity
and stability and use sinister smearing of
the Hong Kong issue
to obstruct China's development.”
Yes, the US sure is smearing the perfectly
innocent
Hong Kong and Chinese governments.
Meanwhile state-run CCTV’s national evening
news program included
11 different segments criticizing the US
for the Hong Kong Human Rights and Democracy
Act.
Tell us how you really feel.
So, remember that former UK Consulate employee
who was detained in China?
Simon Cheng.
Yeah, the Chinese secret police tortured him.
Apparently the Chinese police were so sure
the UK was behind the protests in Hong Kong,
that they tortured him to get answers.
And get this.
They abducted him inside Hong Kong.
Here, at the West Kowloon train station.
It’s the terminal for the high speed train
that links Hong Kong to Mainland China.
It’s in Hong Kong.
But last year, the Hong Kong government
ceded part of it to Mainland Chinese authority.
And so that’s why Chinese secret police
were able to abduct a Hong Kong citizen there,
and then bring him to mainland China for torture.
And the secret police didn’t just torture
Simon Cheng.
They tried to turn him into a spy for China,
and then monitored him even after he was released
back into Hong Kong.
He’s now fled to another country.
Cheng also says that while he was in the Chinese
detention center,
he saw other Hong Kong protesters there.
And that the secret police told him
they had captured batches of Hong Kong protesters
and brought them to mainland China.
Which is pretty much everything that people
in Hong Kong
were afraid of in the first place.
Yeah, clearly Hong Kong people have no reason
to protest...
because it’s all the doings of the UK.
You evil mastermind!
Now it may surprise you,
but China denies Simon Cheng’s torture claim.
“During [Simon Cheng’s] detention,
public security unit guaranteed all of his
rights
and interests according to law.
Zheng Wenjie also made a full confession about
his illegal actions.”
By the way, here’s a photo
of Chinese Foreign Ministry Spokesman Geng
Shuang
to use on the dart board at your local pub.
Extra points if you hit him in the heart.
Just kidding.
He doesn’t have one.
The Epoch Times is one of the few remaining
Chinese-language newspapers in Hong Kong
that refuses to bow to the Chinese regime’s
censorship.
It was founded by Chinese dissidents,
including Falun Gong practitioners.
And the paper has been supportive of the Hong
Kong protesters.
So it wasn’t all that surprising
when a group of masked thugs wielding police
batons
broke into the Epoch Times’ printing press
in Hong Kong.
And then they lit the place on fire.
So, freedom of the press is doing great in
Hong Kong.
Hong Kong protesters often wear face masks
to hide their identities,
because they’re afraid the government will
go after them.
But on October 4,
the Hong Kong government went after them anyway.
They used emergency powers to ban people
from wearing masks at protests.
Not that it actually stopped people from wearing
masks.
It just made all the protesters into criminals.
But good news!
This week, a Hong Kong court
ruled the mask ban is unconstitutional.
And the government said they would stop enforcing
it.
But then bad news:
China’s National People’s Congress
said Hong Kong courts don’t have the power
to rule about what is and what isn’t constitutional,
since Hong Kong is part of China.
Which is a hint that China can just upend
Hong Kong’s entire legal system.
China’s National People’s Congress is
clearly oblivious
as to why people began protesting in the first
place.
That National People’s Congress!
You guys really are NPC’s.
But this gives me hope that maybe someday
soon,
everyone in Hong Kong might join together
and fight their real enemy,
the Chinese Communist Party.
And that’s the latest from us on Hong Kong.
What do you think?
Leave your comments below.
And as I mentioned,
YouTube demonetizes episodes like this,
because it considers “Hong Kong” to be
too controversial a subject for advertisers.
So as a thank you to fans who support the
show on Patreon,
I answer their questions at the end of some
of my episodes.
This question comes from...
Larry Breyer
“I hear comparisons between Tiananmen Square
massacre
and what could happen to Hong Kong.
I would like to remind people of one big difference.
Beijing was only Chinese people.
Hong Kong is an international city.
As long as many people from all over the world
visit Hong Kong,
would CCP dare risk murdering foreigners in
order to put down rebellion?
I wonder if the people of the world could
protect Hong Kong
by standing beside the protesters?”
Good question, Larry.
The Chinese Communist Party does not want
to murder foreigners.
Well, ok, maybe they do.
But they don’t want to get in trouble over
it.
When I was in Hong Kong in June,
I felt like police were careful not to aggravate
foreign reporters like me.
But then in October,
police shoved us around like it didn’t matter
how obviously foreign we looked.
Police have also arrested some foreigners
and have searched foreign tourists.
This is a big change in mentality in the police.
But still, the Chinese Communist Party would
rather solve this
without having to hurt foreigners.
Especially Americans.
Because there’s already enough pressure
on them.
And it could mess up the US-China trade deal.
So more foreigners on the ground observing
what’s happening can definitely help.
But as the police get more aggressive,
it’s probably not going to stop them from
hurting Hongkongers.
And keep in mind that those foreigners
are still taking a risk by just being there.
Especially now that the police have promised
to use deadly force.
Thanks for your question, Larry.
And thank you everyone for watching,
and for supporting China Uncensored.
If you’re not a patron yet,
join our 50-Cent Army!
Go to Patreon.com/China Uncensored and contribute.
The link is below.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.