On this episode of China Uncensored,
China's stock markets crash.
And the world trembles.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored.
I'm your host, Chris Chappell.
Last week, China's stock markets tumbled.
But not to worry!
By the end of the first day,
the government's automatic circuit breakers
kicked in to halt trading.
These circuit breakers were put in place as
a last resort.
So it's maybe not a good sign that they were
triggered twice in one week.
Once on Monday the 4th,
and again on that Thursday
when the stocks fell so much so fast that
within 30 minutes,
the circuit breakers kicked in and stopped
trading for the entire rest of the day.
Chinese markets had already fallen a shocking
11.6% since Monday's open.
"The government put in place so-called circuit
breakers.
But when those circuit breakers were triggered
last week,
people were afraid they wouldn't be able to
sell later on.
They sold more,
and that shut down trading altogether."
What he means is the circuit breakers actually
made investors panic more.
So then authorities got rid of the circuit
breakers
the very thing that was supposed to make the
markets more stable.
Oh, and the rest of the world panicked, too.
During China's terrible stock market week,
the U.S. Dow Jones and the S&P 500 indices
both fell about 5%.
London's FTSE All-World Index that covers
47 countries fell 6.1%
which is the worst weekly fall in that index's
history.
Now some of the global markets are back up
a bit since then,
but there's still a fundamental problem:
China's stock markets are crazy volatile,
and its huge swings can send shockwaves
--good or bad--
through the rest of the world's markets.
Over the past few years,
China's financial system has been integrated
more and more into the global economy.
Like with allowing foreigners to buy Chinese
stocks.
Or the IMF adding China's yuan to its basket
of important currencies.
And there's merit to this,
since China has the world's second largest
economy.
But the Chinese Communist-run government,
on the other hand, well...
they're a force to reckoned with.
"What I think the whole episode has shown,
and the volatility in particular that we have
seen,
is that the Chinese authorities are perhaps
not in charge of what's going on in the markets.
Yeah, Chinese authorities aren't supposed
to have that much control!
Most foreign analysts say China should aim
to let stocks take their course based on the
actual market conditions and the economy.
That's the healthiest thing in the long-run.
Chinese authorities artificially boosting
the stock markets last year is what got people
into this mess in the first place.
But authorities don't want to let go,
because they're concerned about the impact
that a bad stock market
or worse, a slumping economy overall
could have on social unrest.
For example, there were 1,300 strikes and
labor protests in China in 2015.
That's a lot,
and it's twice as many as the year before.
And social unrest could threaten the people
in power.
Of course, in China, the stock market doesn't
really affect the larger economy.
They're not the same thing.
But whether it's a slumping stock market or
a slumping economy,
when Chinese people feel insecure about their
financial future,
they're more likely to be upset with the ruling
Communist Party.
"How come our Chinese markets have become
like this?
What's the Communist Party done?
Even if they want to rob money,
they shouldn't be robbing money from our elderly
people!"
Yeah! They should be robbing money from someone
else! Jeez.
Anyway, China's stock market is extremely
volatile.
And authorities don't seem to have the proper
tools to smooth it out.
So what will happen?
China's stock market may recover a bit,
then go back down, then up, then down again.
We don't know by how much.
But one thing's for sure:
Whether you're in the US, Europe, or Asia,
your stock markets are going to be affected
too, 'cause...
♬ ♬ ♬ "We're all in this together."
So what do you think?
Leave your comments below,
and be sure to like this video and share it
with your friends.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell.
See you next time.