Wow, how do make such great noodles?
Shh...Ancient Chinese secret.
My sister.
Some hotshot!
Here's her ancient Chinese secret.
Opium poppy powder.
Opium poppy powder contains traces of morphine
and codeine,
for that satisfied post-hotpot feeling.
It’s guaranteed to keep you coming back
for more.
Ancient Chinese secret, huh?
Well, ok.
Ancient British secret.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I'm your host Chris Chappell.
You know, it was the ancient Greek physician
Hippocrates who famously said,
"Let food be thy medicine and medicine be
thy food."
Well, that's actually the way traditional
Chinese medicine looks at food, too.
But I don't think they had this in mind.
"35 restaurants are in trouble with the Chinese government
after adding that special something to their dishes.
The secret ingredient was ground poppy powder."
Poppy powder.
You know,
the stuff that's used to make morphine, opium
and heroin.
Now I know why Kung Fu Panda
couldn't stop eating.
Suddenly MSG doesn't seem so bad.
Five of these restaurants in China are already
being prosecuted,
while the other 30 are still under investigation.
The restaurants range from noodle shops and
dumpling joints,
to one of the most popular Beijing hotpot
chains.
Now it's unclear how effective it is in these
doses,
but some cooks believe adding ground poppy
powder can get customers hooked on their food.
Cooks? More like crooks.
I mean, can you imagine adding a potent narcotic
just to sell your product?
Anyway, I believe we have footage from inside
one of these restaurants in Chongqing.
Something with poison in it I think.
Poppies. Poppies."
Now this isn't the first time this has happened.
According to the Guardian,
a noodle seller was busted for this in 2014,
seven restaurants were closed in 2012,
and 215 restaurants were shutdown in 2004.
C'mon, people.
Don't you know that China's Food Safety Law
forbids businesses
from selling food made with "nonfood materials
or chemicals"?
Like melamine in milk.
Or heavy metals in rice.
The problem is,
according to a professor from China Agricultural
University,
"There are so many restaurants in China,
and it is very difficult to effectively inspect
every one of them
to ensure they all follow the law."
That's the funny thing,
in a country without the rule of law,
you have a hard time getting people to follow
the law.
Plus, all the government's inspection resources
are busy spying on China's 700 million Internet
users.
Now, China seems to frequently suffer from
horrendous food scandals.
Ground poppy seeds that may or may not do
anything
are really the least of the country's worries.
Toxic bean-sprouts.
Glow-in-the-dark meat.
Exploding watermelons.
Well the list really goes on.
And on.
It's even affected Western companies operating
in China.
A Shanghai-based supplier was giving unsanitary
expired chicken meat to,
among others, Starbucks, KFC, and McDonalds.
Many China social commentators say it comes
from a society pushing to get rich quick,
without really thinking of the long-term consequences.
Case in point,
basing your country's energy resources around
coal.
So what do you think?
And if you've been to China,
go to the China Uncensored Facebook page now
and leave a comment
or post a video
about the craziest food experience you've
had in mainland China.
I may even feature the best stories in one
of my videos.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell, see you next
time.