China has launched a trade war
hoping to crush Australia.
But Australia refuses to back down.
Welcome to China Uncensored. I’m Chris Chappell.
The Chinese Communist Party has been\h
ramping up a trade conflict with Australia.
It came after the Australian government called for\h
an independent investigation into the origins of\h\h
the coronavirus. And also spoke out to defend\h
Hong Kong’s autonomy and human rights in China.
So the Chinese regime has put tariffs on about $20\h\h
billion dollars worth of Australian\h
exports—like wine, seafood, and coal.
But instead of backing down, members of the\h
Australian government are fighting back.\h\h
That includes Senator for Tasmania, Eric Abetz.
But Abetz is also controversial.
He’s been accused of “racism”\h
in the Australian media.
It came after three Chinese Australians were\h
testifying before a government committee, and\h\h
Senator Abetz asked them if they were willing to\h
condemn the Chinese Communist Party dictatorship.
Is condemning the dictatorship the same\h
as being racist against Chinese people?\h\h
And what implications does this have for\h
other Australians who want to go up against\h\h
the Chinese dictatorship? Senator\h
Abetz joins me now to talk about it.
Thanks for joining me today.
My pleasure.
I know the Chinese Communist Party has been\h
launching a pretty aggressive trade war on\h\h
Australia. And to show my support I've been\h
stocking up on Vegemite. I hope that helps.
And Australian wine I hope.
Yeah. All right. So recently, let's just\h
get to the big topic. You asked Chinese\h\h
Australians testifying in the Senate to denounce\h
the Chinese Communist Party. Why did you do that?
First of all allow me to contextualize. There\h
were three separate groups of witnesses of\h\h
Chinese ethnicity. I only asked one group whether\h
they were prepared to condemn the dictatorship,\h\h
and that was on the basis that they presented to\h
the committee as thought leaders, as academia,\h\h
as think tank contributors. And there had\h
been an academic writing about these matters,\h\h
one, Professor Clive Hamilton, who basically\h
said that if you ask certain people whether\h\h
they're willing to condemn the dictatorship,\h
you'll be, one, labeled a racist and secondly,\h\h
they will offer sufficient criticism to retain\h
credibility, but they will never outright condemn.\h\h
And straight out of the textbook that is\h
exactly what occurred. Might I also say,\h\h
I have received information from the Chinese\h
diaspora in Australia that they were concerned\h\h
about the interference by the Chinese Communist\h
Party within the body politic of Australia and\h\h
within the Chinese diaspora, their community\h
organizations always wanting to be in control\h\h
and manipulating things to the benefit of\h
the Chinese Communist Party dictatorship.
And so these people were presented as thought\h
leaders, I thought it was appropriate. Can I\h\h
also indicate that one of them in their submission\h
started off by saying "Australian politics is too\h\h
wise." In other words, engaging\h
in the politics of identity and\h\h
incomplete contradistinction to what Martin Luther\h
King had pleaded with the American people, namely\h\h
that people be judged on character, on\h
values, and beliefs and not on the color\h\h
of their skin. And it was from there that we then\h
developed a discussion about values and beliefs.\h\h
And I then asked whether or not the dictatorship\h
would be condemned by these people. Keeping in\h\h
mind this is a dictatorship that has one million\h
of its own people in a concentration camp. That\h\h
imprisons people because they house Christians,\h
because they Falun Gong practitioners, because\h\h
they support the pro-democracy movement in Hong\h
Kong. This is a brutal regime that in fact engages\h\h
in organ harvesting from prisoners of conscience.\h
And it is a regime worthy of condemnation.
Well, since you knew the accusations\h
of racism were pretty much guaranteed\h\h
to follow and they did follow. How\h
have you been responding to that?
I've been responding on the basis of calling\h
out the oppressor on behalf of the oppressed,\h\h
is not racism. What is racism is trying to knock\h
out the Uyghurs from Xinjiang province where the\h\h
concentration camps and the other repressions\h
that the regime is undertaking, that is racism.\h\h
And look, it's easy to label somebody a racist and\h
then what I try to do is put you on the defensive.\h\h
My view is, do you support or are you willing\h
to condemn this brutal dictatorship? And each\h\h
and every time I simply say "I stand with the\h
oppressed." With the Uyghurs. With the house\h\h
Christians. With the Falun Gong practitioners.\h
With the pro-democracy movement. And I'm sure\h\h
none of those people would label me a\h
racist for condemning that dictatorship.
So, should all Australians denounce\h
the Chinese Communist Party?
Look, it's more for, I think thought\h
leaders to work consider whether or not\h\h
they should engage in condemnation. My view is\h
that they should because on any humanitarian\h\h
or other criteria the dictatorship needs to be\h
condemned. And we cannot in a civilized world\h\h
seek to turn a blind eye to such an\h
ugly repressive regime. The values\h\h
of the dictatorship are in complete contrast\h
to those values that we hold in Australia\h\h
and in the United States for that matter, amongst\h
the freedom loving countries of the world,\h\h
we have to take a stand. And if we don't, we\h
do a great disservice to all those people that\h\h
are currently in concentration camps and prisons\h
in the Chinese, under the Chinese dictatorship.\h\h
So yes, we should be condemning the regime,\h
calling them out and bringing them to account.
All right, let's go to the big picture right now.\h
So the Chinese Communist Party has been secretly\h\h
infiltrating Australia for years. When\h
did you first become aware of the problem?
That'd be a good question for me to think\h
about. A number of years ago, I became concerned\h\h
about the Chinese Communist Party dictatorships\h
infiltration into Australia. And I was one of\h\h
those I confessed the thought that mainland of\h
China would go the same way as Taiwan, namely\h\h
Taiwan started off as a military dictatorship\h
under Chiang Kai-shek and then slowly but surely\h\h
evolved with Western support into now a fully\h
fledged functional democracy. There were very\h\h
good signs of that as China was beginning to open\h
up, but under the current presidency Xi Jinping,\h\h
he has taken the road of liberalization backwards,\h
become more repressive and more dictatorial,\h\h
he's made himself president for life. He's at the\h
latest national Congress when they have the motion\h\h
about the unification of China, the word peaceful\h
reunification of China that was removed from the\h\h
motion. So these are the subtle changes\h
where you've got Xi Jinping saying that\h\h
Marx was the greatest thought leader ever, and\h
that he's wanted to style himself on the basis\h\h
of Joseph Stalin, the most\h
heinous of the Soviet dictators.
So when you've got all those things coming\h
out the recent years, they had to come a time\h\h
where I had to come to the conclusion, alright,\h
the liberalization that we were all hoping for\h\h
is not happening. In fact, it is regressing\h
and we have to take a stronger stand\h\h
against this dictatorship. So a few years ago,\h
I became quite concerned just as an aside under\h\h
former prime minister, Malcolm Turnbull\h
and his foreign minister, Julie Bishop,\h\h
they were proposing an extradition treaty with\h
China and I got up in the party room and I did\h\h
not make myself popular at the time. I opposed\h
the extradition treaty on the basis that there was\h\h
no equivalents, even at that time between the\h
Chinese legal system and the Australian legal\h\h
system. And therefore I oppose the expedition\h
treaty. I was vilified for the time today,\h\h
not a single person would be promoting an\h
extradition treaty with China. And I think\h\h
that is how the consciousness within Australia has\h
changed. But those of us that were at the vanguard\h\h
of calling it out were vilified at the time. But I\h
think we have now been justified in our warnings.
Well, as you say, things have really\h
turned around in Australia, as far as\h\h
viewing the Chinese Communist Party as a threat,\h
there were the foreign interference laws,\h\h
open discussion of the crimes of the\h
communist party, a call to investigate\h\h
the origin of the coronavirus. How has\h
the Chinese Communist Party responded?
Well the Chinese Communist Party dictatorship\h
has responded to us in a fairly aggressive\h\h
and a robust way. I would call it an ugly\h
way. Some of the commentary referring to\h\h
Australia as being a bit of a nuisance\h
like chewing gum on the sole of your shoe,\h\h
making all sorts of commentary along\h
those lines. And then in practical terms,\h\h
imposing a tariff on our barley, claiming\h
that our premium wines are being dumped\h\h
then our forestry products being stopped at the\h
border, rock lobster being left on the tarmac to\h\h
die and as a result not be saleable,\h
and so the consequences go on.
Norway has suffered similar issues when\h
it sort of support a dissident artist\h\h
from China and I understand the Czech Republic has\h
suffered similarly, Canada has suffered similarly.\h\h
And what this belligerent dictatorship seeks\h
to do is intimidate. And that is why in recent\h\h
times, I've called for all the freedom loving\h
countries of the world to come together and say\h\h
enough is enough Chinese dictatorship we will\h
not allow you to try to pick us off one by one,\h\h
but the freedom loving countries will stand\h
united in solidarity with each other. And I think\h\h
if we can do that, we will be successful\h
in bringing the dictatorship back into\h\h
the realms of some sort of decency and\h
being a good, decent international player.
So do you think the general population in\h
Australia know the extent of the China problem?
I think most Australians are instinctively\h
concerned. I don't think they're fully aware of\h\h
the extent. And I must say I was surprised when\h
the organization of which I'm a member AIPAC,\h\h
the International Parliamentary Alliance on China\h
helped reveal the list of all the names of people\h\h
that have been infiltrating companies, consoles,\h
embassies et cetera, of a whole lot of countries\h\h
around the world. That the extent of the operation\h
is very, very concerning. But each and every time\h\h
the Chinese dictatorship becomes more belligerent.\h
They're just sending some Navy ships down within\h\h
200 nautical miles of the Australian coastline.\h
Those sorts of things tell the Australian people\h\h
that the Chinese dictatorship, no matter what\h
they are clearly not friends of Australia,\h\h
but even more importantly are not friends of\h
the freedom loving countries of the world.
Do you think the Corona virus changed things?
I think the Corona virus issue changed things on a\h
number of fronts. One, Australia's calling for an\h\h
international investigation. So the of\h
the dictatorship focused on Australia,\h\h
and then they've come out with all the quite\h
bizarre assertions. One it started in Italy,\h\h
then it started in the United States, then\h
it came into China via Australian beef,\h\h
yet every day, there's a new story.\h
And the idea that it doesn't match with\h\h
other stories is of no consequence,\h
because if you don't have a free press,\h\h
your president and other people aren't\h
going to be questioned about these things.
The other thing that I think concerns a lot\h
of Australians and in the people right around\h\h
the world is how the dictatorship was able\h
to initially manipulate the world health\h\h
organization and Dr. Tedros to put out the\h
Shanghai Beijing propaganda in relation to\h\h
the coronavirus. And first of all, we were\h
told it was not communicable between people,\h\h
that it was racists that closed down borders.\h
And now you ask where on earth did all this\h\h
misinformation come from, its all traceable back\h
to the Chinese dictatorship they were in denial\h\h
and because of the denial and the propaganda\h
being swallowed by the world health organization,\h\h
we now have a crisis around the world\h
a lot, lot worse than it need be. And I\h\h
think that has opened the eyes of many people\h
within Australia, but all around the world\h\h
to the sort of behaviors and manipulations\h
that the Chinese dictatorship engage in.
Now I know there's been a lot of pushback from\h
the Australian business community about the\h\h
economic damage of going toe to toe with\h
the Chinese regime. Why do you think that\h\h
is? And do you think it will\h
be enough to stop the momentum?
Look, money talks and some people\h
are more concerned about the dollars.\h\h
I'm very pleased that the Australian\h
prime minister, Scott Morrison\h\h
continually talks about Australian values and\h
beliefs, and that our ethics are not for sale.\h\h
And so if, because we stand for human rights,\h
those we are willing to condemn, 1 million\h\h
citizens being in a concentration camp because we\h
want a full international investigation of COVID.\h\h
If that has economic consequences for us as a\h
payback, then that is a matter of great regret.\h\h
But I think the Australian people are up to it.\h
And I detect that other countries in the world\h\h
will say, well, if they don't want your wine,\h
we'll buy it. I know India is very interested in\h\h
our coal and let's be very clear what the Chinese\h
dictatorship is doing with these trade barriers\h\h
against Australian products at the moment, they\h
are cutting off the nose to spite the face,\h\h
because the only basis on which countries\h
trade with each other is for mutual benefit.
So the Chinese buy our products because of\h
the quality of the product, reliability of\h\h
supply and the affordability. It's not to do us a\h
favor that's for those three reasons. So if they\h\h
all of a sudden stop seeking our products, they\h
are denying their own population, the benefit\h\h
of high quality, reliable supply and affordable\h
prices. And so this is what a dictatorship does,\h\h
becomes belligerent and is willing\h
to do things that punish others\h\h
whilst also punishing their own population.\h
So this is a game that they're playing, which\h\h
ultimately will test the resolve of the Australian\h
people and the Australian government. But I trust\h\h
we are up to it because there are certain values\h
and principles that simply are not for sale.
Now, if the United States were to no longer\h\h
take a hard line on China, do you\h
think Australia could go it alone?
If the freedom loving countries of the world\h
were to desert Australia and United States\h\h
clearly would be a major player in that,\h
that would be a matter of great concern,\h\h
but I cannot see that occurring under president\h
Biden or president Trump. say will be president\h\h
Biden, I don't want to get into that debate but\h
irrespective of the party or the person that might\h\h
be leading the United States, the friendship and\h
the unity between our two countries has always\h\h
been exceptionally strong. And might I add, from\h
the Australian perspective, that has been the case\h\h
irrespective of it being a labor government,\h
or as we currently have a liberal government.
And what do you think the other democratic\h
countries of the world can learn from the\h\h
situation Australia has found itself\h
in with the Chinese Communist Party.
What it shows is that if you take a principled\h
stand, the Chinese dictatorship will seek to\h\h
punish you. And that's a test of resolve. And\h
therefore, if you are a freedom loving country\h\h
of the world, that's not currently being punished\h
by China, then you should stand in solidarity\h\h
because at the end of the day, China cannot punish\h
each and every one of the freedom loving countries\h\h
of the world. But what it does show is that\h
there are consequences from this dictatorship\h\h
if you take a principled ethical stand.\h
What it also shows is how unprincipled\h\h
and how unethical the communist dictatorship\h
in China is. And basically if you let Australia\h\h
loose and cut us loose, guess what you'll\h
be next. And that is why it makes good sense\h\h
for every single country that believes in\h
freedoms, that believes in human rights,\h\h
that believes in the rule of law to stick\h
together, to stand in solidarity and say,\h\h
if you pick on Australia, you're picking on\h
Norway, you're picking on the United States,\h\h
you're picking on New Zealand, you're\h
picking on India, you're picking on Japan.\h\h
And if that's the case, then clearly China will\h
need to back off. And that is my hope and prayer.
Well, thank you so much for joining me today.\h
I can't wait till I can go back to Australia.
A pleasure, and it would be a\h
delight to welcome you to Australia.
Thank you, take care.
Great. Thank you.
And thank you for watching. And thanks heaps\h
to all the Aussies out there for sticking it\h\h
out as your government faces blowback from\h
standing up to the Chinese Communist Party.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.\h
Thanks for watching China Uncensored.