On this episode of China Uncensored,
No, guys, it's a silent invasion.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored, I'm your host, Chris Chappell.
It's one of the most controversial books of
the year:
Silent Invasion by Professor Clive Hamilton.
It details how the Chinese Communist Party
is infiltrating Australian society and politics.
I sat down with Mr. Hamilton to discuss why
he refuses to be silent.
About this invasion.
Thank you for joining us today, Professor
Hamilton.
It's a pleasure to be here.
So, In Silent Invasion,
you talk about dark money, spies,
and gullible politicians.
Which should we be most terrified of?
Well, it's a constellation.
I'm sorry.
I wish I could pick out one,
but this is the thing about the CCP's influence
operations in Australia.
As one intelligence official described it
to me,
they call it a "Full Court Press."
I'm sure your American listeners will understand
that basketball term.
I had to look it up.
It means an all-out offensive
and so what I describe in my book
is the whole series of operations whereby
the CCP and its agents have influence in Australia
and, from China, have attempted to influence
at times with great success all of Australia's
major institutions, from politics
to media to business nd of course,
into universities.
Yeah.
Well, I really appreciate
the basketball reference.
It sounds like the communist party really
scored a touchdown.
So, when you're doing
the research for the book,
was there anything that surprised you?
I was constantly surprised...
No.
Nothing is sacred.
No area of Australian society, politics
or culture is free from influence
if there is an opportunity there.
So, as you say, that was one of the
shocking elements that I came across,
the way in which ...
And I don't want to exaggerate this.
My understanding is that this has only happened
in a small way so far, but the way in which
agents
of the CCP have made themselves present in
the
congregations of Chinese Christian churches
in
Australia and of course, the CCP is officially
an
atheist organization, so the infiltration
is certainly not because the CCP feels as
though
it needs to inject a spiritual element into
its ideology.
Is the Communist Party's infiltration targeting
any particular political party?
They're quite eclectic in their political
tastes.
They'll infiltrate anything that they can.
What impact do you hope Silent Invasion will
have?
I wrote the book in order to wake up Australians
to what is happening, to give them the full
picture
of the nature of these operations
and more particularly why.
Why is the CCP targeting Australia in this
way?
So, really, it's to bring about social change,
political change, in response to what I see,
as many others do, as a really big problem
in Australia.
How does this affect your average Australian
who might be more concerned about Rugby
or Vegemite or whatever the average Australian
is into these days?
when I've been going around the country giving
talks,
chatting to people about the book,
is that it seems to me that a very large
number of Australians had a kind of sense
that there was something wrong,
that they'd picked up something in the newspapers
or in the local community about some kind
of
intrusion from the CCP or a major Chinese
corporation
and it worried them.
There's a kind of unease about what's been
happening and therefore,
many non-Chinese-Australians and many
Chinese-Australians have seized upon the book
as a way of explaining more broadly
what has been happening,
this kind of niggling sense that they've had
that
there's something odd going on
that's made them feel uneasy.
What was your reaction when your
publisher told you they weren't going to publish
Silent Invasion?
Were you like,
"Wow.
This is a great story for my book"?
I was deeply shocked.
I've worked with for many, many years.
They have been extremely enthusiastic
about the book right up to the day before
I got the phone call and said,
"We're pulling the plug."
And they said subsequently in the phone call
and then in writing subsequently that they
did
because they were afraid of retaliation
from Beijing and I thought,
"It's a kind of brilliant but unwelcome
vindication of the essential argument of my
book."
So, it really worked out for you.
it certainly drew a huge amount of publicity
to the book and suddenly,
publication of my book became a free speech
issue.
Mind you, it's not a pleasant thing
to spend weeks and weeks feeling,
with good reason,
that the state security apparatus in Beijing
is keeping a very close eye on you.
I mean, am I at any risk,
being here with you right now?
Well, we did have a spy sitting outside of
this building
who was carrying with her what,
I was subsequently told,
was probably a sniffer,
which is a device that looked like a mobile
phone,
but in fact is a quite sophisticated electronic
device
that can pick up all wifi and mobile telephone
communication inside a building.
That sounds fun, to be getting that kind of
attention.
Well, it does unsettle one and after a while,
you do start to take notice of things around
you
that normally you wouldn't bother about...
There's no doubt, based on a vast and from
security
experts and the Australian Federal Police,
that the Chinese authorities in Australia
are
collecting a dossier on me.
I've been the subject of cyber intrusions.
I've been subjected to a really intense campaign
of vilification
Were you surprised by the controversy the
book generated?
You know, I anticipated it,
but in the abstract.
You know, you anticipate something.
I think this is going to be very controversial.
I think I'm going to be accused of racism
and anti-China xenophobia,
but when it actually happened,
it kind of comes on you with an intensity
and an
emotional place that is really quite hard
to take.
You need to have the skin of a rhino
to not want to crawl into a hole and stay
there.
The Chinese Embassy has said,
"Critics of the Chinese Communist Party
are filled with a Cold-War mentality
and anti-China hysteria and paranoia.
Which of those best describes you?"
Well, you know, I grew up in the cold war,
so may some of it's still hanging around me
somewhere,
but you know, the key point which many of
your
listeners understand is that whenever there's
any
criticism of the communist party, the communist
propaganda efforts work very hard to persuade
the
public that, in fact, it's the Chinese people
who are
under attack.
It's the only way it can really defend
itself from this kind of criticisms.
Is racism a real, potential problem?
On the question of whether the book will stimulate
racist elements in our society, anti-China
feeling ...
That was my concern from Day One
I took every measure I could as I researched
and wrote the book to avoid the possibility
that the book could lend any credibility
to those anti-China, racist elements
on the fringe of our society.
I consulted with people in the Chinese-Australian
community and reflected their views in the
book
and I think I do that quite effectively.
So, you really have to work quite hard to
draw
out of the book anything that can be used
to defend
the idea that the book is racist or stimulates
racism.
Some people have worked very hard at drawing
that conclusion from the book.
Some of them, I've been quite surprised.
I thought, "Why are you doing that?"
So, one of the fascinating things that
I've learned in the last four weeks
is how deeply entrenched in some segments
of the political left is the idea that any
criticism
of the communist party is a criticism of Chinese
people
and therefore, we must defend this oppressed
minority.
Give me a break.
I mean, Chinese-Australians that I spoke to,
many of them, don't feel that way.
You, defenders of multiculturalism,
should go and talk to them,
rather than community leaders who actually
represented United Front organizations
that dance to the Communist Party's tune.
You obviously have a lot of connections
in the Chinese-Australian community.
What was their reaction to your book?
Well, they welcomed it when I made contact
with them initially and started to talk to
them.
We found that last week that a group of Chinese-Australians
was very, very eager to have a launch
in Sydney for the book and I was really
blown away by the number of Chinese-Australians
that were packed in that room in Parliament
House in Sydney
and gave the book such an extraordinary,
enthusiastic launch off into the world.
Why do you think that was?
Well, I think that for the last ten to twenty
years,
many Chinese-Australians who are critical
of the Communist Party and say,
"We came to Australia to escape from
the clutches of the Communist party,
and now they're following me,"
Their voices have been silenced.
They've been marginalized.
They've been kicked out of the public debate
and the mainstream media and politicians
have been talking to community leaders,
who are, generally,
one United Front organizations.
So, many Chinese-Australians have been extremely
grateful
that finally someone in the mainstream
has been taking their complaints seriously
and has written a book about it.
And most important question:
how does this affect America?
Well, it has a huge implication for the United
States
and that is because the authorities in the
United States
from Congress to the CIA, FBI,
to think tanks inside the Beltway
that take notice of China to a whole lot of
scholars
across the country,
are watching very, very closely
what is happening in the Australian parliament,
to the debate that we've been discussing today,
with a view to copying the ways in which
Australian governments and Australian society
more broadly pushes back against Beijing's
attempts
to interfere with, influence, guide, and ultimately
control what happens in this country.
in your book it says, "The communist party
is using
democracy to destroy democracy."
What can liberal democracies do to protect
ourselves
and our freedoms?
Well, I think liberal democracies
need to muscle up.
I mean, here is a serious threat
to the foundational values of liberal democracy
led by very powerful economic incentives
coming from the Peoples' Republic of China
and I think we in the liberal democracies
need to
make a really fundamental decision,
one that we haven't been forced to do ...
I'm about to say, "Ever," but certainly
for many decades.
And that is to decide: how much is our freedom
worth?
Thank you for joining us today, Professor
Hamilton.
I've enjoyed it.
Great.
And I would highly recommend
picking up a copy of Silent Invasion.
I've read it myself and you can find a link
to
how you can purchase it in the description
below.
China Uncensored is mainly supported
by contributions from viewers like you.
Our trip here to Australia was funded
not by the CIA or Taiwan--
but by our amazing supporters on Patreon.
Click here to visit our website on Patreon.com
and learn how you can support the show.