A nuclear War with China
Is a “real possibility”
A brazen new attack by Chinese hackers
And a Chinese government plan to boost “masculinity”
That and more on this week’s China news
headlines
Welcome to China Uncensored, I’m Chris Chappell.
We are in a Cold War with the Chinese Communist
Party.\h
And what’s a cold war without the threat
of nuclear annihilation?
A nuclear war with China is a “real possibility”.
That’s according to the head of U.S. Strategic
Command Admiral Charles Richard.
He wrote his rather grim summary in this month’s
issue of "Proceedings," the U.S. Naval Institute’s
monthly magazine.
“There is a real possibility that a regional
crisis with Russia or China could escalate
quickly to a conflict involving nuclear weapons,
if they perceived a conventional loss would
threaten the regime or state.”
Sort of the Andross model.
If I go down, I’m taking you with me.
“Consequently, the U.S. military must shift
its principal assumption from ‘nuclear employment
is not possible’ to ‘nuclear employment
is a very real possibility.’”
Which is why I’m happy to announce a new
company I’m starting called Vault-Tec Industries!
We’ll build for you the absolute highest
quality fallout shelters, guaranteed not to
be secret horrific sociological experiments!
But you shouldn’t worry too much about Cold
War 2.
Because first you should worry about proxy
wars!
Once again, China has sent military planes
into Taiwan’s airspace.
But this time, a US military aircraft joined
as well.
And so China took the opportunity to remind
everyone that Taiwan independence means war.
Obviously, Taiwan is already an independent
country.
China’s not flying provocative warplanes
into their own airspace.
But, uh, let’s not tell them that.\h\h
So how will the Biden Administration handle
an increasingly aggressive Chinese Communist
Party?
A State Department spokesman says Biden wants
to be lockstep with America’s allies on
China.\h
Hopefully the spokesman is referring to being
lockstep with Taiwan on defense—not lockstep
with our European allies on their China investment
deal.
Which brings us to Gina Raimondo.
She’s Biden’s pick for Commerce Secretary.
She’s spoken about protecting US telecom
networks from Chinese companies.
But in her nomination speech, she didn’t
say whether or not the Biden administration
would keep Chinese telecom Huawei on a blacklist.
The US has been calling Huawei a national
security threat since the Obama Administration.
But the Trump Administration went further
by actually putting Huawei on a trade blacklist.
Now, House Republicans, led by Michael McCaul,
the top Republican on the House Foreign Affairs
Committee, want to delay Raimondo’s confirmation,
until the administration makes its Huawei
stance clear.\h
“The fact that the Biden Administration
has still refused to commit to keeping Huawei
on the Department of Commerce’s Entity List
is incredibly alarming and dangerous.”
So they want to, “place a hold on Ms. Raimondo’s
confirmation until the Biden Administration
clarifies their intentions for Huawei and
on export control policies for a country that
is carrying out genocide and threatening our
national security.”
It is kind of hard to say I really want to
do business with a country that’s committing
genocide.
Of course, not all countries have problems
doing business with those committing genocide.
Like Myanmar!
I’ll tell you more after the break.
Welcome back.
Myanmar has billions of dollars of investment
deals going with the Chinese Communist regime.
Myanmar also had a military coup this week.\h
China has blocked the UN from condemning the
coup.
And if the US isn’t careful, it could push
Myanmar closer to China
For more on the Myanmar Coup, and what it
means for the Biden Administration’s attempts
to deal with China, check out yesterday’s
episode on America Uncovered.
According to Reuters, Chinese hackers may
have exploited a bug in SolarWinds software
to spy on a US federal payroll agency.
Don’t worry.
“The software flaw exploited by the suspected
Chinese group is separate from the one the
United States has accused Russian government
operatives of using,” to compromise sensitive
federal agencies.
Is that supposed to make me feel better?
Two hostile authoritarian regimes were able
to separately break into SolarWinds?
I’d actually feel better if they had to
work together to crack it.\h
Like some kind of terrible sequel to Hackers
where Russia is played by Steven Seagal and
China is played by Jackie Chan.
Now to Hong Kong refugees.
Which is now pretty much anyone in Hong Kong
looking to escape the long arm of Beijing.\h
The new Secretary of State Anthony Blinken
has suggested the US could give them sanctuary.
In an interview with MSNBC, Blinken said,
“We see people who are, again, in Hong Kong
standing up for their own rights, the rights
that they felt were guaranteed to them.\h
And if… they’re the victims of repression
from Chinese authorities, we should do something
to give them haven.”
Back in December, there was a bill that would
grant temporary refuge to Hong Kongers.
It unanimously passed in the House, but was
blocked in the Senate by...Ted Cruz.
He worried there weren’t safeguards in place
to prevent Chinese spies from sneaking in
as well.
Meanwhile, the UK is offering Hong Kong residents
a route to citizenship.
Hong Kong residents can apply for a British
National Overseas passport, or BNO.
In response, China said it would no longer
recognize BNOs.
Speaking of the UK, the UK has revoked the
license of Chinese state-owned broadcaster
CGTN, which is the English version of China
Central Television.
It comes after the media regulator Ofcom “concluded
that the news channel was ultimately controlled
by the ruling Communist Party of China.”
I could have told them that years ago.
But better late than never.
It also comes after Ofcom ruled that “CGTN
repeatedly breached impartiality standards
with its coverage of protests last year in
Hong Kong.”
And it *also* comes after a complaint by Peter
Humphrey, a UK citizen who was forced to give
a confession while in a Chinese prison.
CGTN then broadcast that forced confession
on its channel in the UK, which was illegal.
We had Humphrey on our podcast a few months
ago.
Check that out for more.
You may remember in a recent episode I talked
about Lai Xiaomin, China’s most corrupt
official.
He was caught with 3 metric tons of cash that
came from bribes, as well as 100 mistresses.
And now, he has been executed.
For the bribes.
Not for the mistresses.
Jack Ma—one of China’s richest men.
He mysteriously disappeared back in October,
and reappeared in January.
But his troubles are just beginning.
First, Chinese state-run media left his name
off a list of entrepreneurial leaders.
And now his company Ant Group is being forcibly
restructured by Chinese regulators.
Those are the same regulators Ma criticized
back in October.
Before disappearing for months.
And the increased pressure is now causing
Chinese tech companies to turn on each other.
Two of China’s biggest tech companies are
in a lawsuit.
Douyin the company that owns TikTok, is suing
Tencent as the government launches an antitrust
crackdown on China’s tech industry.
China is also stockpiling computer chips in
response to a US ban.
And in the midst of all this, Apple is starting
to move production out of China.
I do hope the iPhone 13 comes with less slave
labor.
Also this week, I want to give a big thank
you to Australian Senator Eric Abetz for mentioning
China Uncensored in the Australian Parliament
after we had him on the show last month.
“China Uncensored, a YouTube program from
the United States.”
Also, I guess, thank you for your many years
of courageously standing up to the CCP.
But mainly, thank you for name dropping China
Uncensored in Parliament.
Does this mean that China Uncensored is now
in the official parliamentary record?\h
Despite all the chaos in the world, the Chinese
Communist Party hasn’t forgotten its core
mission: persecuting Chinese people.
\h
In the past three years, 50 people have been
sent to jail for using Twitter.
But there are bigger problems.
Chinese millennials aren’t getting married.
So obviously, the solution is boosting masculinity
with PE classes!
Surely this won’t become some insane new
government policy that overzealous local officials
take to an extreme.
But China’s top advisory body, the CPPCC,
is worried.
They say “Boys...have become too delicate,
timid and effeminate after being schooled
mostly by women teachers.”
And so, “Some affluent parents, worried
that their sons are too fragile, are sending
them to private boot camps that promise to
turn them into ‘real’ men through army-style
drills.”
In other words, a new generation of soldiers
for the US China Cold War.
And we end where we began.
And now it’s time for me to answer a question
from one of you, a fan who supports China
Uncensored through the crowd funding website
Patreon!
Tommy Hoover asks, “Yall should play socialism
monopoly again..
It was hilarious we watched the whole thing
lol”
Ah, Tommy is talking about a recent episode
of our podcast, China Unscripted.
We play the very real game—Monopoly Socialism.
It was a lot of fun for us.
But this reminds me of an idea I had for a
new show, one where Matt, Shelley, and I talk
about news and politics while playing through
video games.
It could be a fun way to get people into some
topics that might be a little dry or too serious
on their own.
But I’d love to hear what you think about
that\h idea.
Does that sound like a show you’d watch?
Let me know in the comments below.
Thanks for your question Tommy.
And thank you for watching.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.