bjbj,(,( Yzqf Title: An Invitation to Tea
(I m going to kill you MWHAHAHA!) Oh, hi.
I didn t see you come in. Would you like some
tea? I have an extra cup right here. Logo
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored. I m Chris
Chappell. So, if you re a Chinese dissident,
and you get an invitation to tea by authorities,
you can be pretty sure there s not going to
be much tea involved. s sort of like when
Chinese police burst into the homes of activists
in the middle of the night to suggest they
go on a vacation, and get out of Beijing for
a couple of days during politically sensitive
events. Last week there were massive protests
outside the Southern Weekly, a Chinese newspaper
that actually isn t state-run. The paper had
tried to run an article calling for a constitutional
government, but then the local propaganda
chief Tuo Zhen took it upon himself to make
a slight edit. He rewrote it to praise the
CCP. And gosh, China must really be changing
because usually large protests are met with
brutality. But this time, authorities just
invited everyone to tea! I mean, look at how
excited they are! It looks like they just
can t wait to get into that unmarked van.
And here s a student being taken off for tea
after his interview with Second German Broadcast
Network. Look, how nice! They re carrying
him so he doesn t have to walk. It must have
been quite the tea party because they even
invited celebrities. Taiwanese singer Annie
Yi also spoke out on behalf of Southern Weekly,
and someone must have been listening because
she later said on her Weibo, which is like
a Chinese Twitter, that authorities also invited
her to drink tea. That was before a bunch
of her Weibo posts were mysteriously taken
down. In fact, at least 20 people have been
invited to drink tea with authorities in relation
to the Southern Weekly incident alone, including
famous Beijing entrepreneur Li Kaifu and property
developer Ren Zhiqiang. Tea drinking began
in China 4,000 years ago, and plays a huge
role in Chinese culture. That s probably why
authorities can t get enough tea parties.
In fact, to help them out, they ve recently
made a new law that Internet providers and
social media sites have to register the real
names of users. That way, if someone posts
something critical of the government, it s
even easier to invite them to tea and discuss
their differences over tea. How civilized.
h`jo h&Ab gdQ6 [Content_Types].xml #!MB ;c=1
_rels/.rels theme/theme/themeManager.xml sQ\}#
theme/theme/theme1.xml G$$DA : BR \{i5@R V*[_X
,l\Y Ssd+r] 5\|E Vky- V4Ej 6NGU s?^V *<")QH
@\&> 7;wP EBU` 5VD GGHPXNT,
/M,W m2iU [[v _Xtl theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.rels
6?$Q K(M&$R(.1 [Content_Types].xmlPK _rels/.relsPK
theme/theme/themeManager.xmlPK theme/theme/theme1.xmlPK
theme/theme/_rels/themeManager.xml.relsPK
<a:clrMap xmlns:a="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/drawingml/2006/main"
bg1="lt1" tx1="dk1" bg2="lt2" tx2="dk2" accent1="accent1"
accent2="accent2" accent3="accent3" accent4="accent4"
accent5="accent5" accent6="accent6" hlink="hlink"
folHlink="folHlink"/> Chris Normal.dotm Chris
Microsoft Macintosh Word PICT# o\{o\{w kZo\{s
o\{kZw o\{kZkZ o\{o\{w g9g9Z g9kZg9c o\{kZg9s o\{kZs
g9kZ^ g9g9V g9g9o\{o\{g9s g9kZkZg9o\{g9kZkZ Bg9R
g9g9V g9g9 o\{o\{g9g9c g9kZg9g9o\{g9g9c g9g9kZc
g9g9s kZo\{g9kZg9 o\{g9Z o\{o\{s o\{o\{s kZo\{o\
kZg9o\{g9c g9o\{c g9o\{c kZg9s !kZV kZkZg9c g9g9Z
g9kZZ o\{g9Z g9kZc kZg9c g9g9 kZg9kZc g9kZ
o\{o\{s "o\{c o\{kZg9o\{kZw kZo\{o\{kZs kZo\{o\{w g9kZo\{s
o\{o\{kZw kZg9s g9g9s g9g9c g9g9s g9g9kZs kZo\{kZg9s
g9g9 g9o\{g9c g9kZ kZg9kZkZc g9g9Z kZkZg9c
o\{kZw o\{o\{kZo\{o\{kZo\{kZo\{g9s o\{kZo\{kZ^ o\{+s
kZg9o\{w o\{o\{w kZo\{o\{c o\{kZo\{kZg9w o\{kZkZg9o\{w
kZo\{s o\{kZZ g9kZw g9o\{g9o\{c g9kZo\{g9s kZg9g9kZs
o\{g9o\{s g9kZs o\{kZg9kZkZo\{c g9o\{kZo\{c g9g9c
kZg9\{ CkZc o\{g9^ o\{o\{Z kZg9Z kZNsV kZg9^ kZkZo\{kZkZo\{g9kZo\{c
kZkZo\{s kZo\{o\{kZo\{Z o\{g9kZw g9o\{kZo\{g9 kZ
o\{o\{s kZo\{o\{^ o\{kZs kZkZo\{kZo\{o\{g9kZkZs o\{kZs
kZg9o\{kZkZZ g9g9s kZg9kZs kZo\{kZc o\{o\{kZg9s
o\{g9g9kZo\{kZw o\{g9g9^ kZo\{g9g9o\{o\{s g9kZc
kZg9w g9o\{Z kZg9o\{kZo\{g9s kZo\{s g9g9Z ,g9^
kZg9kZZ o\{o\{s o\{g9s o\{o\{w g9kZg9o\{ g9kZ o\{o\{s
kZo\{s o\{o\{s g9<s kZkZs g9kZo\{c g9kZg9kZs g9g9s
o\{kZg9c g9o\{o\{^ kZg9g9^ @g9Z kZkZV kZo\{s kZkZs
o\{kZ o\{o\{w o\{g9o\{s g9g9kZs kZg9c g9g9s kZg9o\{c
kZo\{ o\{o\
g9kZg9g9V kZo\{c g9kZkZg9s g9g9^ Nsg9Z g9kZg9^
o\{g9 .g9o\{kZo\{c o\{g9kZkZw kZkZc o\{o\{kZs o\{kZo\{w
kZo\{o\{kZo\{g9o\{o\{s kZg9o\{kZw o\{kZo\{w kZo\{kZs
g9kZ kZg9kZg9 o\{g9kZs o\{g9kZ\{ o\{o\{kZg9kZg9kZ^
g9o\{s g9kZg9o\{o\{ 1g9R Nso\{ g9kZc g9g9Z g9o\
kZkZg9c .g9g9Z o\{g9R g9g9Z o\{o\{w o\{o\{ o\{g9g9
kZo\{g9g9Z kZg9V g9g9kZ^ g9kZs kZg9g9s kZg9s
kZg9kZg9kZo\{kZ o\{o\{w o\{o\{kZo\{o\{s o\{kZ\{ o\{kZ
!o\{o\{w o\{g9s o\{o\{c o\{o\{s o\{g9s g9kZs o\{g9o\{s
o\{kZs o\{g9c g90kZZ g9g9w o\{o\{c g9g9o\{c o\{g9o\{c
kZkZo\{g9c g9kZc kZo\{ g9g9Z o\{kZZ 0g9g9R o\{o\{Z
g9kZg9o\{g9g9c g9g9s g9g9Z o\{o\{ Title wl\{qf
Microsoft Word 97-2004 Document NB6W Word.Document.8