A huge protest in Hong Kong
Police refused to let them march.
But do you think they listened?
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
I’ve got some sad news for the Chinese Communist
Party:
The people of Hong Kong still don’t want
to be with you.
It’s been 71 days since a million Hong Kongers
took to the streets in protest over an extradition
bill.
That bill would have let the Hong Kong government
send people to China for trial,
which is something people were not thrilled
about.
And two months later,
public anger is only growing stronger.
Yesterday, an estimated 1.7 million people
took to the streets.
Well, technically, they took to Victoria Park,
because the police refused to give people
a permit
to actually march on the streets this time.
But you can’t fit 1.7 million people in
Victoria Park.
So people ended up on the streets anyway.
Oh, and it was raining.
Heavily.
That did not stop them.
Fortunately, the umbrella has been
an important symbol of the protest movement.
Good thing their symbol isn’t white shirts.
The Hong Kong government was not happy about
Sunday’s gathering.
As I said, police had refused to issue a permit
to march,
which forced people into the park.
But the park was too small,
so that forced people onto the streets.
So the government issued this press release,
criticizing the participants for occupying
“a number of thoroughfares on Hong Kong
Island,
seriously affecting traffic and causing
much inconvenience to the community.”
Hmm... “causing much inconvenience to the
community”?
1.7 million people—that is the community.
That’s almost a quarter of Hong Kong.
And you know what’s really
“causing much inconvenience to the community”?
Taking away people’s freedom and the rule
of law.
Or, what the government has been doing
over the past month or so:
labeling protesters as rioters,
so they can sentence them to up to 10 years
in prison.
Yeah, 10 years in prison—that’s inconvenient.
That’s why one of the protesters’ demands
is for the Hong Kong government
to retract the labeling of protests as “riots.”
They also demand the release of all protesters
who’ve been arrested,
the creation of an independent council
to investigate police brutality,
and universal suffrage for Hong Kong.
Oh, and they want that China extradition bill
to be fully and permanently withdrawn.
And really, if the Hong Kong government
had just withdrawn the extradition bill
after a million people marched on the streets,
this whole thing would have been resolved.
There would have been 1 day of protests
instead of more than 70.
There would be no need for tear gas,
no police brutality,
and none of that so-called “inconvenience
to the community.”
But really, this fundamentally comes down
to
the Chinese Communist Party itself.
Ultimately, the Party oversees Hong Kong.
And they won’t back down.
Ever.
Because they think that military and economic
strength
can solve any problem.
And *that* is their biggest weakness.
And it sure doesn’t help with pro-Communist
Party people
interrupt pro-Hong Kong protests around the
world.
Like this one in Sydney.
“I love China!”
Or in Vancouver, where a Chinese guy driving
his Ferrari
yelled at the dumb hong Kongers for being
too poor.
Or this protest sign in London, where the
message is,
I guess, “*We* lick the CCP’s butt, so
why don’t *you*?”
I mean surely, if Chinese people around the
world act like this,
Hong Kongers will see how great the Communist
Party is,
and fall in line.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Before I go, I’ll answer a question from
one of you—
a fan who supports the show by contributing
a dollar or more.
Servando asks:
“What if Hong Kong became independent
to form a democratic people’s party
and ask the rest of China to join them!?
Communism will never work well for anyone.”
Good question, Servando.
The thing is, Hong Kong can no longer get
independence,
no matter what political parties they form.
Legally, they have no choice but to remain
part of the People’s Republic of China.
Why?
The reason dates back to an extremely sneaky
thing
the Chinese Communist Party did in the UN
in 1975...
to trap Hong Kong forever.
To learn more, I suggest you watch my episode
“Why Did the British Give Hong Kong to China?”
Hint—
they didn’t have much of a choice.
Thanks for your question, Servando.
And thank you for watching!
And especially thanks to the several thousand
of you on Patreon
who support us with a dollar or more per episode.
With your contributions,
we could not keep making this show.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.