On this episode of China Uncensored,
does China fear a revolting army?
I mean,
I don’t think they’re all that revolting...
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Protesters sure are a pain.
Unless you’re the Chinese Communist Party.
Then protesters are easily dealt with.
Except of course when the protesters are military
veterans.
Chanting unity is strength,
they had demanded better government support
for military retirees.
There have been other protests by army veterans,
but it’s believed this was the biggest,
lasting 12 hours.
Yes,
over 1,000 People’s Liberation Army veterans
lined up outside the Chinese Ministry of National
Defense in Beijing—
and were quickly surrounded by police and
busses
so no one had to see.
And believe me folks,
when protesting in the capital
of one of the most repressive regimes on Earth,
nothing beats a Pepsi!
Eventually they were all bussed away.
And any mention of the protest on Chinese
social media
was censored.
According to an activist interviewed by AP,
“veterans have staged more than 50 protests
this year alone.”
And this is a problem for the Chinese Communist
Party.
Because it’s in some ways harder to crack
down on veterans
than other groups.
Yes,
veterans can be better organized
and they come equipped with a nationwide network
of comrades-in-arms.
But there’s also the political risk.
The Communist Party may have been able to
convince the nation
that Falun Gong,
a peaceful meditation practice with zero political
aspirations,
was a dangerous group out to destroy China.
It’s a little trickier to do that with your
own troops
We need to crack down on veterans because...
they served our country!
So why are veterans protesting so much in
China?
I mean,
don’t soldiers in China have to swear an
oath
to “follow the leadership of the Communist
Party of China?”
Well, here’s one reason.
Last September,
the Chinese Communist Party held a huge military
parade,
to celebrate how they defeated the Japanese
in World War II.
They did not.
That was a lie.
But during the parade,
soldiers got to line up in rank and file,
new shiny missiles were shown off,
and tanks rolled down the streets of Beijing,
and no students got crushed!
But troops may have realized something was
amiss
when Chinese Leader Xi Jinping gave his speech
at the war parade,
and mentioned “peace” 17 times.
Because what he was trying to tell the troops
was…
“You’re fired.”
I mean,
why do you need so many troops when China
will
“advance the noble cause of global peace
and development,”
“We Chinese love peace,”
and
“In the interest of peace,
China will remain committed to peaceful development?”
And that was all in like two paragraphs.
Xi Jinping wasn’t out to give peace of mind.
He was out to give a piece of his mind—
with massive layoffs.
At the parade,
Xi announced 300,000 military layoffs,
an entire 13% of troops,
to be completed by the end of 2017.
Those are the biggest layoffs to hit the Chinese
military
since 1997,
when half a million soldiers were fired.
Or as the Party calls it,
“demobilized.”
But the real reason for the layoffs
is not that the Communist Party is peace-loving,
but rather, China’s military has grown up.
Literally, actually,
soldiers can’t fit into the old tanks.
But you see,
in the good old days,
you could fight a war
by just throwing wave after wave of your own
men
at the enemy.
Mao even famously said,
“China has a population of 600 million;
even if half of them are killed,
there are still 300 million people left.”
And now that the population has doubled...
It’s the Zap Brannigan strategy
Hit the like button if you get it.
But current Chinese leader Xi Jinping
wants to modernize the military
by spending less on people,
and more on high tech weaponry,
particularly for the air force and navy.
Plus now they want people who have college
educations.
And that’s bad news for the older Chinese
soldiers,
many of whom only went to middle school or
high school.
That makes them more likely to be "demobilized"
into retirement.
There are about 6 million People’s Liberation
Army veterans on welfare.
But China is one of the few major countries
that has
no centralized government department or civic
group
handling veterans affairs.
So it falls to cash-strapped local governments
to give veterans pensions,
healthcare, guaranteed jobs--
all the things the Party promised them.
Could this possibly lead to abuse and corruption?
“We’ve gotten nothing since retiring from
service:
no pensions, no social security.”
That’s according to one of the protesters
interviewed by the Wall Street Journal.
Apparently,
it’s also common for local officials to
pocket
a portion of veterans’ stipends,
which ranks somewhere in between taking candy
from a baby
and stealing old ladies’ purses.
Thirty years ago,
Chinese veterans would just be given jobs
in state-run enterprises.
But a lot of those have shut down.
And now with a slowing economy...
and a tightening job market...
...things aren’t looking good for China’s
veterans.
As one of last week’s protesters told AP,
some veterans living in the countryside are
provided
with as little as $60 a month.
Which,
if you’ve seen my recent episode,
you know that’s barely enough to live above
the abject poverty line
of a dollar ninety per day.
And although last week's protest got a lot
of attention,
this isn't a new issue.
In fact,
the Chinese military has been analyzing veterans
protests
since at least 1991.
And according to NPR,
in 2010,
Party officials listed "dissatisfied veterans"
as one of the three emerging threats to political
stability.
That might be why state-run media have been
emphasizing
over the last few months
that the Party will definitely find jobs for
demobilized soldiers.
So how has the regime responded
to these latest protests from veterans?
By warning of “hostile forces” trying
to take advantage of the situation.
I can’t take all the credit, of course.
Because really,
if there’s any hostile force out to get
veterans,
it would have to be the Chinese Communist
Party.
Because “Veterans say those who protest,
petition and sue the government are often
detained
or kept under surveillance.”
And according to Radio Free Asia,
that's just what happened to some of the protesters
who went to Beijing last week.
They were brought back to their home provinces,
then questioned in temporary detention centers
about who organized the protests.
But hey,
the Chinese regime is working hard.
And not just by arresting veterans
and blaming hostile forces.
They also sent an infuriatingly dismissive
letter to Reuters
saying they really do care about veterans.
The Defense Ministry wrote that the Party
“cares about veterans
and pays high attention to resolving their
problems,"
and,
“the temporary living difficulties of some
veterans
will be resolved."
But considering how they handle most dissidents
in China,
let’s just hope they don’t find a permanent
solution
to those temporary living difficulties.
So what do you think of how the Chinese Communist
Party
treats its veterans?
Leave your comments below.
Once again I’m Chris Chappell,
see you next time.