On this episode of China Uncensored,
China's most dangerous roads.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored. I'm your
host Chris Chappell.
You know, China may have a Stairway to Heaven…
but that doesn't mean you won't find yourself
on…
Well let's just say China also has a lot of
really unsafe highways.
And I'm not talking about all the bridges
that collapse from poor quality construction
and lax safety standards.
Like this one, which collapsed in 2011 because
a large truck drove on it.
I'm talking about roads that were practically
designed to be unsafe.
Because safety standards are really just suggestions,
right?
So here are the 10 most dangerous roads in
China.
Number 10 The Qinglong Road
This road is called the 24 Bends.
Can you guess why?
The steep grade and sharp turn make it extremely
dangerous.
And also, this is true, the perfect spot for
racing!
Number 9 Old Kunyi Road
Well, if 24 bends sounded scary,
check out Old Kunyi Road.
It has 68 bends in just over 4 miles.
Number 8 Tianmen Mountain Road
Want to get to that "stairway to heaven"?
Then you'll have to drive up this road.
With 99 bends a drop of over 3,500 feet, you'll
be getting to heaven
one way or the other.
Number 7 Friendship Highway
This is the road that connects China with
its BFF, Pakistan.
This 800-mile road took 20 years to build,
and more than 1,000 workers died during construction.
The border point, Khunjerab Pass, is nearly
3 miles above sea level.
So if you don't get sick from the altitude,
watch out for: Mudslides. Landslides. Giant
pot holes. Flash floods... border
And Chinese police.
Number 6 The Beijing to Hong Kong Expressway
Now you might have heard of this from the
massive 50 lane traffic jams that happen routinely
around Chinese New Year.
But a part of it running through northern
Guangdong, the Beijing-Zhuhai expressway,
has been given the comforting nickname "Vehicle
Killer."
It's famous for accidents
because overloaded trucks, steep mountainous
roads, and extreme winter cold apparently
don't mix.
Number 5 Badaling Expressway Valley of Death
Yae, though I walk in the valley of the shadow
of death, I fear no evil.
Except for the Badaling Expressway Valley
of Death.
It takes you from Beijing to the Badaling
section of the Great Wall of China.
But when you see this sign,
you know you've reached the Valley of Death.
I mean, it says it’s a black spot, doesn't
it?
It's a little steep.
And if you're not careful…
Number 4 Taike Road
But nothing can compare to what's expected
of you on Taike Road.
One wrong move and...
Accidents happen nearly every week. So why
would you drive here?
Number 3 The 213 National Highway
This highway connects Gansu and Yunnan provinces.
It's got everything.
Windy roads, steep cliffs, landslides, and
it sometimes
simply gets washed out by the river.
Number 2 The Sichuan-Tibet Highway
Well, maybe calling this a road is giving
it too much credit.
Not only is this one of the longest roads
in China
—15 days to drive the whole length—
but it's also considered one of the most dangerous.
You know, steep cliffs and landslides.
Of course, maybe this is intentional,
to discourage people from visiting Tibet.
Or to keep Tibetans in.
And Finally Number 1 The Guoliang Tunnel
The village of Guoliang in central China used
to be so isolated that the only way in or
out was this staircase.
So in the 1970s, they decided to build a slightly
less dangerous path.
13 villagers literally dug this tunnel by
hand.
One died during construction.
It's now become a tourist attraction
for those brave enough to drive it.
And it's become a testament to the ability
of Chinese people to make impossible things
possible.
So what do you think?
And if you've been to China/live there now
and are illegally using a VPN to watch my show
what's your most dangerous Chinese road experience?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again, I'm Chris Chappell. See you next time.