China is invading the US!
Without firing a single shot.
A retired US General tells us how.
Welcome back to China Uncensored,
I’m Chris Chappell.
Tensions between the United States and China
are at an all time high.
In Washington, the dialogue around China has
changed.
The US relationship with China
is now being called strategic competition.
To get a better idea of what that means,
I sat down with recently retired Air Force
General
Robert Spalding in Washington DC.
He was the senior director for strategic planning
on the National Security Council
and advised the Trump administration on China.
Thank you for joining me, General.
Great to be here.
Glad to hear it.
So you advised the White House
and helped draft the national security strategy.
And it mentions China more than any other
country.
Why is that?
So, I mean, I have to take you all the way
back six years,
if you're really interested-
Okay-
Because I've been working on this issue
for really the last six years.
It started in the summer of 2013 when we went
to
the council of foreign relations as a military
fellow.
And that was my first introduction to, kind
of,
the global business world.
Met a lot of people in finance and business,
and at the time, the Air Force was looking
at
to send me to China at some point,
and I knew that.
And I wanted to get as smart as I could about
how China interacted with the global community
through business.
And so, I started asking questions.
And my going in assumption at the time was,
that I think this is indicative of all Americans,
is a sense of hubris.
A sense that our model,
our economic model,
our social model, is-
Number one?
Is number one.
It's without reproach.
And that while China was growing at the time,
it's growth model had come to an end.
It was gonna stagnate.
And then we were gonna essentially flip the
gross switch back and,
and then we were gonna essentially climb away
from it-
And China would become a democracy-
And China ... Well, no.
China would become
a poorer totalitarian country,
which would at some point lead them to believe
that,
"Hey, we need to open up and become a democracy.
And so we can grow again like the United States."
About this time, I met one gentleman who's
a businessman
who had had a lot of money invested in China.
And essentially lost a good portion of it
during
the financial crisis during 2008.
Of course,
we've grown that back up.
And then about 2012, 2013,
he had exited China as a market
because he had realized that China was changing
in ways that he couldn't predict
where that investment might go in the future.
And so our discussion, when I first met him,
was over a lunch at one of the private clubs
in New York.
And we essentially got into an argument.
I said, "Hey, they're gonna stagnate.
They're not going anywhere."
And he said, "Oh, no.
They're not gonna stagnate,
they're gonna grow.
And they're gonna grow and their gonna become
the most powerful country in the world."
And I said, "That can't be."
America's democratic society and free market
system
is much better than, kind of, the state led
model.
And he says, "You don't know what you're talking
about."
And I mean, the truth is,
I'd spend 20 something years in the military
focusing on how to go to war with countries,
not how to go to business with them.
And so, looking back, it was evident that
I didn't know what I was talking about and
he did.
And so, that lead to a relationship where
we,
over the next year, corresponded.
I eventually moved over to the joint staff
to be the advisor on China to the Chairman
of Joint Chiefs.
And he would periodically send me data about
China's economy,
doing business in China, what was going on.
It was the fall of '14 he sent a briefing
to me.
And it sat in my inbox for about a week.
And I opened the email up one day and
when I had a minute of peace in the Pentagon.
And I started reading the briefing.
And literally my mind broke because I realized
that I did not know.
Here I was, I had a PHD in economics,
a decorated military officer,
and I did not know how the international world
worked.
And I suspected, because of that, because
of my background,
that most people didn't know as well.
And so, this started an intense effort to
really dig down deep
into how everything from finance trade, investment,
immigration,
the internet, media, politics, all of that,
how it all works,
and how it serves.
And what I found is how it has served the
Chinese communist party-
Oh, I'm curious what was-
Strategy.
In this briefing that blew your mind.
Yeah, so, again, you have to go back to my
background.
I'm a B2 pilot.
Primarily we train to take societies apart,
right?
If the US wants to impose its will, it has
a political ...
It essentially, as Clausewitz says,
"War is politics by other means."
One good example was the war in Kosovo.
We sought to stop Milosevic.
Again, the way that you create that political
pressure
to stop Milosevic is you eventually strangle
his ability
to control the country.
And then they capitulate.
So I had studied how to do this from the air
with weapons.
What I saw in that briefing,
and because I had a doctorate in economics,
could understand and fathom was that here
was a model
for doing the exact same thing with economics.
And I said-
So business becomes China's B2 bomber?
Exactly.
And it was actually kind of like the B2,
which is a stealth aircraft.
It was a stealthy operation primarily because
our own laws.
Companies can't talk about, and often are
unwilling to talk about,
what happens to them.
Either because it affects their evaluation
or because the general council and their company
says,
"You can't share that."
Or, there's a general uneasiness about talking
to government.
And so, in that briefing,
I saw vignette, after vignette,
about how specifically elements in China
had gone after companies to put them under
pressure, under duress,
in order to acquire some specific piece of
technology,
or intellectual property.
And it was going on across the country.
And I said, "Okay, if this happening,
what else is happening?
What else do I not know?"
And that, like I said, that started this entire
effort.
That lead, ultimately ...
I finished my tour in joint staff.
I went to be the in Beijing,
and eventually to work on the national security
council where,
by that time, I had a good,
fulsome picture of everything that was going
on.
And it really requires you to kind of look
at
the incentive structure of the system.
The thing that America has patented and why
we've so successful,
our democratic model aligned with the liberal
capitalist system,
is we aligned private profit motive with national
interest.
In other words, if you're doing well, the
country is doing well.
What I found was China had done the same thing
except align your private profit motive
wherever you were with their national interest.
And so, if you were doing well, China was
doing well.
And it was actually quite brilliant.
And so basically,
all I had to do at the national security council
was help educate people on what was going
on.
Just like I had spent the last four years
teaching myself
about what was going on.
Then it was just time to essentially
share that with my colleagues.
And once you start to understand how the world
works
along all of these different areas of globalization
then you understand that the system's actually
setup
that a totalitarian regime can actually do
quite well.
And actually, not just do well from an economic
perspective,
but also do well in terms of transferring
their values
into democratic societies.
And so the "So what" of what I found was not
that ...
In the defense department,
we essentially prepare for war.
That's what we do.
And then we go to war if the-
If it comes to that.
What I found was
the Chinese way of doing things didn't require
war,
it just required you to stay open for business.
And then slowly, it would allow the suppression
of freedoms
that we currently take, quite frankly, for
granted.
And so, it's not just,
"Hey, it's gonna improve their economy."
"Hey, it's gonna actually undermine your democracy
over time-"
Yeah, I believe they use the term
"unrestricted warfare" to describe this.
Well that was ... I read that when it came
out in 1999.
I thought, "Well this is preposterous."
First of all, we're never gonna go to war
with China.
We're never gonna have armed conflict.
We're two nuclear armed countries.
Nobody in their right mind wants to go to
war
with a nuclear armed country just because
of all
the potential for risk and devastation.
And so, I discounted it.
And it's because, quite frankly,
the guys that wrote that were actually quite...
They could see into the future,
and see what openness would mean in terms
of an opportunity
for China to essentially get gains out of
democracies expenses
without creating any kind of risk whatsoever.
I think one really clear example you gave
me
was the example of the artificial islands
China's building in the South China Sea.
Why don't you tell us a bit about that
and how that plays into the global market.
Right.
So, if you think about today how global finance
work,
a lot of it is done by index investing.
In other words,
an index tracks a certain set of companies
and institutional investors.
Retirement funds basically invest in those
companies
based on what the index calls for.
So, in recently the MSCI Emerging Markets
Index
increased its weighting from 5% to 20%
and that results in a significant amount of
money
going to China in the next year.
So, over the next year, almost a trillion
US dollars
will go into China's stock market.
That's money that's coming right out of our
retirement funds.
Some of these companies do things
like build islands in the South China Sea,
or build aircraft carriers, or help the oppression
currently going on in Xinjiang.
So, in essence, you have our retirement funds
are being invested in things that, quite frankly,
we call out from a national perspective.
In other words, the department of defense
is sending navy ships
within 12 nautical miles of illegal islands
in the South China Sea
while our public employees are investing in
those islands.
That's insane.
So what would you say is the single biggest
threat
to the US from China?
Well, I mean, when you say that in that way,
it implies that you can isolate it.
Right?
It's so pervasive that you can't isolate it.
And it's integrated as well.
So, I think the single greatest threat
is just their desire to maintain control,
which requires that they essentially suppress
speech,
suppress freedom of religion,
and really use oppression as a tool of government.
All three of those things, essentially,
were called out by FDR in his state of the
union address in 1941.
And essentially those four freedoms became
the basis of our international order.
In other words,
if you look at the Atlantic Charter,
if you look at the UN Charter,
there's two kind of fundamental pieces to
that.
One is free markets and the other is democratic
principals.
And those were the things that specifically
are called out,
in document number nine,
as being not designed for the purpose of promoting
what we believe to be, kind of, universal
norms,
but specifically designed to
take down the Chinese communist party.
So, when you put unrestricted warfare together
with document number nine,
essentially what you have is a theory of victory
and a motive for that struggle, if you will.
So it's their desire to maintain control,
right?
That really becomes a threat to our freedoms.
So you see, sort of,
the current western world order that has these
principals.
That is incompatible with a China lead global
order?
Absolutely.
Because essentially what they've done is
they've taken the same four freedoms and their
social contract
is built around the idea that number one,
the Chinese communist party is the only one
that can return China to its rightful place
in the world.
Number two, in order for us to do that,
we have a social contract with the Chinese
people.
And that social contract is
we will essentially deliver continuous economic
growth
as long as you don't challenge our right to
rule.
And so basically, the way that looks,
if you take FDR's speech,
it says we'll put freedom from want up at
the top
and then you basically forfeit all the other
three freedoms.
And that's a social contract.
So as long as we keep growing economically,
you have no right to challenge our rule.
Well so I guess the fundamental problem
in the United States is that people,
they can look at China and see that the Chinese
communist party
has the largest standing army in the world.
And they know that China is hacking the United
States.
But it seems like there's a lot of specific
strategies
the communist part is using that the American
public
might not be too aware of.
What are some of those strategies?
Well, I already talked about
how they use global finance, basically.
So they're 30 trillion dollars in debt right
now.
They have a non convertible currency in strict
capital controls.
Money, especially from elites, is trying to
flee the country.
They're clamping that down and they're using
the flow of capital from the west
to kind of show up their financial markets.
In trade, you have essentially,
and this is also within the country,
you have a very low regulation.
In other words,
if you look at trade from their standpoint,
we have four inspectors.
The United States has four inspectors in China.
I believe two in Shanghai and two in Shenzhen.
These inspectors are not allowed to look inside
any containers.
They get manifest, they may call out,
"Hey, we think there's a problem here with
this container."
Of course, then the Chinese go
and do the inspections on behalf of them.
Then, you have to deal with the fact that
by Chinese law,
there's no timeline required in terms of
when you declare that container exported.
So it can be already on the ship and gone.
Also, a majority of the lading is done during
the weekends.
And if you're a Chinese customs officer,
you're penalized if you slow down the lading
process.
So in essence you have an export system that
is completely ...
It sends everything that gets produced.
Which is why you have issues like fentanyl
investment.
The Chinese use finance to come and look at
...
Even companies that our defense department
is investing in to develop technologies.
They wait 'til those can't find investment
here in the United States
because it's a tough business keeping a business
going.
If you're trying to prove out a new technology,
they'll swoop in, they'll take the business,
they'll take it back to China.
They'll commercialize it and then they got
the technology
for both their military and they export it
back to the United States.
Intellectual property theft.
They're able to, because of our laws,
one company can steal a technology.
It can transfer that technology to another
company in China.
That company can produce the goods,
export it to the United States.
So now they're making money,
but because of discovery laws in our own legal
system,
the company that was originally ripped off
has no recourse.
And so, along all areas of our connectivity,
they have an ability to, essentially,
they've re engineered globalization to their
advantage.
So they're using our laws to undermine us?
Our laws, our markets, our financial system,
our media, our internet.
You name it.
Well, so what is the US doing about this?
Well I think for the first time
we're actually beginning the process to understand
it.
And then of course because we haven't applied
policy
in a kind of a 21st century competitive format,
we're trying to learn how to do that.
And so, the first step was a national security
strategy.
Just identifying the problem, right?
'Cause the federal bureaucracy's a huge organization.
It's probably the hugest in the world.
And so, you have to identify the problem.
But then once you identify the problem,
that message has to be inculcated in the very
large bureaucracy.
And then after that, the bureaucracy has to
figure out
what does it do about it?
Right?
It's not sufficient just to understand it.
Now you have to figure out,
"Okay, based on our laws,
based on how globalization works,
how do we fix things?"
Okay.
So in your mind,
what would be the ideal US, China policy?
I like the term "Decoupling".
I think being coupled to China in such a fulsome
way
is actually damaging to our democracy.
And so, there's a lot of people that say,
"Hey, we should have no say in the relationship
between the Chinese communist party and the
Chinese people."
And in some respects, I agree with that.
That is up to the Chinese people.
But I would say the relationship of the Chinese
communist party
with the United States is what I would focus
on.
And the less relationship we have, the better,
I think.
In terms of our future freedoms.
How would that be achieved, though?
'Cause I mean our economies are so linked.
It's hard to decouple that.
Well, if you go back to before the WTO,
very single year,
we had a vote in the congress on whether to
extend
those favored nation status to the Chinese.
Prior to that, no major American corporation
would invest in any significant way in China,
right?
Because large companies need to have stability
in their operations.
And so, I think the more we understand about
the problem
and the more that creates a need within the
American people to say,
"Hey, let's rethink the relationship
and let's actually see how it affects us.
Is it in a positive way or is it in a negative
way?"
As those questions begin to be asked,
corporations are gonna have to take a step
back and say,
"Does it make a lot of sense for me to have
significant operations in China
when they can be impacted by the relationship
going forward?"
So, I think in essence,
those things are already beginning to happen.
You're beginning to see corporations rethink
how they structure their operations abroad.
Particularly if they have significant operations
in China.
What they're hoping, and I think wrongly so,
is that these trade negotiations
make everything go back to normal.
Once people begin to wake up to what's going
on,
I think you're gonna see more and more cause,
particularly in congress,
that we actually strictly look at the relationship
for what it is and how it benefits,
or doesn't,
the American people,
and then do the right thing.
One final question.
Do you think China is the next superpower?
No.
Quite frankly, I think that we're gonna
look back at history and we're gonna say,
"After 2008, the Chinese communist party
viewed itself as ascendent."
And I think viewed strategy as ascendent.
And I think that caused them to do some things
that actually they moved away from hide and
bide.
And I think in doing so,
exposed the communist party for what it is.
And therefore allowed people
to kind of wake from their slumber
and understand what's going on.
I think you can't put that back in the box.
It's out for everybody to see,
and now it's just a matter of,
"Will democracies do the right thing,
or they allow themselves to be essentially
bought into
co-opting their freedoms for profit?"
Well that was very enlightening.
Thank you for joining us today, General.
Absolutely.
Thank you again, General.
There's actually much, much more to learn.
Fortunately we sat down together
on the China Unscripted Podcast
and it's frankly pretty horrifying.
So, click the link and check it out.