China launched a war against the free world
While America turned a blind eye
Now China’s political warfare is everywhere
Is the battle lost?
Or can we still fight back?
This is China Uncensored,
I’m Chris Chappell, here in Taipei, Taiwan.
When the Cold War ended,
the world breathed a collective sigh of relief.
And completely forgot about the other massive
Communist power
threatening the world
—the Chinese Communist Party.
Through a sophisticated use of what they call
political warfare,
the Chinese regime has slowly subverted democracies
around the world,
including the United States and Taiwan.
I sat down with Chinese political warfare
expert
Professor Kerry Gershaneck
to learn how we all got trapped in China’s
Red Matrix.
Thanks for joining me today.
Thanks Chris.
Appreciate you having me here today.
Absolutely.
So you're an expert on Chinese commie's party
political warfare.
First, what is political warfare?
Political warfare from the people's Republic
of China perspective
is the number one way it is going to destroy
the democracy on Taiwan.
It is the number one way it will usurp the
United States
as the leading global superpower,
the way it will bring down the hegemon,
and so it can become the hegemon.
The goal of political warfare's to do all
that without fighting.
That is without going kinetic in a mid intensity
or high intensity conflict.
You use political means, you use influence.
Malign influences a term that you'll hear
often.
But it's much more than simple malign influence.
It's all the means that a communist fascist
totalitarian regime,
based on Leninist terror,
as a means of executing your policies, state,
can use.
So I know a lot of terminology around political
warfare,
like gray zone operations, or comprehensive
coercion.
I think that's pretty confusing to a lot of
your average audience.
How would you explain it to like my mom?
You're absolutely right.
The lexicon, the terminology,
that surrounds what is in reality, this war
that we are in,
China is at war with us, and we don't understand
it
because we don't understand the terminology.
We America, and Taiwan, the Republic of China,
all too often we think in terms of discrete
functions
such as diplomacy.
We think in terms of information operations,
we think in terms of psychological operations.
There's a whole array of terminology.
You've addressed the gray zone operations,
but there's proxy armies.
There's a whole array of terms
that gets stovepiped in our thinking.
Our policy leaders,
our elected officials don't understand that
these aren't
just discreet functions from the PRC perspective.
The PRC is waging war against us,
they're waging what we would call in
the military combined arms warfare.
They're using every asset they have.
Every component, the army, Navy, air force,
Marine special operations.
Okay.
Apply that to political warfare.
It's psychological operations, special measures.
Again, going back to their mentors.
This Chinese communist party mentors,
was originally Lenin and then Stalin, in the
Soviet union.
So it's the active measures or special measures,
that they use too, include assassination,
kidnapping, proxy armies,
violence, coercive efforts to influence
and to change the behavior of other countries,
of other groups,
of their own people to conform
with exactly what the CCP wants them to do.
Our terminology frankly, is really undermining
our ability
to fight back effectively against the political
war
that's being waged against us.
Why is the Chinese communist party doing this?
I mean, why can't we just get along?
Excellent question that I know that you know
the answer to,
but for the benefit of your audiences worldwide,
who may not fully understand the issue.
No one cares if we're dealing with a quote
rising Canada.
No one cares if we're dealing with a rising
Brazil.
No one cares if we're dealing even with the
rising Republican-
I care about a rising Canada, I never trusted
them.
You know as well you should, but again,
the maple leaf on that flag flying overhead,
that doesn't instill as much fear in me
as seeing the flag of the People's Republic
of China
flying over Taiwan or Washington DC and here's
why.
The country we're dealing with, the state,
every word here I'm going to say is important.
It is an increasingly militarily and economically
powerful,
hyper nationalistic, expansionist, fascist
totalitarian regime.
All the other countries, Canada included,
are democracies.
They're self correcting.
If the Republic of China next week decided
we're going to build a 550 ship Navy twice
the size of the US Navy,
guess what?
The regime that's in power would be out of
power
come next election because the people can
self correcting.
They're going to vote out people
that improperly utilize national assets,
national treasure to build militaries
that you don't need for peacetime defense.
People's Republic of China
isn't building a military for peace time defense.
They're using it for coercion.
They're using it for expansion.
Again, the nature of the regime counts
and this is what so many American academics
and a lot of policymakers, including foreign
policy
and foreign service officers and even a military
personnel.
Certainly a lot of professors.
I mean it's what they don't get.
We're not dealing with a benign country.
You know, the rise of China.
We can accommodate that.
We can make them like us.
No, we can't.
It is, again, it's a very dangerous state
that
we're dealing with and it has no intention
of being co-opted and turned into a democratic
country
that respects rule of law, respects human
rights,
respects democracy.
Everything they do, everything they do in
terms of their people,
censoring our thoughts overseas, setting up
proxy armies.
Say for example in Myanmar,
the largest non-state military force and most
effective in Asia,
and arguably much of the world is the United
Wa State Army.
It influences every decision made by the government
of Myanmar,
Burma, as we call it in America.
Well, where are they getting those brand new
tanks?
Where are they getting those brand new helicopters,
those brand new uniforms.
The AKs coming out of the crates still in
cosmoline.
They it just fall off the lorry of a PLA truck
in Southern Yunnan.
It's being provided on a systematic basis,
along with the education training facilities.
All the other things that United Wa State
Army
needs to be a coercive proxy army within the
borders of Myanmar.
So this is the nature of the beast we're dealing
with.
So that's why we care.
The nature of the regime here is incredibly
intimidating.
It's totalitarian, and it's not one we can
afford to let win
and hence we must do a much better job of
fighting
on the political warfare battlefields.
So I think this is a very important point
that you're touching on,
that political warfare is not the same as
the normal kind of competition that all countries
engage in?
Political warfare is war, and that is how
the PRC sees it.
They're waging war against us.
Now, think back about 20 years ago.
There was a fellow running around in Southwest
Asia who was saying,
"America, I'm at war with you.
I'm at war with you.
I'm going to kill your people.
I'm at war with you."
And a lot of the officials in Washington DC
were saying,
"Yeah, look, you got a towel on your head.
You live in a cave.
You're nothing serious."
Well then on September 11th,
2001 when we had a several thousand Americans
die,
very hideous deaths at the hands of this individual.
Finally, the US government woke up and said,
"Yeah, no kidding.
He was at war with us."
We need to have the same recognition of
what the people's Republic of China's war
against us.
How that falls out, what that looks like,
and we can't do that based on our own lack
of education.
No one in senior US department of defense
schools
teaches PRC political warfare.
At the academies of course, but when you were
national war colleges,
your army war college, your a Naval war college,
your national defense university,
it isn't preparing us on the military side.
Then you get you have a flawed defense strategy
that can't respond to the political warfare
that PLA
is waging very effectively against us,
and co-opting incidentally retired,
a vice chairman of the joint chiefs of staff
was co-opted under what we call a liaison
program,
a United Front program and as well as
a number of other senior American military
officers.
Same issue on the state department side.
The Schultz Center,
the Foreign Service Institute at Arlington,
Virginia.
They don't teach it.
Go talk to them, interview them and say,
"How do you prepare either our entry level
diplomats,
our foreign service officers,
or the ones coming back from mid level training
or other training.
How do you prepare them to deal with the existential
threat
posed by Beijing with it's political warfare."
The existential threat being, again,
they're trying to destroy our country.
Again, Taiwan is the major target,
but every one of our friends and allies,
how are we preparing our diplomats to do that?
We're not.
Why not?
Complacency.
We won the cold war.
So at the end of the cold war we shut down
our capabilities
to fight on the information battlefield, effectively.
We shut down the US Information Agency.
Arguably it had gotten soft,
it had gotten rotten inside.
It needed to be reformed, it did not need
to be shut down.
The state department was ill-equipped psychologically,
ideologically,
and in terms of manpower to take on that mantle,
especially when it looked like we were Chris
at the end of history,
we didn't need to worry about totalitarian
regimes anymore.
Everything was going to be peace, love, happiness
and flowers,
and so we didn't need that capability.
Now that's a downside.
We have become complacent.
We don't have the education system
in either our government institutions
or our civilian academic institutions.
Go to Georgetown,
go to any other universities that pump out
our future diplomats.
See what programs they have to address political
warfare,
pretty much nonexistent.
So the the downside is we are totally unprepared.
We have generations of diplomats,
generations of department of commerce personnel
at least since 1992,
they're not getting any preparation to deal
with this,
and hence they can't recognize it.
A problem within our country,
but a problem also within our friends and
allies.
Most of them can't recognize it or if they
can recognize it,
they have zero capacity to fight back.
I think the Chinese communist party
would accuse you of a cold war mentality.
I'm saddened, I'm hurt, I'm angered, and I'm
irked,
which is the way that they have conditioned
our news media
and many of our, again, government officials
to respond to anything
that is along the lines of what I just said
about China,
any criticism of China.
We have become conditioned in many cases to
do anything we can
to not anger or upset China.
I get those three words specifically because
if you look at Reuters headlines routinely,
they will always have a headline such as,
"In an a move guaranteed to anger or upset
China.
President Tsai, for example, from Taiwan,
has said she wants democracy
and not one country, two systems for Taiwan."
Reuters could just as easily have written,
"In a move designed to hearten,
give hope to the the free people of Taiwan.
President Tsai has said, we want freedom.
We want democracy.
We don't want one country, two systems."
But again, our news media, many of our academics,
our think tank world, has been infiltrated.
It's been co-opted in many ways,
many in there have allowed themselves
to have their thoughts controlled,
where they instinctively will say what China
wants them to say so as not to upset China,
or in some cases not to upset the flow of
funding
from Chinese organizations.
So based on what you're saying,
it's not so much that the Chinese Communist
Party
is forcing people to act in a way they want.
It's more that they are manipulating them
to,
of their own accord do what the communist
party wants?
It's psychological manipulation that gets
people
to the point that they will do instinctively
what they think that China,
the CCP wants them to do, so as not to offend
China.
So what you have then is preemptive actions.
For example, we've seen this within our own
Department of State
where a lot of the policies that restrict
interaction
with free and democratic Taiwan,
they were never the result of any agreements
with Beijing.
They weren't even presidential level directives.
They were just self-imposed restraints,
increasingly oppressive over the years
within the US government bureaucracy,
that restrained us from what we could do
to support this country to survive.
That extended everything from the arm sales
at the Taiwan Relations Act
was supposed to ... they were supposed to
go on routinely.
Somehow they went back to what, almost zero,
for a total of eight years.
As far as interaction, ship visits even.
There's no agreement that says we can't send
a ship to Kaohsiung,
a US military ship to Kaohsiung.
There's a lot of-
The southern city in Taiwan?
The southern city, the major port in southern
Taiwan.
There all kinds of interaction that was prohibited
because it's self restraint,
under what I would call the red matrix.
I didn't come up with that term,
but the red matrix is you live in this matrix
like world where
you just do everything you think will please
China.
We can't say anything bad about China.
We can't call China totalitarian.
We can't call China fascist.
I've seen this in the think tank world.
I used to work there.
We can't even call it a dictatorship.
Well, why?
Marianne Webster are on our side in this case.
Look up the definition of fascist.
Look up the definition of totalitarian.
Every element in Merriam Webster, the PRC
fulfills.
Dictatorship.
That's written right in its constitution.
Yet I've heard people in the think tank world
and even US government officials saying,
"Well, we won't call it a dictatorship publicly.
We just can't say that about China."
That's the Lord Voldemort syndrome that we
see.
A lot of my students grow up with Harry Potter.
They understand the concept.
We can't say Lord Voldemort's name because
bad things will happen.
Well, we see the under this red matrix,
this self-censorship,
the lower Voldemort's syndrome in play.
Not just in the United States,
not just in an academia here in Taiwan.
In many cases, it's throughout the world.
So the PRC, to give the PRC credit where credit
is due,
it's political warfare has been tremendously
successful worldwide,
in many cases.
Now you could say,
"Well, the election outcome the other day
shows that it wasn't perfect."
No, but it's still ongoing.
They see political warfare as a perpetual
struggle,
"Okay, there's ebbs and flows.
We don't have to go kinetic.
We don't have to go to mid intensity conflict,
but we're going to keep the struggle going
perpetually
until we win."
Well, all right, so let's get specific.
What is the Chinese Communist Party doing
as far as political warfare goes in Taiwan?
In Taiwan, they've a co-opted a lot of the
news media.
They bought for example, through,
again, this is through surrogates.
Everything's a little bit hard to prove in
a court of law,
but in reality, those in the know know what's
going on.
For example, radio stations down South
where they don't read newspapers as much,
but the radio in the rural areas is very important.
They bought the radio,
many radio stations that used to be either
pro Taiwan,
or certainly pro freedom and democracy.
Now you see a very heavy influence of PRC
propaganda
being broadcast over those radio stations.
Want Want, the Times, the different news media
either online,
and or print, that they've been bought or
co-opted here.
So you've got the news media, you've got from
the mainland,
massive social media attacks and social media
infiltration
pretending to be either concern Taiwanese,
pretending to be even Americans.
There's all kinds of ways they're trying to
influence
on the very extensive social media battle
ground.
Infiltration of academia.
There are certainly professors who have gone
what we call pan-Red here.
Political parties for those who aren't familiar
with Taiwan,
DPP Democratic Progressive Parties is a pan-Green.
The KMT is a pan-Blue.
Well, there's another party,
there's other colors as well,
in this color spectrum of political parties
here.
But the ones who've gone over to the PRC,
the ones who are pro quote, reunification,
and that's a misnomer.
But we'll use the PRC term,
the ones who are pro reunification and want
to do it tomorrow,
on Beijing's terms, we call them pan-Reds.
So even they have infiltrated academia
and they have a tremendous influence,
or at least tremendous capability to influence,
the young people of Taiwan
because you have to get A's from those professors.
You have to get their recommendations
if you want to go on for master's degrees,
if you want to go on for PhD.
In many cases they dictate your success or
failure in academia.
If you do what they want, if you to go along,
you get along.
If you don't do what they want, a
nd what they want is for you to support the
PRC, you have trouble.
Well, so what is Taiwan doing about this?
Taiwan has begun to take some steps.
Taiwan is at a disadvantage,
just like the United States because at the
end of the cold war
when we dismantled our capability to fight
on the political warfare battlefields,
that was around the time that Taiwan was democratizing,
and they were able to speak freely about the
white terror,
which was the era when the the KMT ruled with
an iron hand
and basically slaughtered a lot of people
here,
and repressed civil rights,
and used rule of law to oppress people
rather than to provide them
what we would expect a democracy to provide.
Well, around the 1980s the son of Chiang Kai
Shek,
to his great credit,
who had been schooled incidentally ...
Chiang had a son who had been schooled
in Leninist political warfare,
and Leninist tactics within the Soviet union.
But he helped lead his country to democracy,
with the ability to publicly speak about
that really vicious era of repression.
In my mind,
this country went too far the other way in
eliminating laws,
eliminating capabilities that would allow
them to detect,
expose and take appropriate legal action against
infiltration.
Rather recently, last month, I believe,
it was the end of the last year.
At the end of December, the anti infiltration
law was passed.
That was a massive first step in helping to
cut down the amount of money,
the amount of influence that could come in
from overseas affecting,
for example, elections.
Much more needs to be done though in terms
of educating the public,
educating government officials,
educating business leaders about the threats
posed by PRC political warfare.
So why should Americans be concerned about
w
hat the Chinese Communist Party's trying to
do in Taiwan?
Well, first of all, Taiwan is an existential
threat to the CCP.
Americans are slowly beginning to realize
that we're in strategic competition with the
People's Republic of China.
They don't understand fully that the PRC is
at war with us.
Where Taiwan plays a very important role is
again,
it poses the existential threat to the Chinese
Communist Party
because it shows that Chinese people can rule
themselves in a democracy.
It is the narrative from the CCP,
that Chinese people can't have freedom,
they can't have democracy, can't rule themselves.
They need the jackboot of oppression to keep
the country
from fragmenting and having all the splitist
split
and the country devolving into chaos.
Now Taiwan proves Chinese people can rule
themselves
and they can survive with dignity,
and they can survive with prosperity,
under that democratic rule.
So that's one of the many reasons.
There are several reasons that that Beijing
wants to take Taiwan.
For Americans, they have to realize we need
to stand by democracies,
democracies worldwide, and especially Taiwan.
Taiwan has stood up heroically,
and almost alone, to the CCP.
If Taiwan can stand up,
just like the Hong Kong protesters have been,
they've achieved some remarkable things,
especially with the elections in Hong Kong.
If Taiwan can continue to stand up against
an expansionist,
brutally repressive fascist totalitarian regime
that gives hope to democracies around the
world.
America must support Taiwan,
for our own self interest and the interests
of Japan,
Republic of Korea, all the association of
Southeast Asian nations,
ASEAN nations, in the region,
you best hope Taiwan doesn't fall
because if this Island falls to the PRC,
then it becomes a power projection platform.
They don't care about the people of Taiwan
and Beijing.
I think they'll treat them like Xinjiang,
treat them like East Turkestan.
They'll have concentration camps.
I think they'll do the worst they can to punish
them,
if they do reunify.
That's my personal opinion.
But more importantly,
rather than even dealing with the people,
what the PLA, what the CCP also wants this
Island for,
submarine pens, airfields, so they can project
power
further into the South China Sea,
and into Oceania where they have, frankly
a Neo colonization effort
going on throughout the Pacific islands, a
nd a massive malign influence campaigns in
Australia, and New Zealand.
They can support those political warfare campaigns
in Oceania,
Pacific islands, down to Australia, New Zealand
with military power better now,
not just the PLA Navy,
but strategic bombers out of Taiwan,
other vessels and power projection forces
based here.
So the countries who are democracies,
those countries that are democracies around
the world,
best support a democracy like Taiwan,
the David against Goliath here.
But also those countries that even are
authoritarians in the Asia Pacific region,
but do not want to be under the jackboot of
Beijing's oppression.
They best hope that Taiwan does not fall
and become a power protection base for the
People's Liberation Army.
Well I know the Chinese Communist Party
would say that it's really the United States
that's the real troublemaker in the Pacific.
How would you respond to people who argue
that the United States is actually the worst
aggressor?
I lose a lot of sleep over that accusation
by Beijing.
It's tormented me.
It haunts me.
They-
Irks you?
Yeah, it upsets me as well.
As well, look,
it's one of many propaganda narratives
and it's successful in some places.
I've seen the success that they've had,
the infiltrating in the countries that are
supposedly
friends and allies of America.
They've done a pretty good job of infiltrating
on social media
and people buy into that line that we're the
troublemaker.
The reality is we're the only guarantor of
freedom, democracy,
rule of law, post Westphalian rights, within
this region.
If America is not here and to use the PRC
lexicon,
"Making trouble," that is standing up for
democracies like Taiwan,
like Japan, like the Republic of Korea, Australia,
New Zealand.
If we're not here, no one else will have the
strength to do it.
And so we have seen what has happened in the
past
when totalitarian regimes have marched forward
and no one stood up.
You know peace in our time,
we remember the appeasement in Europe in the
1930s
when no one was willing to stand up to Hitler.”
We'll just give him the Sudetenland.
Okay, Czechoslovakia, that's fine.
He'll be happy.
He'll be happy."
No, they're never happy.
So we cannot appease.
We must confront.
We must stop the forward march, the expansionism.
We must be able to counter the political warfare,
which is again,
their primary means of winning what they want
to achieve.
We need to effectively counter it,
and then we have a chance of surviving,
Taiwan will be able to survive, the other
democracies will.
But they cannot do it on their own.
The United States, just as in the cold war,
the United States has to be the leader, the
unifying force.
The powerful country that can give encouragement,
give material support, gives psychological
support,
other types of support to those nations
standing up against the totalitarian regime
that is on the march.
So if anyone watching wanted to learn more
about
you or political warfare, where should they
go?
Well, they can Google my name,
In Political Warfare, a number of articles
will come up,
about 20 in the past year and a half.
They also can go to Project 2049 Institute.
They can go to the Global Taiwan Institute.
They can go to the Hudson Institute.
Now you're beginning to see good organizations
like the three,
and there more, exposing PRC political warfare.
They've all done some very good work on political
warfare.
Not enough though.
We need to encourage masters candidates.
We need to encourage PhD candidates at the
university level
to do their thesis on the issue.
It's not just do it on soft power,
or hard power, or now the popular term is
sharp power.
No, do it on political warfare,
that's the real battle that we're fighting.
Delve into it.
Professors need to encourage that.
So professors need to get out of the Lord
Voldemort syndrome
and start looking into the whole issue themselves.
And again, government officials.
If government grants start flowing
to academic institutions and think tanks
to pursue this and come up with solutions,
"how can we effectively counter,
how can we effectively fight and win on the
information battlefield
to counter PRC political warfare?"
You'll start seeing a lot more intellectual
effort
being invested into this.
As I understand, you do have a book you're
working on?
Got a book that will be published sometime
in late spring or early June,
I'll give you more information on it when
it's published.
But at this point it's coming along very nicely
and it will address a large part of what we
talked about today,
but in substantive detail with somewhere around
400 foot notes.
Fantastic.
I'm looking forward to it.
Okay.
Thank you very much, Chris.
Thanks for being here.
Honored to be here with you.