30 Years ago
The Tanks rolled into Beijing
To this day, the Chinese Communist Party
Pretends like the whole thing never happened
And let’s just say, you don’t want to
disagree
Welcome back to China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
30 years ago, on June 4 1989,
the Chinese Communist Party made it very clear
it wasn’t going to evolve into a liberal
democracy.
I know, shocking right?
In the West, we call it the Tiananmen Square
Massacre,
where thousands of unarmed people were killed.
But the Chinese Communist Party simply refers
to it
as the “June 4 Incident”.
And as they put it, it’s when armed,
violent students attacked poor defenseless
soldiers
who had to fight back to save the country.
But that lovely piece of propaganda only comes
out as a last resort.
The Communist Party much prefers making people
forget the whole thing ever happened.
The mothers of students who were killed have
been silenced.
And most mentions of the June 4th Incident
on the Chinese internet get blocked.
Even including some pretty clever workarounds
by Chinese netizens,
who started calling it May 35th.
It’s gotten to the point that today,
many young people have never even heard of
the Tiananmen Square Massacre.
And it doesn’t help when Western institutions,
like the Encyclopedia Britannica,
decide to no longer call it a massacre.
With the survivors of Tiananmen now entering
their 50’s,
the very real possibility confronts us that
there could come a day when the Tiananmen
Square Massacre
is erased from history.
So the survivors look to new ways to preserve
the story
for future generations.
I sat down with one of the student leaders,
Zhou Fengsuo,
to find out how to keep the memory of Tiananmen
alive.
Thanks for joining me today.
Thank you for having me.
Absolutely.
So you were one of the student leaders
in the Tiananmen protests of 1989.
How does it feel to have been number five
on the Chinese Communist Party's most wanted
list?
t was an honor and also a shock to me when
I saw my name
on the most wanted list.
Immediately I was so immensely proud of what
I had been doing
but on the other hand I was shocked because
I never saw myself
being a top leader.
I was just doing what I was supposed to do
as an ordinary student out of my duty as a
citizen.
So when you went to the protests,
you didn't have in mind that you were doing
something against the government?
I think we knew all along we were against
in some parts of the government,
but it was not against the whole system at
that time.
We were hoping that the system could change
for better of course
but we were just protesting and basically
petitioning,
not really trying to overthrow the government
in the beginning.
Of course, after the massacre things changed.
Okay.
This is kind of related.
The communist party likes to portray what
happened in Tiananmen
as a violent student uprising.
What actually happened?
Why were you there?
It was the most peaceful protest in history,
I mean, looking back the last 30 years from
what I know,
this was the most peaceful protest in the
world,
and of course in China millions of people
in Beijing
are protesting but it was so peaceful,
so orderly that even people are talking,
even criminals, even thieves stop stealing.
It's not a joke.
Five years ago when I went back to China to
protest Tiananmen,
they send me back, but the police who sent
me back basically
told me he still remembered 25 years ago
it was the most peaceful time in his memory
and he had never seen so many people on the
street at the same time,
so that's what's amazing.
I’m amazed you tried to go back to China
considering you were,
at one point, on the top five most wanted
list.
For me, as a survivor,
it's my duty to remember and to remind the
world of what happened
and to pay tribute to these people who died
in particular.
Tiananmen, when I left, we were driven out
by tanks.
It's always my wish to commemorate on Tiananmen.
Even with all the surveillance everything's
so closely watched, monitored, guarded.
I realized there might be an opening if I
just try,
so that's how I was able to get here
using the transit visa on the ground.
Well, so you were there when the tanks rolled
in.
How bad was it?
It was like a war zone but on the one hand
there were these peaceful students with no
weapons,
and on the other hand,
there are the fully armed troops and most
elite troops
of the communist government with tanks, machine
guns, everything,
so it was like a war.
I feel powerless.
I also feel invincible in a way that I would
never surrender
to such brutal senseless violence.
Where does that feeling of invincibility come
from?
I mean, if I were facing down things,
I don't know if I would feel that way.
I mean, just from the belief of what we were
doing.
We were doing something right and we were
ready to sacrifice for it
and just the moral force just so their fear
of this regime
that's completely... and to me, so I was just
really hardened
when I left Tiananmen, said, "We will come
back."
This kind of brutality wouldn't conquer us.
What were some of the things you were protesting
for?
I know you were saying you weren't there to
overthrow the government,
but what did the protesters want?
So from the beginning, very early on on April
18th
there was a petition from Peking University
and there was seven demands,
and out of the seven demands two are the most
important
and one is for press freedom,
the other one is for more transparency and
the wealth,
the family wealth of government officials,
so we are calling for disclosure
of the family wealth of top officials.
These two are the most important ones.
Of course, immediately they were widely applauded
by the public
and that's why it raised so much fear among
the communist regime
because the fear that freedom of speech and
more transparency
will just stop their corruption the their
legitimacy of-
Even though those are the things guaranteed
in China's constitution.
Right, it was completely legal even under
the communist law.
But they answered your demands with tanks.
Right.
Eventually that was the answer.
And actually then, made up its mind to kill
very early.
In April he said he was going to kill
if the students wouldn't stop protests,
he said he's going to kill.
And so were the people in Beijing
supportive of the students and the protestors?
Of course they were because it was so peaceful
and the demands was so widely shared by the
general public.
It was so supported.
It was just overwhelming.
People would bring food and they would take
their kids on the shoulder
to block the troops just to show them this
is a family event.
There's nothing out of order in Beijing.
You should get out.
It was a very touching moment in China where
all the people
could unify for one dream.
So as I understand it,
initially the military that was there were
from the local area
and they were unwilling to crack down on the
students
so the party got military forces from further
away.
Is that accurate?
I think, yeah, it's true the full process
we don't really know from what we know today
the local troop,
the most elite one called 38th Army Troop,
so its commander was court marshalled for
disobeying the Marshall Law
and so that's a very clear sign of how the
soldiers themselves
were not willing to kill.
But in the end, the same troop,
after its commander was removed was the one
that committed most killing because they were
forced to do so
and they were surrounded by many other troops.
That was the escape of just to put a deep
confrontation
between the soldiers and the protestors.
That, to me, explains why there are just so
many killings.
So obviously having the tanks roll into the
nation's capital,
that's not an easy thing to cover up.
People must still remember,
like you talked about the guard you met when
you went back to China
who said he remembered.
How is the communist party able to cover this
up?
For the last 30 years there has been a continuous
campaign
against truth and a memory to erase it completely,
so there's so much fear even in the Chinese
community here
just to talk about it.
For example, our event next Tuesday at St.
John the Divine Cathedral,
I talked to friends who were supportive of
us said,
"Would you come because you support us?"
He said, "You know, I'm looking for people
to join me
but nobody willing and afraid to."
That's the kind of situation now
so there's a pervasive fear of the public
to talk about.
Even 30 years later, Chinese people-
In United States.
In the United States are afraid.
Yes.
So that's how paranoid the communists were
and how much effort they had put here to keep
people's' mouths shut.
In a way, the general public in China and
the Chinese community
are becoming part of the collusion
because most family wouldn't tell their kids,
they would stop their kids from participating,
even today in United States at universities
at any events related to Tiananmen.
And here, even institutions here we talk to,
most of them shows some kind of fear
just for being associated with us.
Well, I guess when the communist party in
showed that they're willing to kill peoples'
children,
people want to protect their children
so they don't want them to be in a situation
where they are at risk from the government.
Yes.
Unfortunately that's the wrong,
the communist forced people,
but for last 30 years that is the way it is
now,
but of course, the facts,
the truth itself has its own power.
Whenever I'm able to talk to younger generations
they are normally very positively receptive,
but if I meet someone at other occasions,
if I bring this up they will try to stay away,
it's a natural reaction.
Do the young people, do they know what happened?
Have they heard anything about it?
If they're interested they can know the history,
I mean, even today, in China, if they try
hard they will,
but because it's 30 years, it's a long time,
even the kids who were born after the massacre
they're in almost 30s now so that's a long
time.
So I think for many young people this is a
remote topic.
On the other hand, it's so intensive, so intense
I mean, so dramatic,
the passion in there so strong just even the
vision, for example,
the tanks come in, the guardians of democracy
and there's a protest,
that was people were shown the picture, normally,
I mean,
they would show natural inclination into was
embracing the protestors.
Is it easy for them to accept
when they see the footage of "Tank Man" for
instance,
can they accept it?
"Oh, this is something my government did to
the people."
Of course it takes time because today's young
students,
they all grow up under the shadow of the fire
wall.
Most of them are so indoctrinated with communist
brainwashing.
It's really hard for them to overcome, but
slowly.
Just yesterday I saw this.
It documented 300 cases of how people realize
what happened at Tiananmen.
Normally it's a slow process
but if they're interested they will know the
facts
and eventually they wouldn't be on the side
of the government
if they know the facts.
What was life like for you after the Tiananmen
Square massacre?
For me, I never imagined I was a student leader.
I was doing my, on my call as a citizen for
my-
You thought you were talking about free press.
Right, yeah, exactly, but I became a political
prisoner.
I spent a year in prison, another year in
a reeducation program,
you know, very poor place under surveillance
and I came to United States in '95.
So for me, Tiananmen was just a beginning
of the last 30 years.
For me, it always has been my passion just
to know more,
to help more of the victims,
so every year the story,
new facts came to me and the story is still
unfolding.
The depths of the sacrifice, the passion,
the perseverance after 30 years,
it's so strong for me,
so I think this is still the most important
issue for me.
Yeah, I know recent research has even suggested
that there were up to ten thousand civilians
killed in the Tiananmen Square massacre.
Right, we don't really know,
so that's why they were successful 30 years
ago
in keeping silence because even for the protestors,
most of them don't know the full scope of
the massacre.
I didn't witness the tank killing until later.
I knew this later when I met Fang Zheng himself,
so that's why when I started Humanitarian
China
we brought his family here to United States.
And he lost his legs to the tank.
Yes.
So at the moment of life and the tanks,
when he realized the tanks were charging at
them,
he choose to push the girl over the fence.
There was a fence separating the street from
the pedestrians.
At that moment he was squashed and later the
girl never saw him again.
The lady he saved.
I believe he told me she even denied knowing
before of pressure.
Because of fear, because of fear of being
implicated as a protestor.
But he is so protective of her.
Of course he knows her identity now.
He never showed any hatred of-
It's incredible.
Of course, he should be proud of himself and
I'm just proud of him.
This was a spirit when the brutal violence
was happening
and you see the other side of human character,
their true nature just shines through.
There are people who are waiting to sacrifice
to save others and these kind of stories,
there are just so many in that whole process
over the last 30 years.
So this China, this is a rarity,
you just couldn't see it to understand,
but these people,
you see the beauty of human nature and that's
what China needs.
So what are you and all the other Tiananmen
survivors doing
to carry on the message or spread awareness?
There are many faults of this project from
Tiananmen what we are doing.
We have been very active in keeping the truth
and knowing the facts,
what happened in 1989.
We are also very active in helping the families
for example,
the Tiananmen Mothers and the Beijing citizens
who are helping students,
most of them were sentenced to very long years
in prison,
also the people who are imprisoned are killed
outside of Beijing.
There were maybe tens of thousands of them
and people we know
a fuller picture of what happened in 1989.
Here in the United States I'm trying to reach
out
to any people who interested in knowing this
and on my social media and everywhere I post
this.
Because of this I was censored on LinkedIn.
On LinkedIn?
On LinkedIn.
On the American job website.
Right.
By the American... backed down after it was-
So what did they do?
Did they block your website everywhere
or just being seen in China?
I actually never tested it.
It's probably blocked in China as a result,
but they just send me a message saying
we have to block you for this and that.
Incredible.
Then later they blame it as technical error
of some kind.
So it is a fight, a continuous fight against
the enforced amnesia.
That's what we are, we are fighting.
This year, 30 years anniversary,
is different in the way that we all realize
we are all over 50.
We have to think if our generation has to
pass on this duty
to next generation what do we show them,
so we're building a few sculptures and we
want to build a museum.
These are in Liberty Sculpture Park near Los
Angeles and-
So a museum dedicated to Tiananmen or history
of communism?
Yeah, it will be called Tiananmen or June
4th Museum
but it will cover the history of China's fight
against communism
and also other countries too.
We hope we can build this in the next five
years.
If this is done after that we want to build
a giant statue of liberty called The Goddess
of Democracy.
Like the statue they had-
Right.
In the center of Tiananmen back then.
Yeah, that was crushed 30 years ago.
We want to erect it here at full length of
64 meters tall.
Wow.
So if we can get all the resources,
this will be our testimony for the future
generations.
So what lesson do you think people today
should take away from the Tiananmen protests
and the Tiananmen Square massacre?
We have to overcome the fear,
so most people on this topic are still living
in the fear
enforced by the communist government and you
have to choose sides.
If you choose to stay with the government
you
are part of the collusion against truth and
justice
for the participants and for the, in particular,
for the whole for better China.
And also we must remember this was a brief
period in China
where the freedom and democracy for China
unified everyone.
It was resonating across the globe for a better
China.
That's the first probably only time.
For all of us who was there,
this was a test of freedom and we must remember
that.
Great.
Thank you so much for joining me today.
Good luck with the 30th anniversary making
sure people
still stay aware about what happened.
Sure.
Thank you.