On this episode of China Uncensored,
welcome to the South China Sea.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
Ah the South China Sea.
It really brings up such nostalgic memories
for me.
Like when I took a Filipino fishing boat to
the Scarborough Shoal,
disputed waters China and the Philippines
have been fighting over
in the middle of the South China Sea.
As far as I’m concerned,
this territorial dispute is over!
But just two weeks after we were there,
Filipino president Rodrigo Duterte
banned fishing within the shoal's lagoon.
I’m sure that was just a coincidence
and had nothing to do with the fact that we
were there.
But it’s an odd move for the Philippines,
if you consider that a recent poll showed
that 84% of Filipinos
want to challenge China’s claim to that
area.
Aww, they call the South China Sea the West
Philippine Sea.
Not much chance of that name sticking
if things go the way they’ve been going,
by the way.
A year ago,
the Philippines might have been in a good
position
to exercise its claim to the region.
Last July,
the Philippines successfully got a UN tribunal
to rule against China’s claim.
But then this man became president of the
Philippines.
And he pushed for closer ties with China,
at the expense of ties with the United States.
And to do that,
he had to “set aside” his country’s
claims
to the South China Sea.
And now that Duterte has had a taste of working
with China,
he wants more.
You see,
the south of the Philippines has a problem
with kidnappings by Islamic extremists.
And so Duterte has asked for China to help patrol
the international waters nearby to prevent
piracy.
These kidnappings are a real problem.
But traditionally,
the Philippines would reach out to the United
States
for help for this sort of thing.
But, oh but there’s been a sea change.
Or should I say, Xi change?
Don't do it, Duterte!
You're playing right into their hands!
So far, the whole world has freaked out
about the Chinese regime's aggressive expansion
in the South China Sea.
Now the Chinese Communist Party always says,
“hey, we’re building all those artificial
islands and stuff
for purely peaceful purposes.”
Which is really convincing.
But if the President of the Philippines asks
for Chinese protection
in the South China Sea,
that gives them a great excuse.
“Look, we’re helping keep sailors safe!
If anything there should be more Chinese military
and coast guard vessels in the South China
Sea.”
Duterte said he only asked China to patrol
international waters,
and not other countries' territorial waters.
Oh, well in that case,
everything is totally fine.
But regardless,
Duterte's request makes China out to be the
hero.
And it legitimizes China’s claims to the
region.
Maybe the Chinese regime
ought to start charging the rest of the surrounding
countries
“protection fees.”
Your weekly dues to us will give you all the
supplemental safety net
you'll ever need.
So what do you think of Duterte’s plea
for Chinese patrols off its coast?
Leave your comments below.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host Chris Chappell,
see you next time.