On this episode of China Uncensored,
these homemade Chinese vehicles are incredible.
Hi and welcome to China Uncensored.
I'm your host, Chris Chappell.
You know, the Chinese people are overflowing
with creativity.
And it's really taking them to new heights.
So let's take a look at some incredible vehicles
made by your average Chinese citizen.
Number 10
This farmer from Wuhan made his very own flying
saucer.
It's 12 feet wide!
Shu Mansheng was able to get it 6 feet off
the ground for over 30 seconds.
And though you might think it's one of a kind,
he's actually made four others.
There's no way this UFO is just swamp gas.
Number 9
A former traffic cop built himself his very
own electric car.
No steering wheel?
No problem!
It uses foot pedals to navigate.
He said he built it specifically for disabled
people and retirees.
And he taught himself how to make it by reading
books.
Number 8
Although this may not have quite the shine
of Lamborghini,
this 9500-dollar home made version can travel
up to 160 mph.
Supposedly.
It was built by a 28 year old mechanic from
a farming family who said he fell in love
with cars when he was 16.
I have to say,
this has really inspired me to try my hand
at building my own dream vehicle
a death star.
Number 7
In China, you're not allowed to own guns.
But how about a tank?
It was made by a 31 year old retired PLA soldier.
He said he got the idea when his son's toy
tank broke and he asked for a new one.
I think his son will be happy with this.
Number: 6
But maybe not as happy as this guy's kid!
It took this farmer 6 months to gather the
scrap metal to make this pretty awesome looking
toy Lamborghini.
Wow, that's a million times cooler than the
Barbie Jeep Wrangler.
And get this, it can travel almost 40 miles
an hour.
Which is probably not safe for a six year
old.
Number 5
You really can't get greener than an electric
car made out of wood.
Unless you were to literally paint it green.
He should get on that.
48 year old Chinese carpenter Liu Fulong put
3200 dollars into his car.
It can reach top speeds of 30 mph and man,
those missiles were a nice touch.
It's also apparently armored and comes equipped
with radar...
for some reason.
Number 4
Do you like cutting edge technology with a
touch of the antique and none of the chic?
Then behold this robot driven rickshaw!
It actually walks,
though that probably means it's not the fastest
rickshaw out there.
Number 3
You got to give this guy credit for trying
to clean up China.
This DIY street sweeper has 12 rotating brooms
attached to the rear!
Though it seems like it would just blow dirt
onto parked cars.
Number 2
Believe it or not,
this 38 year old farmer built his own fully
functional submarine.
It was designed to harvest sea cucumbers.
He's also built 8 other miniature submarines
that can travel at a depth of almost 100 feet
for 10 hours.
Number 1
And finally, a wooden blade helicopter.
Unfortunately, or maybe fortunately,
for 22 year old farmer Wu Zhongyuan,
the local government has forbidden him from
flying it.
Which is too bad because he says it can get
as high as 2600 feet.
So which would you like to ride in most?
Let me know in the comment section below.
Once again I'm Chris Chappell,
see you next time.