On this episode of China Uncensored,
the silver screen is turning red!
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
We’ve talked about it before,
that toxic wasteland spewing its pollution
around the world.
Actually, I’m talking about Hollywood.
But Hollywood may have met its match in China.
By the end of next year,
it’s estimated that China may become
the world’s biggest movie box office.
Yes, even bigger than the United States.
Moviegoers in China will pay an estimated
8.3 billion dollars by the end of this year.
That’s just a few billion away from catching
up with the US.
In fact,
Hollywood movies are now often made
with the Chinese market in mind.
Because if a studio wants its next major blockbuster
to take up a chunk of that multi-billion dollar
market,
it will have to play by the Communist Party’s
rules.
China allows only 34 foreign films a year.
Is it about protecting China’s own film
industry?
Mmm…partly.
But it’s also about censoring ideas that
could,
you know,
undermine social harmony.
So what are Chinese censors looking for?
Well, just ask Party mouthpiece,
Xinhua.
According to a draft
of China’s new film industry handbook,
people in the the film industry must have
“moral integrity.”
How do you do that?
“Practice core socialist values.”
If a Hollywood studio
wants to guarantee success in what
may soon be
the world’s biggest movie market,
that means censor yourself,
or get censored by the
State Administration of Press, Publication,
Radio, Film and Television,
or SAPPRFT.
But this is about even more
than just preventing Chinese people
from seeing movies that don’t adhere
to core socialist values.
This is part of a concerted effort
by the Chinese Communist Party
to control what comes out of Hollywood.
They want to change the way Americans,
and the rest of the world,
think about China.
For more on this,
I sat down with National Security and Cyber
Espionage Expert,
Joshua Philipp,
who recently wrote this article in The Epoch
Times.
Thanks for joining us again, Josh.
The last time you were on the show,
you told us how China uses cyber espionage
to wage war on the United States.
And I couldn’t sleep for a week.
So tell me, why can I never enjoy a movie
again?
The Chinese Communist Party
has vast systems of forcing Hollywood to self censor,
or enticing them to co-produce films
alongside the Chinese Communist Party
so they have a direct hand in censoring the
films
during the production process.
Is this just to control what people see inside
of China
or does it affect us here?
It very much affects us here.
It ties back to what they call
culture warfare
but also what they call soft power.
This is altering the perception
of the Chinese Communist Party
and Chinese governance.
It’s—
you can’t show the Chinese Communist Party
in a negative light;
you can’t show the United States or the
US military
in a positive light.
Wait,
how do they make Hollywood not portray the
US positively?
Well,
if the US creates a film
that shows the US military
or the United States in a positive light,
that film cannot be shown in China.
Really?!
And they lose the Chinese market because of
that.
So the film Captain Phillips,
I think with Tom Hanks,
that was banned in China,
because it showed the US military rescuing,
you know, one guy,
you know the US,
the United States mobilizing its entire military
to rescue one person,
which China would never do.
This encourages Hollywood studios
to never make a film showing the US government
in a positive light
because then that movie won’t get into the
China market,
which is going to be the biggest movie market
in the world.
So why make a moviethat won’t make a lot
of money?
Well and that’s the idea.
From the very get-go they need to think,
would we be willing to sacrifice doubling
our income, potentially,
or just remove this scene
that shows America in a positive light,
or just change the script around a little
bit
so it doesn’t show America positively
or doesn’t show China negatively.
And this is the kind of thought process that
filmmakers
are putting into their movies from the very
get-go
and through the entire process.
And this is the environment of self-censorship
that China has created for the film market.
I always thought the reason China had those
censorship laws
was to control what people inside of China
see.
But really,
China, the Chinese government,
is doing this is to control what we in the
US see as well.
That’s right,
and this actually ties to more,
I mean kind of conniving, you know,
strategies they have.
The Communist Party conniving?
They directly call it ‘culture war,’ in
their own words.
Hu Jintao has used that exact phrase.
Sounds very cultured...
So has Xi Jinping as a matter of fact.
Nazi Germany did the same thing,
the Soviets did the same thing,
and China is now doing the same thing as well.
I’m going to be thinking about this every
time I see a movie now.
Do you enjoy making people feel horrible?
Well, if it's raising awareness about accurate issues,
I think people should feel horrible
when they realize films are being manipulated
with the intention of altering the way they
view the world.
Films are a core piece of the American identity.
Films are a common topic in conversations
with each other.
For a lot of us,
we quote films casually during conversations.
You’re sitting around with friends
you're going to quote a film or two 90% of
the time.
You’re tearing me apart.
If a government is manipulating these systems
of culture
for the purpose of altering the way we view
the world,
altering the way we view ourselves,
altering the way we view international issues,
I think it’s an issue of serious concern.
Thank you very much for joining us again today, Josh.
What do YOU think?
And you'd like more specific examples of how China influences Hollywood,
check out my previous episode,
“5 Hollywood Films Infiltrated by China.”
Want to read Josh’s article?
Link is in the Description below.
Once again, I'm Chris Chappell,
See you next time.