On this episode of China Uncensored,
how far can you push a lie?
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host Chris Chappell.
From the country that brought you
a ban on reincarnation,
comes the most mind-bending
assault on logic yet.
You see, the Chinese Communist Party
is a bit like Richard Simmons.
Only instead of stretching those glutes,
the Communist Party stretches the truth.
Unlike Richard Simmons,
the Communist Party has not
suddenly disappeared.
You may be familiar with the Chinese regime
doing some construction in disputed territorial
waters
in the South China Sea.
This is Fiery Cross Reef.
And here’s a timelapse of Fiery Cross Reef.
You can see a close-up of the 10,000-foot
runway
they built on it,
perfect for military planes.
And according to US officials,
these might be missile silos.
So if you go by what some people call
objective reality,
you’d think the Chinese regime is building
man-made islands for military purposes.
But if you take the red and yellow pill,
things aren’t what they seem.
Because according to Wu Qian,
China’s Defense Minister,
there’s “no such thing.”
In other news:
War is Peace, Freedom is Slavery, and Ignorance
is Strength.
Specifically what the Defense Minister said
was,
"Most of the building is for civilian purposes”
“including necessary defensive facilities”
But he also said:
"There is no such thing
as man-made islands"
In other words,
military falls under the category of civilian.
And there’s no such thing
as what they’re building, anyway.
Yes, none of this exists.
When reporters asked him to explain his comment,
“Wu declined to elaborate,
saying China had already provided a full explanation
of its construction work.”
Construction work that never happened, right?
It's like something out of a movie.
Wait a second!
I know what’s going on!
Wu Qian is trying to use Jedi mind tricks
on us.
“There are no man-made islands.”
Well, Wu Qian, Jedi mind tricks don’t work
on me.
Hey!
C’mon Seamus.
At least Photoshop me onto a character
from one of the good Star Wars movies.
That’s more like it.
Or maybe it's not Star Wars...
Maybe there are no man-made islands
because there is no reality.
We're all just living in some kind of artificial
simulation
of a world that doesn't exist anymore.
Nah, that's just crazy.
Anyway, why is this man-made islands thing
such a big deal?
Well, the Chinese regime is engaged in territorial
disputes
with many of its neighbors
over the resource-rich South China Sea.
China claims pretty much all of it
within this red line,
called the nine-dash line.
Whether or not those claims have historical
legitimacy,
the Chinese regime is proceeding aggressively
by dredging up sand and piling it on
mostly submerged reefs.
Then, they use those man-made islands
to exert territorial claims,
saying those islands belong to China,
since, you know,
China built them.
Then they say they never built them,
even though we have pictures of them
doing it.
Wait!
What if the Chinese regime
didn't build those islands after all?
What if that's what Wu Qian meant
when he said there were no man-made islands?
The Chinese military wasn't dredging up sand
to build islands.
It was merely helping to uncover natural islands
with natural sand that exists
at the bottom of the ocean
and would one day maybe form those exact islands
on those exact coral reefs
that the Chinese military killed
in order to not build those islands on top
of.
If you think about it,
it's very eco-friendly.
Al Gore would approve.
And it’s a great strategy.
Because no matter how insane it is,
what is anyone going to do about it?
No one wants to go to war with China.
And so the Chinese regime
keeps pushing the envelope
until they push it into Crazytown.
Which was primarily built for civilian purposes,
including necessary defensive facilities.
So what do you think of China’s claim
there’s no such thing as man-made islands?
Leave your comments below.
I’d also like to let you know
that China Uncensored is possible
mainly because of support from viewers.
You can contribute through a website called
Patreon.
You can become a supporter of China Uncensored
by pledging, for example, a dollar per episode.
And as a supporter,
you’ll also get some cool rewards
and behind the scenes stuff.
So click the link in the Description
to visit our Patreon webpage.
Thanks for watching this episode of China
Uncensored.
Once again I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
See you next time.