The Chinese Military rotates troops into Hong
Kong.
No protest for protesters.
And who is the real hero of the Hong Kong
protests?
This is China Uncensored.
I’m Chris Chappell.
This week in China’s most politically embarrassing
city,
Hong Kong...
The Chinese People’s Liberation Army—or
PLA—
moved troops into Hong Kong
in the early hours of Thursday morning.
You know it’s true,
because Chinese state-run CCTV broadcast this
footage.
But don’t worry!
It’s just a totally normal troop rotation.
The PLA administers 19 sites in Hong Kong,
including 12 barracks.
One of them is this giant PLA garrison in
downtown Hong Kong.
It’s right next to Chief Executive Carrie
Lam’s office,
and the Legislative Council building.
And every year at roughly this time,
the PLA *does* do a regular troop rotation.
I mean, there’s only so long an individual
soldier
can stand being in Hong Kong.
He eventually needs to get some R&R
back in mainland China,
where he won’t be confused by the uncensored
Internet.
Anyway, this year,
the troop rotation was heavily promoted on
CCTV.
And not just in a standard news report with
one cameraman.
Look at these cinematic tracking shots.
They definitely hired a drone or jib operator.
To subliminally hint that these troops are
a big deal.
But again, don’t worry.
Because it’s *no* big deal!
This was totally a normal troop rotation.
The fact that it’s also a blatant intimidation
tactic
is just a bonus, really.
And frankly, who needs the PLA
when Hong Kong has its own capable police
force?
They’ve been firing tear gas and rubber
bullets.
Even threatening to use their handguns.
But they’ve also allegedly been sexually
assaulting
female Hong Kong protesters.
30,000 people came out on Wednesday night
to protest police sexual violence.
And they brought a familiar face with them.
I never thought I’d say this,
but Pepe looks almost...not creepy.
Ok, never mind.
According to a small survey last week,
23 women say they’ve been sexually abused
by the Hong Kong police since the protests
began in June.
“In one case, the police are accused of
completely stripping a woman demonstrator
during a search at a police station.
In another case, a video shows a half-naked
woman
being dragged away by policemen.”
Good thing Hong Kong Chief Executive Carrie
Lam
is on the side of women.
What’s that, Shelley?
Oh, sorry, I mean police.
She’s on the side of the police.
In a leaked audio recording,
she told a group of young people on Monday
that she strongly opposes
any independent investigation into police
conduct.
In the recording originally published by Apple
Daily,
she said, “Many people want to investigate
the abuse of power of the police,
if they violated this-and-that [rule] during
operations,
so colleagues of the police force
were very much opposed to it.”
Lam went on to say that she couldn’t do
something “hastily”
that would affect the police’s work.
Well if the police don’t want to be investigated,
then case closed.
Good thing Carrie Lam’s own conduct
has also been successfully kept under wraps.
Well, except for this leaked audio.
Speaking of Carrie Lam,
she’s not going to step down.
“I think a responsible chief executive at
this point in time
should continue to hold the fort
and do her utmost to restore law and order
in Hong Kong.
And I wouldn't say that my government has
lost control.
Day in, day out,
we are not only supporting the law enforcement
bodies,
we are also acting responsibly to deal with
other issues.”
Yes, she’s acting very responsibly
by not meeting any of the protesters’ demands.
And guess who’s just been arrested in Hong
Kong?
Activists Joshua Wong,
Andy Chan, and Agnes Chow.
Now granted, they’re not actually protest
leaders—
since this movement doesn’t have any official
leadership,
and decisions seem to be made in big group
huddles,
or group chats on the instant messaging service
Telegram
and the online forum LIHKG.
But that shouldn’t stop authorities from
arresting people anyway.
And they have!
Police have arrested over 900 protesters so
far.
Wong and Chow, by the way, were arrested
for their “inciting and taking part in an
illegal assembly”
outside police headquarters on June 21—
the same event where Shelley and I did a live
broadcast from.
Of course, it could get worse.
Much worse.
Carrie Lam *could* use the “Nuclear Option.”
That’s the Emergency Regulations Ordinance
of 1922.
It says that in the “occasion of emergency
or public danger”,
the Hong Kong Chief Executive may
“make any regulations whatsoever
which he may consider desirable in the public
interest.”
He or she, I guess.
I mean, this regulation was made long before
anyone thought there could be a woman in charge.
But this law is surely not obsolete in any
other way.
So what could the Chief Executive do with
these dictator-like powers?
Well, it’s a pretty extensive list.
It includes: Complete media censorship;
Arrest, detention, and deportation;
Control of all the ports of entry;
The entry and search of premises;
And the confiscation of personal property.
Don’t worry, this Ordinance hasn’t been
used
since the anti-British riots of 1967.
And Hong Kongers love the British now.
At least compared to the People’s Republic
of China.
Speaking of rights being taken away:
the right to peaceably assemble.
The Civil Human Rights Front is the group
that organized
the 1-million person march on June 9th...
The 2-million person march on June 16th...
And the 1.7-million person rally on August
18th
that turned into a march
because not everyone could fit into the park.
Sure, all those events were peaceful.
But also, they’re very dangerous, according
to police.
That’s why the police banned
the rally and march scheduled for tomorrow—
Saturday the 31st.
It was going to honor the call for universal
suffrage
that kicked off the Umbrella Movement five
years ago.
So the Civil Human Rights Front canceled their
event,
and that’s that.
Except that may not actually stop people
from coming out to protest.
Posters like this started appearing,
calling for people to come out and protest
anyway.
Who’s the organizer?
“Nobody”.
I have a feeling a lot of people are going
to show up.
Including well-armed police.
Speaking of well-armed police, there’s a
hero in this story.
Remember how I told you a few weeks ago
about a Hong Kong policeman
who waved his shotgun at protesters?
Well guess what?
Shotgun Cop—
whose name is Officer Lau, by the way—
has been invited to Beijing for the upcoming
celebrations
for the 70th anniversary of the People’s
Republic of China.
As my favorite state-run media The Global
Times put it,
“[Officer] Lau has become
an internet celebrity in the Chinese mainland
for his courage and high morale,
despite the biased coverage
by some Western and Hong Kong media.”
You’re right, Global Times.
Our coverage of him was totally biased.
Shotgun Cop *is* the hero.
He had no choice but to pull out a shotgun
to defend himself against protesters.
Sure, the protesters have no guns.
But they have heart.
And that’s a much more dangerous weapon.
And that’s it for the Hong Kong headlines.
And now it’s time for me to answer a question
from one of you,
a fan who supports us through Patreon—
which I might remind you is critical to our
continued coverage,
since YouTube demonetizes most of our Hong
Kong episodes.
Josiah Faber asks:
“What's Taiwan doing during hong kong?
Are they helping or remaining neutral?”
Good question, Josiah.
Taiwan as a country isn’t directly getting
involved in Hong Kong.
Well, unless you believe Chinese state-run
media
that Taiwan is one of the “black hands”
behind the protests.
But the Taiwan government *has* pledged
to help any Hong Kong protesters
seeking sanctuary on their island.
Apparently, dozens of Hong Kong activists
have already fled to Taiwan.
One politician from the New Power Party
even shared a Facebook post calling for Taiwanese
people
to donate anti-tear gas equipment
and various supplies for Hong Kong protesters.
But that got her in hot water,
because then an opposing KMT politician
said her post violated the security law,
“which forbids Taiwanese from offering supplies
and aid to hostile countries,
including China’s special administrative
regions
of Hong Kong and Macau.”
The KMT politician went on to accuse
the New Power Party politician of “aiding
enemy forces”
and said he would report her to the police.
Wait a minute,
if this KMT guy thinks that the Hong Kong
protesters
are “enemy forces”
does that mean he supports the Chinese Communist
Party?
That means *he’s* the one who’s really
aiding enemy forces.
Thanks for your question, Josiah.
And thank you for your support.
Visit Patreon.com/ChinaUncensored and contribute
so that we can keep making great episodes
for you.
Once again, I’m Chris Chappell.
See you next time.