I call it the “Hug A Nazi, Make a Liberal”
Theory.
That theory just doesn’t work.
And instead, what we’ve done is enrich and
empower
a clique of dictators in China.
Hi, welcome to China Uncensored,
I’m your host, Chris Chappell.
Dana Rohrabacher has been a US congressman
from my home state of California
since 1989 -
the year of the Tiananmen Square Massacre.
He criticized the Chinese Communist Party
then,
and does now, too.
In fact, he’s one of a tiny handful of US
congress people
willing to raise the most taboo issues, the
ones
that the Communist Party absolutely does not
want the public
to talk about.
President-elect Trump has considered Rohrabacher
for a position
in the US State Department.
Also, he’s a folk singer and surfer.
So naturally, I came to Washington, DC
to sit down with Congressman Rohrabacher.
Thank you for joining me today, Congressman
Rohrabacher.
You’ve been a congressman since 1989, and
in that time
you’ve been very vocal about China issues.
Why should Americans care about what happens
in China?
Well China, as a country that’s being controlled
by people who hate the American way of life
is a potential problem
if not a potential threat - an enemy.
A China run by a more democratic country,
that is more in tune with its own people,
that isn’t trying to be belligerent or militaristic
is really a positive force in the world,
and positive for America.
If the Chinese people are free,
and if the Chinese people have their rights
be protected
by their own government,
that’s actually good for America as well.
That’s why we should be on the side, there
in China,
of people who would like a more democratic
and open system.
A more accountable system.
Instead of being run by a bunch of gangsters
that will put you in jail
and cut you open and steal your organs
and sell them for profit.
Hey, the Communist Party denies that any of
that’s happening.
I’m sure.
Ever since Bill Clinton pushed for granted
China
Most Favored Nations trade status,
most politicians have followed the strategy
of:
Step 1: Make China rich
Step 2:
Step 3: Democracy!
Why hasn't that worked?
Well, the idea that you’re going to increase
the
wealth and power of people in a government,
and that will somehow make them more humane,
and more democratic,
it’s a longing that people have,
and obviously it hasn’t worked in China,
and I don’t think I’ve seen it ever have.
I call it the “Hug A Nazi, Make a Liberal”
Theory.
That theory just doesn’t work.
And instead, what we’ve done is enrich and
empower
a clique of dictators in China.
And they’re actually more of a threat now
that they’re wealthy and have wealth at
their command,
than they were when they were poor!
And it’s a mistaken notion that people reject
democracy
because they are poor people.
And the fact is,
even in the communist era,
that’s just not the way it was.
You often speak about things like human rights
abuses,
which make the Chinese Communist Party feel
bad.
How do you expect China to engage with us
if you keep
hurting the feelings of the Chinese people?
Unfortunately, that argument is being made
that we should try our best not to
enrage the butchers in Beijing.
I think, basically, we need to make sure that
we
penetrate that ring and don’t try to make
friends
with the clique that’s running this control.
But instead reach out to the people themselves
and say “we’re on your side.”
And we’re not on the side of this clique
having an iron-fisted grip on you
and the rest of your society.
What are some of the most taboo issues that
the Chinese Communist Party doesn't want American
officials like you to talk about?
I think the harvesting of organs from prisoners
-
especially prisoners who have been arrested
because of their religious convictions,
or other types of things - their writings.
But in terms of the Falun Gong,
people who believe in meditation,
people who believe in self-help,
people who have standards,
humane and valued standards -
putting them in jail and killing them for
their organs
has got to be one of the most heinous crimes
on the planet.
And this is literally taking saints -
we should encourage people to have those values
around the world, including the United States.
The meditation, the actual seeking truth
and seeking to be in harmony with the world
and with others -
We should encourage those types of values.
And killing people like that,
and especially, then,
to add the worst kind of insult,
killing people like that,
and then taking their body parts
in order to make money
to sustain their tormentors.
To sustain the iron grip on their lives.
That is the worst of all tyrannies that I
could see.
There are reports that you are a potential
candidate
for Secretary of State.
If you get the job,
what would your China policy look like?
Well my China policy would be
whatever President Trump wants the China policy
to be.
And that’s the first thing we have to note.
But I can tell you what I would recommend.
And what I recommend is that when people,
when there are high-level meetings between
Chinese officials and American officials,
that we also make it a point
to bring up human rights issues.
And if any American diplomat goes to China,
which they would,
that part of that visit would visiting
people whose humans rights are being violated,
people who are under attack,
so that people know,
yes, we recognize the people in power,
but we also sympathize with others.
For the last 8 years,
every time there’s been a meeting with
heads of state,
our president has not pushed that point at
all.
And so I think it should be part of the agenda
to discuss, and also if someone,
if our diplomats go there,
our elected officials go to China,
they should actually make it a point
to go visit someone who is a dissident.
I understand you once arm wrestled Russian
president Vladimir Putin
to decide whether America or Russia won the
Cold War.
Would you arm wrestle Xi Jinping?
No, because I just had my shoulder replaced.
And I think that I would need
to make sure I’m ready for that fight.
I’m afraid my shoulder’s not ready for
it.
If the opportunity happens, I’m there for
you.
I understand you hurt your shoulder
from a little too much surfing?
That was it.
When I was younger,
I was not told that this was gonna
wear away your shoulder cartilage.
But that’s part of freedom, you know.
They say, “well 25 years of surfing
gave you that arm.”
Would you do it again?
Well, yeah - sure I would!
That’s a vote for surfing.
Surfing is great.
Freedom is great.
People there, and the Falun Gong,
they’ve opened their senses
to being able to experience what life is about
to them
and the universe…
Well, as a surfer,
I sort of did it that way.
Didn’t go through the other provisions
that would make me Falun Gong.
I just did it on the surfboard.
Sounds pretty good to me.
So you have praised president-elect Trump
for taking the phone call from Taiwanese president
Tsai Ing-wen because it showed China
that he wasn't a pushover.
Are there other things that Trump could do
to show China that he isn't a pushover?
Well, the first thing he could do, for example,
I would suggest that he
make sure that he visibly has someone association
with
people who are pushing
for more of a democratic China.
We could also send a message that,
certain business rules of the game have changed.
He could propose that.
And the Chinese will get the message.
Are you concerned that standing up to the
Chinese regime
could make it harder to work with China?
Yes, I am.
We have to understand that there’s nothing
for free
in this world.
And I would predict,
knowing the nature of tyrants and gangsters,
the stronger you are with them,
the broader the area of cooperation will be
because they know respect you,
and know that they can’t go beyond this.
And so, however, you’re risking a breakdown.
And frankly, a breakdown in relations that
we have
may hurt our business community.
But quite frankly,
the business community should understand
their well-being is less important
than the security of the United States.
And in the long run,
we need to have a more democratic China.
That should be our goal.
Do you think there’s a risk of a trade war?
Trade war?
Trade war benefits us!
Why?
It benefits us because,
if we have unequal trade agreements with China
that facilitates the flow of wealth to come
in this way,
If we have a dispute over the basic rules,
that flow of wealth,
it’s not gonna come from here to there.
That flow of wealth will stay in the United
States.
Congressman Rohrabacher, thank you for joining
me today.
I have one final question:
Who do you think won this interview?
I would have to say,
I think the people who believe in freedom
won this interview.
I think there’s only one way to decide…
Next up is Putin!
Thank you again, it was a pleasure.